<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- SourceFormat: VL.  Converted to USX by the STEP project: 2023-08-18 -->
<usx version="2.0">
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <book code="1ES"/>



  <chapter sid="1ES 1"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:1"/>And Iosias celebrated the pascha to his Lord in Ierousalem, and he sacrificed the pascha on the fourteenth day of the first month,<verse eid="1ES 1:1"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:2"/>after he had arranged the priests by their daily duties, robed, in the temple of the Lord.<verse eid="1ES 1:2"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:3"/>And he told the Leuites, temple-slaves of Israel, that they should sanctify themselves to the Lord for the task of putting the holy ark of the Lord in the house that Salomon the king, the son of Dauid, had built,<verse eid="1ES 1:3"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:4"/>"You need no longer carry it on your shoulders. And now, serve the Lord, your God, and attend to his nation Israel, and prepare yourselves by your paternal families and tribes, according to the writing of Dauid, king of Israel, and according to the magnificence of his son Salomon.<verse eid="1ES 1:4"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:5"/>And having stationed yourselves in the temple by the paternal groupings of you, the Leuites, who stand before your kindred, sons of Israel,<verse eid="1ES 1:5"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:6"/>in order, sacrifice the pascha, and prepare the sacrifices for your kindred. And keep the pascha according to the ordinance of the Lord that was given to Moyses."<verse eid="1ES 1:6"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:7"/>To the people who were found there, Iosias presented a gift of thirty thousand lambs and kids and three thousand calves; these were given, according to promise, from the king's possessions to the people and the priests and Leuites.<verse eid="1ES 1:7"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:8"/>Chelkias and Zacharias and Esyelos, the chief officers of the temple, gave the priests two thousand six hundred sheep, three hundred calves, for the pascha.<verse eid="1ES 1:8"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:9"/>And Iechonias and Samaias and his brother Nathanael and Hasabias and Ochielos and Ioram, officers of thousands, gave the Leuites five thousand sheep, seven hundred calves, for the pascha.<verse eid="1ES 1:9"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:10"/>And when these things were done in proper order, the priests and the Leuites, holding the un-leavened bread, stood before the people by tribe and by groupings of fathers to offer to the Lord in accordance with what is written in the book of Moyses, and so they did in the morning.<verse eid="1ES 1:10"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:11"/>And they roasted the pascha with fire, as required, and they boiled the sacrifices in bronze pots and cauldrons, with a pleasing odor, and carried them to all that were from the people.<verse eid="1ES 1:11"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:12"/>Now, after this they prepared both for themselves and for their kindred the priests, sons of Aaron.<verse eid="1ES 1:12"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:13"/>For the priests were offering the fat until quite late, and the Leuites prepared it for themselves and for their kindred the priests, sons of Aaron.<verse eid="1ES 1:13"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:14"/>And the temple-musicians, sons of Asaph, were in their order according to what had been arranged by Dauid-- and Asaph and Zacharias and Eddinous, the king's representatives.<verse eid="1ES 1:14"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:15"/>And the porters were at each gateway. It was not possible that anyone omit his own daily service, for their kindred, the Leuites, made preparations for them.<verse eid="1ES 1:15"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:16"/>And the things that had to do with the sacrifice of the Lord were accomplished in that day: that the pascha was celebrated and that the sacrifices were offered on the altar of the Lord according to the injunction of King Iosias.<verse eid="1ES 1:16"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:17"/>And the sons of Israel who were found at that time celebrated the pascha and the feast of unleavened bread for seven days.<verse eid="1ES 1:17"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:18"/>And no pascha like it had been celebrated in Israel since the times of Samouel the prophet,<verse eid="1ES 1:18"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:19"/>and none of the kings of Israel had celebrated such a pascha as Iosias celebrated, and the priests and the Leuites and the Judeans and all of Israel, who were found in their dwelling place, in Ierousalem.<verse eid="1ES 1:19"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:20"/>This pascha was celebrated in the eighteenth year when Iosias reigned.<verse eid="1ES 1:20"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:21"/>And the deeds of Iosias, done with his heart full of piety, were deemed right in the sight of his Lord.<verse eid="1ES 1:21"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:22"/>Now, also the matters of his reign in previous times have been recorded: about those who sinned and those who acted impiously toward the Lord, more than any nation and kingdom, and how they conspicuously grieved him-- and the words of the Lord rose up against Israel.<verse eid="1ES 1:22"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:23"/>And after all this activity of Iosias, it happened that Pharao, king of Egypt, came to incite war at Charkamys on the Euphrates, and Iosias went out to confront him.<verse eid="1ES 1:23"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:24"/>And the king of Egypt sent a dispatch to him, saying, "What issue do I and you have, O king of Judea?<verse eid="1ES 1:24"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:25"/>I have not been sent out against you by the Lord God, for my war is at the Euphrates. Now then, the Lord is with me! Also, the Lord with me is urging me on! Stand aside, and do not oppose the Lord."<verse eid="1ES 1:25"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:26"/>And Iosias did not turn himself away to his chariot, but he undertook to fight with him, not heeding the words of Ieremias the prophet from the mouth of the Lord.<verse eid="1ES 1:26"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:27"/>On the contrary, he joined battle with him in the plain of Mageddao, and the rulers came down against King Iosias.<verse eid="1ES 1:27"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:28"/>And the king said to his servants, "Take me away from the fight, for I have become very weak." And his servants immediately took him from the line of battle,<verse eid="1ES 1:28"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:29"/>and he got into his secondary chariot. And after he was brought back to Ierousalem, he departed this life and was buried in his ancestral tomb.<verse eid="1ES 1:29"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:30"/>In the whole of Judea they mourned for Iosias. And Ieremias the prophet lamented for Iosias. And the principal men, together with women, lament him to this day. And this has been handed on to the whole race of Israel always to do.<verse eid="1ES 1:30"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:31"/>These things stand inscribed in the document of the events being recorded about the kings of Judea. And every single thing done of the activity of Iosias and of his splendor and of his understanding of the law of the Lord, both which were done by him before and now, have been recorded in the book of the kings of Israel and Ioudas.<verse eid="1ES 1:31"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:32"/>And when the people of the nation had taken Iechonias son of Iosias, they appointed him king in place of Iosias his father, when he was twenty-three years old.<verse eid="1ES 1:32"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:33"/>And he reigned in Ioudas and Ierousalem for three months. And the king of Egypt deposed him from reigning in Ierousalem<verse eid="1ES 1:33"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:34"/>and fined the nation one hundred talents of silver and one talent of gold.<verse eid="1ES 1:34"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:35"/>And the king of Egypt appointed his brother, King Ioakeim, king of Judea and Ierousalem.<verse eid="1ES 1:35"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:36"/>And Ioakeim incarcerated the nobles. But he seized his brother Zarios and brought him back from Egypt.<verse eid="1ES 1:36"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:37"/>Now Ioakeim was twenty-five years old when he began to reign in Judea and Ierousalem; he did what was evil in the sight of the Lord.<verse eid="1ES 1:37"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:38"/>Now Nabouchodonosor, the king of Babylon, came up against him, and he bound him with a bronze fetter and took him away to Babylon.<verse eid="1ES 1:38"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:39"/>Nabouchodonosor also took some sacred vessels of the Lord and carried them away; he deposited them in his shrine in Babylon.<verse eid="1ES 1:39"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:40"/>And the things recorded, about him and his uncleanness and impiety, stand inscribed in the document of the times of the kings.<verse eid="1ES 1:40"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:41"/>And his son Ioakeim became king in his place, for when he was appointed king, he was eighteen years old.<verse eid="1ES 1:41"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:42"/>Now he reigned in Ierousalem for three months and ten days, and he did what was evil in the sight of the Lord.<verse eid="1ES 1:42"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:43"/>And a year later Nabouchodonosor sent and removed him to Babylon, together with the sacred vessels of the Lord.<verse eid="1ES 1:43"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:44"/>And he appointed Sedekias king of Judea and Ierousalem, when Sedekias was twenty-one years old. Now he reigned eleven years.<verse eid="1ES 1:44"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:45"/>And he did what was evil in the sight of the Lord and felt no hesitation arising from the words spoken by Ieremias the prophet from the mouth of the Lord.<verse eid="1ES 1:45"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:46"/>And although he had been made to swear, by King Nabouchodonosor, by the name of the Lord, he broke his oath, rebelled and, having hardened his neck and his heart, he transgressed the precepts of the Lord, God of Israel.<verse eid="1ES 1:46"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:47"/>Now also the leaders of the people and of the priests committed many acts of impiety and lawlessness, more than all the unclean deeds of all the nations, and they defiled the temple of the Lord that had been sanctified in Ierousalem.<verse eid="1ES 1:47"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:48"/>And the God of their fathers sent word through his messenger to call them back, because he tried to spare them and his covert.<verse eid="1ES 1:48"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:49"/>But they mocked at his messengers, and on the day the Lord spoke, they were scoffing at his prophets until in his anger against his nation, on account of their impious acts, he ordered that the kings of the Chaldeans go up against them.<verse eid="1ES 1:49"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:50"/>These killed their young men by sword around about their holy temple, and they did not spare young man or young woman and old man and younger man, but all he handed over into their hands.<verse eid="1ES 1:50"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:51"/>And they took away all the sacred vessels of the Lord, great and small, the treasure chests of the Lord and the royal stores and carried them off to Babylon.<verse eid="1ES 1:51"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:52"/>And they set fire to the house of the Lord, and they wrecked the walls of Ierousalem and burned its towers with fire.<verse eid="1ES 1:52"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:53"/>And they finished rendering useless all its glorious features. And the survivors he led away by sword to Babylon.<verse eid="1ES 1:53"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:54"/>And they were servants to him and to his sons until the Persians reigned, in fulfilment of the word of the Lord by the mouth of Ieremias,<verse eid="1ES 1:54"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 1:55"/>"Until the land takes pleasure in its sabbaths, it shall sabbatize all the time of its desolation until the completion of seventy years."<verse eid="1ES 1:55"/>



  <chapter sid="1ES 2"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:1"/>In the first year that Cyrus was reigning the Persians, with a view to fulfilment of a word of the Lord by Ieremias' mouth,<verse eid="1ES 2:1"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:2"/>the Lord stirred the spirit of Cyrus, king of the Persians, and he proclaimed in his whole kingdom and at the same time in written form,<verse eid="1ES 2:2"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:3"/>"This is what Cyrus, the king of the Persians, says: The Lord of Israel, Lord the Most High, has appointed me king of the world,<verse eid="1ES 2:3"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:4"/>and he indicated to me that I should build him a house in Ierousalem in Judea.<verse eid="1ES 2:4"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:5"/>If anyone of you, therefore, is of his nation, let his Lord be with him, and when they have gone up to Ierousalem, which is in Judea, let him build the house of the Lord of Israel. This is the Lord who encamps in Ierousalem.<verse eid="1ES 2:5"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:6"/>So, as many as dwell in each place, let those in his place help him with gold and with silver, with gifts, along with horses and livestock, together with the other things added as votive offerings for the temple of the Lord that is in Ierousalem."<verse eid="1ES 2:6"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:7"/>And there arose the chiefs of the paternal families of the tribe of Ioudas and Beniamin and the priests and the Leuites and all whose spirit the Lord had stirred to go up to build the house for the Lord, which is in Ierousalem,<verse eid="1ES 2:7"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:8"/>and the people in their surrounding area, and they helped them with everything, with silver and gold, horses and livestock and with the greatest number of vows from many whose mind was stirred.<verse eid="1ES 2:8"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:9"/>And King Cyrus brought out the sacred vessels of the Lord that Nabouchodonosor had removed from Ierousalem and stored them in his own idol temple.<verse eid="1ES 2:9"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:10"/>Now when Cyrus, the king of the Persians, had brought them out, he gave them over to Mithridates, his own treasurer,<verse eid="1ES 2:10"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:11"/>and they were handed over by him to Sanabassaros, administrator of Judea.<verse eid="1ES 2:11"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:12"/>Now the number of these was: gold libation bowls, one thousand; silver libation bowls, one thousand; silver censers, twenty-nine; gold saucers, thirty; silver, two thousand four hundred ten; and other vessels, one thousand.<verse eid="1ES 2:12"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:13"/>Now all the vessels were recovered, gold and silver: five thousand four hundred sixty-nine.<verse eid="1ES 2:13"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:14"/>Now they were carried back by Sanabassaros, along with the people of the captivity, from Babylon to Ierousalem.<verse eid="1ES 2:14"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:15"/>Now in the times under Artaxerxes, the king of the Persians, Beslemos and Mithridates and Tabellios and Raoumos and Beelteemos and Samsaios the scribe and the rest of those associated with them but living in Samaria and the other places wrote out the following letter to him against those who were living in Judea and Ierousalem,<verse eid="1ES 2:15"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:16"/>"To King Artaxerxes, Sir, your servants Raoumos the one for events and Samsaios the scribe and the rest of their council and the judges who are in Coele-Syria and Phoenicia.<verse eid="1ES 2:16"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:17"/>And now, let it be known to the lord king that, when Judeans came up from you to us, having come to Ierousalem, they are building the rebellious and wicked city, repairing both its market places and the walls, and are laying the foundations for a shrine.<verse eid="1ES 2:17"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:18"/>So if this city is built and the walls are completed, not only will they not submit to paying tribute, but they will also resist kings. And since the work on the shrine is in progress, we assume it best not to overlook such a matter but to address our lord king in order that, if it seems good to you, a search may be made in the books from your fathers.<verse eid="1ES 2:18"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:19"/>And you will find in the records what has been written about them and will learn that that city was rebellious, troubling both kings and cities, and that the Judeans were rebels and set up blockades in it from of old, for which reason this city was also laid waste.<verse eid="1ES 2:19"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:20"/>Therefore we are now pointing out to you, Lord King, that if this city is built and its walls rise up, you will no longer have a way down to Coele-Syria and Phoenicia."<verse eid="1ES 2:20"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:21"/>Then the king wrote back the following to Raoumos the recorder of events and to Beelteemos and Samsaios the scribe and to the rest associated with them and living in Samaria and Syria and Phoenicia,<verse eid="1ES 2:21"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:22"/>"I read the letter that you have sent to me. I therefore ordered that a search be made, and it was found that that city from of old has been opposing kings<verse eid="1ES 2:22"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:23"/>and that the people in it perpetrate rebellions and wars and that strong and cruel kings used to be masters in Ierousalem and were extracting tribute from Coele-Syria and Phoenicia.<verse eid="1ES 2:23"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:24"/>Now, therefore, I have ordered that you prevent those people from building the city and that you take care that nothing more be done and that such wicked proceedings go no further so as to annoy kings."<verse eid="1ES 2:24"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 2:25"/>Then when what was written by King Artaxerxes had been read, Raoumos and Samsaios the scribe and those associated with them marched in haste to Ierousalem with cavalry and a throng of the first rank and began to hinder those who were building. And the construction of the temple that is in Ierousalem stopped until the second year of the reign of Darius, the king of the Persians.<verse eid="1ES 2:25"/>



  <chapter sid="1ES 3"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:1"/>And King Darius gave a great banquet for all who were under him and for all his homebred and for all the nobles of Media and of Persia<verse eid="1ES 3:1"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:2"/>and for all the satraps and generals and district governors that were under him in the hundred twenty-seven satrapies from India to Ethiopia.<verse eid="1ES 3:2"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:3"/>And they ate and drank, and when they were satisfied, they went away, but Darius the king went to his bedroom and went to sleep but woke up again.<verse eid="1ES 3:3"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:4"/>Then the three young men, the bodyguards, who kept guard over the person of the king, said one to another,<verse eid="1ES 3:4"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:5"/>"Let us state, each of us, one thing which will prove superior, and whosever his statement seems wiser than the other-- Darius the king will give him grand gifts and great prizes of victory<verse eid="1ES 3:5"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:6"/>and that he be clothed in purple and drink from wrought gold and sleep on gold and have a chariot with a gold studded bridle and a turban of fine linen and a torque around his neck.<verse eid="1ES 3:6"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:7"/>And because of his wisdom, he shall take his seat next to Darius and shall be called Kinsman of Darius."<verse eid="1ES 3:7"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:8"/>And then they wrote, each his own statement, sealed it and put it under the pillow of Darius the king. And they said,<verse eid="1ES 3:8"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:9"/>"When the king gets up, they will give him what is written, and whomever the king picks-- and the three nobles of Persia-- because his statement is wisest, to him the victory shall be given, as it stands written."<verse eid="1ES 3:9"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:10"/>The first wrote, "Wine proves superior."<verse eid="1ES 3:10"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:11"/>The second wrote, "The king proves superior."<verse eid="1ES 3:11"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:12"/>The third wrote, "Women prove superior, but above all things truth is victorious."<verse eid="1ES 3:12"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:13"/>And when the king awoke, they took what was written and gave it to him, and he read.<verse eid="1ES 3:13"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:14"/>And he sent and summoned all the nobles of Persia and of Media and satraps and generals and district governors and consuls<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'prefects'</char></note>, and he took his seat in the council chamber, and what was written was read in their presence.<verse eid="1ES 3:14"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:15"/>And he said, "Call the young men, and they themselves shall explain their statements." And they were summoned and came in.<verse eid="1ES 3:15"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:16"/>And they said to them, "Tell us about what you have written." And the first, who had spoken of the strength of wine, began and spoke thus,<verse eid="1ES 3:16"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:17"/>"O Gentlemen, how does wine prove superior? It leads astray the thoughts of all men who drink it.<verse eid="1ES 3:17"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:18"/>It makes equal the thoughts of both the king and the orphan, of both the domestic and the free, of both the poor and the rich.<verse eid="1ES 3:18"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:19"/>And it turns every thought to feasting and mirth and does not remember any sorrow or any obligation.<verse eid="1ES 3:19"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:20"/>And it makes all hearts rich and does not remember king or satrap and makes everyone talk in talents<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'large sums of money'</char></note>.<verse eid="1ES 3:20"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:21"/>And when people drink, they do not remember to be friendly with friends and kindred, and before long they draw daggers.<verse eid="1ES 3:21"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:22"/>And when they recover from the wine, they do not remember what they did.<verse eid="1ES 3:22"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 3:23"/>O Gentlemen, does not wine prove superior, since it forces people to behave thus?" And when he had said this, he fell silent.<verse eid="1ES 3:23"/>



  <chapter sid="1ES 4"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:1"/>And the second, who had spoken of the strength of the king, began to speak,<verse eid="1ES 4:1"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:2"/>"O Gentlemen, do not humans prove superior, since they rule over land and sea and all that is in them?<verse eid="1ES 4:2"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:3"/>But the king proves superior and is lord of all and their master, and whatever he says to them they heed.<verse eid="1ES 4:3"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:4"/>If he tells them to make war one against the other, they do it, and if he sends them out against enemies, they proceed and conquer mountains and walls and towers.<verse eid="1ES 4:4"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:5"/>They murder and are murdered and do not transgress the king's bidding, and if they are victorious, they bring everything to the king-- whatever spoil they take and everything else.<verse eid="1ES 4:5"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:6"/>And as many as do not serve in the army or go to war, they instead till the soil; in turn, whenever they sow and reap, they send some to the king, and one compels the other to bring levies to the king.<verse eid="1ES 4:6"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:7"/>And he is one single man! If he tells them to kill, they kill. He tells them to release, they release;<verse eid="1ES 4:7"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:8"/>he tells them to smite, they strike; he tells them to lay waste, they lay waste; he tells them to build, they build;<verse eid="1ES 4:8"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:9"/>he tells them to cut down, they cut down; he tells them to plant, they plant.<verse eid="1ES 4:9"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:10"/>And all his people and his forces heed him. Furthermore, he himself reclines; he eats and drinks and sleeps,<verse eid="1ES 4:10"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:11"/>but they keep watch all around him, and no one may go away and tend to his own affairs, nor do they disobey him.<verse eid="1ES 4:11"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:12"/>O Gentlemen, how does not the king prove superior, since he is to be obeyed in this way?" And he fell silent.<verse eid="1ES 4:12"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:13"/>Now the third, who had spoken of women and truth (he was Zorobabel) , began to speak,<verse eid="1ES 4:13"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:14"/>"Gentlemen, is not the king great, are not men many, and does not wine prove superior? Who is it, then, that is master over them, or who is lord over them? Is it not women?<verse eid="1ES 4:14"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:15"/>Women give birth to the king and to all people that are lord over sea and land.<verse eid="1ES 4:15"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:16"/>And from them they were born, and it is they that brought up those who plant the vineyards from which comes the wine.<verse eid="1ES 4:16"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:17"/>And it is they that make men's robes, and it is they that bring men glory, and men cannot exist apart from women.<verse eid="1ES 4:17"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:18"/>Now if men gather gold and silver or any beautiful thing, and they see one woman lovely in appearance and beauty,<verse eid="1ES 4:18"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:19"/>they then let all those things go and gape at her and with open mouths stare at her, and all choose her rather than gold or silver or any beautiful thing.<verse eid="1ES 4:19"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:20"/>A man leaves his own father, who brought him up, and his own country and clings to his own wife.<verse eid="1ES 4:20"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:21"/>And with his wife he releases his soul and neither remembers father or mother or country.<verse eid="1ES 4:21"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:22"/>And as a result you must realize that women are lords over you. "Do you not labor and toil and bring and give everything to women?<verse eid="1ES 4:22"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:23"/>And a man takes his sword and goes out to travel and rob and steal and to sail the sea and rivers,<verse eid="1ES 4:23"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:24"/>and he faces the lion, and he proceeds through darkness, and when he steals and robs and plunders, he brings it back to her he desires.<verse eid="1ES 4:24"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:25"/>And a man loves his own wife more than his father and mother.<verse eid="1ES 4:25"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:26"/>And many have been driven to distraction by their own minds because of women and have become slaves because of them.<verse eid="1ES 4:26"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:27"/>And many have perished and stumbled and sinned because of women.<verse eid="1ES 4:27"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:28"/>And now, do you not believe me? "Is not the king great in his authority? Do not all lands fear to touch him?<verse eid="1ES 4:28"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:29"/>I have watched him and Apame the daughter of the illustrious Bartacos, the king's concubine, sitting at the king's right hand<verse eid="1ES 4:29"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:30"/>and taking the diadem from the king's head and put it on herself. And she would slap the king with her left hand.<verse eid="1ES 4:30"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:31"/>And at this the king would gaze at her with mouth agape. And if she smiles at him, he laughs, but if she is cross with him, he flatters her so that she may be reconciled to him.<verse eid="1ES 4:31"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:32"/>O Gentlemen, how are women not strong, since thus they act?"<verse eid="1ES 4:32"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:33"/>And then the king and the nobles looked one at the other. And he began to speak about truth,<verse eid="1ES 4:33"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:34"/>"Gentlemen, are not women strong? The earth is vast, and the sky is high, and swift is the sun in its course, for it makes the circuit of the sky and returns again to its own place in one day.<verse eid="1ES 4:34"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:35"/>Is not the one who does these things great? Truth also is great and stronger than all things.<verse eid="1ES 4:35"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:36"/>"All the earth calls upon truth, and heaven blesses her. And all his<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:36</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'heaven'</char></note> works quake and tremble, and with him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:36</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'heaven'</char></note> there is nothing unrighteous.<verse eid="1ES 4:36"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:37"/>Wine is unrighteous; the king is unrighteous; women are unrighteous; all sons of men are unrighteous, and all their works are unrighteous-- all such things. And there is no truth in them, and in<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:37</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'by'</char></note> their injustice they will perish.<verse eid="1ES 4:37"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:38"/>But truth endures and is strong forever and lives and prevails forever and ever.<verse eid="1ES 4:38"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:39"/>And with it there is no partiality or preference, but it does what is righteous instead of anything that is unrighteous or wicked. And all approve her deeds,<verse eid="1ES 4:39"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:40"/>and there is nothing unrighteous in her judgment. And to her belongs the strength and the kingship and the authority and the majesty of all the ages. Blessed be the God of truth!"<verse eid="1ES 4:40"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:41"/>And he stopped speaking, and all the people then shouted and then said, "Great is truth, and it proves superior!"<verse eid="1ES 4:41"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:42"/>Then the king said to him, "Request what you want in addition to what is written, and we will give it to you, for you have been found to be the wisest. And you shall sit next to me and be called my Kinsman."<verse eid="1ES 4:42"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:43"/>Then he said to the king, "Remember the vow that you made on the day you received your kingship to build Ierousalem<verse eid="1ES 4:43"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:44"/>and to send back all the vessels that had been taken from Ierousalem, which Cyrus set apart when he vowed to destroy Babylon and vowed to send them back there.<verse eid="1ES 4:44"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:45"/>You also vowed to build the shrine, which the Idumeans burned when Judea was laid waste by the Chaldeans.<verse eid="1ES 4:45"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:46"/>And now, O Lord King, this is what I ask of you and what I request of you, and this is greatness that is yours. I pray, therefore, that you fulfill the vow that you vowed with your mouth to do for the king of heaven."<verse eid="1ES 4:46"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:47"/>Then Darius the king got up and kissed him and wrote letters for him to all the stewards and district governors and generals and satraps, that they should give safe conduct to him and all who were going up with him to build Ierousalem.<verse eid="1ES 4:47"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:48"/>He also wrote letters to all the district governors in Coele-Syria and Phoenicia and to those in Lebanon, to convey cedar timber from Lebanon to Ierousalem, and that they should build the city with him.<verse eid="1ES 4:48"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:49"/>He also wrote for all the Judeans who were going from his kingdom to Judea, in the interest of their freedom, that no officer or satrap or district governor or steward should assail their doors<verse eid="1ES 4:49"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:50"/>and that all the country they would seize should be theirs without tribute and that the Idumeans should give up the villages of the Judeans that they held and<verse eid="1ES 4:50"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:51"/>that twenty talents a year should be given for the building of the temple until it was built<verse eid="1ES 4:51"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:52"/>and an additional ten talents a year for whole burnt offerings to be offered on the altar every day, in accordance with the commandment they have, to offer seventeen,<verse eid="1ES 4:52"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:53"/>and that all who would come from Babylonia to found the city should have their freedom, both they and their children and all the priests who would come.<verse eid="1ES 4:53"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:54"/>Now, he also stipulated the expense and the priestly vestment, in what way they would serve in it.<verse eid="1ES 4:54"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:55"/>He also stipulated that they should give the Leuites the expense until the day when the house would be finished and Ierousalem built.<verse eid="1ES 4:55"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:56"/>He also stipulated that they give allotments of land and wages to all who would guard the city.<verse eid="1ES 4:56"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:57"/>He also sent back from Babylon all the vessels that Cyrus had set apart, and everything that Cyrus said that he would do he too instructed to be done and to be sent back to Ierousalem.<verse eid="1ES 4:57"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:58"/>And when the young man went out, he lifted up his face to heaven toward Ierousalem and blessed the king of heaven, saying,<verse eid="1ES 4:58"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:59"/>"From you comes victory, and from you comes wisdom, and yours is the glory. And I am your domestic.<verse eid="1ES 4:59"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:60"/>Blessed are you, who have given me wisdom, and you I acknowledge, O Master of our fathers."<verse eid="1ES 4:60"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:61"/>And he took the letters and departed, and he went to Babylon and told all his kindred.<verse eid="1ES 4:61"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:62"/>And they blessed the God of their fathers, because he had given them permission and release<verse eid="1ES 4:62"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 4:63"/>to go up and build Ierousalem and the temple where his name is named on it, and with music and rejoicing they drank hard for seven days.<verse eid="1ES 4:63"/>



  <chapter sid="1ES 5"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:1"/>Now, after these things the leaders of the house of the paternal families and their wives and sons and daughters and their male and female servants and their livestock were chosen to go up by their tribes.<verse eid="1ES 5:1"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:2"/>And Darius sent along with them a thousand cavalry until they would restore them to Ierousalem in peace, and with the music of drums and flutes.<verse eid="1ES 5:2"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:3"/>And all their kindred were making merry, and he made them go up along with them.<verse eid="1ES 5:3"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:4"/>And these are the names of the men who went up, by their paternal families for the tribes, over their groups:<verse eid="1ES 5:4"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:5"/>the priests, sons of Phinees son of Aaron: Iesous the son of Iosedek the son of Saraias and Ioakeim the son of Zorobabel the son of Salathiel, of the house of Dauid, of the lineage of Phares and of the tribe of Ioudas,<verse eid="1ES 5:5"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:6"/>who spoke wise words before Darius, the king of the Persians, in the second year of his reign, in the month of Nisan, the first month.<verse eid="1ES 5:6"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:7"/>Now, the following are those from Judea who went up out of the captivity in exile, whom Nabouchodonosor, the king of Babylon, had deported to Babylon,<verse eid="1ES 5:7"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:8"/>and each returned to Ierousalem and the rest of Judea, to his own town, those who came with their leaders Zorobabel and Iesous, Neemias, Zaraias, Resaias, Enenios, Mardochaias, Beelsaros, Aspharasos, Borolias, Roimos and Baana.<verse eid="1ES 5:8"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:9"/>The number of those from the nation and their leaders: sons of Phoros, two thousand one hundred seventy-two; sons of Saphat, four hundred seventy-two;<verse eid="1ES 5:9"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:10"/>sons of Aree, seven hundred fifty-six;<verse eid="1ES 5:10"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:11"/>sons of Phaathmoab, with respect to the sons of Iesous and Ioab, two thousand eight hundred twelve;<verse eid="1ES 5:11"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:12"/>sons of Olamos, one thousand two hundred fifty-four; sons of Zatos, nine hundred forty-five; sons of Chorbe, seven hundred five; sons of Bani, six hundred forty-eight;<verse eid="1ES 5:12"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:13"/>sons of Bebai, six hundred twenty-three; sons of Asgad, three thousand three hundred twenty-two;<verse eid="1ES 5:13"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:14"/>sons of Adonikam, six hundred sixty-seven; sons of Bagoi, two thousand sixty-six; sons of Adinos, four hundred fifty-four;<verse eid="1ES 5:14"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:15"/>sons of Ater son of Hezekias<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'Ater son of Hezekias':  Or 'Ater Hezekias'</char></note>, ninety-two; sons of Kilan and Azetas, sixty-seven; sons of Azouros, four hundred thirty-two;<verse eid="1ES 5:15"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:16"/>sons of Hannias, one hundred one; sons of Arom; sons of Bassai, three hundred twenty-three; sons of Hariphos, one hundred twelve;<verse eid="1ES 5:16"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:17"/>sons of Baiterous, three thousand five; sons from Baithlomon, one hundred twenty-three.<verse eid="1ES 5:17"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:18"/>Those from Netebas, fifty-five; those from Enatos, one hundred fifty-eight; those from Baitasmon, forty-two;<verse eid="1ES 5:18"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:19"/>those from Kariathiarios, twenty-five; those from Kapiras and Berot, seven hundred forty-three.<verse eid="1ES 5:19"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:20"/>The Chadiasai and Hammidians, four hundred twenty-two; those from Kiramas and Gabbes, six hundred twenty-one;<verse eid="1ES 5:20"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:21"/>those from Makalon, one hundred twenty-two; those from Baitolion, fifty-two. Sons of Niphis, one hundred fifty-six;<verse eid="1ES 5:21"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:22"/>sons of the other Kalamo and Onous, seven hundred twenty five; sons of Ierechos, three hundred forty-five;<verse eid="1ES 5:22"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:23"/>sons of Sanaas, three thousand three hundred thirty.<verse eid="1ES 5:23"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:24"/>The priests: sons of Ieddos the son of Iesous, with reference to the sons of Anasib, nine hundred seventy-two; sons of Emmeros, one thousand and fifty-two;<verse eid="1ES 5:24"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:25"/>sons of Phassouros, one thousand two hundred forty-seven; sons of Charme, one thousand seventeen.<verse eid="1ES 5:25"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:26"/>Now, the Leuites: sons of Iesous and Kadmielos and Bannos and Houdias, seventy-four.<verse eid="1ES 5:26"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:27"/>The temple-musicians: sons of Asaph, one hundred forty-eight.<verse eid="1ES 5:27"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:28"/>The porters: sons of Saloum, sons of Atar, sons of Tolman, sons of Akoub, sons of Hateta, sons of Sobi, in all one hundred thirty-nine.<verse eid="1ES 5:28"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:29"/>The temple-slaves: sons of Esau, sons of Hasipha, sons of Tabaoth, sons of Keras, sons of Soua, sons of Phadaias, sons of Labana, sons of Haggaba,<verse eid="1ES 5:29"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:30"/>sons of Akoud, sons of Outa, sons of Ketab, sons of Hagaba, sons of Sybai, sons of Hanan, sons of Kathoua, sons of Geddour,<verse eid="1ES 5:30"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:31"/>sons of Iairos, sons of Daisan, sons of Noeba, sons of Chaseba, sons of Gazera, sons of Ozias, sons of Phinoe, sons of Asara, sons of Basthai, sons of Asana, sons of Maani, sons of Naphisi, sons of Akouph, sons of Hachiba, sons of Hasour, sons of Pharakim, sons of Basaloth,<verse eid="1ES 5:31"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:32"/>sons of Meedda, sons of Koutha, sons of Charea, the sons of Barchous, sons of Serar, sons of Thomoi, sons of Nasie, sons of Hatipha.<verse eid="1ES 5:32"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:33"/>Sons of Salomon's servants: sons of Hassaphioth, sons of Pharida, sons of Ieeli, sons of Lozon, sons of Geddel, sons of Saphythi,<verse eid="1ES 5:33"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:34"/>sons of Hatil, sons of Phakareth of Sabie<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:34</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'Phakareth of Sabie':  Or 'Phakareth Sabie'</char></note>, sons of Sarothie, sons of Masias, sons of Gas, sons of Addous, sons of Soubas, sons of Apherra, sons of Barodis, sons of Saphat, sons of Amon.<verse eid="1ES 5:34"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:35"/>All the temple-slaves and the sons of Salomon's servants were three hundred seventy-two.<verse eid="1ES 5:35"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:36"/>And the following are those who came up from Thermelee and Thelersas with Charaath leading them: Adan and Amar--<verse eid="1ES 5:36"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:37"/>and they could not prove by their paternal families or generations how they were from Israel-- sons of Dalan the son of Touban, sons of Nekodan, six hundred fifty-two.<verse eid="1ES 5:37"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:38"/>Also, from the priests those who had assumed the priesthood but were not found: sons of Hobbia, sons of Hakkos and the sons of Ioddous who took Augia to wife, one of the daughters of Pharzellaias, and was called by his name.<verse eid="1ES 5:38"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:39"/>And when their genealogical entry was sought in the register and was not found, they were excluded from serving as priests,<verse eid="1ES 5:39"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:40"/>and Neemias and Hattharias told them that they were not to share in the holy things until a high priest should arise wearing Explanation and Truth.<verse eid="1ES 5:40"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:41"/>Now, their total was: of Israel, twelve or more years of age, besides male and female servants, forty-two thousand three hundred sixty; their male and female servants were seven thousand three hundred thirty-seven; there were two hundred forty-five harpists and harp singers.<verse eid="1ES 5:41"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:42"/>There were four hundred thirty-five camels and seven thousand thirty-six horses, two hundred forty-five mules and five thousand five hundred twenty-five beasts of burden.<verse eid="1ES 5:42"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:43"/>And some of those who led by paternal families, when they arrived at the temple of God that is in Ierousalem, vowed that they would erect the house on its site according to their power<verse eid="1ES 5:43"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:44"/>and that they would give to the temple treasury for the work a thousand minas<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:44</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek 1 mina = 0.6 kg</char></note> of gold and five thousand minas of silver and one hundred priests' vestments.<verse eid="1ES 5:44"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:45"/>And the priests and the Leuites and those who were from his people were settled in Ierousalem and its vicinity, and the temple-musicians and the porters and all Israel were in their villages.<verse eid="1ES 5:45"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:46"/>Now, when the seventh month came and the sons of Israel were all in their own homes, they gathered with a single purpose in the open area of the first eastward facing gateway.<verse eid="1ES 5:46"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:47"/>And Iesous the son of Iosedek with his brothers, the priests and Zorobabel the son of Salathiel with his kindred took their places and prepared the altar of the God of Israel<verse eid="1ES 5:47"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:48"/>so that they could offer whole burnt offerings upon it, following what was prescribed in the book of Moyses the man of God.<verse eid="1ES 5:48"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:49"/>And some from the other nations of the land joined them. And they erected the altar in their place, because all the nations that were in the land were hostile to them and were stronger than they, and they offered sacrifices at the proper time and whole burnt offerings to the Lord in the morning and late afternoon.<verse eid="1ES 5:49"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:50"/>They celebrated the feast of tent pitching, as it is ordered in the law, and sacrifices every day, as was proper,<verse eid="1ES 5:50"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:51"/>and thereafter the perpetual offerings and sacrifices on sabbaths and new moons and all the consecrated feasts.<verse eid="1ES 5:51"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:52"/>And as many as had made a vow to God began to offer sacrifices to God from the new moon of the seventh month, and the shrine of God had not yet been built.<verse eid="1ES 5:52"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:53"/>And they gave money<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:53</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'silver'</char></note> to the masons and carpenters and food and drink and carts to the Sidonians and the Tyrians, to deliver cedar logs from Lebanon, to convey them in rafts to the harbor of Joppe, according to the written ordinance that they had from Cyrus, the Persians' king.<verse eid="1ES 5:53"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:54"/>And in the second year after his arrival at the temple of God in Ierousalem, during the second month, Zorobabel the son of Salathiel and Iesous the son of Iosedek and their kindred, the Leuitical priests, and all who had arrived at Ierousalem from the captivity made a beginning<verse eid="1ES 5:54"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:55"/>and laid the foundation of the shrine of God on the new moon of the second month in the second year of their coming to Judea and Ierousalem.<verse eid="1ES 5:55"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:56"/>And they appointed the Leuites who were twenty or more years of age to have charge of the work of the Lord. And Iesous stood, along with his sons and kindred, both Kadmiel his brother and the sons of Iesous Emadaboun<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:56</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Perhaps 'son of Emadaboun'</char></note> and the sons of Ioda son of Iliadoun with their sons and kindred, all the Leuites, as taskmasters functioning with a single purpose for the work on the house of the Lord. And the builders built the shrine of the Lord,<verse eid="1ES 5:56"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:57"/>and the priests stood in their vestments with musical instruments and trumpets, and the Leuites, sons of Asaph, holding cymbals, were singing hymns to the Lord and blessing according to Dauid, the king of Israel,<verse eid="1ES 5:57"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:58"/>and they intoned through hymns, acknowledging the Lord, because his goodness and his glory are forever in all Israel.<verse eid="1ES 5:58"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:59"/>And all the people trumpeted and shouted with a loud voice, singing hymns to the Lord for the erection of the house of the Lord.<verse eid="1ES 5:59"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:60"/>And some of the Leuitical priests and of those who presided over their paternal families, the old men who had seen the house before this one, came to the building of this one with outcries and loud weeping,<verse eid="1ES 5:60"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:61"/>and many people with trumpets and joy with a loud sound,<verse eid="1ES 5:61"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:62"/>so that the people could not hear the trumpets because of the people's weeping. For it was the crowd that was trumpeting so loudly that they were heard far away.<verse eid="1ES 5:62"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:63"/>And when the enemies of the tribe of Ioudas and Beniamin heard it, they came to learn what the sound of trumpets meant.<verse eid="1ES 5:63"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:64"/>And they learned that those who were from the captivity were building the shrine for the Lord, God of Israel,<verse eid="1ES 5:64"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:65"/>and when they approached Zorobabel and Iesous and the leaders of the paternal families they said to them, "We will build along with you.<verse eid="1ES 5:65"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:66"/>For, like you, we hear<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:66</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'obey'</char></note> your Lord, and we have been making offerings<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:66</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'burning incense'</char></note> to him ever since the days of Asbasareth, the king of the Assyrians, who transferred us to here."<verse eid="1ES 5:66"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:67"/>And Zorobabel and Iesous and the leaders of the paternal families of Israel said to them, "You have nothing to do with us in building the house for the Lord, our God,<verse eid="1ES 5:67"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:68"/>for we alone will build it for the Lord of Israel, following what Cyrus, the king of the Persians, has ordered us."<verse eid="1ES 5:68"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:69"/>But the nations of the land, by falling asleep over<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:69</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'falling asleep over':  Greek uncertain</char></note> those in Judea and laying siege to them, con strained the building.<verse eid="1ES 5:69"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 5:70"/>And by bringing about plots and demagoguery and uprisings, they prevented the completion of the building as long as King Cyrus lived. And they were kept from building for two years until the reign of Darius.<verse eid="1ES 5:70"/>



  <chapter sid="1ES 6"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:1"/>Now in the second year of the reign of Darius, the prophets Haggaios and Zacharias the son of Eddo prophesied to the Judeans who were in Judea and Ierousalem, in the name of the Lord, God of Israel, who is over them.<verse eid="1ES 6:1"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:2"/>Then Zorobabel the son of Salathiel and Iesous the son of Iosedek arose and began to build the house of the Lord that is in Ierousalem, the prophets of the Lord joining in and helping them.<verse eid="1ES 6:2"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:3"/>At the same time, there came to them Sisinnes, the governor of Syria and Phoenicia, and Sathrabouzanes and their associates, and they said to them,<verse eid="1ES 6:3"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:4"/>"By whose order to you are you building this house and this roof and are finishing all the other things? And who are the builders that are finishing these things?"<verse eid="1ES 6:4"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:5"/>And the elders of the Judeans had favor with the captives, due to consideration from the Lord,<verse eid="1ES 6:5"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:6"/>and they were not prevented from building until Darius would be notified about them and his orders be issued.<verse eid="1ES 6:6"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:7"/>A copy of a letter Sisinnes, the governor of Syria and Phoenicia-- and Sathrabouzanes and their associate leaders in Syria and Phoenicia-- wrote to Darius and sent, "To King Darius, greetings!<verse eid="1ES 6:7"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:8"/>Let it be fully known to our lord the king that, when we arrived in the region of Judea and entered the city of Ierousalem, we found the elders of the Judeans of the captivity building in the city of Ierousalem a great new house for the Lord, using smoothed stones with costly timbers in the walls,<verse eid="1ES 6:8"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:9"/>and that those projects are proceeding with speed and that the work is going well in their hands and that they are being completed with all splendor and care.<verse eid="1ES 6:9"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:10"/>Then we inquired of these elders, saying, 'By whose orders are you building this house and laying the foundations of these projects?'<verse eid="1ES 6:10"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:11"/>So, in order that we might inform you and write you about who the individuals are that lead them, we questioned them and asked them for the list of the names of the proponents.<verse eid="1ES 6:11"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:12"/>But they answered us, 'We are the servants of the Lord who created heaven and earth.<verse eid="1ES 6:12"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:13"/>And the house had been built rather many years ago by a great and strong king of Israel, and it was completed.<verse eid="1ES 6:13"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:14"/>And when our fathers sinned against the heavenly Lord of Israel, provoking him, he gave them into the hands of Nabouchodonosor, king of Babylonia, king of the Chaldeans.<verse eid="1ES 6:14"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:15"/>They, having pulled it down, both burned the house and carried off the people captive to Babylon.<verse eid="1ES 6:15"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:16"/>But in the first year that Cyrus reigned over the country of Babylonia, King Cyrus wrote that they could build this house.<verse eid="1ES 6:16"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:17"/>And the sacred vessels of gold and silver, which Nabouchodonosor had taken out of the house in Ierousalem and stored in his own shrine, these Cyrus the king took out again from the shrine in Babylon, and they were given to Zorobabel and Sanabassaros the governor,<verse eid="1ES 6:17"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:18"/>and he ordered him to return all these vessels and put them in the shrine in Ierousalem, and that this shrine of the Lord should be built on its site.<verse eid="1ES 6:18"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:19"/>Then when this Sanabassaros arrived, he put in the foundations of the house of the Lord that is in Ierousalem, and although it has been in the process of construction from that time until now, it has not reached completion.'<verse eid="1ES 6:19"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:20"/>Now therefore, O King, if it is judged right, let there be a search in our lord king's royal archives in Babylon,<verse eid="1ES 6:20"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:21"/>and if it is found that the building of the house of the Lord, which is in Ierousalem, was done with the consent of Cyrus the king and if it be judged right by our lord king, let him give us directions about these things."<verse eid="1ES 6:21"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:22"/>Then King Darius ordered that search be made in the royal archives that were stored in Babylon. And in Ecbatana, the bastion<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'tower'</char></note> that is in the country of Media, one volume was found in which the following was recorded,<verse eid="1ES 6:22"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:23"/>"The first year of the reign of Cyrus: King Cyrus ordered that the house of the Lord that is in Ierousalem, where they make offerings<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:23</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'make offerings':  Or 'burned incense'</char></note> with perpetual fire, be built;<verse eid="1ES 6:23"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:24"/>its height is to be sixty cubits and its width sixty cubits, with three courses of smoothed stones and one course of new native timber, and the cost to be paid from the house of Cyrus the king,<verse eid="1ES 6:24"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:25"/>and that the sacred vessels of the house of the Lord, both of gold and of silver, which Nabouchodonosor took out of the house in Ierousalem and carried away to Babylon, should be restored to the house in Ierousalem where they used to be in order that they be placed there."<verse eid="1ES 6:25"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:26"/>Now, he ordered Sisinnes, the governor of Syria and Phoenicia, and Sathrabouzanes and their associates and those who were appointed as leaders in Syria and Phoenicia to take care to keep away from the place and to permit Zorobabel the servant of the Lord and governor of Judea and the elders of the Judeans to build that house of the Lord at the site.<verse eid="1ES 6:26"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:27"/>"And I have also instructed that they build it completely and that they watch carefully that they work closely with those who have returned from the captivity of Judea until the house of the Lord be finished<verse eid="1ES 6:27"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:28"/>and that from the tribute of Coele-Syria and Phoenicia a portion be scrupulously given to these people, to Zorobabel the governor, for sacrifices to the Lord, for bulls and rams and lambs,<verse eid="1ES 6:28"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:29"/>and likewise also wheat and salt and wine and oil, perpetually, on a yearly basis, without quibbling, for daily use as the priests in Ierousalem may indicate,<verse eid="1ES 6:29"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:30"/>in order that libations may be offered to the Most High God for the king and his servants<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:30</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'children'</char></note>, and they might pray for their life,<verse eid="1ES 6:30"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:31"/>and I order that, if any should transgress or even not act on any of the things herein said and written, a beam should be taken out of their own house, and they should be hanged upon it, and their property be forfeited to the crown.<verse eid="1ES 6:31"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:32"/>"For the same reasons, also, may the Lord, whose his name is there called upon, destroy any king and nation that shall stretch out its hand to hinder or damage that house of the Lord that is in Ierousalem.<verse eid="1ES 6:32"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 6:33"/>"I, King Darius, have decreed that it be done with all diligence as here prescribed."<verse eid="1ES 6:33"/>



  <chapter sid="1ES 7"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 7:1"/>Then Sisinnes, the governor of Coele-Syria and Phoenicia, and Sathrabouzanes and their associates, in compliance with the orders given by King Darius,<verse eid="1ES 7:1"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 7:2"/>supervised the sacred work with very great care, assisting the elders of the Judeans and the temple officials.<verse eid="1ES 7:2"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 7:3"/>And the sacred work prospered while the prophets Haggaios and Zacharias were prophesying,<verse eid="1ES 7:3"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 7:4"/>and they completed it by the sixth year of Darius, the king of the Persians, due to the ordinance of the Lord, God of Israel, and with the consent of Cyrus and Darius and Artaxerxes, kings of the Persians.<verse eid="1ES 7:4"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 7:5"/>The holy house was completed by the twenty-third of the month of Adar, in the sixth year of King Darius.<verse eid="1ES 7:5"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 7:6"/>And the sons of Israel, even the priests, the Leuites and the rest of those added from the captivity, acted in accordance with what is in the book of Moyses.<verse eid="1ES 7:6"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 7:7"/>At the dedication of the temple of the Lord, they offered one hundred bulls, two hundred rams, four hundred lambs,<verse eid="1ES 7:7"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 7:8"/>twelve male goats for the sin of all Israel, according to the number of the twelve tribal leaders of Israel,<verse eid="1ES 7:8"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 7:9"/>and the priests and the Leuites stood in their vestments, by tribe, for the projects of the Lord, God of Israel, following the book of Moyses, and the porters stood at each gateway.<verse eid="1ES 7:9"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 7:10"/>And the sons of Israel, of those from the captivity, celebrated the pascha on the fourteenth of the first month, when the priests and the Leuites had been sanctified together.<verse eid="1ES 7:10"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 7:11"/>And not all sons of the captivity were sanctified, because the Leuites were all sanctified together<verse eid="1ES 7:11"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 7:12"/>and sacrificed the pascha for all the sons of the captivity and for their brothers the priests and for themselves.<verse eid="1ES 7:12"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 7:13"/>And the sons of Israel who had returned from captivity ate it, all those who had been separated from the abominations of the nations of the land, as they were seeking the Lord.<verse eid="1ES 7:13"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 7:14"/>They also celebrated the feast of unleavened bread seven days, rejoicing before the Lord,<verse eid="1ES 7:14"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 7:15"/>because he had changed the will of the king of the Assyrians concerning them, to strengthen their hands for the projects of the Lord, God of Israel.<verse eid="1ES 7:15"/>



  <chapter sid="1ES 8"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:1"/>And later than these, when Artaxerxes king of the Persians was reigning, Esdras came-- son of Saraias the son of Ezerias the son of Chelkias the son of Salemos<verse eid="1ES 8:1"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:2"/>the son of Saddoukos the son of Achitob the son of Amarias the son of Ezias the son of Mareroth the son of Zaraias the son of Saouia the son of Bokka son of Abisoue the son of Phinees the son of Eleazar the son of Aaron the first priest.<verse eid="1ES 8:2"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:3"/>This Esdras went up from Babylon as a scribe, being a man of genius in the law of Moyses, which had been delivered by the God of Israel,<verse eid="1ES 8:3"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:4"/>and the king showed him honor, for he found favor before the king in all his requests<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'in all his requests':  Or 'for all his worthy projects'</char></note>.<verse eid="1ES 8:4"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:5"/>And some of the sons of Israel and of the priests and Leuites and temple-musicians and porters and temple-slaves came back with him to Ierousalem<verse eid="1ES 8:5"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:6"/>in the seventh year of the reign of Artaxerxes, in the fifth month (this was the king's seventh year) , for they left Babylon on the new moon of the first month and arrived in Ierousalem on the new moon of the fifth month, due to the successful journey that the Lord gave them.<verse eid="1ES 8:6"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:7"/>For Esdras possessed much knowledge, so that he omitted nothing from the law of the Lord or the commandments to teach all Israel all the statutes and judgments.<verse eid="1ES 8:7"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:8"/>The written ordinance from Artaxerxes the king, having come to the attention of Esdras the priest and reader of the law of the Lord, a copy of which follows,<verse eid="1ES 8:8"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:9"/>"King Artaxerxes to Esdras the priest and reader of the law of the Lord, greetings.<verse eid="1ES 8:9"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:10"/>Since I on my part have also decided on humane treatment, I have given orders that those that desire of the nation of Judeans and of the priests and the Leuites and, moreover, those in our own realm-- if they so choose-- go together with you to Ierousalem.<verse eid="1ES 8:10"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:11"/>Let as many as are so disposed, therefore, set out with you, just as both I and the seven Friends, my counsellors, have decreed,<verse eid="1ES 8:11"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:12"/>in order to look into the affairs of Judea and the affairs of Ierousalem, in accordance with what is in the law of the Lord,<verse eid="1ES 8:12"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:13"/>and to take along to Ierousalem the gifts for the Lord of Israel that both I and the Friends have vowed and to collect for the Lord in Ierousalem all the gold and silver that may be found in the country of Babylonia, together with what is given by the nation for the temple of their Lord which is in Ierousalem,<verse eid="1ES 8:13"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:14"/>both the gold and the silver for bulls and rams and lambs and what goes with them,<verse eid="1ES 8:14"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:15"/>so as to offer sacrifices to the Lord on the altar of their Lord, which is in Ierousalem.<verse eid="1ES 8:15"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:16"/>And whatever you, along with your kindred, wish to do with gold and silver, discharge it in accordance with the will of your God;<verse eid="1ES 8:16"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:17"/>also you shall place before your God who is in Ierousalem the sacred vessels of the Lord that have been given you for the use of the temple of your God that is in Ierousalem. And whatever else occurs to you as required for the temple of your God,<verse eid="1ES 8:17"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:18"/>you will provide out of the royal treasury.<verse eid="1ES 8:18"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:19"/>"Moreover, I, King Artaxerxes, have ordered the treasurers of Syria and Phoenicia that whatever Esdras the priest and reader of the law of the Most High God sends for, they are to take care to give to him, up to one hundred talents of silver,<verse eid="1ES 8:19"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:20"/>and likewise also up to one hundred kors<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew 1 kor = 22 liters</char></note> of wheat and one hundred measures<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek 1 metretes = 22 liters</char></note> of wine and salt in abundance.<verse eid="1ES 8:20"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:21"/>Let all things prescribed in accordance with the law of God be scrupulously fulfilled for the Most High God so that wrath may not come upon the realm of the king and his sons.<verse eid="1ES 8:21"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:22"/>You are also informed that no tribute or any other imposition be laid on any of the priests and the Leuites and temple-musicians and porters and temple-slaves and officials of this temple and that no one has authority to impose such things on them.<verse eid="1ES 8:22"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:23"/>"And you, Esdras, in keeping with the wisdom of God, appoint judges and justices to judge all those who know the law of your God, throughout all Syria and Phoenicia; moreover you shall teach it to those who do not know.<verse eid="1ES 8:23"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:24"/>And all who transgress both the law of your God and the royal law shall be strictly punished, whether by death and physical punishment or by financial penalty or arrest."<verse eid="1ES 8:24"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:25"/>Blessed be the Lord alone, who put this into the heart of the king, to glorify his house, which is in Ierousalem,<verse eid="1ES 8:25"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:26"/>and who honored me before the king and those who give him counsel and all his Friends and nobles.<verse eid="1ES 8:26"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:27"/>As for me-- I became encouraged by the support of the Lord my God, and I gathered men from Israel to go up with me.<verse eid="1ES 8:27"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:28"/>And these are the leaders, by their paternal families and their groups, who went up with me from Babylon in the reign of Artaxerxes the king:<verse eid="1ES 8:28"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:29"/>Of the sons of Phinees, Garsomos. Of the sons of Ietamaros, Gamelos. Of the sons of Dauid, Hattous the son of Sechanias.<verse eid="1ES 8:29"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:30"/>Of the sons of Phoros, Zacharias, and with him a hundred fifty men from the register.<verse eid="1ES 8:30"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:31"/>Of the sons of Phaathmoab, Eliaonias son of Zaraias, and with him two hundred men.<verse eid="1ES 8:31"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:32"/>Of the sons of Zathoe, Sechanias son of Iezelos, and with him three hundred men. Of the sons of Adinos, Ben son of Ionathos, and with him two hundred fifty men.<verse eid="1ES 8:32"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:33"/>Of the sons of Elam, Iesias son of Gotholias, and with him seventy men.<verse eid="1ES 8:33"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:34"/>Of the sons of Saphatias, Zaraias son of Michaelos, and with him seventy men.<verse eid="1ES 8:34"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:35"/>Of the sons of Ioab, Abadias son of Iezelos, and with him two hundred twelve men.<verse eid="1ES 8:35"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:36"/>Of the sons of Bania, Sali-moth son of Iosaphias, and with him a hundred sixty men.<verse eid="1ES 8:36"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:37"/>Of the sons of Babi, Zacharias son of Bebai, and with him twenty-eight men.<verse eid="1ES 8:37"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:38"/>Of the sons of Asgath, Ioanes son of Hakatan, and with him a hundred ten men.<verse eid="1ES 8:38"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:39"/>Of the sons of Adonikam-- they were the last ones, and these were their names: Eliphalatos, Ieouel and Samaias, and with them seventy men.<verse eid="1ES 8:39"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:40"/>Of the sons of Bago, Outhi the son of Istalkouros, and with him seventy men.<verse eid="1ES 8:40"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:41"/>And I gathered them at the river called Theras, and we encamped at that spot three days, and I inspected them.<verse eid="1ES 8:41"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:42"/>And when I found there none of the sons of the priests or of the Leuites,<verse eid="1ES 8:42"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:43"/>I sent word to Eleazaros and Idouelos and Maasmas and Elnatan and Samaias and Ioribos, Nathan, Ennatan, Zacharias and Mosollamos, who were the leaders and men of knowledge,<verse eid="1ES 8:43"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:44"/>and I told them to go to Addaios, who was the leading man at the place of the treasury<verse eid="1ES 8:44"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:45"/>and commanded them to discuss with Addaios and his kindred and the treasurers at that place to send us men to serve as priests in the house of our Lord.<verse eid="1ES 8:45"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:46"/>And by the mighty hand of our Lord they brought us knowledgeable men of the sons of Mooli son of Leui son of Israel: Asebebias and his sons and kindred, who numbered eighteen;<verse eid="1ES 8:46"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:47"/>also Hasebias and Announos and Osaias, a brother from the sons of Chanounaios, and their sons, twenty men;<verse eid="1ES 8:47"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:48"/>and of the temple-slaves, whom Dauid and the leaders had given for the service of the Leuites, two hundred twenty temple-slaves; the list of all their names was reported.<verse eid="1ES 8:48"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:49"/>And I proclaimed there a fast for the young men before our Lord<verse eid="1ES 8:49"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:50"/>so that we could seek from him both a successful journey for ourselves and for our children and the livestock that were with us.<verse eid="1ES 8:50"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:51"/>For I hesitated to ask the king for both foot soldiers and cavalry and for an escort for security against those who were opposed to us,<verse eid="1ES 8:51"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:52"/>for we had said to the king, "The strength of our Lord will be with those who seek after him for complete restoration."<verse eid="1ES 8:52"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:53"/>And again we petitioned our Lord about all these things, and we found him very merciful.<verse eid="1ES 8:53"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:54"/>And I set apart twelve men from the tribal leaders of the priests, both Serebias and Hassamias, and ten men from their kindred with them,<verse eid="1ES 8:54"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:55"/>and I weighed out to them the silver and the gold and the sacred vessels of the house of our Lord, which the king himself had granted-- and his counselors and the nobles and all Israel.<verse eid="1ES 8:55"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:56"/>And when I had weighed out, I handed over to them six hundred fifty talents of silver and silver vessels worth a hundred talents and a hundred talents of gold and twenty items of wrought gold and twelve bronze vessels of fine bronze that glittered like gold.<verse eid="1ES 8:56"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:57"/>And I said to them, "You too are holy to the Lord, and the vessels are holy, and the silver and the gold as a vow to the Lord, Lord of our fathers.<verse eid="1ES 8:57"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:58"/>Be watchful and on guard until you deliver them to the tribal leaders of the priests and the Leuites and to the leaders of the paternal families of Israel, in Ierousalem, in the priests' chambers of the house of our Lord."<verse eid="1ES 8:58"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:59"/>And the priests and the Leuites who took along the silver and the gold and the vessels that had been in Ierousalem carried them to the temple of the Lord.<verse eid="1ES 8:59"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:60"/>And when we had left the river Theras on the twelfth of the first month, we traveled until we arrived in Ierousalem by the mighty hand of our Lord, which was upon us; the Lord rescued us from investigation-- from every enemy, and we came to Ierousalem.<verse eid="1ES 8:60"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:61"/>And when we had been at that location three days, the silver and the gold having been weighed were handed over in the house of our Lord to the priest Marmothi of Ourias--<verse eid="1ES 8:61"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:62"/>and with him was Eleazar the son of Phinees, and there were with them the Leuites, Iosabdos son of Iesous and Moeth son of Sabannos-- all by count and weight, and the weight of everything was recorded at that very time.<verse eid="1ES 8:62"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:63"/>Now, those who had arrived from captivity offered sacrifices to God, Lord of Israel: twelve bulls on behalf of all Israel, ninety-six rams, seventy-two lambs, twelve male goats for deliverance-- all as a sacrifice to the Lord.<verse eid="1ES 8:63"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:64"/>And they delivered the king's ordinances to the royal stewards and to the governors of Coele-Syria and Phoenicia, and they honored the nation and the temple of the Lord.<verse eid="1ES 8:64"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:65"/>And when these things had been completed, the leaders came to me, saying,<verse eid="1ES 8:65"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:66"/>"The nation of Israel and the rulers and the priests and the Leuites have not put away from themselves the alien nations of the land as their uncleanness requires-- the Chananites and Chettites and Pherezites and Iebousites and Moabites and Egyptians and Idumeans.<verse eid="1ES 8:66"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:67"/>For both they and their sons have lived with their daughters, and the holy seed has been mixed with the alien nations of the land, and from the beginning of the matter the leaders and the nobles have been sharing in this lawlessness."<verse eid="1ES 8:67"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:68"/>And it happened that, as soon as I heard these things, I tore my garments and my sacred clothing and pulled out hair from my head and beard and sat in anxiety and grief.<verse eid="1ES 8:68"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:69"/>And all that were ever moved at the word of the Lord of Israel gathered together to me, as I mourned over this lawlessness, and I sat grief-stricken until the late afternoon sacrifice.<verse eid="1ES 8:69"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:70"/>And when I rose from my fast, with my garments and my sacred clothing torn, when I had bent my knees and stretched out my hands to the Lord, I said,<verse eid="1ES 8:70"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:71"/>"O Lord, I am ashamed; I am embarrassed before your face.<verse eid="1ES 8:71"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:72"/>For our sins have exceeded the height of our heads, and our mistakes had piled up to the sky<verse eid="1ES 8:72"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:73"/>already from the times of our fathers, and we are in great sin to this day.<verse eid="1ES 8:73"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:74"/>And on account of our sins and the sins of our fathers, we with our kindred and with our kings and with our priests were given over to the kings of the earth for sword and captivity and plundering, in shame until this selfsame day.<verse eid="1ES 8:74"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:75"/>And now in some measure mercy has come to us from you, O Lord, so that a root has been left to us and a name in the location of your holiness<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:75</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'holy precinct'</char></note>,<verse eid="1ES 8:75"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:76"/>even to uncover our light in the house of our Lord, to give us food in the time of our slavery. And when we were in slavery, we were not forsaken by our Lord,<verse eid="1ES 8:76"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:77"/>but he brought us into favor before the kings of the Persians, to give us nourishment<verse eid="1ES 8:77"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:78"/>and to honor our temple and to raise desolate Sion for us as a stronghold in Judea and Ierousalem.<verse eid="1ES 8:78"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:79"/>"And now, O Lord, what shall we say, when we have these things? For we have transgressed your ordinances, which you gave by the hand of your servants the prophets, saying,<verse eid="1ES 8:79"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:80"/>'The land that you are entering to possess is a land polluted with the pollution of the aliens of the land, and they have filled it with their uncleanness.<verse eid="1ES 8:80"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:81"/>And now, do not let their daughters marry your sons, and do not give your daughters to their sons,<verse eid="1ES 8:81"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:82"/>and do not seek at any time to have peaceful relations with them in order that you may prevail and eat the good of the land and leave it for an inheritance to your children forever.'<verse eid="1ES 8:82"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:83"/>And all that is happening to us results from our evil deeds and our great sins. For you, O Lord, you canceled our sins<verse eid="1ES 8:83"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:84"/>and gave us such a root as this. Again we have turned back to transgress your law so as to be mixed up with the uncleanness of the nations of the land.<verse eid="1ES 8:84"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:85"/>Were you not angry enough with us to destroy us without leaving us root and seed and name?<verse eid="1ES 8:85"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:86"/>O Lord of Israel, you are genuine, for we were left as a root on this very day.<verse eid="1ES 8:86"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:87"/>Behold, we are now before you with our lawless deeds, for no one is able to stand in your presence any longer because of these things."<verse eid="1ES 8:87"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:88"/>And when Esdras was praying-- he was making confession-- weeping, on the ground before the temple, there gathered to him a very large crowd from Ierousalem, men and women and youths. For there was great weeping among the multitude.<verse eid="1ES 8:88"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:89"/>And Iechonias son of Ieelos, of the sons of Israel, called out and said to Esdras, "We have sinned against the Lord and have married alien women from the nations of the land. Even now there is hope for Israel.<verse eid="1ES 8:89"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:90"/>Let us take an oath to the Lord on this, that we will put out all our alien wives along with their children, because it was judged right by you-- and as many as submit to the authority of the law of the Lord.<verse eid="1ES 8:90"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:91"/>Rise up, and get it done, for the task is yours, and we are with you to enforce it."<verse eid="1ES 8:91"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 8:92"/>And Esdras stood up and put under oath the tribal leaders of the priests and the Leuites of all Israel to do this. And they took an oath.<verse eid="1ES 8:92"/>



  <chapter sid="1ES 9"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:1"/>And Esdras got up and went from the court of the temple to the priest's chamber of Ioanan the son of Eliasibos.<verse eid="1ES 9:1"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:2"/>And though he spent the night there, he did not taste food or drink water, mourning over the great acts of lawlessness of the multitude.<verse eid="1ES 9:2"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:3"/>And a proclamation occurred throughout the whole of Judea and Ierousalem to all who had returned from the captivity that they should assemble at Ierousalem.<verse eid="1ES 9:3"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:4"/>And if any did not present themselves within two or three days, in accordance with the judgment of the ruling elders, their livestock would be devoted to temple use, and he himself would be deemed estranged from the multitude of the captivity.<verse eid="1ES 9:4"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:5"/>And all those from the tribe of Ioudas and Beniamin assembled together at Ierousalem within three days; this was the ninth month, on the twentieth of the month.<verse eid="1ES 9:5"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:6"/>And the entire multitude sat together in the large open area before the temple, shivering because of present winter.<verse eid="1ES 9:6"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:7"/>And Esdras stood up and said to them, "You have broken the law and married alien women to add sins to Israel.<verse eid="1ES 9:7"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:8"/>Now then, give glory, as a confession, to the Lord, God of our fathers,<verse eid="1ES 9:8"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:9"/>and do his will, and be separated from the nations of the land and from the alien women."<verse eid="1ES 9:9"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:10"/>And the entire multitude shouted and said with a loud voice, "We will do as you have said.<verse eid="1ES 9:10"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:11"/>But the multitude is large, and the weather is wintry, and we do not have the strength to stand in the open air and have not found it, and the task we cannot do in one day or two. For we have sinned rather much in these things.<verse eid="1ES 9:11"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:12"/>But let the leaders of the multitude take a stand, and let all those from our settlements, as many as have alien wives, come, having received time,<verse eid="1ES 9:12"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:13"/>and furthermore the elders and judges of each location, until they undo from us the anger of the Lord over this matter."<verse eid="1ES 9:13"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:14"/>Ionathas son of Azaelos and Iezias son of Thokanos undertook the matter on these terms, and Mosollamos and Leuis and Sabbataios served together as arbitrators for them.<verse eid="1ES 9:14"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:15"/>Those from the captivity acted in accordance with all this.<verse eid="1ES 9:15"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:16"/>And Esdras the priest chose for himself men who were leaders of their paternal families, all of them by name, and on the new moon of the tenth month they sat down together to examine the matter.<verse eid="1ES 9:16"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:17"/>And the cases of the men who had taken to themselves alien wives were brought to an end by the new moon of the first month.<verse eid="1ES 9:17"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:18"/>And of the priests, those who gathered together and were found to have alien wives were:<verse eid="1ES 9:18"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:19"/>of the sons of Iesous son of Iozedek and his kindred, Maseas and Eleazaros and Ioribos and Iodanos.<verse eid="1ES 9:19"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:20"/>And they put on their hands<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'put on their hands':  Possibly 'pledged themselves'</char></note> to put away their wives and as expiation to offer rams for their mistake.<verse eid="1ES 9:20"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:21"/>And of the sons of Emmer: Hananias and Zabdaios and Manes and Samaios and Iereel and Azarias.<verse eid="1ES 9:21"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:22"/>And of the sons of Phaisour: Elioenais, Maesias, Ismaelos and Nathanaelos and Okidelos and Salthas.<verse eid="1ES 9:22"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:23"/>And of the Leuites: Iozabdos and Semeis and Kolios (this is, Kalitas) and Pathaios and Ooudas and Ioanas.<verse eid="1ES 9:23"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:24"/>Of the temple-musicians: Eliasibos, Bakchouros.<verse eid="1ES 9:24"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:25"/>Of the porters: Salloumos and Tolbanes.<verse eid="1ES 9:25"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:26"/>Of Israel: of the sons of Phoros: Iermas and Iezias and Melchias and Miaminos and Eleazaros and Hasibias and Bannaias.<verse eid="1ES 9:26"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:27"/>Of the sons of Elam: Matthanias and Zacharias and Iezrielos and Obadios and Ieremoth and Elias.<verse eid="1ES 9:27"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:28"/>And of the sons of Zamoth: Eliadas, Eliasimos, Othonias, Iarimoth and Sabathos and Zerdaias.<verse eid="1ES 9:28"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:29"/>And of the sons of Bebai: Ioanes and Hananias and Zabdos and Emathis.<verse eid="1ES 9:29"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:30"/>And of the sons of Mani: Olamos, Mallouchos, Iedaios, Iasoubos and Asaelos and Ieremoth.<verse eid="1ES 9:30"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:31"/>And of the sons of Addi: Naathos and Moossias, Lakkounos and Naidos and Matthanias and Sesthel and Balnouos and Manasseas.<verse eid="1ES 9:31"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:32"/>And of the sons of Hannan: Elionas and Asaias and Melchias and Sabbaias and Simon Chosamaios.<verse eid="1ES 9:32"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:33"/>And of the sons of Hasom: Maltannaios and Mattathaias and Sabadaious and Eliphalat and Manasses and Semei.<verse eid="1ES 9:33"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:34"/>And of the sons of Baani: Ieremias, Moadios, Maeros, Iouel, Mamdai and Pedias and Anos, Karabasion and Eliasibos and Mamnitanaimos, Eliasis, Bannous, Elialis, Someis, Selemias, Nathanias. And of the sons of Ezora: Sesis, Ezril, Azaelos, Samatos, Zambris, Iosepos.<verse eid="1ES 9:34"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:35"/>And of the sons of Nooma: Mazitias, Zabadaias, Edais, Iouel, Banaias.<verse eid="1ES 9:35"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:36"/>All these had married alien women, and they divorced them together with their children.<verse eid="1ES 9:36"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:37"/>And the priests and the Leuites and those from Israel settled down in Ierousalem and throughout the country. On the new moon of the seventh month-- and the sons of Israel were in their settlements--<verse eid="1ES 9:37"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:38"/>and the entire multitude gathered with one accord in the large open area before the gateway toward the east of the temple,<verse eid="1ES 9:38"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:39"/>and they told Esdras the chief priest and reader to bring the law of Moyses that had been handed over by the Lord, God of Israel.<verse eid="1ES 9:39"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:40"/>And Esdras the chief priest brought the law for the entire multitude, from man to woman, and for all the priests to hear the law, on the new moon of the seventh month.<verse eid="1ES 9:40"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:41"/>And he kept reading aloud in the large open area before the gateway of the temple from dawn until midday in the presence of both men and women, and the entire multitude gave its attention to the law.<verse eid="1ES 9:41"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:42"/>And Esdras the priest and reader of the law stood on the wooden platform that had been prepared,<verse eid="1ES 9:42"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:43"/>and beside him stood Mattathias, Sammous, Hananias, Azarias, Ourias, Hezekias and Baalsamos on his right<verse eid="1ES 9:43"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:44"/>and on his left Phadaios, Misael, Melchias, Lothasoubos, Nabarias, Zacharias.<verse eid="1ES 9:44"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:45"/>And when Esdras took up the book of the law in the presence of the multitude (for he was seated in the place of honor in the presence of all)<verse eid="1ES 9:45"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:46"/>and when he opened the law, they all stood straight. And Esdras blessed the Lord, God Most High, God Sabaoth, Almighty,<verse eid="1ES 9:46"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:47"/>and the whole multitude exclaimed "Amen," and when they lifted up their hands and fell to the ground, they did obeisance to God.<verse eid="1ES 9:47"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:48"/>The Leuites Iesous and Annious and Sarabias, Iadinos, Iakoubos, Sabbataios, Hautaias, Maiannas, Kalitas, Azarias and Iozabdos, Hananias, Phalias were teaching the law of the Lord and were reading the law of the Lord to the multitude, at the same time inspiring the reading.<verse eid="1ES 9:48"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:49"/>And Hattharates said to Esdras, the chief priest and reader, and to the Leuites who were teaching the multitude, with regard to all,<verse eid="1ES 9:49"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:50"/>"This day is holy to the Lord"-- and all were weeping when they heard the law--<verse eid="1ES 9:50"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:51"/>"so proceed, and eat fats, and drink sweet drinks, and send portions to those who do not have,<verse eid="1ES 9:51"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:52"/>for the day is holy to the Lord. And do not be sorrowful, for the Lord will exalt you."<verse eid="1ES 9:52"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:53"/>And the Leuites were commanding all the common people, saying, "This day is holy; do not be sorrowful."<verse eid="1ES 9:53"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:54"/>And they all departed to eat and drink and enjoy themselves and to give portions to those who had none and to be greatly joyful,<verse eid="1ES 9:54"/>
    <verse sid="1ES 9:55"/>because they were also inspired by the words by which they had been taught, and they had gathered together.<verse eid="1ES 9:55"/>
</usx>
