<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- SourceFormat: VL.  Converted to USX by the STEP project: 2023-08-18 -->
<usx version="2.0">
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <book code="2MA"/>



  <chapter sid="2MA 1"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:1"/>The fellow Judeans in Hierosolyma and those in the land of Judea, to their Judean brothers in Egypt, greetings and true peace.<verse eid="2MA 1:1"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:2"/>May God do good to you, and may he remember his covenant with Abraam and Isaak and Iakob, his faithful slaves.<verse eid="2MA 1:2"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:3"/>May he give you all a heart to worship him and to do his will with a strong heart and a willing spirit.<verse eid="2MA 1:3"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:4"/>May he open your heart to his law and his ordinances, and may he bring peace.<verse eid="2MA 1:4"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:5"/>May he heed your prayers and be reconciled to you, and may he not forsake you in a time of evil.<verse eid="2MA 1:5"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:6"/>We are now praying for you here.<verse eid="2MA 1:6"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:7"/>In the reign of Demetrius, in the one hundred sixty-ninth year, we Judeans wrote to you in the critical distress that came upon us in those years after Jason and his company revolted from the holy land and the kingdom<verse eid="2MA 1:7"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:8"/>and burned the gate and shed innocent blood. We prayed to the Lord and were heard, and we offered sacrifice and grain offering, and we lit the lamps and set out the loaves.<verse eid="2MA 1:8"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:9"/>And now see that you keep the days of the feast of tent pitching in the month of Chaseleu.<verse eid="2MA 1:9"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:10"/>In the one hundred eighty-eighth year. The people of Hierosolyma and of Judea and the senate and Ioudas, to Aristobulus, who is of the family of the anointed priests, teacher of King Ptolemy, and to the Judeans in Egypt, greetings and good health.<verse eid="2MA 1:10"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:11"/>Having been saved by God out of grave dangers we thank him greatly as men drawing up in battle-order against the king,<verse eid="2MA 1:11"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:12"/>for he drove out those who drew up in battle-order against the holy city.<verse eid="2MA 1:12"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:13"/>When the leader and his army, which seemed irresistible, reached Persia, they were cut to pieces in the temple of Nanea by a deception employed by the priests of the goddess Nanea.<verse eid="2MA 1:13"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:14"/>On the pretext of intending to marry her, Antiochus came to the place together with his Friends, to take most of the money in name of a dowry.<verse eid="2MA 1:14"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:15"/>When the priests of the temple of Nanea had set it out and that man had come with a few men inside the wall of the sacred precinct, they closed the temple as soon as he had entered it.<verse eid="2MA 1:15"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:16"/>Opening a secret door in the paneled ceiling, they threw stones and struck down the leader, and they dismembered them and cut off their heads and threw them to the people outside.<verse eid="2MA 1:16"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:17"/>Blessed in every way be our God, who has delivered up those who have behaved impiously.<verse eid="2MA 1:17"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:18"/>Since we intend to celebrate the purification of the temple on the twenty-fifth of Chaseleu, we thought it necessary to notify you in order that you also may celebrate it, as the feast of tent pitching and of the fire, given when Neemias, who built both the temple and the altar and offered sacrifices.<verse eid="2MA 1:18"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:19"/>For when our fathers were being led captive to Persia, the pious priests of that time took some of the fire of the altar and secretly hid it in a cavity, which had the appearance of a waterless cistern, where they kept it safe so that the place was unknown to anyone.<verse eid="2MA 1:19"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:20"/>But after many years had passed, when it pleased God, Neemias, having been sent by the king of Persia, sent the descendants of the priests who had hidden it after the fire. When they reported to us that they had not found fire but only marsh water, he ordered them to draw it up and bring it.<verse eid="2MA 1:20"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:21"/>When the materials for the sacrifices were presented, Neemias ordered the priests to sprinkle the water on the wood and on the things laid upon it.<verse eid="2MA 1:21"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:22"/>When this had been done and some time had passed and when the sun, which had been clouded over, shone out, a great fire was kindled so that all marvelled.<verse eid="2MA 1:22"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:23"/>And while the sacrifice was being consumed, the priests offered prayer-- the priests and everyone. Ionathas led, and the rest responded, as did Neemias.<verse eid="2MA 1:23"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:24"/>The prayer was to this effect: "O Lord, Lord God, Creator of all things, you are awe-inspiring and strong and just and merciful; you alone are king and are kind;<verse eid="2MA 1:24"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:25"/>you alone are bountiful; you alone are just and almighty and everlasting. You rescue Israel from every evil; you chose the fathers and sanctified them.<verse eid="2MA 1:25"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:26"/>Accept this sacrifice on behalf of all your people Israel, and preserve your portion, and make it holy.<verse eid="2MA 1:26"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:27"/>Gather together our scattered people; set free those who are slaves among the nations; look on those who are rejected and despised, and let the nations know that you are our God.<verse eid="2MA 1:27"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:28"/>Punish those who oppress and are insolent with pride.<verse eid="2MA 1:28"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:29"/>Plant your people in your holy place, as Moyses said."<verse eid="2MA 1:29"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:30"/>Then the priests sang the hymns.<verse eid="2MA 1:30"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:31"/>After the materials of the sacrifice had been consumed, Neemias ordered that the water that was left should be poured on large stones.<verse eid="2MA 1:31"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:32"/>When this was done, a flame blazed up, but when the light from the altar shone back, it was consumed.<verse eid="2MA 1:32"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:33"/>When this matter became known and it was reported to the king of the Persians that, in the place where the exiled priests had hidden the fire, the water had appeared, with which Neemias' men had purified the materials of the sacrifice,<verse eid="2MA 1:33"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:34"/>the king investigated the matter and enclosed the place and made it sacred.<verse eid="2MA 1:34"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:35"/>And with those persons whom the king favoured he exchanged many excellent gifts.<verse eid="2MA 1:35"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 1:36"/>Neemias' men called this "nephthar," which means purification, but by most people it is called "nephthai."<verse eid="2MA 1:36"/>



  <chapter sid="2MA 2"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:1"/>One finds in the records that the prophet Ieremias ordered those who were being deported to take some of the fire, as has been mentioned,<verse eid="2MA 2:1"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:2"/>and that the prophet, after giving them the law, commanded those who were being deported not to forget the ordinances of the Lord or to be led astray in their thoughts on seeing the gold and silver statues and their adornment.<verse eid="2MA 2:2"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:3"/>And with other similar words he exhorted them that the law should not depart from their hearts.<verse eid="2MA 2:3"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:4"/>It was also in the document that the prophet, having received an oracle, ordered that the tent and the ark should follow with him and that he went out to the mountain where Moyses had gone up and had seen the inheritance of God.<verse eid="2MA 2:4"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:5"/>Ieremias came and found a cave dwelling, and he brought there the tent and the ark and the altar of incense; then he sealed up the entrance.<verse eid="2MA 2:5"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:6"/>Some of those who followed him came up intending to mark the way but could not find it.<verse eid="2MA 2:6"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:7"/>When Ieremias learned of it, he rebuked them and declared, "The place shall remain unknown until God gathers his people together again and shows his mercy.<verse eid="2MA 2:7"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:8"/>Then the Lord will disclose these things, and the glory of the Lord will appear, and the cloud, as it showed itself to Moyses, and as Salomon prayed that the place be specially sanctified."<verse eid="2MA 2:8"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:9"/>It was also told that, possessing wisdom, he offered sacrifice for the dedication and completion of the temple.<verse eid="2MA 2:9"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:10"/>Just as Moyses prayed to the Lord and fire came down from heaven and ate up the sacrifices, so also Salomon prayed, and the fire came down and consumed the whole burnt offerings.<verse eid="2MA 2:10"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:11"/>And Moyses said, "They were eaten up because the sin offering had not been eaten."<verse eid="2MA 2:11"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:12"/>Likewise Salomon also kept the eight days.<verse eid="2MA 2:12"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:13"/>The same things are reported in the records and in the memoirs of Neemias, and also that he founded a library and collected the books about the kings and prophets, and the writings of Dauid, and letters of kings about votive offerings.<verse eid="2MA 2:13"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:14"/>In the same way Ioudas also collected all the books that had been lost on account of the war that had come upon us, and they are in our possession.<verse eid="2MA 2:14"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:15"/>So if you have need of them, send people to get them for you.<verse eid="2MA 2:15"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:16"/>Since, therefore, we are about to celebrate the purification, we write to you. You would do well to keep the days too.<verse eid="2MA 2:16"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:17"/>It is God who has saved all his people and has returned the inheritance to all, and the kingship and the priesthood and the sanctification,<verse eid="2MA 2:17"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:18"/>as he promised through the law. We therefore have hope in God that he will soon have mercy on us and will gather us from everywhere under heaven to his holy place, for he has rescued us from great evils and has cleansed the place.<verse eid="2MA 2:18"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:19"/>The story of Ioudas Makkabaios and his brothers and the purification of the greatest temple and the dedication of the altar<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = 'bômos'</char></note><verse eid="2MA 2:19"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:20"/>and further the wars against Antiochus Epiphanes and his son Eupator<verse eid="2MA 2:20"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:21"/>and the appearances that came from heaven to those who behaved themselves manfully for Judaism so that though few in number they seized the whole land and pursued the barbarian hordes<verse eid="2MA 2:21"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:22"/>and regained possession of the temple famous throughout the world and liberated the city and reestablished the laws that were about to be abolished, while the Lord with great kindness became gracious to them--<verse eid="2MA 2:22"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:23"/>all this, which has been set forth by Jason of Cyrene in five volumes, we shall attempt to condense into a single book.<verse eid="2MA 2:23"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:24"/>For considering the flood of figures involved and the difficulty there is for those who wish to enter upon the narratives of history because of the mass of material,<verse eid="2MA 2:24"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:25"/>we have aimed to please those who wish to read, to make it easy for those who are inclined to memorize and to profit all those who happen to read this.<verse eid="2MA 2:25"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:26"/>For us who have undertaken the toil of abbreviating, it is no light matter but calls for sweat and loss of sleep,<verse eid="2MA 2:26"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:27"/>just as it is not easy for one who prepares a banquet and seeks the benefit of others. Nevertheless, to secure the gratitude of many we will gladly endure the uncomfortable toil,<verse eid="2MA 2:27"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:28"/>leaving the responsibility for exact details to the compiler, while devoting our effort to arriving at the outlines of the condensation.<verse eid="2MA 2:28"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:29"/>For as the master builder of a new house must be concerned with the whole construction, while the one who undertakes its painting and decoration has to consider only what is suitable for its adornment, such in my judgment is the case with us.<verse eid="2MA 2:29"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:30"/>It is the duty of the original historian to occupy the ground, to discuss matters from every side and to take trouble with details,<verse eid="2MA 2:30"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:31"/>but the one who recasts the narrative should be allowed to strive for brevity of expression and to forego exhaustive treatment.<verse eid="2MA 2:31"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 2:32"/>At this point, therefore, let us begin our narrative, while adding just this to what has already been said; for it would be foolish to lengthen the preface while cutting short the narrative itself.<verse eid="2MA 2:32"/>



  <chapter sid="2MA 3"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:1"/>While the holy city was inhabited in unbroken peace and the laws were strictly observed because of the piety of the high priest Onias and his hatred of wickedness,<verse eid="2MA 3:1"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:2"/>it came about that the kings themselves honored the place and glorified the temple with the finest presents,<verse eid="2MA 3:2"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:3"/>even to the extent that Seleucus, the king of Asia, defrayed from his own revenues all the expenses connected with the ministry of the sacrifices.<verse eid="2MA 3:3"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:4"/>But a man named Simon, of the tribe of Balgea, who had been made captain of the temple, had a disagreement with the high priest about the administration of the city market.<verse eid="2MA 3:4"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:5"/>Since he could not prevail over Onias, he went to Apollonius son of Thraseas<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Göttingen Ed. = 'Thrasaios'</char></note>, who at that time was governor of Coele-Syria and Phoenicia,<verse eid="2MA 3:5"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:6"/>and reported to him that the treasury in Hierosolyma was full of untold sums of money, so that the amount of the funds could not be reckoned, and that they did not belong to the account of the sacrifices, but that it was possible for them to fall under the control of the king.<verse eid="2MA 3:6"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:7"/>When Apollonius met the king, he told him of the money about which he had been informed. And he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the king'</char></note> chose Heliodorus, who was in charge of his affairs, and sent him with commands to effect the removal of the reported wealth.<verse eid="2MA 3:7"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:8"/>Heliodorus at once set out on his journey, ostensibly to make a tour of inspection of the cities of Coele-Syria and Phoenicia but in fact to carry out the king's purpose.<verse eid="2MA 3:8"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:9"/>When he had arrived at Hierosolyma and had been kindly welcomed by the high priest of the city, he told about the disclosure that had been made and stated why he had come. But he inquired whether this really was the situation.<verse eid="2MA 3:9"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:10"/>The high priest explained that there were some deposits belonging to widows and orphans<verse eid="2MA 3:10"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:11"/>and also some money of Hyrcanus son of Tobias, a man of very prominent position, and that it totalled in all four hundred talents of silver and two hundred of gold. To such an extent the impious Simon had misrepresented the facts.<verse eid="2MA 3:11"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:12"/>And he said that it was utterly impossible that wrong should be done to those people who had trusted in the holiness of the place and in the sanctity and inviolability of the temple that is honored throughout the whole wide world.<verse eid="2MA 3:12"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:13"/>But the other one, because of the commands he had from the king, said that this money must in any case be confiscated for the king's treasury.<verse eid="2MA 3:13"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:14"/>So he set a day and went in to direct the inspection of these funds. There was no little distress throughout the whole city.<verse eid="2MA 3:14"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:15"/>The priests prostrated themselves before the altar in their priestly vestments and called toward heaven upon him who had given the law about deposits, that he should keep them safe for those who had deposited them.<verse eid="2MA 3:15"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:16"/>To see the appearance of the high priest was to be wounded at heart, for his face and the change in his color disclosed the anguish of his soul.<verse eid="2MA 3:16"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:17"/>For terror and bodily trembling had come over the man, which plainly showed to those who looked at him the pain lodged in his heart.<verse eid="2MA 3:17"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:18"/>People also were hurrying out of their houses in crowds to the supplication of the entire people because the holy place was about to be brought into dishonor.<verse eid="2MA 3:18"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:19"/>Women, girded with sackcloth under their breasts, thronged the streets. Of the virgins who were kept indoors, some ran together to the gates and some to the walls, while others peered out of the windows.<verse eid="2MA 3:19"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:20"/>And holding up their hands to heaven, they all made supplication.<verse eid="2MA 3:20"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:21"/>There was something pitiable in the prostration of the whole populace and the anxiety of the high priest in his great anguish.<verse eid="2MA 3:21"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:22"/>While they were calling upon the Almighty Lord that he would keep what had been entrusted safe and secure for those who had entrusted it,<verse eid="2MA 3:22"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:23"/>Heliodorus went on with what had been decided.<verse eid="2MA 3:23"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:24"/>But when he was present at the treasury with his bodyguards, then and there the Sovereign of spirits and of all authority caused so great a manifestation, that all who had been so bold as to accompany him were astounded by the power of God and became faint with terror.<verse eid="2MA 3:24"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:25"/>For there appeared to them a magnificently caparisoned horse with a frightening rider; it rushed furiously at Heliodorus and struck at him with its front hoofs. He who sat upon it was seen to have a full golden harness.<verse eid="2MA 3:25"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:26"/>Two young men also appeared to him, remarkably strong, gloriously beautiful and splendidly dressed, who stood on either side of him and flogged him continuously, inflicting many blows on him.<verse eid="2MA 3:26"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:27"/>When he suddenly fell to the ground and deep darkness came over him, they took him up, put him on a stretcher<verse eid="2MA 3:27"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:28"/>and carried him, who had just entered the aforesaid treasury with a great retinue and all his bodyguard but was now with all his weapons unable to help himself, away. They<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:28</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Göttingen Ed. = 'he'</char></note> thus clearly recognized the dominance of God.<verse eid="2MA 3:28"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:29"/>While he lay prostrate, speechless because of the divine intervention and deprived of any hope of recovery,<verse eid="2MA 3:29"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:30"/>they praised the Lord who had acted marvellously for his own place. And the temple, which a little while before was full of fear and disturbance, was filled with joy and gladness now that the Almighty Lord had appeared.<verse eid="2MA 3:30"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:31"/>Some of Heliodorus' friends quickly begged Onias to call upon the Most High to grant life to one who was lying quite at his last breath.<verse eid="2MA 3:31"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:32"/>So the high priest having become suspicious that the king might get the notion that some foul play had been perpetrated by the Judeans with regard to Heliodorus, offered sacrifice for the man's recovery.<verse eid="2MA 3:32"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:33"/>While the high priest was making an atonement, the same young men appeared again to Heliodorus dressed in the same clothing, and they stood and said, "Be very grateful to the high priest Onias, since for his sake the Lord has granted you your life.<verse eid="2MA 3:33"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:34"/>And see that you, who have been flogged by heaven, report to all people the majestic power of God." Having said this they vanished.<verse eid="2MA 3:34"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:35"/>Then Heliodorus offered sacrifice to the Lord and made very great vows to the Savior of his life, and having bidden Onias farewell, he marched off with his forces to the king.<verse eid="2MA 3:35"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:36"/>He bore testimony to all concerning the deeds of the supreme God, which he had seen with his own eyes.<verse eid="2MA 3:36"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:37"/>When the king asked Heliodorus what sort of person would be suitable to be sent on another mission to Hierosolyma, he replied,<verse eid="2MA 3:37"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:38"/>"If you have any enemy or plotter against your government, send him there, for you will get him back thoroughly flogged, if he survives at all, for there is certainly some divine power about the place.<verse eid="2MA 3:38"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:39"/>For he who has his dwelling in heaven watches over that place himself and brings it aid, and he strikes and destroys those who come to do it injury."<verse eid="2MA 3:39"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 3:40"/>This was the outcome of the episode of Heliodorus and the protection of the treasury.<verse eid="2MA 3:40"/>



  <chapter sid="2MA 4"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:1"/>The previously mentioned Simon, who had informed about the money against his own country, slandered Onias, saying that it was he who had incited Heliodorus and had been the real cause of the evils.<verse eid="2MA 4:1"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:2"/>He dared to designate as a plotter against the government the man who was the benefactor of the city, the protector of his compatriots and a zealot for the laws.<verse eid="2MA 4:2"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:3"/>When his hatred progressed to such a degree that even murders were committed by one of Simon's approved agents,<verse eid="2MA 4:3"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:4"/>Onias recognized that the rivalry was serious and that Apollonius son of Menestheus, and governor of Coele-Syria and Phoenicia, was intensifying the malice of Simon.<verse eid="2MA 4:4"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:5"/>So he appealed to the king, not accusing his compatriots but having in view the welfare, both public and private, of all the people.<verse eid="2MA 4:5"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:6"/>For he saw that without the king's attention public affairs could not again reach a peaceful settlement and that Simon would not stop his folly.<verse eid="2MA 4:6"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:7"/>When Seleucus died and Antiochus, who was called Epiphanes, succeeded to the kingdom, Jason the brother of Onias obtained the high priesthood by corruption,<verse eid="2MA 4:7"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:8"/>promising the king at an interview three hundred sixty talents of silver and from another source of revenue eighty talents.<verse eid="2MA 4:8"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:9"/>In addition to this he promised to pay one hundred fifty more, if permission were given to establish by his authority a gymnasium and a body of youth for it and to draw up the list of the 'Antiochenes' amongst those in Hierosolyma.<verse eid="2MA 4:9"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:10"/>When the king assented and he came to office, he at once shifted his compatriots over to the Greek way of life.<verse eid="2MA 4:10"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:11"/>He set aside the existing humane royal concessions to the Judeans, secured through Ioannes the father of Eupolemus, who went on the mission to establish friendship and alliance with the Romans, and he destroyed the polity's lawful ways of living and introduced new customs contrary to the law.<verse eid="2MA 4:11"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:12"/>He took delight in establishing a gymnasium right under the acropolis, and subjugating them, he induced the noblest of the young men to wear the Greek hat.<verse eid="2MA 4:12"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:13"/>There was such an extreme of hellenization and increase in the adoption of allophylism<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'alien ways'</char></note> because of the surpassing wickedness of Jason, who was impious and no true high priest,<verse eid="2MA 4:13"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:14"/>that the priests were no longer intent upon their ministry at the altar. Rather, despising the shrine and neglecting the sacrifices, they hurried to take part in the unlawful distribution of the oil<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'of ointments'</char></note> in the wrestling arena after the signal for the discus throwing,<verse eid="2MA 4:14"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:15"/>disdaining the honors prized by their ancestors and putting the highest value upon Greek forms of prestige.<verse eid="2MA 4:15"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:16"/>For this reason heavy disaster overtook them, and those whose ways of living they admired and wished to imitate completely became their enemies and avengers.<verse eid="2MA 4:16"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:17"/>It is no light thing to show impiety to the divine laws-- a fact that later events will make clear.<verse eid="2MA 4:17"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:18"/>When the quinquennial games were being held at Tyre and the king was present,<verse eid="2MA 4:18"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:19"/>the vile Jason sent envoys, chosen as being 'Antiochian' citizens from Hierosolyma, to carry three hundred silver drachmas for the sacrifice to Heracles. Those who carried the money, however, thought best not to use it for sacrifice, because that was inappropriate, but to expend it for another purpose.<verse eid="2MA 4:19"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:20"/>So this money was intended by the sender for the sacrifice to Heracles, but by the decision of its carriers it was applied to the construction of triremes.<verse eid="2MA 4:20"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:21"/>When Apollonius the son of Menestheus was sent to Egypt for the coronation of Philometor as king, Antiochus learned that the other had become hostile to his government, and he took measures for his own security. Therefore upon arriving at Joppe he proceeded to Hierosolyma.<verse eid="2MA 4:21"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:22"/>He was welcomed magnificently by Jason and the city and ushered in with a blaze of torches and with shouts. Then he marched off to Phoenicia in the same manner.<verse eid="2MA 4:22"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:23"/>After a period of three years Jason sent Menelaus, the brother of the previously mentioned Simon, to carry the money to the king and to complete the records of essential business.<verse eid="2MA 4:23"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:24"/>But he, when presented to the king, extolled him with an air of authority and secured the high priesthood for himself, outbidding Jason by three hundred talents of silver.<verse eid="2MA 4:24"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:25"/>After receiving the king's commands he returned, possessing no qualification for the high priesthood but having the hot temper of a cruel tyrant and the rage of a savage wild beast.<verse eid="2MA 4:25"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:26"/>So Jason, who after supplanting his own brother was supplanted by another man, was driven as a fugitive into the land of Ammon.<verse eid="2MA 4:26"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:27"/>Although Menelaus continued to hold the office, he did not pay regularly any of the money promised to the king.<verse eid="2MA 4:27"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:28"/>So when Sostratus the captain of the acropolis kept requesting payment-- for the collection of the revenue was his responsibility-- the two of them were summoned by the king on account of this issue.<verse eid="2MA 4:28"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:29"/>Menelaus left his own brother Lysimachus as deputy in the high priesthood, while Sostratus left Crates, the commander of the Cyprian troops.<verse eid="2MA 4:29"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:30"/>While such was the state of affairs, it happened that the people of Tarsus and of Mallus revolted because their cities had been given as a present to Antiochis, the king's concubine.<verse eid="2MA 4:30"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:31"/>So the king went hurriedly to settle the trouble, leaving Andronicus, a man of high rank, to act as his deputy.<verse eid="2MA 4:31"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:32"/>But Menelaus, thinking he had obtained a suitable opportunity, stole some of the gold vessels of the temple and gave them to Andronicus; other vessels, as it happened, he had sold to Tyre and the neighboring cities.<verse eid="2MA 4:32"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:33"/>When Onias became fully aware of these acts, he publicly exposed them, having first withdrawn to a place of sanctuary at Daphne near Antioch.<verse eid="2MA 4:33"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:34"/>Therefore Menelaus, taking Andronicus aside, urged him to kill Onias. Andronicus came to Onias, and resorting to treachery, offered him sworn pledges and gave him his right hand; he persuaded him, though still suspicious, to come out from the place of sanctuary; then, with no regard for justice, he immediately put him out of the way.<verse eid="2MA 4:34"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:35"/>For this reason not only Judeans, but many also of other nations, were grieved and displeased at the unjust slaughter of the man.<verse eid="2MA 4:35"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:36"/>When the king returned from the region of Cilicia, the Judeans in the city appealed to him with regard to the unreasonable murder of Onias, and the Greeks shared their hatred of the crime.<verse eid="2MA 4:36"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:37"/>Therefore Antiochus was grieved at heart and filled with pity and wept because of the moderation and good conduct of the deceased.<verse eid="2MA 4:37"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:38"/>Inflamed with anger, he immediately stripped off the purple robe from Andronicus, tore off his clothes and led him around the whole city to that very place where he had committed the outrage against Onias, and there he removed the bloodthirsty fellow from the world. The Lord thus repaid him with the punishment he deserved.<verse eid="2MA 4:38"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:39"/>When many acts of sacrilege had been committed in the city by Lysimachus with the connivance of Menelaus and when report of them had spread abroad, the populace gathered against Lysimachus, because many of the gold vessels had already been stolen.<verse eid="2MA 4:39"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:40"/>Since the crowds were becoming aroused and filled with anger, Lysimachus armed about three thousand men and launched an unjust attack under the leadership of a certain Auranus, a man advanced in years and no less advanced in folly.<verse eid="2MA 4:40"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:41"/>But when they became aware that Lysimachus was attacking them, some picked up stones, some blocks of wood, and others took handfuls of the ashes that were lying around and threw them in wild confusion at Lysimachus' men.<verse eid="2MA 4:41"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:42"/>As a result, they wounded many of them and killed some and put all the rest to flight; the temple robber himself they killed close by the treasury.<verse eid="2MA 4:42"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:43"/>Charges were brought against Menelaus about this incident.<verse eid="2MA 4:43"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:44"/>When the king came to Tyre, three men sent by the senate presented the case before him.<verse eid="2MA 4:44"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:45"/>But Menelaus, already as good as beaten, promised a substantial bribe to Ptolemy son of Dorymenes to win over the king.<verse eid="2MA 4:45"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:46"/>Therefore, Ptolemy, taking the king aside into a colonnade as if for refreshment, induced the king to change his mind.<verse eid="2MA 4:46"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:47"/>Menelaus, the cause of all the trouble, he acquitted of the charges against him, while he sentenced to death those unfortunate men, who would have been freed uncondemned, if they had pleaded even before Scythians.<verse eid="2MA 4:47"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:48"/>And so those who had spoken for the city and the villages and the holy vessels quickly suffered the unjust penalty.<verse eid="2MA 4:48"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:49"/>Therefore even the Tyrians, showing their hatred of the crime, provided magnificently for their funeral.<verse eid="2MA 4:49"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 4:50"/>But Menelaus, because of the greed of those in power, remained in office, growing in wickedness, having become the chief plotter against his compatriots.<verse eid="2MA 4:50"/>



  <chapter sid="2MA 5"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:1"/>About this time Antiochus made his second invasion of Egypt.<verse eid="2MA 5:1"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:2"/>And it happened that, for almost forty days, there appeared over all the city golden-clad cavalry charging through the air, in companies fully armed with lances and drawn daggers--<verse eid="2MA 5:2"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:3"/>troops of cavalry drawn up, attacks and counterattacks made on this side and on that, brandishing of shields, massing of spears, hurling of missiles, the flash of golden trappings and armor of all kinds.<verse eid="2MA 5:3"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:4"/>Therefore everyone prayed that the apparition might prove to have been a good omen.<verse eid="2MA 5:4"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:5"/>When a false rumor arose that Antiochus was dead, Jason took no fewer than a thousand men and suddenly made an assault on the city. When the troops on the wall had been forced back and at last the city was being taken, Menelaus took refuge in the acropolis.<verse eid="2MA 5:5"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:6"/>But Jason kept relentlessly slaughtering his compatriots, not realizing that success at the cost of one's kindred is the greatest misfortune but imagining that he was setting up trophies of victory over enemies and not over compatriots.<verse eid="2MA 5:6"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:7"/>He did not, however, gain control of the government; in the end he got only disgrace from his conspiracy and fled again into the Ammanitis.<verse eid="2MA 5:7"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:8"/>Finally he met a miserable end. Accused<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Göttingen Ed. = 'confined'</char></note> before Aretas the ruler of the Arabs, fleeing from city to city, pursued by everyone, hated as a rebel against the laws and abhorred as the executioner of his country and his compatriots, he was cast ashore in Egypt.<verse eid="2MA 5:8"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:9"/>There he, who had driven many from their own country into exile, died in exile, having embarked to go to the Spartans in hope of finding protection because of their kinship.<verse eid="2MA 5:9"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:10"/>He who had cast out many to lie unburied had no one to mourn for him; he had no funeral of any sort and no place in his ancestral tomb.<verse eid="2MA 5:10"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:11"/>When news of what had happened reached the king, he took it to mean that Judea was in revolt. So, raging inwardly, he left Egypt and took the city by force.<verse eid="2MA 5:11"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:12"/>He commanded his soldiers to cut down relentlessly everyone they met and to kill those who went into their houses.<verse eid="2MA 5:12"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:13"/>Then there were massacres of young and old, destruction of women and children, slayings of virgins and infants.<verse eid="2MA 5:13"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:14"/>Within the total of three days eighty thousand were destroyed, forty thousand in hand-to-hand fighting, and as many were sold into slavery as were killed.<verse eid="2MA 5:14"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:15"/>Not content with this, Antiochus dared to enter the most holy temple in all the world, guided by Menelaus, who had become a traitor both to the laws and to his country,<verse eid="2MA 5:15"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:16"/>taking the sacred vessels with his polluted hands and pulling down with profane hands the votive offerings that other kings had made to enhance the glory and honor of the place.<verse eid="2MA 5:16"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:17"/>Antiochus was elated in spirit and did not perceive that the Lord was angered for a little while because of the sins of those who lived in the city and that this was the reason he was disregarding the place.<verse eid="2MA 5:17"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:18"/>But if it had not happened that they were involved in many sins, this man would have been flogged and turned back from his rash act as soon as he came forward, just as Heliodorus had been, whom King Seleucus sent to inspect the treasury.<verse eid="2MA 5:18"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:19"/>But the Lord did not choose the nation for the sake of the place, but the place for the sake of the nation.<verse eid="2MA 5:19"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:20"/>Therefore the place itself shared in the misfortunes that befell the nation and afterward participated in its benefits, and what was forsaken in the wrath of the Almighty was restored again in all its glory when the great Lord became reconciled.<verse eid="2MA 5:20"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:21"/>So Antiochus carried off eighteen hundred talents from the temple and hurried away to Antioch, thinking in his arrogance that he could make the land navigable and the sea passable on foot, because his heart was elated.<verse eid="2MA 5:21"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:22"/>He left governors to oppress the people: at Hierosolyma, Philip, by birth a Phrygian and in character more barbarous than the man who appointed him;<verse eid="2MA 5:22"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:23"/>and on Garizim<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:23</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Göttingen Ed. = 'Argarizin'</char></note>, Andronicus, and besides these Menelaus, who lorded it over the citizens worse than the others did because of his malice toward the Judean citizens.<verse eid="2MA 5:23"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:24"/>Antiochus sent Apollonius, the captain of the Mysians, with an army of twenty-two thousand and ordered him to kill all the grown men and to sell the women and boys as slaves.<verse eid="2MA 5:24"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:25"/>When this man arrived in Hierosolyma, he pretended to be peaceably disposed and waited until the holy sabbath day; then, finding the Judeans not at work, he ordered his troops to parade under arms.<verse eid="2MA 5:25"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:26"/>He put to the sword all those who came out to see them, then rushed into the city with his armed warriors and killed great numbers of people.<verse eid="2MA 5:26"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 5:27"/>But Ioudas Makkabaios, with about nine others, got away to the wilderness and kept himself and his companions alive in the mountains as wild animals do; they continued to live on what grew wild so that they might not share in the defilement.<verse eid="2MA 5:27"/>



  <chapter sid="2MA 6"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:1"/>Not long after this, the king sent an Athenian senator to compel the Judeans to forsake their ancestral laws and no longer to live by the laws of God--<verse eid="2MA 6:1"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:2"/>also to pollute the shrine in Hierosolyma and to call it the shrine of Olympian Zeus and to call the one on Garizim the shrine of Zeus-the-Friend-of-Strangers, as the people who lived in that place had petitioned.<verse eid="2MA 6:2"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:3"/>Harsh and utterly grievous was the onslaught of evil.<verse eid="2MA 6:3"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:4"/>For the temple was filled with debauchery and revelling by the nations, who dallied with prostitutes and had intercourse with women within the sacred precincts, and besides brought in things for sacrifice that were unfit.<verse eid="2MA 6:4"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:5"/>The altar was covered with abominable offerings that were forbidden by the laws.<verse eid="2MA 6:5"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:6"/>People could neither keep the sabbath nor observe their ancestral feasts nor so much as confess themselves to be Judeans.<verse eid="2MA 6:6"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:7"/>On the monthly celebration of the king's birthday, the Judeans were taken, under bitter constraint, to partake of the sacrifices, and when a feast of Dionysus was celebrated, they were compelled to wear wreathes of ivy and to walk in the procession in honor of Dionysus.<verse eid="2MA 6:7"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:8"/>At the suggestion of Ptolemy a vote was issued to the neighboring Greek cities that they should adopt the same policy toward the Judeans and make them partake of the sacrifices<verse eid="2MA 6:8"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:9"/>and should kill those who did not choose to change over to Greek customs. One could see, therefore, the misery that had come upon them.<verse eid="2MA 6:9"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:10"/>For example, two women were brought in for having circumcised their children. They publicly paraded them around the city with their babies hanging at their breasts and then hurled them down headlong from the wall.<verse eid="2MA 6:10"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:11"/>Others who had assembled in the caves nearby in order to observe the seventh day secretly were betrayed to Philip and were all burned together, because their piety kept them from defending themselves, in view of their regard for that most holy day.<verse eid="2MA 6:11"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:12"/>Now I urge those who read this book not to be depressed by such calamities, but to recognize that these punishments were designed not to destroy but to discipline our people.<verse eid="2MA 6:12"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:13"/>In fact, it is a sign of great kindness not to let the impious alone for long but to punish them immediately.<verse eid="2MA 6:13"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:14"/>For in the case of the other nations the Lord waits patiently to punish them until they have reached the full measure of their sins, but he does not deal in this way with us<verse eid="2MA 6:14"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:15"/>in order that he may not take vengeance on us afterward, when our sins have reached their height.<verse eid="2MA 6:15"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:16"/>Therefore he never withdraws his mercy from us. While he disciplines us with calamities, he does not forsake his own people.<verse eid="2MA 6:16"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:17"/>Let what we have said serve as a reminder; we must go on briefly with the story.<verse eid="2MA 6:17"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:18"/>Eleazaros, one of the scribes in high position, a man now advanced in age and of noble presence, was being forced to open his mouth to eat swine's flesh.<verse eid="2MA 6:18"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:19"/>But he, welcoming death with honor rather than life with pollution, went up to the rack of his own accord, spitting out the flesh,<verse eid="2MA 6:19"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:20"/>as all ought to do who have the courage to refuse things that it is not right to taste, even for the natural love of life.<verse eid="2MA 6:20"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:21"/>Those who were in charge of that unlawful sacrifice took the man aside because of their long acquaintance with him and privately urged him to bring meat of his own providing, proper for him to use, and to pretend that he was eating the flesh of the sacrificial meal that had been ordered by the king<verse eid="2MA 6:21"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:22"/>so that by doing this he might be saved from death and be treated kindly on account of his old friendship with them.<verse eid="2MA 6:22"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:23"/>But making a high resolve, worthy of his years and the dignity of his old age and the grey hairs that he had reached with distinction and his excellent bearing even from childhood, and moreover according to the holy God-given law, he declared himself quickly, telling them to send him to Hades.<verse eid="2MA 6:23"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:24"/>"To pretend is not worthy of our time of life," he said, "for many of the young might suppose that Eleazaros in his ninetieth year had gone over to allophylism<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'alien ways'</char></note>,<verse eid="2MA 6:24"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:25"/>and through my pretence, for the sake of living a brief moment longer, they would be led astray because of me, while I defile and disgrace my old age.<verse eid="2MA 6:25"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:26"/>Even if for the present I would avoid the punishment of mortals, yet whether I live or die I shall not escape the hands of the Almighty.<verse eid="2MA 6:26"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:27"/>Therefore, by bravely giving up my life now, I will show myself worthy of my old age<verse eid="2MA 6:27"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:28"/>and leave to the young a noble example of how to die a good death willingly and nobly for the revered and holy laws." When he had said this, he went at once to the rack.<verse eid="2MA 6:28"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:29"/>Those who a little before had acted toward him with goodwill now changed to ill will, because the words he had uttered were in their opinion sheer madness.<verse eid="2MA 6:29"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:30"/>When he was about to die under the blows, he groaned aloud and said: "It is clear to the Lord in his holy knowledge that, though I might have been saved from death, I am enduring terrible sufferings in my body under this beating, but in my soul I am glad to suffer these things, because I fear him."<verse eid="2MA 6:30"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 6:31"/>So in this way he died, leaving in his death an example of nobility and a memorial of courage, not only to the young but also to the great body of his nation.<verse eid="2MA 6:31"/>



  <chapter sid="2MA 7"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:1"/>It happened also that seven brothers and their mother were arrested and were being compelled by the king, under torture with whips and thongs, to partake of unlawful swine's flesh.<verse eid="2MA 7:1"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:2"/>One of them, acting as their spokesman, said, "What do you intend to ask and learn from us? For we are ready to die rather than transgress our ancestral laws."<verse eid="2MA 7:2"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:3"/>The king fell into a rage and ordered to have frying-pans and cauldrons heated.<verse eid="2MA 7:3"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:4"/>These were heated immediately, and he ordered that the tongue of their spokesman be cut out and that they scalp him and cut off his hands and feet, while the rest of the brothers and the mother looked on.<verse eid="2MA 7:4"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:5"/>When he was utterly helpless, the king ordered them to take him to the fire, still breathing, and to fry him in a pan. The smoke from the frying-pan spread widely, but the brothers and their mother encouraged one another to die nobly, saying,<verse eid="2MA 7:5"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:6"/>"The Lord God is watching over us and in truth has compassion on us, as Moyses declared in his song that bore witness against the people to their faces, when he said, 'And he will have compassion on his slaves.' "<verse eid="2MA 7:6"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:7"/>After the first brother had died in this way, they brought forward the second for their sport. They tore off the skin of his head with the hair and asked him, "Will you eat rather than have your body punished limb by limb?"<verse eid="2MA 7:7"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:8"/>He replied in his ancestral language and said to them, "No." Therefore he in turn underwent tortures as the first had done.<verse eid="2MA 7:8"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:9"/>And when he was at his last breath, he said, "You accursed wretch, you dismiss us from this present life, but the King of the universe will raise us up to an everlasting renewal of life, because we have died for his laws."<verse eid="2MA 7:9"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:10"/>After him, the third was the victim of their sport. When it was demanded, he quickly put out his tongue and courageously stretched forth his hands<verse eid="2MA 7:10"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:11"/>and said nobly, "I got these from Heaven, and because of his laws I disdain them, and from him I hope to get them back again."<verse eid="2MA 7:11"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:12"/>As a result the king himself and those with him were astonished at the young man's spirit, for he regarded his sufferings as nothing.<verse eid="2MA 7:12"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:13"/>After he too had died, they maltreated and tortured the fourth in the same way.<verse eid="2MA 7:13"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:14"/>When he was near death, he said, "It is desirable that those who die at the hands of human beings should cherish the hope God gives of being raised again by him. But for you there will be no resurrection to life!"<verse eid="2MA 7:14"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:15"/>Next they brought forward the fifth and maltreated him.<verse eid="2MA 7:15"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:16"/>But he looked at him and said, "Because you have authority among human beings, though you also are mortal, you do what you please. But do not think that our people have been forsaken by God.<verse eid="2MA 7:16"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:17"/>Keep on, and see how his mighty power will torture you and your descendants!"<verse eid="2MA 7:17"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:18"/>After him they brought forward the sixth. And when he was about to die, he said, "Do not deceive yourself in vain. For we are suffering these things on our own account, because of our sins against our own God. Therefore astounding things have happened.<verse eid="2MA 7:18"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:19"/>But do not think that you will go unpunished for having tried to fight against God!"<verse eid="2MA 7:19"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:20"/>The mother was especially admirable and worthy of honorable memory. Although she saw her seven sons perish within the course of a single day, she bore it with good courage because of her hope in the Lord.<verse eid="2MA 7:20"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:21"/>She encouraged each of them in their ancestral language. Filled with a noble spirit, she reinforced her woman's reasoning with a man's courage and said to them,<verse eid="2MA 7:21"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:22"/>"I do not know how you came into being in my womb. It was not I who gave you life and breath, nor I who set in order the elements within each of you.<verse eid="2MA 7:22"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:23"/>Therefore the Creator of the world, who shaped the origin of man and devised the origin of all things, will in his mercy give life and breath back to you again, since you now forget yourselves for the sake of his laws."<verse eid="2MA 7:23"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:24"/>Antiochus felt that he was being treated with contempt, and he was suspicious of her reproachful tone. The youngest brother being still alive, Antiochus not only appealed to him in words but also promised with oaths that he would make him rich and enviable, if he would turn from his ancestral ways, and that he would take him for his Friend and entrust him with public affairs.<verse eid="2MA 7:24"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:25"/>Since the young man would not listen to him at all, the king called the mother to him and urged her to advise the youth to save himself.<verse eid="2MA 7:25"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:26"/>After much urging on his part, she undertook to persuade her son.<verse eid="2MA 7:26"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:27"/>But, leaning close to him, she spoke in their ancestral language as follows, deriding the cruel tyrant: "My son, have pity on me. I carried you nine months in my womb and nursed you for three years and have reared you and brought you up to this point in your life and have taken care of you.<verse eid="2MA 7:27"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:28"/>I implore you, my child, to look at the heaven and the earth and see everything that is in them and recognize that God did not make them out of things that existed. And in the same way the human race came into being.<verse eid="2MA 7:28"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:29"/>Do not fear this hangman, but prove worthy of your brothers and accept death so that in his mercy I may get you back again along with your brothers."<verse eid="2MA 7:29"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:30"/>While she was still speaking, the young man said, "What are you waiting for? I will not obey the king's ordinance, but I obey the ordinance of the law that was given to our fathers through Moyses.<verse eid="2MA 7:30"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:31"/>But you, who have contrived all sorts of evil against the Hebrews, will certainly not escape the hands of God.<verse eid="2MA 7:31"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:32"/>For we are suffering because of our own sins.<verse eid="2MA 7:32"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:33"/>And if our living Lord is angry for a little while, to rebuke and discipline us, he will again be reconciled with his own slaves.<verse eid="2MA 7:33"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:34"/>But you, unholy wretch, you most defiled of all mortals, do not be elated in vain and puffed up by uncertain hopes, when you raise your hand against the children of heaven.<verse eid="2MA 7:34"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:35"/>You have not yet escaped the judgment of the Almighty, all-seeing God.<verse eid="2MA 7:35"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:36"/>For our brothers, after enduring a brief suffering, have fallen heir to everlasting life under the power of a divine covenant, but you, by the judgment of God, will receive just punishment for your arrogance.<verse eid="2MA 7:36"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:37"/>I, like my brothers, give up body and life for our ancestral laws, appealing to God to show mercy soon to our nation and by torments and plagues to make you acknowledge that he alone is God<verse eid="2MA 7:37"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:38"/>and through me and my brothers to bring to an end the wrath of the Almighty that has justly fallen on our whole nation."<verse eid="2MA 7:38"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:39"/>The king fell into a rage and handled him worse than the others, being exasperated at his scorn.<verse eid="2MA 7:39"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:40"/>So he died in his integrity, putting his whole trust in the Lord.<verse eid="2MA 7:40"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:41"/>Last of all, the mother died, after her sons.<verse eid="2MA 7:41"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 7:42"/>Let this be enough, then, about the eating of sacrifices and the extreme tortures.<verse eid="2MA 7:42"/>



  <chapter sid="2MA 8"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:1"/>Meanwhile Ioudas, who was also called Makkabaios, and his companions secretly entered the villages and summoned their kindred and enlisted those who had continued in the Judean faith, and so they gathered about six thousand.<verse eid="2MA 8:1"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:2"/>They implored the Lord to look upon the people who were oppressed by all and to have pity on the shrine that had been profaned by the impious,<verse eid="2MA 8:2"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:3"/>to have mercy on the city that was being destroyed and about to be leveled to the ground and to hearken to the blood that cried out to him,<verse eid="2MA 8:3"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:4"/>to remember also the lawless slaughter of the innocent babies and the blasphemies committed against his name and to show his hatred of evil.<verse eid="2MA 8:4"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:5"/>As soon as Makkabaios got his army organized, he became insuperable for the nations, for the wrath of the Lord had turned to mercy.<verse eid="2MA 8:5"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:6"/>Coming without warning, he would set fire to towns and villages. He captured strategic positions and put to flight not a few of the enemy.<verse eid="2MA 8:6"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:7"/>He found the nights most advantageous for such attacks. And talk of his valor spread everywhere.<verse eid="2MA 8:7"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:8"/>When Philip saw that the man was gaining ground little by little and that he was pushing ahead with more frequent successes, he wrote to Ptolemy, the governor of Coele-Syria and Phoenicia, to come to the aid of the king's government.<verse eid="2MA 8:8"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:9"/>Then Ptolemy promptly appointed Nikanor son of Patroclus, one of the king's chief Friends, and sent him, in command of no fewer than twenty thousand nations of all races, to wipe out the whole race of Judea. He associated with him Gorgias, a general and a man of experience in military service.<verse eid="2MA 8:9"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:10"/>Nikanor determined to make up for the king the tribute due to the Romans, two thousand talents, by selling the captured Judeans into slavery.<verse eid="2MA 8:10"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:11"/>So he immediately sent to the towns on the seacoast, inviting them to buy Judean slaves and promising to hand over ninety slaves for a talent, not expecting the judgment from the Almighty that was about to overtake him.<verse eid="2MA 8:11"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:12"/>Word came to Ioudas concerning Nikanor's invasion, and when he told his companions of the arrival of the army,<verse eid="2MA 8:12"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:13"/>those who were cowardly and distrustful of God's justice ran off and got away.<verse eid="2MA 8:13"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:14"/>Others sold all their remaining property and at the same time implored the Lord to rescue those who had been sold by the ungodly Nikanor before he ever met them,<verse eid="2MA 8:14"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:15"/>if not for their own sake, then for the sake of the covenants made with their fathers and because he had called them by his holy and glorious name.<verse eid="2MA 8:15"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:16"/>But Makkabaios gathered his forces together, to the number six thousand, and exhorted them not to be frightened by the enemy and not to fear the great multitude of nations, who were wickedly coming against them, but to fight nobly,<verse eid="2MA 8:16"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:17"/>keeping before their eyes the outrage that they had lawlessly committed against the holy place and the torture of the derided city and, besides, the destruction of the ancestral polity.<verse eid="2MA 8:17"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:18"/>"For they trust to arms and acts of daring," he said, "but we trust in the Almighty God, who is able with a single nod to strike down those who are coming against us and even, if necessary, the whole world."<verse eid="2MA 8:18"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:19"/>Moreover, he told them of the occasions when help came to their ancestors; how, in the time of Sennachereim, when one hundred and eighty-five thousand perished,<verse eid="2MA 8:19"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:20"/>and the time of the battle against the Galatians that took place in Babylonia, how they saw action, eight thousand of them in all, along with four thousand Macedonians; yet when the Macedonians were at a loss, the eight thousand, by the help that came to them from heaven, destroyed one hundred twenty thousand Galatians and took a great amount of booty.<verse eid="2MA 8:20"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:21"/>With these words he filled them with courage and made them ready to die for the laws and the fatherland; then he divided his army into four parts.<verse eid="2MA 8:21"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:22"/>He appointed his brothers also, Simon and Iosepos and Ionathan, as leaders of each division, putting fifteen hundred men under each.<verse eid="2MA 8:22"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:23"/>Besides, he appointed Eleazaros to read aloud from the holy book and gave the watchword, "Divine Help"; then, leading the first maniple himself, he joined battle with Nikanor.<verse eid="2MA 8:23"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:24"/>With the Almighty as their ally, they killed more than nine thousand of the enemy and wounded and disabled most of Nikanor's army and forced them all to flee.<verse eid="2MA 8:24"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:25"/>They captured the money of those who had come to buy them as slaves. After pursuing them for quite some time, they returned because they were pressed for time.<verse eid="2MA 8:25"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:26"/>It was the day before the sabbath, and for that reason they did not continue their pursuit.<verse eid="2MA 8:26"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:27"/>When they had gathered their own arms together and had stripped the arms off their enemies, they kept the sabbath, giving great praise and acknowledgement to the Lord, who had preserved them until this day and allotted it to them as the beginning of mercy.<verse eid="2MA 8:27"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:28"/>After the sabbath, they gave some of the spoils to those who had been tortured and to the widows and orphans and distributed the rest among themselves and their children.<verse eid="2MA 8:28"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:29"/>When they had done this, they made common supplication and implored the merciful Lord to be wholly reconciled with his slaves.<verse eid="2MA 8:29"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:30"/>In encounters with the forces of Timothy and Bacchides they killed more than twenty thousand of them and very easily got possession of some exceedingly high strongholds, and they divided a very large amount of spoils, giving to those who had been tortured and to the orphans and widows and also to the aged shares equal to their own.<verse eid="2MA 8:30"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:31"/>Having gathered their armor together, and they carefully stored all of them in strategic places; the rest of the spoils they carried to Hierosolyma.<verse eid="2MA 8:31"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:32"/>They killed the commander of Timothy's forces, a most wicked man, and one who had greatly troubled the Judeans.<verse eid="2MA 8:32"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:33"/>While they were celebrating the victory in the fatherland, they burned those who had set fire to the sacred gates and Callisthenes, who had fled into one little house; so these received the proper reward for their impiety.<verse eid="2MA 8:33"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:34"/>The thrice-accursed Nikanor, who had brought the thousand merchants to buy the Judeans,<verse eid="2MA 8:34"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:35"/>having been humbled with the help of the Lord by opponents whom he regarded as of the least account, took off his splendid uniform and made his way alone like a runaway slave through the interior and reached Antioch, having succeeded chiefly in the destruction of his army!<verse eid="2MA 8:35"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 8:36"/>So he who had taken it upon himself to secure tribute for the Romans by the capture of the people of Hierosolyma proclaimed that the Judeans had a Defender and that therefore the Judeans were invulnerable, because they followed the laws ordained by him.<verse eid="2MA 8:36"/>



  <chapter sid="2MA 9"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:1"/>About that time, as it happened, Antiochus had retreated in disorder from the region of Persia.<verse eid="2MA 9:1"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:2"/>He had entered the city called Persepolis and attempted to rob the temples and control the city. Therefore the people rushed to the rescue with arms and put him to flight, and it happened that Antiochus, having been put to flight by the inhabitants, beat a shameful retreat.<verse eid="2MA 9:2"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:3"/>While he was in Ecbatana, news came to him of what had happened to Nikanor and the forces of Timothy.<verse eid="2MA 9:3"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:4"/>Transported with rage, he conceived the idea of turning upon the Judeans the injury done by those who had put him to flight; so he instructed his charioteer to drive without stopping until he completed the journey. But the judgment of heaven rode with him! For in his arrogance he said, "When I get there I will make Hierosolyma a cemetery of Judeans."<verse eid="2MA 9:4"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:5"/>But the all-seeing Lord, the God of Israel, struck him with an incurable and invisible blow. As soon as he stopped speaking he was seized with a pain in his bowels for which there was no relief, and with sharp internal tortures--<verse eid="2MA 9:5"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:6"/>and that very justly, for he had tortured the bowels of others with many and strange inflictions.<verse eid="2MA 9:6"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:7"/>Yet he did not in any way stop his insolence but was even more filled with arrogance, breathing fire in his rage against the Judeans and giving orders to speed up the journey. And so it came about that he fell out of his chariot as it was rushing along and that, through the grievous fall, all the limbs of the body were racked.<verse eid="2MA 9:7"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:8"/>Thus he, who only a little while before had thought in his superhuman arrogance that he could command the waves of the sea and had imagined that he could weigh the high mountains in a balance, was brought down to earth and carried in a litter, making the power of God manifest to all,<verse eid="2MA 9:8"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:9"/>so that worms broke out of the unbeliever's eyes, and while he was still living in anguish and pain, his flesh rotted away, and because of his stench the whole army felt revulsion at the decay.<verse eid="2MA 9:9"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:10"/>Because of the unbearable oppressiveness of the stench no one was able to carry the man who a little while before had thought that he could touch the stars of heaven.<verse eid="2MA 9:10"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:11"/>Then it was that, broken in spirit, he began to lose much of his arrogance and to come to his senses under the divine scourge, for he was tortured with pain every moment.<verse eid="2MA 9:11"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:12"/>And when he could not endure his own stench, he uttered these words, "It is right to be subject to God and that a mortal should not think haughtily."<verse eid="2MA 9:12"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:13"/>Then the abominable fellow made a vow to the Lord, who would no longer have mercy on him, stating<verse eid="2MA 9:13"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:14"/>that the holy city, which he was hurrying to level to the ground and to make a cemetery, he was now declaring to be free,<verse eid="2MA 9:14"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:15"/>and the Judeans, whom he had not considered worthy even of a grave but had planned to throw out with their children for the wild animals and for the birds to eat, he would make, all of them, equal to citizens of Athens,<verse eid="2MA 9:15"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:16"/>and the holy shrine, which he had formerly plundered, he would adorn with the finest offerings, and all the holy vessels he would give back many times over, and the expenses incurred for the sacrifices he would provide from his own revenues,<verse eid="2MA 9:16"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:17"/>and in addition to all this he also would become a Judean and would visit every inhabited place to proclaim the power of God.<verse eid="2MA 9:17"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:18"/>But when his sufferings did not in any way abate, for the just judgment of God had justly come upon him, he gave up all hope for himself and wrote to the Judeans the following letter in the form of a supplication. This was its content:<verse eid="2MA 9:18"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:19"/>"To his worthy Judean citizens, Antiochus, their king and general, sends hearty greetings and good wishes for their health and prosperity.<verse eid="2MA 9:19"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:20"/>If you and your children are well and your affairs are as you wish, I profess very great thanks to God, having my hope in heaven.<verse eid="2MA 9:20"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:21"/>As for me, I was weakly disposed, but I remember with affection your esteem and goodwill. On my way back from the region of Persia I suffered an annoyance suffering from a disease, and I have deemed it necessary to take thought for the common security of all.<verse eid="2MA 9:21"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:22"/>Not giving myself up as hopeless but having good hope of recovering from my illness,<verse eid="2MA 9:22"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:23"/>I nevertheless observed that even my father, on the occasions when he made expeditions into the upper country, appointed his successor<verse eid="2MA 9:23"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:24"/>so that, if anything unexpected happened or any unwelcome news came, the people throughout the realm would not be troubled, for they would know to whom the government was left.<verse eid="2MA 9:24"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:25"/>Moreover, since I understand how the princes along the borders and the neighbors of my kingdom keep watching for opportunities and waiting to see what will happen, I have appointed my son Antiochus to be king, whom I have often entrusted and commended to most of you when I hurried off to the upper provinces, and I have written to him what is written here.<verse eid="2MA 9:25"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:26"/>I therefore urge and implore you to remember the public and private services rendered to you and to maintain your present goodwill, each of you, toward me and my son.<verse eid="2MA 9:26"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:27"/>For I am sure that he will follow my policy and will accommodate himself to you mildly and with kindness."<verse eid="2MA 9:27"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:28"/>So the murderer and blasphemer, having endured the most intense suffering, such as he had inflicted on others, came to the end of his life by a most pitiable fate among the mountains in a strange land.<verse eid="2MA 9:28"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 9:29"/>And Philip, who had been brought up with him, took his body home; then, fearing the son of Antiochus, he withdrew to Ptolemy Philometor in Egypt.<verse eid="2MA 9:29"/>



  <chapter sid="2MA 10"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:1"/>Now Makkabaios and his followers, the Lord leading them on, recovered the temple and the city;<verse eid="2MA 10:1"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:2"/>they tore down the altars<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = 'bômos'</char></note> that had been built in the public square by the allophyles and also destroyed the sacred precincts.<verse eid="2MA 10:2"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:3"/>And having purified the shrine, they made another altar of sacrifice; then, igniting flint stones and taking fire out of them, they offered sacrifices, after a lapse of two years, and they offered incense and put up lamps and set out the presentation of the loaves.<verse eid="2MA 10:3"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:4"/>When they had done this, they fell prostrate and implored the Lord that they might never again fall into such misfortunes, but that, if they should ever sin, they might be disciplined by him with forbearance and not be handed over to blasphemous and barbarous nations.<verse eid="2MA 10:4"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:5"/>It happened that on the same day on which the shrine had been profaned by allophyles the purification of the shrine took place, that is, on the twenty-fifth day of the same month, which was Chaseleu.<verse eid="2MA 10:5"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:6"/>They celebrated it for eight days with rejoicing, in the manner of coverts, remembering how not long before, during the feast of tents, they had been inhabiting the mountains and caves like wild animals.<verse eid="2MA 10:6"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:7"/>Therefore, carrying ivy-wreathed wands and beautiful branches and also fronds of palm, they offered hymns of thanksgiving to him who had given success to the purifying of his own holy place.<verse eid="2MA 10:7"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:8"/>They decreed by public ordinance and by vote that the whole nation of the Judeans should observe these days every year.<verse eid="2MA 10:8"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:9"/>Such then was the end of Antiochus, who was called Epiphanes.<verse eid="2MA 10:9"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:10"/>Now we will make known what took place under Antiochus Eupator, who was the son of that impious man, and will give a brief summary of the calamities of the wars.<verse eid="2MA 10:10"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:11"/>This man, when he succeeded to the kingdom, appointed a certain Lysias, the chief governor of Coele-Syria and Phoenicia, to be in charge of the government.<verse eid="2MA 10:11"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:12"/>Ptolemy, who was called Macron, taking the lead in observing justice towards the Judeans because of the wrong that had been done to them, attempted to maintain peaceful relations with them.<verse eid="2MA 10:12"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:13"/>As a result he was accused before Eupator by the king's Friends. He heard himself called a traitor at every turn, because he had abandoned Cyprus, which Philometor had entrusted to him, and had gone over to Antiochus Epiphanes. Unable to execute his noble office honorably, he took poison and ended his life.<verse eid="2MA 10:13"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:14"/>When Gorgias became governor of the region, he maintained mercenaries, and at every turn kept attacking the Judeans.<verse eid="2MA 10:14"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:15"/>Besides this, the Idumeans, too, who had control of strategic strongholds, were harassing the Judeans; they received those who were banished from Hierosolyma and endeavored to keep up the war.<verse eid="2MA 10:15"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:16"/>But Makkabaios and his forces, after making solemn supplication and imploring God to fight on their side, moved towards the strongholds of the Idumeans.<verse eid="2MA 10:16"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:17"/>Attacking them vigorously, they gained possession of the places and beat off all who fought upon the wall and slaughtered those whom they encountered, killing no fewer than twenty thousand.<verse eid="2MA 10:17"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:18"/>When at least nine thousand took refuge in two fortified towers exceedingly well equipped to withstand a siege,<verse eid="2MA 10:18"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:19"/>Makkabaios left Simon and Iosepos and also Zakchaios and his troops, a force sufficient to besiege them, and he himself set off for places where he was more urgently needed.<verse eid="2MA 10:19"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:20"/>But those with Simon, who were money-hungry, were bribed with silver by some of those who were in the towers, and on receiving seventy thousand drachmas, let some of them slip away.<verse eid="2MA 10:20"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:21"/>When word of what had happened came to Makkabaios, he gathered the leaders of the people and accused these men of having sold their kindred for money by setting free those who were hostile to them.<verse eid="2MA 10:21"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:22"/>Then he killed these men who had turned traitor and immediately captured the two towers.<verse eid="2MA 10:22"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:23"/>Having success at arms in everything he undertook, he destroyed more than twenty thousand in the two strongholds.<verse eid="2MA 10:23"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:24"/>Now Timothy, who had been defeated by the Judeans before, having gathered a tremendous force of mercenaries and having collected the cavalry from Asia in no small number, came on, intending to take Judea by storm.<verse eid="2MA 10:24"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:25"/>As he drew near, Makkabaios and his men sprinkled dust on their heads and girded their loins with sackcloth in supplication to God, and<verse eid="2MA 10:25"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:26"/>falling down at the foot of the altar, they implored him to be gracious to them and to be an enemy to their enemies and an adversary to their adversaries, as the law shows plainly.<verse eid="2MA 10:26"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:27"/>And rising from their prayer, they took up their arms and advanced a considerable distance from the city, and when they came near the enemy, they halted.<verse eid="2MA 10:27"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:28"/>Just as morning was breaking both attacked, the one having as pledge of success and victory not only their valor but also their recourse to the Lord, while the other made rage their leader in the fight.<verse eid="2MA 10:28"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:29"/>When the battle became fierce, there appeared to the enemy from heaven five illustrious men on horses with golden bridles, and they were leading the Judeans.<verse eid="2MA 10:29"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:30"/>Two of them took Makkabaios between them, and shielding him with their own suits of armor and weapons, they kept him unharmed. They showered arrows and thunderbolts on the enemy so that, confounded by blindness, they fled in complete disorder.<verse eid="2MA 10:30"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:31"/>Twenty thousand five hundred were slaughtered, besides six hundred cavalry.<verse eid="2MA 10:31"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:32"/>Timothy himself fled to a stronghold called Gazara, especially well garrisoned, where Chaereas was commander.<verse eid="2MA 10:32"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:33"/>Then Makkabaios and his men were glad, and they besieged the fort for four days.<verse eid="2MA 10:33"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:34"/>The men within, relying on the strength of the place, kept blaspheming terribly and uttering wicked words.<verse eid="2MA 10:34"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:35"/>But at dawn of the fifth day, twenty young men of those who were with Makkabaios, fired with anger because of the blasphemies, bravely stormed the wall and with savage fury cut down everyone they met.<verse eid="2MA 10:35"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:36"/>Others who came up in the same way wheeled around against the defenders and set fire to the towers; they kindled fires and burned the blasphemers alive. Others broke open the gates and let in the rest of the force, and they captured the city.<verse eid="2MA 10:36"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:37"/>They killed Timothy, who was hiding in a cistern, and his brother Chaereas and Apollophanes.<verse eid="2MA 10:37"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 10:38"/>When they had accomplished these things, with hymns and thanksgivings they blessed the Lord who shows great kindness to Israel and gives them the victory.<verse eid="2MA 10:38"/>



  <chapter sid="2MA 11"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:1"/>Very soon after this, Lysias, the king's guardian and kinsman, who was in charge of the government, being vexed at what had happened,<verse eid="2MA 11:1"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:2"/>gathered about eighty thousand infantry and all his cavalry and came against the Judeans. He intended to make the city a home for Greeks<verse eid="2MA 11:2"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:3"/>and to levy tribute on the temple as he did on the other sacred precincts of the nations and to put up the high priesthood for sale every year.<verse eid="2MA 11:3"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:4"/>He took no account whatever of the power of God but was elated with his ten thousands of infantry and his thousands of cavalry and his eighty elephants.<verse eid="2MA 11:4"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:5"/>Invading Judea, he approached Baithsoura, which was a fortified place about five stadia<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek 1 stadion = 200 meters</char></note> from Hierosolyma, and pressed it hard.<verse eid="2MA 11:5"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:6"/>When Makkabaios and his men heard that he was besieging the strongholds, they prayed to the Lord, together with the masses, with lamentations and tears, to send a good angel to save Israel.<verse eid="2MA 11:6"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:7"/>Makkabaios himself was the first to take up arms, and he urged the others to run the risk, together with him, of aiding their brothers. Then they eagerly rushed off together.<verse eid="2MA 11:7"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:8"/>And there, while they were near Hierosolyma, a horseman appeared as their leader, in a white garment, brandishing weapons of gold.<verse eid="2MA 11:8"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:9"/>Together they all praised the merciful God and were strengthened in spirit, ready to assail not only humans but also the wildest animals or walls of iron.<verse eid="2MA 11:9"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:10"/>They advanced in battle order, having their heavenly ally, for the Lord had mercy on them.<verse eid="2MA 11:10"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:11"/>They hurled themselves like lions against the enemy and laid low eleven thousand of them and sixteen hundred cavalry and forced all the rest to flee.<verse eid="2MA 11:11"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:12"/>Most of them were preserved wounded and naked, and Lysias himself escaped by disgraceful flight.<verse eid="2MA 11:12"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:13"/>As he was not without intelligence, he pondered over the defeat that had befallen him and realized that the Hebrews were invincible, because the mighty God fought on their side. So he sent to them<verse eid="2MA 11:13"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:14"/>and persuaded them to agree to all just conditions, since he would persuade the king, constraining him to be their friend.<verse eid="2MA 11:14"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:15"/>Makkabaios, having regard for the common good, agreed to all that Lysias urged. For the king granted every request which Makkabaios delivered to Lysias in writing concerning the Judeans.<verse eid="2MA 11:15"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:16"/>The letters written to the Judeans by Lysias were to this effect: "Lysias to the multitude of the Judeans, greetings.<verse eid="2MA 11:16"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:17"/>Ioannes and Abessalom, who were sent by you, have delivered your petition copied below and have implored about the matters indicated in it.<verse eid="2MA 11:17"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:18"/>I have informed the king of everything that needed to be brought before him, and he has agreed to what was possible.<verse eid="2MA 11:18"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:19"/>If you will maintain your goodwill toward the government, I will endeavour in the future to help promote your welfare.<verse eid="2MA 11:19"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:20"/>And concerning details, I have commanded these men and my members of staff to confer with you.<verse eid="2MA 11:20"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:21"/>Farewell. The one hundred forty-eighth year, Dioscorinthius twenty-fourth."<verse eid="2MA 11:21"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:22"/>The king's letter ran thus: "King Antiochus to his brother Lysias, greetings.<verse eid="2MA 11:22"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:23"/>Now that our father has gone on to the gods, we, desiring that the subjects of the kingdom be undisturbed in caring for their own affairs,<verse eid="2MA 11:23"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:24"/>hearing that the Judeans do not consent to our father's change to Greek customs but prefer their own way of living and implore that their own precepts be allowed them,<verse eid="2MA 11:24"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:25"/>thus choosing that this nation also should be free from disturbance, judge that their temple be restored to them and that they shall live according to the customs of their ancestors.<verse eid="2MA 11:25"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:26"/>You will do well, therefore, to send word to them and give them pledges of friendship so that they may know our policy and be of good cheer and turn happily to the conduct of their own affairs."<verse eid="2MA 11:26"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:27"/>To the nation the king's letter was as follows: "King Antiochus to the senate of the Judeans and to the other Judeans, greetings.<verse eid="2MA 11:27"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:28"/>If you are well, it is as we desire. We also are in good health.<verse eid="2MA 11:28"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:29"/>Menelaus has informed us that you wish to return and look after your own affairs.<verse eid="2MA 11:29"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:30"/>Therefore those who go home by the thirtieth of Xanthikos will have our pledge of friendship and safe conduct<verse eid="2MA 11:30"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:31"/>for the Judeans to enjoy their own way of living and laws, just as formerly, and none of them shall be molested in any way for errors made through ignorance.<verse eid="2MA 11:31"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:32"/>And I have also sent Menelaus to encourage you.<verse eid="2MA 11:32"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:33"/>Farewell. The one hundred forty-eighth year, Xanthikos fifteenth."<verse eid="2MA 11:33"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:34"/>The Romans also sent them a letter, which read thus: "Quintus Memmius, Titus Manius, envoys of the Romans, to the people of the Judeans, greetings.<verse eid="2MA 11:34"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:35"/>With regard to what Lysias the Kinsman of the king has granted you, we also give consent.<verse eid="2MA 11:35"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:36"/>But as to the matters that he decided are to be referred to the king: Having considered them, send someone immediately so that we can outline how it would be appropriate for you, since we are on our way to Antioch.<verse eid="2MA 11:36"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:37"/>Therefore make haste and send messengers so that we, too, may get to know what your viewpoint is.<verse eid="2MA 11:37"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 11:38"/>Farewell. The one hundred forty-eighth year, Xanthikos fifteenth."<verse eid="2MA 11:38"/>



  <chapter sid="2MA 12"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:1"/>When these agreements had been reached, Lysias departed on his way to the king, and the Judeans went about their farming.<verse eid="2MA 12:1"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:2"/>But some of the local governors, Timothy and Apollonius son of Gennaios, as well as Hieronymos and Demophon, and in addition to these Nikanor the governor of Cyprus, would not let them live quietly and in peace.<verse eid="2MA 12:2"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:3"/>And the Joppites did so ungodly a deed as this: they invited the Judeans who lived among them to embark, with their wives and children, on boats that they had provided, as though there were no ill will towards them,<verse eid="2MA 12:3"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:4"/>and this was done by public vote of the city. When they accepted, because they wished to live peaceably and suspected nothing, they drowned them as soon as they had gone out to sea, at least two hundred.<verse eid="2MA 12:4"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:5"/>When Ioudas heard of the abomination inflicted on his compatriots, he gave orders to his men<verse eid="2MA 12:5"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:6"/>and, calling upon God the righteous judge, attacked the murderers of his kindred. He set fire to the harbor by night, burned the boats and massacred those who had taken refuge there.<verse eid="2MA 12:6"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:7"/>Then, because the town was shut in its walls, he withdrew, intending to come again and root out the whole community of the Joppites.<verse eid="2MA 12:7"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:8"/>But learning that the people in Jamnia, too, meant in the same way to wipe out the Judeans who were living among them,<verse eid="2MA 12:8"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:9"/>he attacked the Jamnites by night and set fire to the harbor and the fleet so that the gleam of the light was seen in Hierosolyma, two hundred and forty stadia<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek 1 stadion. = 200 meters</char></note> distant.<verse eid="2MA 12:9"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:10"/>When they had gone nine stadia<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek 1 stadion. = 200 meters</char></note> from there, on their march against Timothy, Arabs attacked him, no fewer than five thousand with five hundred cavalry.<verse eid="2MA 12:10"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:11"/>After a hard fight, Ioudas' men, with God's help, were successful, and the nomads, being defeated, implored Ioudas to grant them pledges of friendship, promising to give Ioudas and his men sheep and cattle and to help them in other ways.<verse eid="2MA 12:11"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:12"/>Ioudas, realizing that they might indeed be useful in many ways, agreed to make peace with them, and after receiving his pledges, they went back to their tents.<verse eid="2MA 12:12"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:13"/>He also attacked a certain town that was strongly fortified with earthen ramparts<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'earthen ramparts': Greek uncertain</char></note> and enclosed by walls and inhabited by all sorts of nations. Its name was Kaspin.<verse eid="2MA 12:13"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:14"/>Those who were within, relying on the strength of the walls and on their supply of provisions, behaved most insolently toward Ioudas' men, railing at them and even blaspheming and saying what is not lawful.<verse eid="2MA 12:14"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:15"/>But Ioudas' men, invoking the great Sovereign of the world, who without battering-rams or engines of war overthrew Iericho in the days of Iesous, rushed upon the walls like wild animals and<verse eid="2MA 12:15"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:16"/>took the town by the will of God and committed innumerable slaughters so that the adjoining lake, two stadia<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek 1 stadion = 200 meters</char></note> wide, appeared to be irrigated and filled up with blood.<verse eid="2MA 12:16"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:17"/>When they had gone seven hundred and fifty stadia<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek 1 stadion = 200 meters</char></note> from there, they came to the fortification<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'the fortification':  Or 'Charax'</char></note>, to the Judeans who are called Toubiaeni.<verse eid="2MA 12:17"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:18"/>They did not find Timothy in that region, however, for he had by then left the region without accomplishing anything, but a garrison, exceedingly strong, left behind by him in one place.<verse eid="2MA 12:18"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:19"/>Dositheos and Sosipatros, from among the leaders who were with Makkabaios, marched out and destroyed those who had been left behind by Timothy in the stronghold, more than ten thousand men.<verse eid="2MA 12:19"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:20"/>But Makkabaios arranged the army that was with him in cohorts and set men in command of the divisions and hurried after Timothy, who had with him one hundred twenty thousand infantry and two thousand five hundred cavalry.<verse eid="2MA 12:20"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:21"/>When he learned of the approach of Ioudas, Timothy sent off the women and the children and also the other members of the household to a place called Karnion, for that place was hard to besiege and difficult of access because of the narrowness of all the approaches.<verse eid="2MA 12:21"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:22"/>But when Ioudas' first division appeared and terror and fear came over the enemies at the manifestation to them of him who sees all things, in their flight they rushed headlong in every direction so that often they were injured by their own men and pierced by the points of their own rapiers.<verse eid="2MA 12:22"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:23"/>Ioudas pressed the pursuit with the utmost vigor, putting the sinners to the sword, and destroyed as many as thirty thousand.<verse eid="2MA 12:23"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:24"/>Timothy himself fell into the hands of Dositheos and Sosipatros and their men and with great guile he implored them to let him go in safety, because he held the parents of most of them and the brothers of some to whom no consideration would otherwise be shown.<verse eid="2MA 12:24"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:25"/>And when with many words he had confirmed his solemn promise to restore them unharmed, they let him go, for the sake of saving their kindred.<verse eid="2MA 12:25"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:26"/>Then Ioudas marched against Karnion and the temple of Atargatis and slaughtered twenty-five thousand people.<verse eid="2MA 12:26"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:27"/>After the rout and destruction of these, he marched also against Ephron, a fortified town where multitudes of people of all nationalities lived<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:27</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Göttingen Ed. = 'in it'</char></note>. Stalwart young men took their stand before the walls and made a vigorous defence, and great stores of war engines and missiles were there.<verse eid="2MA 12:27"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:28"/>But the Judeans called upon the Sovereign, who with power shatters the might of his enemies, and they got the town into their hands and killed as many as twenty-five thousand of those who were in it.<verse eid="2MA 12:28"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:29"/>Setting out from there, they hastened to Scythopolis, which is six hundred stadia<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:29</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek 1 stadion = 200 meters</char></note> from Hierosolyma.<verse eid="2MA 12:29"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:30"/>But when the Judeans who lived there bore witness to the goodwill that the people of Scythopolis had towards them and their courtesy towards them in times of misfortune,<verse eid="2MA 12:30"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:31"/>they thanked them and exhorted them to be well disposed to their race in the future also and went up to Hierosolyma, as the feast of weeks was close at hand.<verse eid="2MA 12:31"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:32"/>After the feast called Pentecost, they hurried against Gorgias, the governor of Idumea.<verse eid="2MA 12:32"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:33"/>He came out with three thousand infantry and four hundred cavalry.<verse eid="2MA 12:33"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:34"/>When they joined battle<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:34</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'When they joined battle': Göttingen Ed. = transposed</char></note>, it happened<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:34</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'it happened': Göttingen Ed. = transposed</char></note> that a few of the Judeans fell.<verse eid="2MA 12:34"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:35"/>But a certain Dositheos, one of Bakenor's men, who was on horseback and was a strong man, caught hold of Gorgias and, grasping his cloak, was dragging him off mightily. And while he wanted to take the accursed alive, one of the Thracian cavalry bore down on him and broke his shoulder, and Gorgias escaped to Marisa.<verse eid="2MA 12:35"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:36"/>As Esdris and his men had been fighting for a long time and were weary, Ioudas called upon the Lord to show himself their ally and leader in the battle.<verse eid="2MA 12:36"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:37"/>In their ancestral language he raised the battle cry with hymns; then he charged against Gorgias' troops when they were not expecting it and put them to flight.<verse eid="2MA 12:37"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:38"/>Then Ioudas assembled his army and went to the city of Odollam. As the seventh day was coming on, they purified themselves according to the custom and kept the sabbath there.<verse eid="2MA 12:38"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:39"/>On the next day, when the need for it had arisen, Ioudas' men went to recover the bodies of those fallen earlier and to bring them back to lie with their kindred in their ancestral sepulchres.<verse eid="2MA 12:39"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:40"/>Then under the tunic of each one of the dead they found sacred tokens of the idols of Jamnia, which the law forbids the Judeans to wear. And it became clear to all that this was the reason these men had fallen.<verse eid="2MA 12:40"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:41"/>So they all blessed the ways of the Lord, the righteous judge, who makes visible the things that are hidden,<verse eid="2MA 12:41"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:42"/>and they turned to supplication, imploring that the sin that had been committed might be wholly blotted out. The noble Ioudas exhorted the people to keep themselves free from sin, for they had seen with their own eyes what had happened as the result of the sin of those who had fallen.<verse eid="2MA 12:42"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:43"/>He also took up a collection, man by man, to the amount of two thousand drachmas of silver, and sent it to Hierosolyma to provide for a sin offering. In doing this he acted very well and honorably, taking account of the resurrection.<verse eid="2MA 12:43"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:44"/>For if he were not expecting that those who had fallen would rise again, it would have been superfluous and foolish to pray for the dead.<verse eid="2MA 12:44"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 12:45"/>But if he was looking to the splendid reward that is laid up for those who fall asleep in godliness, it was a holy and pious thought. Therefore he made atonement for the dead so that they might be delivered from their sin.<verse eid="2MA 12:45"/>



  <chapter sid="2MA 13"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:1"/>In the one hundred forty-ninth year word came to Ioudas and his men that Antiochus Eupator was coming with great numbers of soldiers against Judea,<verse eid="2MA 13:1"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:2"/>and with him Lysias, the guardian and chancellor, also<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Göttingen Ed. = 'each with'</char></note> a Greek force of one hundred ten thousand infantry, five thousand three hundred cavalry, twenty-two elephants and three hundred chariots bearing scythes.<verse eid="2MA 13:2"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:3"/>Menelaus also joined them and with much hypocrisy urged Antiochus on, not to save the fatherland but because he thought that he would be established in government.<verse eid="2MA 13:3"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:4"/>But the King of kings aroused the anger of Antiochus against the sinner, and when Lysias informed him that this man was the originator of all the trouble, he ordered them to take him to Beroea and to put him to death by the method that is customary in that place.<verse eid="2MA 13:4"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:5"/>For there is a tower there, fifty cubits high, full of ashes, and it has a rim running around it that on all sides inclines precipitously into the ashes.<verse eid="2MA 13:5"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:6"/>There they all push to destruction anyone who is guilty of temple robbery or has committed an excess of other evils.<verse eid="2MA 13:6"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:7"/>By such a fate it came about that Menelaus the lawbreaker died without even burial in the earth,<verse eid="2MA 13:7"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:8"/>and this was eminently just; because he had committed many sins against the altar<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = 'bômos'</char></note> whose fire and ashes were holy, he met his death in ashes.<verse eid="2MA 13:8"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:9"/>The king, who had become barbarous in his thinking, was coming to show the Judeans the worst things amongst those that had happened in his father's time.<verse eid="2MA 13:9"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:10"/>But when Ioudas heard of this, he ordered the crowd to call upon the Lord day and night, now if ever to help those who were on the point of being deprived of the law and their country and the holy temple<verse eid="2MA 13:10"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:11"/>and not to allow the people who had just begun to revive a little to fall into the hands of the blasphemous nations.<verse eid="2MA 13:11"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:12"/>When they had all joined in the same petition and had implored the merciful Lord with weeping and fasting and lying prostrate for three days without ceasing, Ioudas exhorted them and ordered them to stand ready.<verse eid="2MA 13:12"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:13"/>After consulting privately with the elders, he determined to march out and decide the matter by the help of God before the king's army could enter Judea and get possession of the city.<verse eid="2MA 13:13"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:14"/>So, committing the decision to the Creator of the world and exhorting those with him to fight bravely to the death for the laws, temple, city, fatherland and constitution, he pitched his camp near Modein.<verse eid="2MA 13:14"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:15"/>He gave his troops the watchword, "Divine Victory," and with those young men judged best, he attacked the king's pavilion at night and killed close to two thousand men in the camp and stabbed the lead elephant and its rider to death.<verse eid="2MA 13:15"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:16"/>In the end they filled the camp with terror and confusion and withdrew in triumph.<verse eid="2MA 13:16"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:17"/>This happened just as day was dawning, because the Lord's shelter helped him.<verse eid="2MA 13:17"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:18"/>The king, having had a taste of the daring of the Judeans, made an attempt on their positions through tricks.<verse eid="2MA 13:18"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:19"/>He advanced against Baithsoura, a strong fortress of the Judeans, was turned back, attacked again, was defeated.<verse eid="2MA 13:19"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:20"/>Ioudas kept sending in to those inside whatever was necessary.<verse eid="2MA 13:20"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:21"/>But Rhodokos, a man from the ranks of the Judeans, gave secret information to the enemy; he was sought for and caught and put in prison.<verse eid="2MA 13:21"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:22"/>The king negotiated a second time with the people in Baithsoura, gave pledges, received theirs, withdrew, attacked Ioudas and his men, was defeated;<verse eid="2MA 13:22"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:23"/>he got word that Philip, who had been left in charge of the government in Antioch, had revolted; he was perturbed, called in the Judeans, yielded and swore to observe all their rights, settled with them and offered sacrifice, honored the shrine and showed generosity to the place.<verse eid="2MA 13:23"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:24"/>He received Makkabaios, left Hegemonides as governor from Ptolemais to Gerar<verse eid="2MA 13:24"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:25"/>and went to Ptolemais. The people of Ptolemais were indignant over the treaties. In fact, they were so furious that they wanted to annul their terms.<verse eid="2MA 13:25"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 13:26"/>Lysias took the rostrum, made the defence to the best of his ability, convinced them, appeased them, gained their goodwill and set out for Antioch. This is how the king's attack and withdrawal turned out.<verse eid="2MA 13:26"/>



  <chapter sid="2MA 14"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:1"/>Three years later, word came to Ioudas and his men that Demetrius son of Seleucus had sailed into the harbour of Tripolis with a strong army and a fleet<verse eid="2MA 14:1"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:2"/>and had taken possession of the country, having made away with Antiochus and his guardian Lysias.<verse eid="2MA 14:2"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:3"/>Now a certain Alcimus, who had formerly been high priest but had willfully defiled himself in the times of separation, realized that there was no way for him to be safe or to have access again to the holy altar<verse eid="2MA 14:3"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:4"/>and went to King Demetrius in about the one hundred fifty-first year, presenting to him a crown of gold and a palm and, besides these, some of the customary olive branches from the temple. During that day he kept quiet,<verse eid="2MA 14:4"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:5"/>but he seized the right moment for his own folly when he was invited by Demetrius to a meeting of the council and was asked in what condition and counsel the Judeans were he replied to this:<verse eid="2MA 14:5"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:6"/>"Those of the Judeans who are called Hasideans, whose leader is Ioudas Makkabaios, are keeping up war and stirring up sedition and will not let the kingdom attain stability.<verse eid="2MA 14:6"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:7"/>Therefore I have been deprived of my ancestral glory-- I mean the high priesthood-- and have now come here,<verse eid="2MA 14:7"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:8"/>first because I am genuinely concerned for the interests of the king, second because I have regard also for my compatriots. For through the folly of those whom I have mentioned earlier our whole people are now in no small misfortune.<verse eid="2MA 14:8"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:9"/>"Since you are acquainted, O king, with the details of this matter, may it please you to take thought for our country and our hard-pressed people as is commensurate with the affable kindness that you show to all.<verse eid="2MA 14:9"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:10"/>For as long as Ioudas lives, it is impossible for the government to find peace."<verse eid="2MA 14:10"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:11"/>When he had said this, the rest of the king's Friends, who were hostile to Ioudas, quickly inflamed Demetrius still more.<verse eid="2MA 14:11"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:12"/>He immediately chose Nikanor, who was the elephantarch, appointed him governor of Judea and sent him off<verse eid="2MA 14:12"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:13"/>with commands<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">14:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Göttingen Ed. = 'letters'</char></note> to do away with Ioudas, to scatter those with him, yet to install Alcimus as high priest of the greatest temple.<verse eid="2MA 14:13"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:14"/>And the nations throughout Judea, who had fled before Ioudas, met Nikanor in flocks, thinking that the misfortunes and calamities of the Judeans would mean prosperity for themselves.<verse eid="2MA 14:14"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:15"/>When the Judeans heard of Nikanor's coming and the gathering of the nations, they sprinkled dust on their heads and prayed to him who established his own people forever and always upholds his own heritage by manifesting himself.<verse eid="2MA 14:15"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:16"/>At the leader's order, they set out from there immediately and met them at a village called Dessau.<verse eid="2MA 14:16"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:17"/>Simon the brother of Ioudas had encountered Nikanor but had temporarily stumbled because of the sudden perplexity caused by the adversaries.<verse eid="2MA 14:17"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:18"/>Nevertheless Nikanor, hearing of the valor of Ioudas and his troops and their courage in battle for their country, shrank from deciding the issue by bloodshed.<verse eid="2MA 14:18"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:19"/>Therefore he sent Posidonius, Theodotus and Mattathias to give and receive pledges of friendship.<verse eid="2MA 14:19"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:20"/>When they had been fully considered and the leader had informed the multitude and it had appeared that they were of one mind, they consented to the treaties.<verse eid="2MA 14:20"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:21"/>They set a day on which everyone was supposed to come to the same place by himself, and a chariot came forward from each side, and they set up seats of honor;<verse eid="2MA 14:21"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:22"/>Ioudas posted armed men in readiness at key places to prevent sudden treachery on the part of the enemy; so they duly held the consultation.<verse eid="2MA 14:22"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:23"/>Nikanor stayed on in Hierosolyma and did nothing out of the way but dismissed the flocks of people that had gathered.<verse eid="2MA 14:23"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:24"/>And he kept Ioudas always in his presence; he was cordially attached to the man.<verse eid="2MA 14:24"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:25"/>He urged him to marry and have children; so Ioudas married, settled down, shared the common life.<verse eid="2MA 14:25"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:26"/>But when Alcimus noticed their goodwill for one another, he took the treaties that had been made, went to Demetrius and told him that Nikanor was disloyal to the government, since he had appointed that conspirator against his kingdom, Ioudas, to be his successor.<verse eid="2MA 14:26"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:27"/>The king became enraged and, provoked by the false accusations of that thoroughly depraved man, wrote to Nikanor, asserting that he was displeased with the treaties and commanding him to send Makkabaios to Antioch as a prisoner without delay.<verse eid="2MA 14:27"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:28"/>When the news came to Nikanor, he was confounded and grieved that he had to annul the agreements when the man had done no wrong.<verse eid="2MA 14:28"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:29"/>Since it was not possible to oppose the king, he watched for a good opportunity to accomplish this by a stratagem.<verse eid="2MA 14:29"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:30"/>But Makkabaios, noticing that Nikanor was more austere in his dealings with him and conducted the customary meeting more rudely, concluded that this austerity did not spring from the best motives, gathered not a few of his men and went into hiding from Nikanor.<verse eid="2MA 14:30"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:31"/>When the latter became aware that he had been cleverly outmaneuvered by the man, he went to the great and holy temple while the priests were offering the customary sacrifices and commanded them to hand the man over.<verse eid="2MA 14:31"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:32"/>When they declared on oath that they did not know where the man was whom he wanted,<verse eid="2MA 14:32"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:33"/>he stretched out his right hand toward the shrine and swore this oath: "If you do not hand Ioudas over to me as a prisoner, I will level this precinct of God to the ground and tear down the altar and build here a notable temple to Dionysus."<verse eid="2MA 14:33"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:34"/>Having said this, he went away, but the priests stretched out their hands toward heaven and called upon the constant Defender of our nation, in these words:<verse eid="2MA 14:34"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:35"/>"O Lord of all, though you have need of nothing, you were pleased that there should be a shrine for your encamping among us;<verse eid="2MA 14:35"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:36"/>so now, O holy One, Lord of all sanctification, keep undefiled forever this house that has been so recently purified."<verse eid="2MA 14:36"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:37"/>A certain Razis, one of the elders of Hierosolyma, was denounced to Nikanor as a man who loved his compatriots and was very well thought of and for his goodwill was called father of the Judeans.<verse eid="2MA 14:37"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:38"/>In former times, when there was no mingling with the nations, he had been accused of Judaism, and he had risked body and life for Judaism with all possible zeal.<verse eid="2MA 14:38"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:39"/>Nikanor, wishing to exhibit the enmity that he had for the Judeans, sent more than five hundred soldiers to arrest him,<verse eid="2MA 14:39"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:40"/>for he thought that by arresting him he would do them an injury.<verse eid="2MA 14:40"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:41"/>When the hordes were about to capture the tower and were forcing the door of the courtyard, they ordered that fire be brought and the doors burned. Being surrounded, he fell upon his own rapier,<verse eid="2MA 14:41"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:42"/>preferring to die nobly rather than to fall into the hands of sinners and suffer outrages unworthy of his noble birth.<verse eid="2MA 14:42"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:43"/>But in the heat of the struggle he did not hit exactly, and while the masses were now rushing in through the doorways, he courageously ran up on the wall, and in a manly manner, threw himself down into the masses.<verse eid="2MA 14:43"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:44"/>But as they quickly drew back, a space opened and he fell in the middle of the empty space.<verse eid="2MA 14:44"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:45"/>Still alive and aflame with anger, he rose, and though his blood gushed forth and his wounds were severe, he ran through the crowd, and standing upon a steep rock<verse eid="2MA 14:45"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 14:46"/>with his blood already completely drained from him, he tore out his entrails, took them in both hands and hurled them at the crowd, calling upon the Lord of life and spirit to give them back to him again. This was the manner of his death.<verse eid="2MA 14:46"/>



  <chapter sid="2MA 15"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:1"/>When Nikanor heard that Ioudas and his troops were in the region of Samaria, he made plans to attack them with complete safety on the day of rest.<verse eid="2MA 15:1"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:2"/>When the Judeans who were compelled to follow him said, "By no means destroy so savagely and barbarously but show respect for the day that has been pre-eminently honored with holiness by him who sees all things,"<verse eid="2MA 15:2"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:3"/>the thrice-accursed wretch asked if there were a sovereign in heaven who had ordered the keeping of the sabbath day.<verse eid="2MA 15:3"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:4"/>When they declared, "It is the living Lord himself, the Sovereign in heaven, who ordered us to observe the seventh day,"<verse eid="2MA 15:4"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:5"/>the other one said, "But I am a sovereign also, on earth, and I order you to take up arms and finish the king's business." Nevertheless, he did not succeed in carrying out his abominable design.<verse eid="2MA 15:5"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:6"/>This Nikanor, showing off with all his boastfulness, had determined to erect a public monument of victory over Ioudas and his forces.<verse eid="2MA 15:6"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:7"/>But Makkabaios did not cease to trust with all confidence that he would get help from the Lord.<verse eid="2MA 15:7"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:8"/>He exhorted those with him not to fear the approach of the nations but to keep in mind the former times when help had come to them from heaven and so to look for the victory that the Almighty would give them.<verse eid="2MA 15:8"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:9"/>Encouraging them from the law and the prophets and reminding them also of the struggles they had accomplished, he made them the more eager.<verse eid="2MA 15:9"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:10"/>When he had aroused their courage, he issued orders, at the same time pointing out the perfidy of the nations and their violation of oaths.<verse eid="2MA 15:10"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:11"/>He armed each of them not so much with confidence in shields and spears as with the encouragement of good words, and he cheered them all by relating a dream, a sort of vision, which was worthy of belief.<verse eid="2MA 15:11"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:12"/>What he saw was this: Onias, who had been high priest, a beautiful and good man, of modest bearing and gentle manner, one who was well-spoken and had been trained from childhood in all that belongs to excellence, was praying with outstretched hands for the whole community of the Judeans.<verse eid="2MA 15:12"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:13"/>Then in the same fashion another appeared, distinguished by his grey hair and appearance, and of marvelous and most glorious dignity.<verse eid="2MA 15:13"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:14"/>And Onias spoke, saying, "This man is the one who loves his brothers, who prays much for the people and the holy city-- Ieremias, the prophet of God."<verse eid="2MA 15:14"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:15"/>Ieremias stretched out his right hand and gave to Ioudas a golden sword, and as he gave it he addressed him as follows:<verse eid="2MA 15:15"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:16"/>"Take the holy sword as a gift from God with which you will strike down your adversaries."<verse eid="2MA 15:16"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:17"/>Encouraged by the words of Ioudas, so noble and so effective in arousing valor and awaking courage in the souls of the young, they determined not to encamp<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">15:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Göttingen Ed. = 'advance'</char></note> but to attack bravely and to decide the matter by fighting hand to hand with all courage, because the city and the holy things and the temple were in danger.<verse eid="2MA 15:17"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:18"/>Their concern for wives and children and also for brothers and relatives lay upon them less heavily; their greatest and first fear was for the consecrated shrine.<verse eid="2MA 15:18"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:19"/>And those who were left behind in the city were in no small anxiety, being troubled over the attack in the open country.<verse eid="2MA 15:19"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:20"/>When all were already looking forward to the imminent confrontation and the enemy was already coming near with the army drawn up in battle-order, the animals strategically stationed and the cavalry deployed on the flanks,<verse eid="2MA 15:20"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:21"/>Makkabaios, observing the masses present and the varied supply of arms and the savagery of the elephants, stretched out his hands toward heaven and called upon the Lord who works wonders because he knew that it is not by arms, but as it seems good to God that he procures victory for those who are worthy.<verse eid="2MA 15:21"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:22"/>He called upon him in this manner: "O Master, you sent your angel in the time of King Hezekias of Judea, and he killed fully one hundred eighty-five thousand in the camp of Sennachereim.<verse eid="2MA 15:22"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:23"/>So now, O Sovereign of the heavens, send a good angel before us to inspire terror and trembling.<verse eid="2MA 15:23"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:24"/>By the might of your arm may those who come with blasphemy against your holy people be struck down." With these words he ended.<verse eid="2MA 15:24"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:25"/>Nikanor and his troops advanced with trumpets and battle cries,<verse eid="2MA 15:25"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:26"/>but Ioudas and his troops met the enemy with invocation and prayers.<verse eid="2MA 15:26"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:27"/>So, fighting with their hands and praying to God in their hearts, they laid low no less than thirty-five thousand and were greatly gladdened by God's manifestation.<verse eid="2MA 15:27"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:28"/>When the action was over and they were leaving with joy, they recognized Nikanor, lying dead, in full armor.<verse eid="2MA 15:28"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:29"/>Then there was shouting and tumult, and they blessed the Sovereign in the language of the fathers.<verse eid="2MA 15:29"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:30"/>Then the man who was ever in body and soul the defender of his people, the man who maintained his youthful goodwill toward his compatriots, ordered them to cut off Nikanor's head and his hand with his shoulder and carry them to Hierosolyma.<verse eid="2MA 15:30"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:31"/>When he arrived there and had called his compatriots together and stationed the priests before the altar, he sent for those who were in the citadel.<verse eid="2MA 15:31"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:32"/>He showed them the vile Nikanor's head and that profane man's arm, which he had boastfully stretched out against the holy house of the Almighty<verse eid="2MA 15:32"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:33"/>and, cutting out the tongue of the ungodly Nikanor, commanded it to be fed piecemeal to the birds and the rewards of his folly to be hung opposite the shrine.<verse eid="2MA 15:33"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:34"/>And they all offered praise to heaven, blessed the manifest Lord, saying, "Blessed is he who has kept his own place undefiled!"<verse eid="2MA 15:34"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:35"/>Ioudas fastened Nikanor's head to the citadel, visible to all and an obvious sign of the help of the Lord.<verse eid="2MA 15:35"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:36"/>And they all decreed by public vote never to let this day go unobserved but to have the thirteenth day of the twelfth month, which is called Adar in the Syrian language, marked, the day before Mardochaios' day.<verse eid="2MA 15:36"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:37"/>This is how it went with Nikanor, and from that time the city has been ruled by the Hebrews. So I myself will here bring my story to a halt.<verse eid="2MA 15:37"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:38"/>If it is well written and elegantly dispositioned, that is what I myself desired; if it is poorly done and mediocre, that was all I could manage.<verse eid="2MA 15:38"/>
    <verse sid="2MA 15:39"/>For just as it is harmful to drink wine alone or, again, to drink water alone, while wine mixed with water produces a delightful taste, so also the style of the story delights the ears of those who read the composition. And here will be the end.<verse eid="2MA 15:39"/>
</usx>
