<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- SourceFormat: VL.  Converted to USX by the STEP project: 2023-08-18 -->
<usx version="2.0">
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <book code="DEU"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:1"/>These are the words that Moyses spoke to all Israel beyond the Jordan-- in the wilderness, towards the west near the Red Sea, among Pharan, Tophol and Lobon and Courts<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'Enclosures'</char></note>-- and Gold-places<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'Goldworks'</char></note>--<verse eid="DEU 1:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:2"/>(a route of eleven days from Choreb, by way of Mount Seir, up to Kades Barne).<verse eid="DEU 1:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:3"/>And it happened in the fortieth year, in the eleventh month, on the first of the month, that Moyses spoke to all the sons of Israel according to all that the Lord had commanded him for them.<verse eid="DEU 1:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:4"/>After he struck Seon king of the Amorrites, who lived in Hesebon, and Og king of Basan, who lived in Astaroth and in Edrain,<verse eid="DEU 1:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:5"/>across from the Jordan, in the land of Moab, Moyses began to clarify this law, saying:<verse eid="DEU 1:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:6"/>The Lord our God spoke to us at Choreb, saying, "Let it be sufficient for you to live at this mountain.<verse eid="DEU 1:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:7"/>Turn, and depart, you, and go into the mountain of the Amorrites and to all those who live around Araba, to mountain and plain and to the south and seacoast, the land of Chananites and Anti-Lebanon, as far as the great river Euphrates.<verse eid="DEU 1:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:8"/>See, I have given the land before you; when you have gone in, inherit the land that I swore to your fathers, to Abraam and Isaak and Iakob, to give to them and to their offspring after them."<verse eid="DEU 1:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:9"/>And I said to you in that time, saying: "I will not be able alone to bear you.<verse eid="DEU 1:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:10"/>The Lord your God has multiplied you, and look, you are today like the stars of the sky in number.<verse eid="DEU 1:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:11"/>May the Lord, the God of your fathers, add to you, as you are, a thousand times and bless you, as he has spoken to you!<verse eid="DEU 1:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:12"/>How will I be able alone to bear your hardship and your substance and your disputes?<verse eid="DEU 1:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:13"/>Assign for yourselves men, wise and discerning and prudent for your tribes, and I will appoint them as your leaders."<verse eid="DEU 1:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:14"/>And you answered me and said, "The word which you have spoken to do is good."<verse eid="DEU 1:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:15"/>And I took from you men, wise and discerning and prudent, and appointed them to be leaders over you-- officers of thousands and officers of hundreds and officers of fifties and officers of tens and recorders for your judges.<verse eid="DEU 1:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:16"/>And I commanded your judges at that time, saying: "Give a full hearing among your brothers, and judge rightly between a man and between his brother and between his guest.<verse eid="DEU 1:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:17"/>You shall not recognize the person when judging: like the small so you shall judge the great; you shall not shrink from the face of a person, for the judgment is God's. And the matter, if it be too hard for you, you will bring it to me, and I will hear it."<verse eid="DEU 1:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:18"/>And I commanded you in that time all the things that you should do.<verse eid="DEU 1:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:19"/>And after we departed from Choreb, we went through all that great and terrible wilderness that you saw, by route of the mountain of the Amorrite, just as the Lord our God had commanded us, and we came as far as Kades Barne.<verse eid="DEU 1:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:20"/>And I said to you, "You have come as far as the mountain of the Amorrite, which the Lord our God is giving you.<verse eid="DEU 1:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:21"/>See, the Lord your God has given over to you the land before you. After you have gone up, inherit, as the Lord, the God of your fathers, said to you; do not fear, neither be afraid."<verse eid="DEU 1:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:22"/>And all of you came to me and said, "Let us send men ahead of us, and let them explore the land for us, and let them report to us a decision regarding the route through which we shall go up on it and the cities into which we will come into them."<verse eid="DEU 1:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:23"/>And the matter was pleasing to me, and I took from you twelve men, one man a tribe.<verse eid="DEU 1:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:24"/>And after they had set out, they went up into the mountain and went as far as Cluster Ravine and surveyed it.<verse eid="DEU 1:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:25"/>And they took in their hands some of the fruit of the land and brought it down to us and said, "The land is good that the Lord our God is giving us."<verse eid="DEU 1:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:26"/>And you did not want to go up. And you disobeyed the word of the Lord your God,<verse eid="DEU 1:26"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:27"/>and you grumbled in your tents and said, "It is because the Lord hates us that he brought us out of the land of Egypt, to give us into the hands of the Amorrites to destroy us utterly.<verse eid="DEU 1:27"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:28"/>Where are we going up? Our brothers have disquieted our hearts, saying, 'A great and numerous nation and more powerful than we, and cities, large and walled up to the sky! Nay, even sons of giants we have seen there!'"<verse eid="DEU 1:28"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:29"/>And I said to you, "Do not be alarmed, neither be afraid of them.<verse eid="DEU 1:29"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:30"/>The Lord your God, who goes before you, he will fight them together with you, according to all which he did for you in the land of Egypt<verse eid="DEU 1:30"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:31"/>and in this wilderness which you saw, how the Lord your God nursed you, as some person would nurse his son, along all the way that you went until you came to this place.<verse eid="DEU 1:31"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:32"/>And in this matter you did not believe the Lord your God,<verse eid="DEU 1:32"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:33"/>who went before you on the way to choose a place for you, leading you by fire at night, showing you the route whereby you should go upon it, and in a cloud by day."<verse eid="DEU 1:33"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:34"/>And the Lord heard the sound of your words and, being provoked, he swore, saying:<verse eid="DEU 1:34"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:35"/>"If one of these men shall see this good land that I swore to your fathers!<verse eid="DEU 1:35"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:36"/>Except Chaleb son of Iephonne, he shall see it, and to him I will give the land on which he trod, and to his sons, because he followed closely the things of the Lord."<verse eid="DEU 1:36"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:37"/>Even with me the Lord was angry on your account, saying, "Not even you shall enter there.<verse eid="DEU 1:37"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:38"/>Iesous son of Naue, who stands beside you, he shall enter there; strengthen him, for he will take possession of it for Israel.<verse eid="DEU 1:38"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:39"/>And every young child, who today does not know good or evil, they shall enter there, and to them I will give it, and they shall inherit it.<verse eid="DEU 1:39"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:40"/>And when you have turned, march into the wilderness, by the route toward the Red Sea."<verse eid="DEU 1:40"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:41"/>And you answered and said to me, "We have sinned against the Lord our God! Let us go up and fight, in accordance with all that the Lord our God commanded us." And, each of you, when you had strapped on your battle gear and had gathered, went up into the mountain.<verse eid="DEU 1:41"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:42"/>And the Lord said to me, "Say to them, 'You shall not go up, neither shall you fight, for I am not with you, and you shall not be wiped out before your enemies.'"<verse eid="DEU 1:42"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:43"/>And I spoke to you, but you did not listen to me. And you transgressed the word of the Lord, and by force<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:43</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'by force':  Possibly 'presumptuously'</char></note> you went up into the mountain.<verse eid="DEU 1:43"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:44"/>And the Amorrite who lived in that mountain came out to meet you and chased you as bees might do. And they were wounding you from Seir as far as Herma.<verse eid="DEU 1:44"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:45"/>And when you sat down, you were weeping before the Lord, and the Lord neither listened to your voice nor paid you any attention.<verse eid="DEU 1:45"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 1:46"/>And you stayed at Kades for many days, however many days you stayed.<verse eid="DEU 1:46"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:1"/>And after we had turned, we departed into the wilderness by way of the Red Sea, as the Lord had told me, and went around Mount Seir for many days.<verse eid="DEU 2:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:2"/>And the Lord said to me:<verse eid="DEU 2:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:3"/>"Let it be sufficient for you to go around this mountain. Turn therefore to the north,<verse eid="DEU 2:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:4"/>and command the people, saying: You are passing through the borders of your brothers, the sons of Esau, who live in Seir. And they will be afraid of you, and they will be very cautious.<verse eid="DEU 2:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:5"/>Do not engage in battle with them, for I will not even give you a foot's pace of their land, since I have given Mount Seir to Esau as an allotment.<verse eid="DEU 2:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:6"/>Purchase food from them, and you will eat, and you shall also take water by measure from them for money, and you will drink.<verse eid="DEU 2:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:7"/>For the Lord our God has blessed you in every work of your hands. Consider how you crossed this great and terrible wilderness. Look, for forty years the Lord your God has been with you; you have not been in need of a thing."<verse eid="DEU 2:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:8"/>And we passed by our brothers, the sons of Esau who live in Seir, along the route of the Araba, from Ailon and from Gasion Gaber. And after we had turned, we went along the wilderness route of Moab,<verse eid="DEU 2:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:9"/>and the Lord said to me: "Do not act with enmity against the Moabites, and do not engage in battle with them, for I will not give you any of their land as an allotment, for I have given Aroer to the sons of Lot to inherit."<verse eid="DEU 2:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:10"/>(The erstwhile Ommin-- a nation large and numerous and mighty like the Enakim-- had settled in it.<verse eid="DEU 2:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:11"/>Like the Enakim, these also shall be reckoned as Rephain, and the Moabites name them Ommin.<verse eid="DEU 2:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:12"/>And the Chorrite had formerly lain couched in Seir, and the sons of Esau destroyed them and wiped them out from before them, and they were settled in their place, as Israel did with the land of its inheritance that the Lord gave them.)<verse eid="DEU 2:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:13"/>"Now then, rise up, and depart, and go alongside the ravine of Zared." So we passed along the ravine of Zared.<verse eid="DEU 2:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:14"/>And the days which we had gone alongside from Kades Barne until we passed along the ravine of Zared were thirty-eight years until the entire generation of the men, warriors of the camp, had fallen away, as the Lord had sworn to them.<verse eid="DEU 2:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:15"/>And the hand of God was against them, to eliminate them from the camp until they fell away.<verse eid="DEU 2:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:16"/>And it happened, when all the men, the warriors, had fallen away, since they were dying off from among the people,<verse eid="DEU 2:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:17"/>that the Lord spoke to me, saying,<verse eid="DEU 2:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:18"/>"Today you are going to pass the boundary of Moab at Aroer,<verse eid="DEU 2:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:19"/>and you will draw near to the sons of Amman. Do not act with enmity against them, and do not engage them in battle, for I will not give any of the land of the sons of Amman to you as an allotment, because I have given it to the sons of Lot as an allotment."<verse eid="DEU 2:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:20"/>(It will be reckoned as a land of Rephain, for the Rephain formerly inhabited it, and the Ammanites name them Zomzommin,<verse eid="DEU 2:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:21"/>a nation, great and numerous and rather powerful, just as the Enakim, and the Lord destroyed them from before them, and they took possession and were settled in place of them.<verse eid="DEU 2:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:22"/>Just as they<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the Raphain'</char></note> did to the sons of Esau, who live in Seir, as they<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the sons of Esau'</char></note> wiped out the Chorrite before them, so they took possession and were settled in their place even to this day.<verse eid="DEU 2:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:23"/>As for the Heuites, who live in Haseroth as far as Gaza, and the Cappadocians, who came from Cappadocia, they wiped them out and were settled in their place.)<verse eid="DEU 2:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:24"/>"Now then, arise, and depart, and pass through the ravine of Arnon. See, I have given into your hands King Seon the Amorrite of Hesebon and his land. Begin to inherit; engage him in battle.<verse eid="DEU 2:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:25"/>On this day begin to put your trembling and your fear upon all the nations beneath the sky who, when they hear your name, will be troubled and have pains because of you."<verse eid="DEU 2:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:26"/>And I sent ambassadors from the wilderness of Kedmoth to King Seon of Hesebon with words of peace, saying:<verse eid="DEU 2:26"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:27"/>"I will pass by through your land; I will travel along the road; I will turn neither right nor left.<verse eid="DEU 2:27"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:28"/>You will sell me food for money, and I will eat, and you will sell me water for money, and I will drink. Only that I will pass by on foot--<verse eid="DEU 2:28"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:29"/>just as the sons of Esau who live in Seir did for me and likewise the Moabites who live in Aroer-- until I pass the Jordan into the land that the Lord our God is giving us."<verse eid="DEU 2:29"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:30"/>And King Seon of Hesebon did not want to let us pass by him, for the Lord our God had hardened his spirit and prevailed over his heart in order that he might be delivered into your hands, as it is on this day.<verse eid="DEU 2:30"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:31"/>And the Lord said to me, "See, I have begun to give King Seon the Amorrite of Hesebon and his land over before you. Begin to inherit his land."<verse eid="DEU 2:31"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:32"/>And Seon came out to meet us, he and all his people for battle at Iasa,<verse eid="DEU 2:32"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:33"/>and the Lord our God gave him over before us, and we struck him down, and his sons and all his people.<verse eid="DEU 2:33"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:34"/>And we captured all the cities at that time, and we utterly destroyed every city in order, and their women and their children we did not leave alive.<verse eid="DEU 2:34"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:35"/>Only the cattle we plundered, and the spoils of the cities we took:<verse eid="DEU 2:35"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:36"/>from Aroer, which is along the edge of the Wadi Arnon, and the city that is in the ravine, even as far as the mountain of Galaad. There was not a city which escaped us. The Lord our God gave over all of them into our hands.<verse eid="DEU 2:36"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 2:37"/>We did not enter, however, into the land of the sons of Amman, all the regions bordering the Wadi Iabok as well as the cities of the hill country, just as the Lord our God had commanded us.<verse eid="DEU 2:37"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:1"/>And after we had turned, we went up the road to Basan. And King Og of Basan came out to meet us, he and all his people, for battle at Edrain.<verse eid="DEU 3:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:2"/>And the Lord said to me, "Do not fear him, for I have given him over into your hands, and all his people and all his land. And you shall do to him as you did to King Seon of the Amorrites, who used to live in Hesebon."<verse eid="DEU 3:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:3"/>And the Lord our God delivered him into our hands, even King Og of Basan and all his people. And we struck him down until we did not leave him offspring.<verse eid="DEU 3:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:4"/>And at that time we captured all his cities; there was no city that we did not take from them-- sixty cities, all the environs of Argob, the kingdom of Og in Basan.<verse eid="DEU 3:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:5"/>All these were strong cities, high walls, gates and bars, besides the very many cities of the Pherezites.<verse eid="DEU 3:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:6"/>We utterly destroyed them, as we did King Seon of Hesebon, and we utterly destroyed every city in order, and the women and the children.<verse eid="DEU 3:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:7"/>And all the cattle and the spoils of the cities we plundered for ourselves.<verse eid="DEU 3:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:8"/>And at that time we took out of the hands of the two Amorrite kings who were beyond the Jordan the land from the Wadi Arnon up to Haermon<verse eid="DEU 3:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:9"/>(the Phoenicians named Haermon Sanior, and the Amorrite named it Sanir).<verse eid="DEU 3:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:10"/>All were cities of Misor and all of Galaad and all of Basan, as far as Selcha and Edrain, cities of Og's kingdom in Basan.<verse eid="DEU 3:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:11"/>(Because only King Og of Basan was left from the Raphain. Look, his bed was an iron bed; look, it is in the citadel of the sons of Amman. By a man's forearm<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'a man's forearm':  I.e. the common (non-standardized) cubit</char></note> it is nine cubits long and four cubits wide.)<verse eid="DEU 3:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:12"/>And we took possession of that land at that time, from Aroer, which is along the edge of the Wadi Arnon, and half of the mountainous area of Galaad and its cities I gave to Rouben and to Gad.<verse eid="DEU 3:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:13"/>And I gave to the half-tribe of Manasse the rest of Galaad and all of Basan, Og's kingdom, and all the environs of Argob, all of said Basan. (It will be reckoned a land of Raphain.)<verse eid="DEU 3:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:14"/>And Iair son of Manasse took all the environs of Argob as far as the borders of Gargasi and Homachathi, and he named them after his name-- Basan Hauoth Iair-- until this day.<verse eid="DEU 3:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:15"/>And to Machir I gave Galaad.<verse eid="DEU 3:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:16"/>And to Rouben and to Gad I gave from Galaad as far as the Wadi Arnon, the middle of the wadi being a boundary, and up to the Iabok, the wadi being the boundary for the sons of Amman,<verse eid="DEU 3:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:17"/>the Araba also and the Jordan, being a boundary of Machanarath even up to the sea of Araba, the Salt Sea, under Asedoth of Phasga on the east.<verse eid="DEU 3:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:18"/>And at that time I commanded you, saying: "The Lord your God gave you this land as an allotment; proceed fully armed before your brothers, the sons of Israel, every mighty one of you.<verse eid="DEU 3:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:19"/>Only your wives and your children and and your cattle-- I know that you have much cattle-- let them settle in your cities that I have given to you<verse eid="DEU 3:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:20"/>until the Lord your God gives your brothers rest, as also you and they too will inherit the land that the Lord your God is giving them beyond the Jordan, and you will return, each one to his inheritance that I have given to you."<verse eid="DEU 3:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:21"/>And I commanded Iesous at that time, saying: "Your eyes have seen everything that the Lord your God has done to these two kings; so the Lord will do to all the kingdoms which you are about to cross into there.<verse eid="DEU 3:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:22"/>You shall not be fearful of them, for the Lord your God himself will fight for you."<verse eid="DEU 3:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:23"/>At that time, too, I entreated the Lord, saying:<verse eid="DEU 3:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:24"/>"O Lord, Lord, you have begun to show your attendant your strength and your power and your strong hand and your high arm. For what god is there in the sky or on the earth who will do as you have done, and according to your strength?<verse eid="DEU 3:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:25"/>After I cross over, therefore, I will see this good land, which is beyond the Jordan, this good mountainous area and the Anti-Lebanon."<verse eid="DEU 3:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:26"/>And the Lord ignored me on your account and did not listen to me. And the Lord said to me, "Let it be sufficient for you! Do not continue any longer to speak to me of this matter!<verse eid="DEU 3:26"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:27"/>Go up to the top of Hewn, and look with your eyes to the sea and the north and the southwest and the east, and see with your eyes, for you shall not cross over this Jordan.<verse eid="DEU 3:27"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:28"/>And command Iesous, and strengthen him, and encourage him, because he will cross over ahead of this people, and it is he who will secure for them the possession of the land that you have seen."<verse eid="DEU 3:28"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 3:29"/>And we remained in a glen near the house of Phogor.<verse eid="DEU 3:29"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:1"/>And now, Israel, hear the statutes and judgments that I am teaching you to do today so that you may live and, after you have entered, may inherit the land that the Lord, the God of your fathers, is giving you.<verse eid="DEU 4:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:2"/>You shall not add to the word I command you, and you shall not take away from it. Keep the commandments of the Lord your God with which I command you today.<verse eid="DEU 4:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:3"/>Your eyes have seen all that the Lord your<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Wevers Ed. = 'our'</char></note> God did to Beelphegor-- that, every person who went after Beelphegor, the Lord your God wiped him out from among you,<verse eid="DEU 4:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:4"/>but those of you who held fast to the Lord your God are all alive today.<verse eid="DEU 4:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:5"/>See, I have shown you statutes and ordinances, as the Lord has commanded me, to do so in the land into which you are entering there to inherit it.<verse eid="DEU 4:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:6"/>And you shall keep and do them, because this is your wisdom and discernment before all the nations, as many as might hear all these statutes, and they will say, "Look, this great nation is a wise and understanding people!"<verse eid="DEU 4:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:7"/>For what sort of great nation has a god for itself so near to them as the Lord our God is in everything whenever we invoke him?<verse eid="DEU 4:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:8"/>And what sort of great nation has for itself statutes and righteous judgment in accord with all this law that I am giving before you today?<verse eid="DEU 4:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:9"/>Take heed to yourself, and guard your soul closely, lest you forget all the things that your eyes have seen, and let them not be far from your heart all the days of your life, and you shall direct your sons and your sons' sons<verse eid="DEU 4:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:10"/>about the day when you stood before the Lord your God at Choreb, on the day of the assembly when the Lord said to me, "Assemble the people to me, and let them hear my words so that they may learn to fear me all the days as long as they live on the earth and may teach their sons,"<verse eid="DEU 4:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:11"/>and you approached and stood at the foot of the mountain, and the mountain was burning with fire up to the sky: darkness, gloom, tempest.<verse eid="DEU 4:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:12"/>And the Lord spoke to you from the midst of the fire. You heard the sound of words but you did not notice a likeness, only a voice.<verse eid="DEU 4:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:13"/>And he announced to you his covenant, which he commanded you to do, the ten words, and he wrote them on two stone tablets.<verse eid="DEU 4:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:14"/>And the Lord commanded me at that time to teach you statutes and ordinances for you to do them in the land into which you are entering there to inherit it.<verse eid="DEU 4:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:15"/>And guard your souls closely, because you did not notice a likeness on the day the Lord spoke to you at Choreb in the mountain from the midst of the fire.<verse eid="DEU 4:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:16"/>Do not act lawlessly and make for yourselves an engraved likeness, any kind of icon-- a likeness of male or female,<verse eid="DEU 4:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:17"/>a likeness of any animal of those that are on the earth, a likeness of any winged bird that flies under the sky,<verse eid="DEU 4:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:18"/>a likeness of any reptile that creeps on the ground, a likeness of any fish that is in the waters beneath the earth.<verse eid="DEU 4:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:19"/>And do not, when you look up to the sky and see the sun and the moon and the stars, even any ornament of the sky, be led astray and do obeisance to them and serve them-- those things that the Lord your God has allotted to all the nations beneath the sky.<verse eid="DEU 4:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:20"/>But God has taken you and brought you out of the iron furnace, out of Egypt, to become for him an allotted people, as in this day.<verse eid="DEU 4:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:21"/>And the Lord was angry with me because of the things being said by you, and he swore that I would not cross this Jordan and that I would not enter into the land that the Lord God is giving to you as an allotment.<verse eid="DEU 4:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:22"/>For I am going to die in this land, and I am not crossing over this Jordan, but you are going to cross over, and you will take possession of this good land.<verse eid="DEU 4:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:23"/>As for you, take care, lest you forget the covenant of the Lord your God, which he made with you, and make for yourselves an engraved likeness of all of the things that the Lord your God has instructed you.<verse eid="DEU 4:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:24"/>For the Lord your God is a devouring fire, a jealous god.<verse eid="DEU 4:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:25"/>Now if you bear sons and sons' sons and live long in the land and you act lawlessly and make an engraved likeness of anything and do what is evil before the Lord your God, to provoke him to anger,<verse eid="DEU 4:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:26"/>I call sky and earth to witness against you today that by destruction you will perish from the land that you are crossing the Jordan to inherit there; you will not prolong days on it but will be wiped out with a wiping.<verse eid="DEU 4:26"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:27"/>And the Lord will scatter you among all the nations, and you will be left few in number among the nations into which the Lord will bring you there.<verse eid="DEU 4:27"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:28"/>And there you will serve other gods, works of human hands, wood and stone, who will neither see nor hear nor eat nor smell.<verse eid="DEU 4:28"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:29"/>And there you will seek the Lord your God, and you will find him when you seek him out with your whole heart and with your whole soul, (30) in your distress.<verse eid="DEU 4:29"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:30"/>And all these words shall find you in the end of days, and you will return to the Lord your God and listen to his voice.<verse eid="DEU 4:30"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:31"/>Because the Lord your God is a compassionate god, he will neither abandon you nor wipe you out; he will not forget the covenant with your fathers that he swore to them.<verse eid="DEU 4:31"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:32"/>Ask of former days which occurred long before your own, from the day that God created a human being on the earth; ask<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:32</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> at the end of the sky up to the end of the sky whether a thing this great has ever happened, whether such a thing has been heard of;<verse eid="DEU 4:32"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:33"/>whether any nation has ever heard the voice of a living god speaking from the midst of the fire, as you have heard, and you lived,<verse eid="DEU 4:33"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:34"/>whether a god ever attempted to go and take a nation for himself from the midst of a nation, by trial and by signs and by wonders and by war and by a strong hand and a high arm and by great exhibits, like all which the Lord your God did in Egypt before you, as you were looking on<verse eid="DEU 4:34"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:35"/>so that you might know that the Lord your God he is God, and there is no other besides him.<verse eid="DEU 4:35"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:36"/>From the sky his voice became audible to discipline you, and on earth he showed you his great fire, and you heard his words coming from the midst of the fire.<verse eid="DEU 4:36"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:37"/>Because he loved your fathers, he also chose you, their offspring after them, and himself brought you out of Egypt, by his great power,<verse eid="DEU 4:37"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:38"/>to destroy utterly before you great nations, and mightier than yourselves, to bring you in, to give you their land to inherit, as you have today.<verse eid="DEU 4:38"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:39"/>And you will know today and bear in mind that the Lord your God, he is God in the sky above and on the earth beneath, and there is no other besides him.<verse eid="DEU 4:39"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:40"/>And you will keep his statutes and his commandments, which I command you today, so that it may be well with you and with your sons after you so that you may be long-lived in the land that the Lord your God is giving you for all your days.<verse eid="DEU 4:40"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:41"/>Then Moyses set apart three cities beyond the Jordan toward the rising of the sun<verse eid="DEU 4:41"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:42"/>for the murderer to flee there, whoever might unintentionally kill his neighbor, and he did not hate him before yesterday and the third day, and he shall flee to one of these cities and live:<verse eid="DEU 4:42"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:43"/>Bosor in the wilderness on the plain country belonging to Rouben and Ramoth in Galaad belonging to Gaddi and Gaulon in Basan belonging to Manasse.<verse eid="DEU 4:43"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:44"/>This is the law that Moyses set before the sons of Israel.<verse eid="DEU 4:44"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:45"/>These are the testimonies and the statutes and the judgments that Moyses spoke to the sons of Israel when they had come out of the land of Egypt,<verse eid="DEU 4:45"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:46"/>beyond the Jordan in the valley near the house of Phogor, in the land of King Seon of the Amorrites, who used to live in Hesebon, whom<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:46</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the Amorrites'</char></note> Moyses and the sons of Israel defeated when they had come out of the land of Egypt.<verse eid="DEU 4:46"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:47"/>And they took possession of his land and the land of King Og of Basan, two kings of the Amorrites who were beyond the Jordan toward the rising of the sun,<verse eid="DEU 4:47"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:48"/>from Aroer, which is on the edge of the Wadi Arnon, and to Mount Seon (that is, Haermon) ,<verse eid="DEU 4:48"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 4:49"/>all the Araba beyond the Jordan toward the rising of the sun, east under Asedoth quarried from rock.<verse eid="DEU 4:49"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:1"/>And Moyses called all Israel and said to them: Hear, O Israel, the statutes and judgments that I am speaking in your ears this day, and you shall learn them and be watchful to perform them.<verse eid="DEU 5:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:2"/>The Lord your God established a covenant with you at Choreb.<verse eid="DEU 5:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:3"/>Not with your fathers did the Lord establish this covenant, but with all of you here alive today.<verse eid="DEU 5:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:4"/>The Lord spoke with you face-to-face at the mountain, from the midst of the fire,<verse eid="DEU 5:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:5"/>and I stood between the Lord and you at that time, to report to you the words of the Lord, for you were afraid because of the fire and did not go up into the mountain, saying:<verse eid="DEU 5:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:6"/>I am the Lord your God who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of a house of slavery.<verse eid="DEU 5:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:7"/>You shall have no other gods before me.<verse eid="DEU 5:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:8"/>You shall not make for yourself a carved object or likeness of anything whatever is in heaven above and whatever is in the earth beneath and whatever is in the waters under the earth.<verse eid="DEU 5:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:9"/>You shall not do obeisance to them, nor are you to serve them, because I am the Lord your God, a jealous god, repaying the sins of fathers upon children to the third and fourth generation to those who hate me,<verse eid="DEU 5:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:10"/>and doing mercy unto thousands, for those who love me and keep my ordinances.<verse eid="DEU 5:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:11"/>You shall not take the name of the Lord your God in vain. For the Lord will never acquit the one who takes his name in vain.<verse eid="DEU 5:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:12"/>Keep the day of the sabbaths to consecrate it, as the Lord your God commanded you.<verse eid="DEU 5:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:13"/>Six days you shall labor and do all your labor,<verse eid="DEU 5:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:14"/>but on the seventh day there is Sabbata to the Lord your God; you shall not do in it any labor-- you and your son and your daughter, your male slave and your female slave, your ox and your draft animal and any animal of yours and the guest within your gates so that your male slave and your female slave may rest as well as you.<verse eid="DEU 5:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:15"/>And you shall remember that you were a domestic in the land of Egypt, and the Lord your God brought you out from there with a strong hand and with a high arm; therefore, the Lord your God instructed you to keep the day of the sabbaths and to consecrate it.<verse eid="DEU 5:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:16"/>Honor your father and your mother, as the Lord your God commanded you, so that it may be well with you and that you may be long-lived in the land that the Lord your God is giving you.<verse eid="DEU 5:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:17"/>(18) You shall not commit adultery.<verse eid="DEU 5:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:18"/>(17) You shall not murder.<verse eid="DEU 5:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:19"/>You shall not steal.<verse eid="DEU 5:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:20"/>You shall not testify falsely against your neighbor with a false testimony.<verse eid="DEU 5:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:21"/>You shall not covet your neighbor's wife; you shall not covet your neighbor's house or his field or his male slave or his female slave or his ox or his draft animal, or any animal of his or whatever belongs to your neighbor.<verse eid="DEU 5:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:22"/>These words the Lord spoke to your whole gathering at the mountain, from the midst of the fire-- darkness, blackness, tempest, a loud voice-- and he did not add. And he wrote them on two stone tablets and gave them to me.<verse eid="DEU 5:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:23"/>And it happened, when you heard the voice from the midst of the fire and the mountain was burning with fire, that you approached me, all the leaders of your tribes and your council of elders,<verse eid="DEU 5:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:24"/>and you said, "Look, the Lord our God has shown us his glory, and we have heard his voice from the midst of the fire. This day we have seen that God will speak to a person, and he will live.<verse eid="DEU 5:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:25"/>And now let us not die. For this great fire will consume us; if we continue to hear the voice of the Lord our God any longer, then we will die.<verse eid="DEU 5:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:26"/>For what flesh, which has heard the voice of the living God when he speaks from the midst of fire, as we have, shall also live?<verse eid="DEU 5:26"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:27"/>Go you near, and hear whatever the Lord our God may say. And you shall speak to us all things, whatever the Lord our God may speak to you, and we will hear and do it."<verse eid="DEU 5:27"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:28"/>And the Lord heard the sound of your words when you were speaking to me, and the Lord said to me: "I have heard the sound of the words of this people, what they have spoken to you; all that they have spoken they have spoken<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:28</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'they have spoken':  Lacking in Greek</char></note> correctly.<verse eid="DEU 5:28"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:29"/>Who shall grant that their heart be in them in such a way that they fear me and keep my commandments in all their days so that it might go well with them and with their sons forever!<verse eid="DEU 5:29"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:30"/>Go, say to them, 'Return to your houses.'<verse eid="DEU 5:30"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:31"/>But you, stand here with me, and I will speak to you the commandments and the statutes and the judgments that you shall teach them, and let them do them in the land that I am giving them as an allotment."<verse eid="DEU 5:31"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:32"/>And you shall be watchful to do as the Lord your God has commanded; you shall not turn right or left,<verse eid="DEU 5:32"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 5:33"/>to go according to all the way that the Lord your God has commanded so that he may give you rest and that it may go well with you and that you may prolong your days upon the land that you shall inherit.<verse eid="DEU 5:33"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:1"/>And these are the commandments and the statutes and the ordinances that the Lord your God commanded to teach you to do so in the land which you are entering there to inherit<verse eid="DEU 6:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:2"/>so that you may fear the Lord your God, to keep all his statutes and his commandments that I command you today, you and your sons and your sons' sons, all the days of your life so that you may be long-lived.<verse eid="DEU 6:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:3"/>Now hear, O Israel, and be watchful to perform so that it may be well with you and that you may multiply greatly, just as the Lord, the God of your fathers, has spoken, to give you a land flowing with milk and honey.<verse eid="DEU 6:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:4"/>And these are the statutes and the judgments, which the Lord commanded to the sons of Israel in the wilderness as they were coming out from the land of Egypt. Hear, O Israel: The Lord our God is one Lord.<verse eid="DEU 6:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:5"/>And you shall love the Lord your God with the whole of your mind and with the whole of your soul and with the whole of your power.<verse eid="DEU 6:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:6"/>And these words that I command you today shall be in your heart and in your soul.<verse eid="DEU 6:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:7"/>And you shall teach them to your sons and talk on them while sitting at home and going on the road and lying down and rising up.<verse eid="DEU 6:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:8"/>And you shall bind them as a sign on your hand, and they shall be things unshakable<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'things unshakable':  Possibly 'fixtures'</char></note> before your eyes,<verse eid="DEU 6:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:9"/>and you shall write them on the doorposts of your houses and of your gates.<verse eid="DEU 6:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:10"/>And it shall be, whenever the Lord your God brings you into the land that he swore to your fathers, to Abraam and Isaak and Iakob, to give you large and fine cities that you did not build,<verse eid="DEU 6:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:11"/>houses full of all sorts of goods that you did not fill, dug cisterns that you did not dig out, vineyards and olive groves that you did not plant. And when you eat and become full,<verse eid="DEU 6:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:12"/>take care for yourself, lest you forget the Lord your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of a house of slavery.<verse eid="DEU 6:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:13"/>The Lord your God you shall fear, and him you shall serve, and to him you shall cling, and by his name you shall swear.<verse eid="DEU 6:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:14"/>Do not go after other gods from the gods of the nations around you,<verse eid="DEU 6:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:15"/>because the Lord your God, who is present with you, is a jealous god. Lest the Lord your God, being angered with wrath against you<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'being angered with wrath against you':  Or 'who is present with you, being angered with wrath'</char></note>, destroy you utterly from the face of the earth.<verse eid="DEU 6:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:16"/>You shall not tempt the Lord your God, as you tempted in the Temptation.<verse eid="DEU 6:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:17"/>By guarding, you shall keep the commandments of the Lord God, the testimonies and the statutes that he has commanded you.<verse eid="DEU 6:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:18"/>And you shall do what is pleasing and good before the Lord your God, so that it may be well for you and that you may go in and inherit the good land that the Lord swore to your fathers,<verse eid="DEU 6:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:19"/>to chase out all your enemies before you, as he said.<verse eid="DEU 6:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:20"/>And it shall be, when your son asks you tomorrow, saying, "What are the testimonies and the statutes and the judgments that the Lord our God has commanded you<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Wevers Ed. = 'us'</char></note>?"<verse eid="DEU 6:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:21"/>that you shall say to your son, "We were domestics to Pharao in the land of Egypt, and the Lord brought us from there with a strong hand and with a high arm.<verse eid="DEU 6:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:22"/>And the Lord gave before us signs and wonders, great and evil in Egypt, against Pharao and against his household.<verse eid="DEU 6:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:23"/>And he brought us out from there in order to bring us in, to give to us this land that he swore to give to our fathers.<verse eid="DEU 6:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:24"/>And the Lord commanded us to perform all these statutes, to fear the Lord our God, so that it may be well for us all our days so that we may live, as it is today.<verse eid="DEU 6:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 6:25"/>If we are watchful to perform all these commandments before the Lord our God, as he has commanded us, there will also be mercy for us."<verse eid="DEU 6:25"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:1"/>Now if the Lord your God brings you into the land that you are entering there to inherit and shall clear away great and numerous nations before you-- the Chettite and the Gergesite and the Amorrite and the Chananite and the Pherezite and the Heuite and the Iebousite, seven nations numerous and mightier than you--<verse eid="DEU 7:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:2"/>and the Lord your God shall deliver them into your hands and you shall strike them, by annihilation you shall annihilate them. You shall not establish a covenant with them, neither shall you have mercy on them.<verse eid="DEU 7:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:3"/>Neither shall you intermarry with them. You shall not give your daughter to his son, and you shall not take his daughter for your son,<verse eid="DEU 7:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:4"/>for she<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'it'</char></note> will turn away your son from me, and he will serve other gods. And the Lord will be angered with wrath against you and will utterly destroy you quickly.<verse eid="DEU 7:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:5"/>But thus you shall do to them: you shall break down their altars<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = 'bômos'</char></note> and smash their steles and cut down their groves and burn the carved objects of their gods with fire.<verse eid="DEU 7:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:6"/>For you are a people holy to the Lord your God, and the Lord your God has chosen you to be for him an exceptional people, more than all the nations on the face of the earth.<verse eid="DEU 7:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:7"/>It was not because you are more numerous than all nations that the Lord chose you and picked you-- for you are very few in comparison with all the nations.<verse eid="DEU 7:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:8"/>Rather, because the Lord loved you, and since he was keeping the oath that he swore to your fathers, the Lord brought you out with a strong hand and with a high arm and redeemed you from a house of slavery, from the hand of Pharao king of Egypt.<verse eid="DEU 7:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:9"/>And you shall know that the Lord your God, he is God, the faithful God, who keeps the covenant and mercy with those who love him and keep his commandments, to a thousand generations,<verse eid="DEU 7:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:10"/>and who repays those who hate him to their face, to destroy them utterly. And he will not delay with those who hate him; to their face he will repay them.<verse eid="DEU 7:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:11"/>And you will keep the commandments and the statutes and these judgments-- that I command you today to do.<verse eid="DEU 7:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:12"/>And it shall be, whenever you hear all these statutes and keep and do them, that the Lord your God will guard closely for you the covenant and the mercy as he swore to your fathers,<verse eid="DEU 7:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:13"/>and he will love you and bless you and multiply you, and he will bless the progeny of your belly and the fruit of your land, your grain and your wine and your oil, the herds of your oxen and the flocks of your sheep, in the land that the Lord swore to your fathers to give you.<verse eid="DEU 7:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:14"/>Blessed you shall be among all the nations; there shall not be an impotent one nor a sterile one among you or your cattle.<verse eid="DEU 7:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:15"/>And the Lord will remove from you every illness, and all the dread diseases of Egypt that you have seen and that you experienced he will not inflict on you, but he will inflict them on all who hate you.<verse eid="DEU 7:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:16"/>And you shall eat all the spoils of the nations that the Lord your God is giving to you; your eye shall not be sparing to them, and you shall not serve their gods, for this is a stumbling block to you.<verse eid="DEU 7:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:17"/>But if you say in your mind, "This nation is more numerous than I; how will I be able to destroy them utterly?"<verse eid="DEU 7:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:18"/>you shall not be afraid of them. With remembrance you shall remember what the Lord your God did to Pharao and to all the Egyptians,<verse eid="DEU 7:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:19"/>the great trials that your eyes saw, the signs and those great wonders, the strong hand and the high arm as the Lord your God brought you out. The Lord our God will do thus to all the nations of whose faces you are afraid.<verse eid="DEU 7:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:20"/>And the Lord your God will send the hornets against them until even the ones who have been left and those hidden from you are wiped out<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'from you are wiped out':  Or 'are destroyed from you'</char></note>.<verse eid="DEU 7:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:21"/>You shall not be wounded before them, for the Lord your God with you is a great and strong god.<verse eid="DEU 7:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:22"/>And the Lord your God will consume these nations before you little by little; you will not be able to consume them quickly, lest the land become a wilderness and the wild animals be multiplied against you.<verse eid="DEU 7:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:23"/>And the Lord your God will deliver them into your hands, and he will destroy them with a great destruction until he has destroyed them utterly.<verse eid="DEU 7:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:24"/>And he will deliver their kings into your hands, and you shall destroy their name from that place; no one will be able to stand up against you until you have destroyed them utterly.<verse eid="DEU 7:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:25"/>The carved objects of their gods you shall burn with fire. You shall not desire silver and gold from them, and you shall not take for yourself, lest you stumble by means of it, for it is an abomination to the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 7:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 7:26"/>And you shall not bring an abomination into your house, or you will be an anathema like it. With an offense you shall take offense, and with abhorrence you shall abhor it, for it is an anathema.<verse eid="DEU 7:26"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:1"/>All the commandments that I command you today you shall be watchful to perform so that you may live and increase and go in and inherit the land that the Lord swore to your fathers.<verse eid="DEU 8:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:2"/>And you shall remember all the way that the Lord your God has led you in the wilderness so that he might distress you and test you and discern the things in your heart, whether you would keep his commandments or not.<verse eid="DEU 8:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:3"/>And he distressed you and let you hunger and fed you with manna with which your fathers were not acquainted in order to announce to you that man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word that goes out through the mouth of God man shall live.<verse eid="DEU 8:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:4"/>Your clothes were not worn off you; your feet did not become hard; look, for forty years!<verse eid="DEU 8:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:5"/>And you shall know in your heart that as a certain person might discipline his son, so the Lord your God will discipline you.<verse eid="DEU 8:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:6"/>And you shall keep the commandments of the Lord your God, to go in his ways and to fear him.<verse eid="DEU 8:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:7"/>For the Lord your God is bringing you into a good and extensive land in which there are wadis of waters, springs of underground waters, flowing out through the plains and through the mountains,<verse eid="DEU 8:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:8"/>a land of wheat and barley, vines, figs, pomegranates, a land of olive trees of oil and of honey,<verse eid="DEU 8:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:9"/>a land in which you will eat your bread without poverty and will not be in need of anything therein, a land whose stones are iron and from its mountains you will mine copper.<verse eid="DEU 8:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:10"/>And you shall eat and be filled and bless the Lord your God on the good land that he gave you.<verse eid="DEU 8:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:11"/>Take heed for yourself lest you forget the Lord your God, so as not to keep his commandments and his judgments and his statutes, which I command you today.<verse eid="DEU 8:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:12"/>Lest, when you have eaten and been filled and, having built fine houses and lived in them,<verse eid="DEU 8:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:13"/>and when your oxen and sheep have multiplied and when silver and gold have been multiplied to you and when all that you own has been multiplied to you,<verse eid="DEU 8:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:14"/>you become exalted in heart and forget the Lord your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of a house of slavery,<verse eid="DEU 8:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:15"/>who led you through that great and fearsome wilderness, where there was a biting snake and a scorpion and thirst, where there was no water, who brought out for you from flint rock a spring of water,<verse eid="DEU 8:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:16"/>who fed you with manna in the wilderness that your fathers did not know so that he might distress you and test you, that you might do well at your end.<verse eid="DEU 8:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:17"/>Do not say in your heart, "My strength and the mastery of my hand have produced for me this great power."<verse eid="DEU 8:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:18"/>And you shall remember the Lord your God, for it is he who gives you strength to produce power-- and so that he may uphold his covenant that he swore to your fathers, as today.<verse eid="DEU 8:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:19"/>And it shall be, if by forgetting you forget the Lord your God and go after other gods and serve them and do obeisance to them, I call you to witness<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'call you to witness':  Or 'bear witness against you'</char></note> today that with destruction you shall perish.<verse eid="DEU 8:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 8:20"/>As also the remaining nations, which the Lord is destroying before you, so shall you perish, because you have not heard the voice of the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 8:20"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:1"/>Hear, O Israel! You are crossing the Jordan today, to go in to dispossess nations rather larger and mightier than you, cities great and walled up to the sky,<verse eid="DEU 9:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:2"/>a great people, both numerous and tall, sons of Enak, whom you know and of whom you have heard: "Who can stand up against sons of Enak?"<verse eid="DEU 9:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:3"/>And you shall know today that the Lord your God-- he proceeds before you; a devouring fire is he; he will destroy them utterly, and he will divert them before you, and you will destroy them quickly, as the Lord has said to you.<verse eid="DEU 9:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:4"/>When the Lord your God eliminates these nations before you, do not say in your heart, saying: "It is because of my righteousness that the Lord has brought me in to inherit this good land," but because of the impiety of these nations the Lord will destroy them utterly before you.<verse eid="DEU 9:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:5"/>It is not because of your righteousness or the holiness of your heart that you are going in to inherit their land, but because of the impiety of these nations the Lord will destroy them utterly before you, and in order that he may uphold the covenant that the Lord swore to your fathers, to Abraam and Isaak and Iakob.<verse eid="DEU 9:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:6"/>And you shall know, today, that it is not because of your righteousness the Lord your God is giving you this good land to inherit, for you are a stiff-necked people.<verse eid="DEU 9:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:7"/>Remember, do not forget how you provoked the Lord your God in the wilderness; from the day you came out of Egypt until you came into this place, you have continued being disobedient regarding things concerning the Lord.<verse eid="DEU 9:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:8"/>Even at Choreb you provoked the Lord, and the Lord was angry enough with you to destroy you utterly,<verse eid="DEU 9:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:9"/>when I was going up the mountain to receive the stone tablets, the tablets of the covenant that the Lord established with you, and I stayed on the mountain forty days and forty nights; I did not eat bread nor did I drink water.<verse eid="DEU 9:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:10"/>And the Lord gave me the two stone tablets written with the finger of God, and on them had been written all the words that the Lord had spoken to you at the mountain.<verse eid="DEU 9:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:11"/>And it happened, throughout forty days and forty nights, that the Lord gave to me the two stone tablets, tablets of covenant.<verse eid="DEU 9:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:12"/>And the Lord said to me, "Get up, go down quickly from here, for your people whom you brought from the land of Egypt have acted lawlessly. They have digressed quickly from the way that you commanded them; they have made for themselves a molten image."<verse eid="DEU 9:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:13"/>And the Lord said to me, "I have spoken to you once and twice, saying: I have seen this people, and look, it is a stiff-necked people.<verse eid="DEU 9:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:14"/>Permit me to destroy them utterly, and I will blot out their name from beneath the sky, and I will make of you a nation great and strong and more numerous than this one."<verse eid="DEU 9:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:15"/>And after I had turned, I went down from the mountain, and the mountain was burning with fire, and the two tablets were in my two hands.<verse eid="DEU 9:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:16"/>And when I saw that you had sinned against the Lord your God and had made for yourselves a molten image and had digressed from the way that the Lord had commanded you,<verse eid="DEU 9:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:17"/>then having taken hold of the two tablets, I flung them from my two hands and smashed them before you.<verse eid="DEU 9:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:18"/>And I petitioned before the Lord a second time as also the first, forty days and forty nights; I did not eat bread, and I did not drink water on account of all your sins that you had sinned, by doing what was evil before the Lord your God, to provoke him.<verse eid="DEU 9:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:19"/>And I was terrified on account of the wrath and the anger, because the Lord had been provoked against you to destroy you utterly. And the Lord listened to me this time also.<verse eid="DEU 9:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:20"/>And the Lord was very full of wrath against Aaron to destroy him utterly, and I prayed also on behalf of Aaron at that time.<verse eid="DEU 9:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:21"/>And your sin which you had made, the bull calf, I took it and burned it with fire and crushed it, grinding thoroughly, until it became fine and it was as dust, and I threw the dust into the wadi that runs down from the mountain.<verse eid="DEU 9:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:22"/>And at The Burning also and at The Temptation and at The Graves of Lust<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'Craving'</char></note>, you were provoking the Lord your God<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'your God':  Wevers Ed. = Omit</char></note>.<verse eid="DEU 9:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:23"/>And when the Lord sent you from Kades Barne, saying, "Go up, and inherit the land that I am giving you," then you disobeyed the word of the Lord your God and did not trust him and did not listen to his voice.<verse eid="DEU 9:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:24"/>You were disobedient in regard to things concerning the Lord from the day he knew you.<verse eid="DEU 9:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:25"/>And I petitioned before the Lord, for forty days and for forty nights that I petitioned, for the Lord said that he would destroy you utterly.<verse eid="DEU 9:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:26"/>And I prayed to God and said, "O Lord, Lord, king of the gods, do not utterly destroy your people and your possession whom you redeemed by your great strength, whom you brought out of the land of Egypt with your great strength and with your strong hand and your high arm.<verse eid="DEU 9:26"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:27"/>Remember Abraam and Isaac and Iakob your attendants to whom you swore by yourself; do not look upon the stubbornness of this people and upon the impieties and upon their sins,<verse eid="DEU 9:27"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:28"/>lest the inhabitants of the land from whence you have brought us say, saying: 'Because the Lord was not able to bring them into the land that he mentioned to them and because he hates them, he brought them out to kill them in the wilderness.'<verse eid="DEU 9:28"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 9:29"/>And these are your people and your allotment whom you brought out of the land of Egypt by your great strength and by your high arm."<verse eid="DEU 9:29"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:1"/>At that time the Lord said to me, "Carve out for yourself two tablets of stone like the former ones, and come up to me on the mountain, and you will make for yourself an ark of wood.<verse eid="DEU 10:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:2"/>And I will write on the tablets the words that were on the former tablets, which you smashed, and you shall put them in the ark."<verse eid="DEU 10:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:3"/>And I made an ark of indestructible boards and carved the two tablets of stone like the former ones and went up the mountain with the two tablets in my hands.<verse eid="DEU 10:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:4"/>And he wrote on the tablets, in accord with the first writing, the ten words that the Lord had spoken to you on the mountain from the midst of the fire, and the Lord gave them to me.<verse eid="DEU 10:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:5"/>And I turned and came down from the mountain and put the tablets in the ark that I had made, and they were there, as the Lord commanded me.<verse eid="DEU 10:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:6"/>(And the sons of Israel departed from Beroth of the sons of Iakim Misadai. There Aaron died, and there he was buried, and his son Eleazar became priest instead of him.<verse eid="DEU 10:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:7"/>From there they departed to Gadgad and from Gadgad to Ietebatha, a land with a wadi of waters.<verse eid="DEU 10:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:8"/>At that time the Lord set apart the tribe of Leui to carry the ark of the covenant of the Lord, to stand before the Lord to minister and to pray in his name, to this day.<verse eid="DEU 10:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:9"/>Therefore, for the Leuites there is not a part or allotment among their brothers; the Lord himself is his allotment, as he said to him.)<verse eid="DEU 10:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:10"/>And I stayed on the mountain forty days and forty nights. And the Lord listened to me in that time also. And the Lord did not want to destroy you utterly.<verse eid="DEU 10:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:11"/>And the Lord said to me, "Go, depart before this people, and let them go in and inherit the land that I swore to their fathers to give them."<verse eid="DEU 10:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:12"/>And now, O Israel, what does the Lord your God ask from you but to fear the Lord your God, to go in all his ways and to love him and to serve the Lord your God with the whole of your heart and with the whole of your soul,<verse eid="DEU 10:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:13"/>to keep the commandments of the Lord your God and his statutes that I command you today so that it may be well with you?<verse eid="DEU 10:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:14"/>Look, the sky and the sky of the sky belong to the Lord your God, the earth and all that is in it.<verse eid="DEU 10:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:15"/>Yet, your fathers, the Lord chose to love them, and he picked you, their offspring after them, you, among all the nations, as it is this day.<verse eid="DEU 10:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:16"/>And you shall circumcise your hardheartedness and shall not harden your neck any longer.<verse eid="DEU 10:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:17"/>For the Lord your God is God of gods and Lord of lords, the great God, mighty and fear-inspiring, who does not marvel at a person, neither will he take a bribe,<verse eid="DEU 10:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:18"/>doing justice to the guest and orphan and widow and loving the guest, to give him food and clothing.<verse eid="DEU 10:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:19"/>You shall also love the guest, for you were guests in the land of Egypt.<verse eid="DEU 10:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:20"/>You shall fear the Lord your God, and him you shall serve, and to him you shall hold fast, and by his name you shall swear.<verse eid="DEU 10:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:21"/>He is your boast, and he is your God, who did among you these great and glorious things that your eyes have seen.<verse eid="DEU 10:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 10:22"/>Your fathers went down to Egypt with seventy persons, and now the Lord your God has made you as the stars in the sky in number.<verse eid="DEU 10:22"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:1"/>And you shall love the Lord your God and keep his orders and his statutes and his commandments and his judgments always.<verse eid="DEU 11:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:2"/>And you shall know today that it was not your children who have not known or seen the discipline of the Lord your God and his magnificent works and his strong hand and his high arm<verse eid="DEU 11:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:3"/>and his signs and his wonders that he did in the midst of Egypt to Pharao, king of Egypt, and to all his land,<verse eid="DEU 11:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:4"/>and what he did to the force of the Egyptians, to their chariots and their horses, how he made the water of the Red Sea flow over them as they pursued you from your rear, and the Lord has destroyed them to this very day,<verse eid="DEU 11:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:5"/>and what he did for you in the wilderness until you came to this place,<verse eid="DEU 11:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:6"/>and what he did to Dathan and Abiron sons of Eliab son of Rouben whom the earth having opened its mouth swallowed them up, along with their households and their tents and all their substance which was with them in the midst of all Israel<verse eid="DEU 11:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:7"/>For it is your eyes that saw all the great deeds of the Lord that he did for you today.<verse eid="DEU 11:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:8"/>And you shall keep all his commandments that I command you today so that you may live and be multiplied and go in and inherit the land into which you are crossing over the Jordan to take possession of it there,<verse eid="DEU 11:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:9"/>so that you may live long in the land that the Lord swore to your fathers to give them and their offspring after them, a land flowing with milk and honey.<verse eid="DEU 11:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:10"/>For the land into which you are about to enter there to inherit it is not like the land of Egypt, whence you are coming from there, when they sow the seed and water it with the feet like a garden of vegetables.<verse eid="DEU 11:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:11"/>But the land into which you are entering there to inherit it is a hilly land and flat; it will drink water from the rain of the sky,<verse eid="DEU 11:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:12"/>a land that the Lord your God regards it. The eyes of the Lord your God are always on it, from the beginning of the year even until the end of the year.<verse eid="DEU 11:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:13"/>Now if by hearing you hear all his commandments that I command you today-- to love the Lord your God and to serve him with the whole of your heart and with the whole of your soul--<verse eid="DEU 11:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:14"/>he too will give the rain for your land in season, early rain and later rain, and you will gather in your grain and your wine and your oil,<verse eid="DEU 11:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:15"/>and he will give fodder in your fields for your cattle.<verse eid="DEU 11:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:16"/>And, when you have eaten and been filled, (16) take care to yourself, lest your heart be expanded, and you turn away and serve other gods and do obeisance to them,<verse eid="DEU 11:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:17"/>and the Lord, being wrathful, be angry against you and shut up the sky, and there will be no rain, and the land will not give its fruit, and you will perish quickly off the good land that the Lord gave you.<verse eid="DEU 11:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:18"/>And you shall put these words in your heart and in your soul, and you shall bind them as a sign on your hand, and they shall be things unshakable before your eyes.<verse eid="DEU 11:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:19"/>And you shall teach your children to say them when they are sitting at home and going on the way and lying down and rising.<verse eid="DEU 11:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:20"/>And you shall write them on the door-posts of your houses and of your gates<verse eid="DEU 11:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:21"/>so that you may be long-lived, and the days of your sons, in the land that the Lord swore to your fathers to give them, may be as the days of the sky above the earth.<verse eid="DEU 11:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:22"/>And it shall be, if by hearing you hear all these commandments that I command you today to do-- to love the Lord your God, to go in all his ways and to hold fast to him--<verse eid="DEU 11:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:23"/>the Lord too will drive out all these nations before you, and you will dispossess nations great and rather stronger than you.<verse eid="DEU 11:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:24"/>Every place, wherever you may plant the trace of your foot, shall be yours, from the wilderness and Anti-Lebanon and from the great river, the river Euphrates, and up to the western sea shall be your borders.<verse eid="DEU 11:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:25"/>No one will stand against you; the Lord your God will put the trembling of you and fear of you on the face of all the land on which you may go upon it, as the Lord spoke to you.<verse eid="DEU 11:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:26"/>See, I am giving before you today a blessing and a curse:<verse eid="DEU 11:26"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:27"/>the blessing, if you hear the commandments of the Lord your God that I command you today,<verse eid="DEU 11:27"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:28"/>and the curse, if you do not hear the commandments of the Lord your God which I command you today and if you wander from the way that I command you, having gone to serve other gods that you do not know.<verse eid="DEU 11:28"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:29"/>And it shall be, when the Lord your God has brought you into the land into which you are crossing there to inherit it, you shall give the blessing on Mount Garizin and the curse on Mount Gaibal.<verse eid="DEU 11:29"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:30"/>Look, are these not across the Jordan beyond, by the way of the setting of the sun, in the land of Chanaan, that which is situated to the west, near Golgol, beside the high oak?<verse eid="DEU 11:30"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:31"/>For you are crossing the Jordan when you go in to inherit the land that the Lord your God is giving you as an allotment, for all days, and you will inherit it and live in it.<verse eid="DEU 11:31"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 11:32"/>And you shall be watchful to perform all these ordinances and these judgments that I am giving before you today.<verse eid="DEU 11:32"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:1"/>And these are the ordinances and the judgments that you shall be watchful to perform in the land that the Lord, the God of your fathers, is giving you as an allotment all the days that you live on the earth.<verse eid="DEU 12:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:2"/>You shall with destruction destroy all the places, there where the nations whom you are about to dispossess serve their gods on the high mountains and on the dunes and beneath every leafy tree.<verse eid="DEU 12:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:3"/>And you shall chop down their altars<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = 'bômos'</char></note> and smash their steles and cut down their groves and burn with fire the carved objects of their gods and blot out their name from that place.<verse eid="DEU 12:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:4"/>You shall not do so to the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 12:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:5"/>But the place which the Lord your God may choose in one of your tribes, to designate that his name be called there, you too will seek and enter there.<verse eid="DEU 12:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:6"/>And you will bring there your whole burnt offerings and your sacrifices and your first fruits and your votive gifts, your freewill gifts and the firstlings of your oxen and sheep.<verse eid="DEU 12:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:7"/>And you shall eat there in the presence of the Lord your God and shall rejoice in all things to which you put your hands, you and your households, as the Lord your God has blessed you.<verse eid="DEU 12:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:8"/>You shall not do all things that we are doing here today, each one doing what is pleasing before him,<verse eid="DEU 12:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:9"/>for you have not come until now into the rest and into the inheritance that the Lord your God is giving you.<verse eid="DEU 12:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:10"/>And you shall cross over the Jordan and live in the land that the Lord your God is allotting to you, and he will give you rest from all your enemies around, and you will live in safety.<verse eid="DEU 12:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:11"/>And it shall be that the place, wherever the Lord your God may choose for his name to be called there, there you shall bring all that I command you today-- your whole burnt offerings and your sacrifices and your tithes and the first fruits of your hands and your gifts and every choice one of your gifts, whatever you may vow to your God.<verse eid="DEU 12:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:12"/>And you shall be joyful before the Lord your God, you and your sons and your daughters, your male and female slaves and the Leuite who is at your gates (since he has no part or allotment with you).<verse eid="DEU 12:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:13"/>Take care to yourself lest you bring your whole burnt offerings at any place where you may look.<verse eid="DEU 12:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:14"/>But at the place, that which the Lord your God may choose in one of your tribes-- there you shall offer your whole burnt offerings, and there you shall do everything I command you today.<verse eid="DEU 12:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:15"/>Yet at your every desire you shall slaughter and eat meat, according to the blessing of the Lord your God which he has given you within any city; the unclean one among you and the clean together shall eat of it, as they would<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'they would':  Lacking in Greek</char></note> gazelle or deer.<verse eid="DEU 12:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:16"/>The blood, however, you shall not eat; you shall pour it out on the ground like water.<verse eid="DEU 12:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:17"/>You shall not be able to eat within your cities the tithe of your grain and of your wine and of your oil, the firstlings of your oxen and of your sheep and all votive gifts that you may vow and your agreements and the first fruits of your hands.<verse eid="DEU 12:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:18"/>But these you shall eat in the presence of the Lord your God at the place, that which the Lord your God may choose, you and your son and your daughter, your male slave and your female slave and the guest in your cities, and you shall be joyful in the presence of the Lord your God in all things where you may put your hand.<verse eid="DEU 12:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:19"/>Take care to yourself lest you neglect the Leuite all the time that you may live in the land.<verse eid="DEU 12:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:20"/>Now if the Lord your God enlarges your borders, as he has said to you, and you shall say, "I am going to eat meat," if your soul desires to eat meat, in every desire of your soul, you shall eat meat.<verse eid="DEU 12:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:21"/>But if the place the Lord your God may choose for his name to be called there is rather far away from you, then you shall slaughter from your oxen and from your sheep that God may give you as I have commanded you, then you shall eat within your cities according to the desire of your soul.<verse eid="DEU 12:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:22"/>Just as the gazelle is eaten and the deer, so you shall eat it; the unclean one among you and the clean alike shall eat it.<verse eid="DEU 12:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:23"/>Take great care not to eat blood, because its blood is life; the life shall not be eaten with the meat.<verse eid="DEU 12:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:24"/>You shall not eat it; you shall pour it out on the ground like water.<verse eid="DEU 12:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:25"/>You shall not eat it so that it may go well with you and your sons after you, if you do what is good and pleasing before the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 12:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:26"/>But when you have taken your sacred things, whatever you may have, and your votive gifts, you shall come to the place which the Lord your God may choose for himself for his name to be called there.<verse eid="DEU 12:26"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:27"/>And you shall make your whole burnt offerings; the meat you will offer on the altar of the Lord your God, but the blood of your sacrifices you will pour out at the base of the altar of the Lord your God, but the meat you shall eat.<verse eid="DEU 12:27"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:28"/>Keep, and hear, and you will do all the words that I command you so that it may go well with you and with your sons forever, if you do what is good and pleasing before the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 12:28"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:29"/>Now if the Lord your God utterly destroys from before you the nations among which you may enter there to inherit their land, and you dispossess them and live in their land,<verse eid="DEU 12:29"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:30"/>take care to yourself lest you seek to follow them, after they have been utterly destroyed from before you: you shall not seek their gods, saying, "How do these nations act toward their gods? I will do the same."<verse eid="DEU 12:30"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:31"/>You shall not do thus to the Lord your God, for the abominations to the Lord, which he hates, they have done for their gods. For they burn their sons and their daughters in fire to their gods.<verse eid="DEU 12:31"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 12:32"/>Every word that I command you today, this you shall be watchful to perform; you shall not add to it or take from it.<verse eid="DEU 12:32"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:1"/>Now if a prophet or one who divines by a dream should appear among you and give you a sign or a wonder,<verse eid="DEU 13:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:2"/>and the sign or the wonder should come about, which he spoke to you, saying: "Let us go and serve other gods (whom you have not known) ,"<verse eid="DEU 13:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:3"/>you shall not hear the words of that prophet or diviner by that dream, for the Lord God is testing you, to know whether you love the Lord your God with the whole of your heart and with the whole of your soul.<verse eid="DEU 13:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:4"/>Go after the Lord your God, and him you shall fear, and his commandments you shall keep, and his voice you shall hear, and to him you shall be joined.<verse eid="DEU 13:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:5"/>And that prophet or that diviner by dream shall die, for he spoke to lead you astray from the Lord your God-- who brought you out of the land of Egypt, who redeemed you from slavery-- to thrust you from the way that the Lord your God commanded you to go upon it. And you shall eliminate the evil one from yourselves.<verse eid="DEU 13:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:6"/>Now if your brother from your father or from your mother or your own son or daughter or the wife in your bosom or the friend who is like your own soul secretly entreats you, saying, "Let us go and serve other gods," whom you do not know, you nor your fathers,<verse eid="DEU 13:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:7"/>from the gods of the nations that are around you, those near you or far away from you, from an end of the earth up to an end of the earth,<verse eid="DEU 13:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:8"/>you shall not yield to him and listen to him. And your eye shall not be sparing toward him; you shall not have a longing for him, neither shall you shield him.<verse eid="DEU 13:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:9"/>Reporting, you shall report concerning him, and your own hands shall be first against him to kill him, and afterwards the hands of all the people.<verse eid="DEU 13:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:10"/>And they shall stone him with stones, and he shall die because he sought to turn you away from the Lord your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of a house of slavery.<verse eid="DEU 13:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:11"/>And all Israel, when they have heard, will be afraid and never do again according to this evil thing among you.<verse eid="DEU 13:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:12"/>Now if you hear in one of the cities that the Lord your God is giving you to live therein, saying:<verse eid="DEU 13:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:13"/>"Lawless men have gone out from among you and led all the inhabitants of their city astray, saying, 'Let us go and serve other gods,'" whom you have not known,<verse eid="DEU 13:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:14"/>then you shall examine and ask and make a thorough investigation, and look, the charge is clearly true, this abomination has been done among you,<verse eid="DEU 13:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:15"/>wiping out, you shall wipe out all the inhabitants of that city by slaughter by dagger; with an anathema, you shall anathematize it, and everything in it.<verse eid="DEU 13:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:16"/>And all of its spoil you shall gather into its streets, and you shall burn with fire the city and all its spoil with its population, before the Lord your God. It shall remain uninhabited forever, never to be rebuilt.<verse eid="DEU 13:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:17"/>Nothing from that which is anathema shall stick to your hand so that the Lord may turn from the heat of his anger, and he shall give you mercy and be merciful to you and multiply you, as the Lord swore to your fathers,<verse eid="DEU 13:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 13:18"/>if you hear the voice of the Lord your God to keep all his commandments that I command you today, to do what is good and pleasing before the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 13:18"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:1"/>You are sons of the Lord your God. You shall not practice purification rites<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">14:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'practice purification rites':  Greek uncertain</char></note>; you shall not place a baldness between your eyes for a corpse.<verse eid="DEU 14:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:2"/>For you are a people holy to the Lord your God, and it is you the Lord your God has chosen to be an exceptional people to him out of all the nations on the face of the earth.<verse eid="DEU 14:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:3"/>You shall not eat any abomination.<verse eid="DEU 14:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:4"/>These are the animals you shall eat: calf of cows and lamb of sheep and kid of goats,<verse eid="DEU 14:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:5"/>deer and gazelle and roebuck and wild goat and white-rumped antelope and antelope and giraffe.<verse eid="DEU 14:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:6"/>Any animal that divides the hoof and splits the hooves into two parts and brings up the cud, among the animals-- these you shall eat.<verse eid="DEU 14:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:7"/>And these you shall not eat of those that regurgitate the cud and of those dividing the hoofs and making distinct claws: the camel and hare and coney, because these regurgitate the cud but do not divide the hoof; these are unclean for you.<verse eid="DEU 14:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:8"/>And the pig, because this animal divides the hoof and makes distinct claws but this one does not chew the cud; this one is unclean for you. You shall not eat their flesh, and you shall not touch their carcasses.<verse eid="DEU 14:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:9"/>And of all that live in water you shall eat these: whatever has fins and scales you shall eat.<verse eid="DEU 14:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:10"/>And whatever does not have fins and scales you shall not eat; these are unclean for you.<verse eid="DEU 14:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:11"/>You shall eat any clean bird.<verse eid="DEU 14:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:12"/>And these, you shall not eat from them: the eagle and the bearded vulture and the osprey<verse eid="DEU 14:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:13"/>and the vulture and the kite and those like it,<verse eid="DEU 14:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:14"/>and every raven and those like it, (15) and ostrich and little owl and sea gull and hawk and those like it,<verse eid="DEU 14:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:15"/>(16) and heron and swan and ibis<verse eid="DEU 14:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:16"/>(17) and diving petrel and hoopoe and long-eared owl<verse eid="DEU 14:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:17"/>(18) and pelican and water plover and those like it, and water hen and bat.<verse eid="DEU 14:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:18"/>(19) All creeping ones of those that fly<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">14:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'creeping ones of those that fly':  I.e. 'insects'</char></note>-- these are unclean for you; you shall not eat from them.<verse eid="DEU 14:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:19"/>(20) You shall eat any clean winged creature.<verse eid="DEU 14:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:20"/>(21) And you shall not eat any carcass; it shall be given to the resident alien in your cities, and he will eat, or you shall sell to a stranger. For you are a people holy to the Lord your God. You shall not boil a lamb in its mother's milk.<verse eid="DEU 14:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:21"/>(22) You shall tithe a tithe of all the yield of your seed, the yield of your field, year by year.<verse eid="DEU 14:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:22"/>(23) And you shall eat it in the presence of the Lord your God, in the place that the Lord your God may choose for his name to be called there you shall bring the tithes of your grain and of your wine and of your oil, the firstlings of your cows and of your sheep so that you may learn to fear the Lord your God all your days.<verse eid="DEU 14:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:23"/>(24) But if the distance is far from you and you are unable to transport them, because the place which the Lord your God may choose for his name to be called there is far away from you, because the Lord your God will bless you,<verse eid="DEU 14:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:24"/>(25) you shall then convert them into money and take the money in your hands and go to the place, that which the Lord your God may choose,<verse eid="DEU 14:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:25"/>(26) and you shall give the money for whatever your soul may desire-- for oxen or for sheep, for wine or for sikera<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">14:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Aramaic = 'strong drink'</char></note> or for whatever your soul desires. And you shall eat there in the presence of the Lord your God, and you and your household shall be joyful,<verse eid="DEU 14:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:26"/>(27) and the Leuite in your cities, because he has no part or allotment with you.<verse eid="DEU 14:26"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:27"/>(28) After three years you shall bring out every tithe of your yield; in that year, you shall store it within your cities,<verse eid="DEU 14:27"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 14:28"/>(29) and the Leuite shall come, because he has no part or allotment with you, and the guest and the orphan and the widow in your cities, and they shall eat and shall be filled so that the Lord your God may bless you in all the works whatever you may do.<verse eid="DEU 14:28"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:1"/>Through seven years you shall make a remission.<verse eid="DEU 15:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:2"/>And thus is the ordinance of the remission: you shall remit every personal debt which your neighbor owes you, and you shall not ask it back of your brother, because a remission to the Lord your God has been proclaimed.<verse eid="DEU 15:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:3"/>Of a stranger you may ask back whatever he has that belongs to you; to your brother you must make a release of the debt to you.<verse eid="DEU 15:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:4"/>For there will be no one in need among you, because by blessing the Lord your God will bless you in the land that the Lord your God is giving you as an allotment to inherit it.<verse eid="DEU 15:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:5"/>But if by hearing you listen to the voice of the Lord your God by keeping and doing all these commandments that I command you today--<verse eid="DEU 15:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:6"/>because the Lord your God has blessed you, as he said to you-- you will even lend to many nations, but you will not borrow, and you will rule over many nations, but they will not rule over you.<verse eid="DEU 15:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:7"/>Now if there is among you anyone of your brothers in need in one of your cities within the land that the Lord your God is giving you, you shall not rid your heart of love, neither shall you close up your hand from your needy brother.<verse eid="DEU 15:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:8"/>By opening, you shall open your hands to him; you shall lend a loan to him whatever he may need, in accord with what he needs.<verse eid="DEU 15:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:9"/>Be careful to yourself, lest a secret word is in your heart, something lawless, saying, "The seventh year, a year of release, is near," and your eye be evil towards your needy brother, and you will not give to him, and he will cry out to the Lord against you, and it will be for you a great sin.<verse eid="DEU 15:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:10"/>Giving you shall give to him, and you shall lend him a loan whatever he needs, and you shall not be grieved in your heart when you give to him, because through this thing the Lord your God will bless you in all your works and in all to which you may put your hand.<verse eid="DEU 15:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:11"/>For the needy shall not fail from the earth; I therefore command you to do this thing, saying, "By opening, you shall open your hands to your brother who is poor and to the needy in your land."<verse eid="DEU 15:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:12"/>But if your brother is sold to you, whether a Hebrew man or a Hebrew woman, he shall be subject to you six years, and in the seventh year you shall send him out a free person from you.<verse eid="DEU 15:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:13"/>And when you send him out from you a free person, you shall not send him out empty.<verse eid="DEU 15:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:14"/>You shall provide provisions to him from your sheep and from your grain and from your wine press; as the Lord your God has blessed you, you will give to him.<verse eid="DEU 15:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:15"/>And you shall remember that you were a domestic in the land of Egypt, and the Lord your God redeemed you from there; for this reason I command you to do this thing.<verse eid="DEU 15:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:16"/>But if he says to you, "I will not go out from you," because he loved you and your household, since it is good for him with you,<verse eid="DEU 15:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:17"/>you shall then take an awl and pierce his ear against the door, and he shall be a domestic to you forever. And you shall do likewise with regard to your female slave.<verse eid="DEU 15:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:18"/>It shall not be hard on you when they are being sent out from you as free persons, because for six years he was a slave to you in lieu of an annual wage for the hired laborer, and the Lord your God will bless you in all that you may do.<verse eid="DEU 15:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:19"/>Every firstling that may be born among your cows and among your sheep, you shall consecrate the males to the Lord your God; you shall not do work with your firstling calf, and you shall not shear the firstling of your sheep.<verse eid="DEU 15:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:20"/>In the presence of the Lord your God you shall eat it, year by year at the place that the Lord your God may choose, you and your household.<verse eid="DEU 15:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:21"/>But if there is a defect in it-- be it lame or blind-- or even any serious defect, you shall not sacrifice it to the Lord your God;<verse eid="DEU 15:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:22"/>within your cities you shall eat it; the unclean and the clean alike shall eat, like gazelle or deer.<verse eid="DEU 15:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 15:23"/>But its blood you shall not eat; you shall pour it out on the ground like water.<verse eid="DEU 15:23"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:1"/>Observe the month of new things, and you shall perform the pascha<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">16:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'passover'</char></note> for the Lord your God, for in the month of new things you came out of Egypt by night.<verse eid="DEU 16:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:2"/>And you shall sacrifice the pascha for the Lord your God, sheep and cows, at the place that the Lord your God may choose for his name to be called there.<verse eid="DEU 16:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:3"/>You shall not eat leaven with it. For seven days you shall eat unleavened with it-- bread of affliction-- because you came out of Egypt in haste so that all the days of your life you may remember the day of your departure from the land of Egypt.<verse eid="DEU 16:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:4"/>Leaven shall not be seen with you in all your borders for seven days, and none of the meat of what you may sacrifice in the evening on the first day shall lie until morning.<verse eid="DEU 16:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:5"/>You shall not be able to offer the pascha within any of your cities that the Lord your God is giving you.<verse eid="DEU 16:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:6"/>But at the place that the Lord your God may choose for his name to be called there, you shall offer the pascha, in the evening at sunset, the time when you departed from Egypt.<verse eid="DEU 16:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:7"/>And you shall boil and roast and eat it at the place that the Lord your God may choose, and you shall return the next morning and go back to your houses.<verse eid="DEU 16:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:8"/>For six days you shall eat unleavened bread, and on the seventh day there shall be a finale, a feast for the Lord your God; you shall do no work on it except that which shall be done for life.<verse eid="DEU 16:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:9"/>You shall count for yourself seven complete weeks; when you have started the sickle on the standing grain, you shall begin to count seven weeks.<verse eid="DEU 16:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:10"/>And you shall make the feast of weeks for the Lord your God, according as your hand is able, whatever he may give to you, as the Lord your God has blessed you.<verse eid="DEU 16:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:11"/>And you shall be joyful before the Lord your God-- you and your son and your daughter, your male slave and your female slave and the Leuite who is in your cities, as well as the guest and the orphan and the widow who is among you-- at the place that the Lord your God may choose for his name to be called there.<verse eid="DEU 16:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:12"/>And you shall remember that you were a domestic in the land of Egypt, and you shall keep and do these commandments.<verse eid="DEU 16:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:13"/>You shall make for yourself a feast of tents for seven days, when you have gathered in from your threshing floor and from your wine press.<verse eid="DEU 16:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:14"/>And you shall be joyful at your feast, you and your son and your daughter, your male slave and your female slave and the Leuite and the guest and the orphan and the widow in your cities.<verse eid="DEU 16:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:15"/>Seven days you shall feast for the Lord your God at the place, that which the Lord your God may choose. Now if the Lord your God blesses you in all your yield and in every work of your hands, then you shall be joyful.<verse eid="DEU 16:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:16"/>Three times a year every male among you shall appear before the Lord your God at the place, that which the Lord may choose: at the feast of unleavened bread and at the feast of weeks and at the feast of tent pitching. You shall not appear before the Lord your God empty-handed,<verse eid="DEU 16:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:17"/>each according to the strength of your hands, according to the blessing of the Lord your God that he gave you.<verse eid="DEU 16:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:18"/>You shall appoint for yourselves judges and recorders in all your cities that the Lord your God is giving you, by tribe, and they shall render just decisions for the people.<verse eid="DEU 16:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:19"/>They shall not bend justice; they shall not recognize a person, neither shall they take gifts. For gifts blind the eyes of the wise and nullify the words of the righteous.<verse eid="DEU 16:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:20"/>You shall pursue justice fairly so that you may live, and when you have entered, you may inherit the land that the Lord your God is giving you.<verse eid="DEU 16:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:21"/>You shall not plant for yourself a grove, any tree beside the altar of the Lord your God which you will make for yourself;<verse eid="DEU 16:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 16:22"/>you shall not set up for yourself a stele-- things which the Lord your God hated.<verse eid="DEU 16:22"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:1"/>You shall not sacrifice to the Lord your God a calf or a sheep, that in which there is a defect, anything wrong, for it is an abomination to the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 17:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:2"/>Now if there be found among you, in one of your cities that the Lord your God is giving you, a man or woman who will do what is evil in the sight of the Lord your God, to transgress his covenant,<verse eid="DEU 17:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:3"/>and, having gone out, they should serve other gods and do obeisance to them-- whether the sun or the moon or any of what belongs to the adornment of the sky, which I have not ordered--<verse eid="DEU 17:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:4"/>and if it be reported to you and you will make a thorough inquiry and behold, the matter has truly occurred, this abomination has occurred in Israel,<verse eid="DEU 17:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:5"/>then you shall bring out that man or that woman and stone them with stones, and they will die.<verse eid="DEU 17:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:6"/>On two witnesses or upon three witnesses, the one who is to die shall die; he shall not die on the basis of one witness.<verse eid="DEU 17:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:7"/>And the hand of the witnesses shall be the first against him to put him to death, and the hand of all the people last. And you shall remove the evil one from yourselves.<verse eid="DEU 17:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:8"/>But if a matter be too difficult for you in judgment: bloodshed from bloodshed and legal right from legal right and assault from assault and dispute from dispute-- matters of judgment in your cities-- then, having arisen, you shall go up to the place that the Lord your God may choose for his name to be called there,<verse eid="DEU 17:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:9"/>and you shall come to the priests, the Leuites and to the judge whoever may be in those days, and, after they have inquired, they shall announce to you the judgment.<verse eid="DEU 17:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:10"/>And you shall do according to the word whatever they report to you from the place that the Lord your God may choose for his name to be called there, and you shall guard very much to do according to all things whatever is legislated for you.<verse eid="DEU 17:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:11"/>You shall act according to the law and according to the judgment that they tell you; you shall not turn aside from the decision that they may announce to you, right or left.<verse eid="DEU 17:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:12"/>And as for the person who may act in pride by not obeying the priest in attendance, to minister in the name of the Lord your God, or the judge, whoever may be in those days, that person shall die, and you shall remove the evil one from Israel.<verse eid="DEU 17:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:13"/>And all the people, when they have heard, will be afraid and will not act impiously again.<verse eid="DEU 17:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:14"/>Now if you come into the land that the Lord your God is giving you and take possession of it and live in it and you say, "I will set a ruler over me, like the rest of the nations that are around me,"<verse eid="DEU 17:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:15"/>by appointing, you shall appoint over you a ruler, him whom the Lord your God may choose. One of your own brothers you shall appoint as ruler over you; you shall not have power to appoint a strange person over you, because he is not your brother.<verse eid="DEU 17:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:16"/>For he shall not multiply cavalry for himself or return the people to Egypt in order to multiply cavalry for himself, but the Lord has said to you, "You shall never add to return that way."<verse eid="DEU 17:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:17"/>And he shall not multiply wives for himself, neither shall his heart turn away; also silver and gold he shall not multiply exceedingly for himself.<verse eid="DEU 17:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:18"/>And it shall be, when he has sat upon the seat of his rule, that he shall write for himself this second law in a book from the priests, the Leuites.<verse eid="DEU 17:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:19"/>And it shall be with him, and he shall read from it all the days of his life so that he may learn to fear the Lord his God, to keep all these commandments and these statutes to do them<verse eid="DEU 17:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 17:20"/>so that his heart may not be exalted above his brothers so that he not turn aside from the commandments, right or left, in order that he be long-lived in his rule, he and his sons among the sons of Israel.<verse eid="DEU 17:20"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:1"/>There shall not be for the priests, the Leuites, the whole tribe of Leui, a part or allotment with Israel. The offerings of the Lord are their allotment; they shall eat of them,<verse eid="DEU 18:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:2"/>but he shall have no allotment among his brothers; the Lord himself is his allotment, as he said to him.<verse eid="DEU 18:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:3"/>And this is the judgment for priests, things due from the people, from those offering sacrifices, whether a calf, whether a sheep, and he shall give to the priest the shoulder and the cheeks and the paunch<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">18:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'fourth stomach of ruminating animals'</char></note>.<verse eid="DEU 18:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:4"/>And the first fruits of your grain and your wine and your oil and the first of the fleeces of your sheep you shall give him.<verse eid="DEU 18:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:5"/>For the Lord has chosen him out of all your tribes, to stand before the Lord your God to minister and to bless in his name, he and his sons all the days.<verse eid="DEU 18:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:6"/>Now if a Leuite departs (from one of your cities, from all the sons of Israel wherever he sojourns, as his soul desires) for the place that the Lord may choose,<verse eid="DEU 18:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:7"/>he shall minister in the name of the Lord his God, like all his brothers-- the Leuites who stand there before the Lord.<verse eid="DEU 18:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:8"/>He shall eat an allotted portion, apart from the sale which is by paternal lineage<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">18:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'by paternal lineage':  Possibly 'due to inheritance'</char></note>.<verse eid="DEU 18:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:9"/>Now if you enter into the land that the Lord your God is giving you, you shall not learn to act according to the abominations of those nations.<verse eid="DEU 18:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:10"/>There shall not be found among you one who cleanses his son or his daughter by fire, one who practices divination, one who acts as diviner, one who practices ornithomancy, a sorcerer,<verse eid="DEU 18:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:11"/>one who casts spells, a ventriloquist<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">18:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'one who gives oracles from the belly'</char></note> and one who observes signs and one who inquires of the dead.<verse eid="DEU 18:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:12"/>For anyone who does these things is an abomination to the Lord your God, for it is because of these abominations that the Lord your God will destroy them utterly from before you.<verse eid="DEU 18:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:13"/>You shall be perfect before the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 18:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:14"/>For these nations that you are about to dispossess, these will hear omens and divinations, but as for you, the Lord your God has not granted you to do so.<verse eid="DEU 18:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:15"/>The Lord your God will raise up for you a prophet like me from among your brothers; you shall hear him.<verse eid="DEU 18:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:16"/>According to all that you requested of the Lord your God at Choreb on the day of the assembly, saying: "We shall not any more hear the voice of the Lord our God and again see this great fire-- and we shall not die."<verse eid="DEU 18:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:17"/>And the Lord said to me: "They are right in all that they have said.<verse eid="DEU 18:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:18"/>I will raise up for them a prophet just like you from among their brothers, and I will give my word in his mouth, and he shall speak to them whatever I command him.<verse eid="DEU 18:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:19"/>And the person who does not hear his words, whatever the prophet may speak in my name, I will exact vengeance from him.<verse eid="DEU 18:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:20"/>But the prophet who acts impiously by speaking a word in my name that I have not ordered to speak and who speaks in the name of other gods, that prophet shall die."<verse eid="DEU 18:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:21"/>But if you say in your heart, "How will we know the word that the Lord has not spoken?"<verse eid="DEU 18:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 18:22"/>whatever the prophet might speak in the name of the Lord but the thing does not take place and does not happen, this is the word that the Lord has not spoken. That prophet has spoken it in impiety; you shall not spare him.<verse eid="DEU 18:22"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:1"/>Now if the Lord your God annihilates the nations whose land your God is giving you and you dispossess them and live in their cities and in their houses,<verse eid="DEU 19:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:2"/>you shall set apart three cities for yourself in the midst of your land that the Lord your God is giving you.<verse eid="DEU 19:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:3"/>Calculate for yourself the distance, and you shall divide into three regions your land that the Lord your God apportions you, and there shall be a refuge there for every murderer.<verse eid="DEU 19:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:4"/>Now this is the ordinance for a murderer who flees there and shall live: He who strikes his neighbor unintentionally and he did not hate him before yesterday and before the third day,<verse eid="DEU 19:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:5"/>and he who goes into the forest with his neighbor to gather wood and his hand is knocked aside when he cuts the wood with the ax, and the iron slips from the wood and happens to strike his neighbor, and he dies, this one shall flee to one of these cities and live,<verse eid="DEU 19:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:6"/>lest the avenger of blood pursue after the murderer, because his heart is hot, and overtake him-- if the road was rather long-- and he strike his soul, and he dies, and to this one there is not a death sentence, since he did not hate him before yesterday and before the third day.<verse eid="DEU 19:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:7"/>Therefore I command you this thing, saying: You shall set apart three cities for yourself.<verse eid="DEU 19:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:8"/>But if the Lord your God enlarges your borders, as he swore to your fathers, and he gives you all the land that he said he would give your fathers,<verse eid="DEU 19:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:9"/>-- if you give heed to do all these commandments that I command you today, to love the Lord your God and to walk in all his ways all the days-- then you shall add for yourself three more cities to these three,<verse eid="DEU 19:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:10"/>and innocent blood shall not be shed in your land that the Lord your God is giving you as an allotment, and there shall not be among you one guilty of blood.<verse eid="DEU 19:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:11"/>But if there be a person hating his neighbor and he lies in wait for him and attacks him and strikes his life and he dies and flees into one of these cities,<verse eid="DEU 19:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:12"/>then the council of elders of his city shall send and take him from there and deliver him into the hand of the avenger of blood, and he shall die.<verse eid="DEU 19:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:13"/>Your eye shall not be sparing toward him, and you shall cleanse the innocent blood from Israel, and it shall be well with you.<verse eid="DEU 19:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:14"/>You shall not move your neighbor's boundaries, which your fathers have set up on the inheritance you were allotted in the land that the Lord your God is giving you to inherit.<verse eid="DEU 19:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:15"/>One witness shall not suffice against a person in any injustice and in any wrongdoing and in any sin that he may sin. By the mouth of two or three witnesses shall any word be sustained.<verse eid="DEU 19:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:16"/>But if an unjust witness comes forward against a person, alleging impiety against him,<verse eid="DEU 19:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:17"/>then the two persons between whom is the dispute shall stand before the Lord and before the priests and before the judges, who may be in those days,<verse eid="DEU 19:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:18"/>and if the judges make a thorough inquiry and, look, an unjust witness has testified unjustly, he has stood up against his brother,<verse eid="DEU 19:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:19"/>then you shall do to him just as he connived to do to his brother. And you shall remove the evil one from yourselves.<verse eid="DEU 19:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:20"/>And the rest, when they hear, shall be afraid and will not add to act again according to this evil thing among you.<verse eid="DEU 19:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 19:21"/>Your eye shall not be sparing against him: soul for soul, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot.<verse eid="DEU 19:21"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:1"/>Now if you go out to war against your enemies and see horse and rider and a people more numerous than you, you shall not be afraid of them, for the Lord your God is with you, who made you go up from the land of Egypt.<verse eid="DEU 20:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:2"/>And it shall be when you draw near for battle, then the priest, when he has come forward, shall speak to the people<verse eid="DEU 20:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:3"/>and say to them: "Hear, O Israel! Today you are advancing to battle against your enemies. Let your heart not be undone; be not afraid, nor be shattered, nor turn aside from before them,<verse eid="DEU 20:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:4"/>for it is the Lord your God who advances with you, to fight with you against your enemies, to save you."<verse eid="DEU 20:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:5"/>Then the scribes shall speak to the people, saying, "Who is the person who built a new house and did not dedicate it? Let him go and return to his house, lest he die in the battle, and another person will dedicate it.<verse eid="DEU 20:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:6"/>And who is the person who planted a vineyard and has not had enjoyment from it? Let him go and return to his house, lest he die in the battle and another person will have enjoyment from it.<verse eid="DEU 20:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:7"/>And who is the person who became engaged to a woman but has not yet taken her? Let him go and return to his house, lest he die in the battle and another person will take her."<verse eid="DEU 20:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:8"/>And the scribes shall add to speak to the people and will say, "Who is the person fearful and cowardly in heart? Let him go and return to his house, lest he cause the heart of his brother to be cowardly like his own."<verse eid="DEU 20:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:9"/>And it shall be when the scribes have ceased speaking to the people, then they shall appoint commanders of the army, as leaders for the people.<verse eid="DEU 20:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:10"/>Now if you draw near to a city to fight against it, then you shall call them out with peace.<verse eid="DEU 20:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:11"/>If they respond to you peaceably and open to you, it shall be that all the people found in it shall be bearers of tribute and be subject to you.<verse eid="DEU 20:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:12"/>But if they do not respond to you and make war against you, then you shall besiege it,<verse eid="DEU 20:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:13"/>and the Lord your God will deliver it into your hands, and you shall strike every male in it with slaughter by dagger,<verse eid="DEU 20:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:14"/>except the women and the baggage. And all the livestock and all which is in the city and all the spoil you shall take as plunder for yourself, and you shall eat all the plunder of your enemies, which the Lord your God is giving you.<verse eid="DEU 20:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:15"/>Thus you shall do to all the cities that are very far from you, which are not of the cities of these nations.<verse eid="DEU 20:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:16"/>But look, of the cities of these nations that the Lord your God is giving you to inherit their land, you shall not let anything of them that breathes remain alive.<verse eid="DEU 20:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:17"/>But with anathema, you shall anathematize them-- the Chettite and the Amorrite and the Chananite and the Pherezite and the Heuite and the Iebousite and the Gergesite-- as the Lord your God has commanded you,<verse eid="DEU 20:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:18"/>lest they teach you to do all their abominations that they did for their gods and you sin before the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 20:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:19"/>But if you besiege a city for rather many days, to make war against it in order to take it, you shall not utterly destroy its trees by wielding iron against them; rather you shall eat from it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">20:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Perhaps 'a fruit-bearing tree'</char></note>, but you shall not cut it down. Is the tree in the field a human being that it should enter into the palisade from before you?<verse eid="DEU 20:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 20:20"/>But a tree that you know does not produce edible fruit, this one you shall utterly destroy and cut down, and you shall build siege works against the city that makes war with you until it be delivered up.<verse eid="DEU 20:20"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:1"/>Now if, in the land that the Lord your God is giving you to inherit, someone wounded is found having fallen on the plain, and they do not know who struck him down,<verse eid="DEU 21:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:2"/>the council of elders and the judges shall come out and measure out to the cities that surround the wounded.<verse eid="DEU 21:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:3"/>And it shall be the city nearest the wounded, and the council of elders of that city shall take a heifer from the cows that has not been worked and which has not pulled in a yoke,<verse eid="DEU 21:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:4"/>and the council of elders of that city shall make the heifer go down to a rugged ravine, which is neither worked nor sown, and shall hamstring the heifer in the ravine.<verse eid="DEU 21:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:5"/>And the priests, the Leuites, shall come forward, for the Lord God has chosen them to stand by him and to bless in his name, and by their mouth every dispute and every assault shall be.<verse eid="DEU 21:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:6"/>And the entire council of elders of that city, those nearest the wounded, shall wash their hands over the head of the heifer that was hamstrung in the ravine,<verse eid="DEU 21:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:7"/>and in reply they shall say: "Our hands did not shed this blood, and our eyes have not seen.<verse eid="DEU 21:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:8"/>Be merciful to your people Israel, whom you redeemed, O Lord, so that innocent blood may not be among your people Israel." And the blood will be propitiated for them.<verse eid="DEU 21:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:9"/>But you shall remove innocent blood from yourselves, if you do what is pleasing and good in the sight of the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 21:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:10"/>Now if you go out to war against your enemies and the Lord your God delivers them into your hands and you take as plunder their booty<verse eid="DEU 21:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:11"/>and you see among the booty a woman, beautiful in appearance, and you desire her and take her for yourself as wife,<verse eid="DEU 21:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:12"/>then you shall bring her inside your house, and you shall shave her head and pare her nails,<verse eid="DEU 21:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:13"/>and you shall remove her clothes of captivity from her, and she shall settle in your house and mourn for her father and her mother days of a month<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">21:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'days of a month':  I.e. 'a whole month'</char></note>, and after that you shall go in to her and live together with her, and she shall be your wife.<verse eid="DEU 21:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:14"/>And it shall be, if you do not want her, you shall send her away free, and by a sale she shall not be sold for money. You shall not break faith with her, since you have humbled her.<verse eid="DEU 21:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:15"/>Now if a man has two wives, one of them loved and one of them hated, and if both the loved and the hated bear him children and the firstborn son is of the one who is hated,<verse eid="DEU 21:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:16"/>it shall be, then, on the day when he wills his possessions to his sons, he shall not be able to treat the son of the loved as the firstborn by ignoring the son of the hated who is the firstborn.<verse eid="DEU 21:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:17"/>On the contrary, he shall acknowledge the firstborn son of the one who is hated by giving him a double portion of all things which he is found to have, since he is the first issue of his children and to this one belongs the right of the firstborn.<verse eid="DEU 21:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:18"/>Now if someone has a disobedient and contentious son who does not obey the voice of his father and the voice of his mother, and they discipline him, and he does not listen to them,<verse eid="DEU 21:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:19"/>then his father and his mother, after they have taken hold of him, shall also bring him out to the council of elders of his city and to the gate of his place.<verse eid="DEU 21:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:20"/>And they shall say to the men of his city, "This son of ours is disobedient and contentious. He does not obey our voice. Being disposed to feasting, he is a drunkard."<verse eid="DEU 21:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:21"/>And the men of his city shall stone him with stones, and he shall die. And you shall remove the evil one from yourselves and the others, when they hear, will be afraid.<verse eid="DEU 21:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:22"/>Now if there is in someone sin, a judgment of death, and he dies and you hang him on a tree,<verse eid="DEU 21:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 21:23"/>his body shall not sleep upon the tree, but with burial you shall bury him that same day, for anyone hanging on a tree is cursed by a god. And you shall not defile the land that the Lord your God is giving you as an allotment.<verse eid="DEU 21:23"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:1"/>When you see your brother's bull calf or his sheep straying away on the road, do not overlook them; by restoring, you shall restore them to your brother.<verse eid="DEU 22:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:2"/>Now if your brother is not near you or you do not know him, you shall bring them inside in your house, and they shall be with you until your brother seeks them; then you shall give them back to him.<verse eid="DEU 22:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:3"/>So you shall treat his donkey, and so you shall treat his garment, and so you shall act in every loss of your brother, whatever may be lost by him and you find; you shall not be able to overlook.<verse eid="DEU 22:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:4"/>You shall not see your brother's donkey or his bull calf fallen on the road. Do not overlook them; raising, you shall raise them up with him.<verse eid="DEU 22:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:5"/>There shall not be the equipment of a man upon a woman, nor shall a man put on a woman's garment, because anyone doing these things is an abomination to the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 22:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:6"/>Now if you come on a nest of birds before you on the road or in any tree or on the ground, with fledglings or eggs, and the mother is brooding on the fledglings or on the eggs, you shall not take the mother with the young ones.<verse eid="DEU 22:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:7"/>By release, you shall release the mother, but the young you shall take for yourself in order that it may go well with you and you may live long.<verse eid="DEU 22:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:8"/>Now if you build a new house, you shall make a parapet for your building, and you will not do murder in your house, if one who falls should fall from it.<verse eid="DEU 22:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:9"/>You shall not sow your vineyard different in kind, lest the produce and the seed be sanctified, whatever you sow with the yield of your vineyard.<verse eid="DEU 22:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:10"/>You shall not plow with an calf and a donkey together.<verse eid="DEU 22:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:11"/>You shall not wear something adulterated-- wool and linen combined.<verse eid="DEU 22:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:12"/>You shall make tassels for yourself on the four corners of your garments, those in which you may wrap yourself.<verse eid="DEU 22:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:13"/>Now if any one takes a woman and cohabits with her and hates her<verse eid="DEU 22:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:14"/>and places upon her specious charges and brings upon her an evil name and says, "I have taken this woman, but when I had approached her, I failed to find proofs of her virginity,"<verse eid="DEU 22:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:15"/>then the father of the girl and her mother, having taken them, shall bring the proofs of the girl's virginity to the council of elders at the gate.<verse eid="DEU 22:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:16"/>And the father of the girl shall say to the council of elders: "I gave this my daughter to this man for a wife, but, hating her,<verse eid="DEU 22:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:17"/>he is now placing specious charges against her, saying, 'I failed to find in your daughter proofs of virginity.' But these are the proofs of my daughter's virginity." And they shall spread out the garment before the council of elders of the city.<verse eid="DEU 22:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:18"/>And the council of elders of that city shall take that man and discipline him,<verse eid="DEU 22:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:19"/>and they shall fine him one hundred shekels, and they shall give them to the young woman's father because he cast an evil name upon an Israelite virgin. And she shall be his wife; he shall not be able to send her away for all time.<verse eid="DEU 22:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:20"/>But if this charge is true and the evidence of the young woman's virginity was not found,<verse eid="DEU 22:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:21"/>then they shall bring the young woman out to her father's doors, and the men of her city shall stone her with stones, and she will die, because she did folly in Israel by prostituting her father's house. And you shall remove the evil one from yourselves.<verse eid="DEU 22:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:22"/>Now if a man is found lying with a woman married to a man, you will kill both of them, the man who lay with the woman and the woman. And you shall remove the evil one from Israel.<verse eid="DEU 22:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:23"/>But if there is a girl, a virgin engaged to a man, and a man finding her in the city should lie with her,<verse eid="DEU 22:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:24"/>bring both of them to the gate of their city, and they shall be stoned with stones, and they shall die-- the young woman, because she did not cry out in the city, and the man, because he humbled his neighbor's woman. And you shall remove the evil one from yourselves.<verse eid="DEU 22:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:25"/>But if a man finds the engaged girl in the field and, having forced her, should lie with her, you shall kill only the man who lay with her.<verse eid="DEU 22:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:26"/>And you shall do nothing to the young woman; the young woman has not committed an offense punishable by death, because it is as if some man would rise up against his neighbor and murder his soul; so is this deed.<verse eid="DEU 22:26"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:27"/>Since he found her in the field, the engaged young woman cried for help, but there was no one to help her.<verse eid="DEU 22:27"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:28"/>But if someone finds the girl, the virgin, who is not engaged, and, after he forces her, lies with her and he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">22:28</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'it'</char></note> is discovered,<verse eid="DEU 22:28"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:29"/>the man who lay with her shall give fifty silver didrachmas to the young woman's father, and she shall become his wife. Because he humbled her, he shall not be able to send her away for all time.<verse eid="DEU 22:29"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 22:30"/>A man shall not take his father's wife, and he shall not uncover his father's cover.<verse eid="DEU 22:30"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:1"/>A castrated male and one made a eunuch shall not enter the assembly of the Lord.<verse eid="DEU 23:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:2"/>One from a prostitute shall not enter the assembly of the Lord.<verse eid="DEU 23:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:3"/>No Ammanite and Moabite shall enter into the assembly of the Lord. Even to the tenth generation, he shall not enter into the assembly of the Lord, even forever,<verse eid="DEU 23:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:4"/>due to the fact that they did not meet you with bread and water on the way when you were coming out of Egypt and because they hired against you Balaam son of Beor, from Mesopotamia, to curse you.<verse eid="DEU 23:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:5"/>(And the Lord your God did not want to listen to Balaam, and the Lord your God turned the curses into blessings, because the Lord your God loved you.)<verse eid="DEU 23:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:6"/>You shall not address things of peace to them and things of profit to them all your days, forever.<verse eid="DEU 23:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:7"/>You shall not abhor an Idumean, for he is your brother. You shall not abhor an Egyptian, because you were a resident alien in his land.<verse eid="DEU 23:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:8"/>If sons are born to them in the third generation, they shall enter into the assembly of the Lord.<verse eid="DEU 23:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:9"/>Now if you go out to encamp against your enemies, you shall guard against any evil thing.<verse eid="DEU 23:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:10"/>If there is a person among you who is not clean from his flow at night, he shall go outside the camp, and he shall not enter into the camp.<verse eid="DEU 23:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:11"/>And it shall be, at evening, that he shall wash his body with water, and when the sun has set, he shall enter into the camp.<verse eid="DEU 23:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:12"/>And you shall have a place outside the camp, and you shall go there outside.<verse eid="DEU 23:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:13"/>On your belt you shall have a pin<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">23:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'peg'</char></note>, and it shall be, when you sit down apart outside, that you shall dig a hole with it and then, returning the earth, you shall cover up your disgrace with it.<verse eid="DEU 23:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:14"/>Because the Lord your God walks about in your camp, to deliver you and to hand over your enemy before you, and your camp shall be holy, and there shall not be seen a disgrace of a matter among you, and he shall turn away from you.<verse eid="DEU 23:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:15"/>You shall not hand over to an owner a servant who has been added to you from his owner.<verse eid="DEU 23:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:16"/>He shall reside with you; among you he shall live, in every place wherever he may please; you shall not oppress him.<verse eid="DEU 23:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:17"/>There shall not be a prostitute among the daughters of Israel; there shall not be one that practices prostitution among the sons of Israel. There shall not be an initiate among the daughters of Israel, and there shall not be anyone initiated among the sons of Israel.<verse eid="DEU 23:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:18"/>You shall not bring the fee of a prostitute or the exchange for a dog into the house of the Lord your God for any vow, for it is an abomination to the Lord your God-- in fact both.<verse eid="DEU 23:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:19"/>You shall not charge interest to your brother, interest on money and interest on provisions and interest on any thing that may be lent.<verse eid="DEU 23:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:20"/>To a stranger you shall charge interest but to your brother you shall not charge interest, so that the Lord your God may bless you in all your works in the land into which you are entering there to inherit it.<verse eid="DEU 23:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:21"/>Now if you vow a vow to the Lord your God, you shall not delay to pay it. For the Lord your God, when he requires, will require it of you, and it will be a sin with you.<verse eid="DEU 23:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:22"/>But if you do not want to vow, it will not be a sin to you.<verse eid="DEU 23:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:23"/>The things that proceed from your lips you shall guard, and you shall do as you have vowed a gift to the Lord your God, which you said with your mouth.<verse eid="DEU 23:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:24"/>(25) Now if you go into your neighbor's standing grain, then you shall collect ears with your hand, and you shall not cast a sickle on your neighbor's standing grain.<verse eid="DEU 23:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 23:25"/>(24) And if you go into your neighbor's vineyard, you shall eat grapes, as much as to fill your soul, but you shall not put any in a container.<verse eid="DEU 23:25"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:1"/>Now if anyone takes a wife and lives with her, and it shall be, if she does not find favor before him because he found a shameful thing in her, then he shall write her a bill of divorce and shall give it into her hands and shall send her out of his house,<verse eid="DEU 24:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:2"/>and if, having gone out, she becomes another man's<verse eid="DEU 24:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:3"/>and the last man hates her, then he will write her a bill of divorce and give it in her hands and send her out of his house, or if the last man who took her for himself as wife dies,<verse eid="DEU 24:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:4"/>the former man, who sent her away, shall not be able, having returned, to take her for himself as his wife after she has been defiled, for it is an abomination before the Lord your God, and you shall not defile the land that the Lord your God is giving you as an allotment.<verse eid="DEU 24:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:5"/>But if anyone should have taken a wife recently, he shall not go out to war, and he shall not be charged with any matter. He shall be innocent in his house one year; he shall make joyful his wife whom he has taken.<verse eid="DEU 24:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:6"/>No one shall take a mill or the upper millstone in pledge, for this one is taking a soul in pledge.<verse eid="DEU 24:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:7"/>And if a person is caught stealing a soul from his brothers, the sons of Israel, and, having overpowered him, he be sold, that thief shall die. And you shall remove the evil one from yourselves.<verse eid="DEU 24:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:8"/>Guard yourself against the attack of leprosy; you shall be very watchful to do according to all the law, whatever the priests, the Leuites, may announce to you. As I have commanded you, be watchful to perform.<verse eid="DEU 24:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:9"/>Remember what the Lord God did to Mariam on the way, when you were coming out of Egypt.<verse eid="DEU 24:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:10"/>Now if there is a debt with your neighbor, a debt of any kind, you shall not go into his house to take the pledge.<verse eid="DEU 24:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:11"/>You shall stand outside, and the person from whom your debt is due shall bring the pledge to you outside.<verse eid="DEU 24:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:12"/>If the person is poor, you shall not sleep in his pledge.<verse eid="DEU 24:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:13"/>By giving back you shall give his pledge back by sunset, and he shall sleep in his garment and bless you, and to you shall be mercy before the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 24:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:14"/>You shall not unjustly withhold the wages of a needy and indigent person from your brothers or from the guests in your cities.<verse eid="DEU 24:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:15"/>You shall pay his wages daily; the sun shall not set upon it, because he is needy and on it he has his hope, and he shall not cry to the Lord against you, and it shall be sin for you.<verse eid="DEU 24:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:16"/>Fathers shall not die for their children, and sons shall not be put to death for fathers; each one shall die for his own sin.<verse eid="DEU 24:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:17"/>You shall not divert the justice of a guest and an orphan and a widow, and you shall not take a widow's garment in pledge.<verse eid="DEU 24:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:18"/>And you shall remember that you were a domestic in the land of Egypt, and the Lord your God redeemed you from there; on account of this, I command you to do this thing.<verse eid="DEU 24:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:19"/>Now if you harvest a harvest in your field and forget a sheaf in your field, you shall not return to take it; it shall be for the guest and the orphan and the widow so that the Lord your God may bless you in all the works of your hands.<verse eid="DEU 24:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:20"/>And if you gather olives, you shall not return to glean what is behind you; it shall be for the guest and the orphan and the widow. And you shall remember that you were a domestic in the land of Egypt; on account of this, I command you to do this thing.<verse eid="DEU 24:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:21"/>And if you harvest your vineyard, you shall not re-harvest it for things behind you; it shall be for the guest and the orphan and the widow.<verse eid="DEU 24:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 24:22"/>And you shall remember that you were a domestic in the land of Egypt; on account of this, I command you to do this thing.<verse eid="DEU 24:22"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:1"/>Now if a dispute occurs between people and they enter into litigation and they<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">25:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the judges'</char></note> judge and justify the righteous one and condemn the impious,<verse eid="DEU 25:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:2"/>then it shall be, if the impious is worthy of lashes, that you shall make him sit down before the judges, and they shall beat him in their presence according to his impiety.<verse eid="DEU 25:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:3"/>They shall beat him with the number forty; they shall not add, but if they add to beat him more, beyond these lashes, your brother will be shamed before you.<verse eid="DEU 25:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:4"/>You shall not muzzle a threshing ox.<verse eid="DEU 25:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:5"/>Now if brothers reside together and one of them dies and there is no offspring to him, the wife of the deceased shall not be outside, for a man not close. Her husband's brother shall go in to her and shall take her for himself as wife and shall live with her,<verse eid="DEU 25:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:6"/>and it shall be that the child that she might bear shall be established from the name of the deceased, and his name shall not be blotted out from Israel.<verse eid="DEU 25:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:7"/>But if the man does not wish to take his brother's wife, then the woman shall go up to the gate to the council of elders and say, "My husband's brother does not want to perpetuate his brother's name in Israel; my husband's brother has been unwilling."<verse eid="DEU 25:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:8"/>And the council of elders of his city shall summon him and speak to him. And, while standing, he should say, "I do not wish to take her,"<verse eid="DEU 25:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:9"/>and his brother's wife, having approached him in the presence of the elders, shall also loosen his sandal, the one from his foot, and shall spit in his face and, while answering, shall say, "Thus shall they do to the man who will not build up his brother's house."<verse eid="DEU 25:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:10"/>And throughout Israel his name shall be called "the house of him whose sandal has been pulled off."<verse eid="DEU 25:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:11"/>Now if men get into a fight together, a man with his brother, and the wife of one of them comes in to rescue her husband from the hand of the one who strikes him and, extending her hand, should seize his twins<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">25:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'testicles'</char></note>,<verse eid="DEU 25:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:12"/>you shall cut off her hand; your eye shall not be sparing toward her.<verse eid="DEU 25:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:13"/>There shall not be in your bag weight and weight, large or small.<verse eid="DEU 25:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:14"/>There shall not be in your house measure and measure, large or small.<verse eid="DEU 25:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:15"/>You shall have only a true and just weight, and you shall have only a true and just measure so that you may be long-lived in the land that the Lord your God is giving you as an allotment.<verse eid="DEU 25:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:16"/>For every one who does these things, every one who acts unjustly, is an abomination to the Lord.<verse eid="DEU 25:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:17"/>Remember what Amalek did to you on the way, when you were coming out of the land of Egypt,<verse eid="DEU 25:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:18"/>how he withstood you on the way and cut off your tail, all those who lagged behind you, but you were hungry and weary, and he did not fear God.<verse eid="DEU 25:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 25:19"/>And it shall be, when the Lord your God gives you rest from all your enemies who surround you, in the land that the Lord your God is giving you as an allotment to inherit, you shall blot out the name of Amalek from under the sky, and you shall not forget.<verse eid="DEU 25:19"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 26"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:1"/>And it shall be, if you come into the land that the Lord your God is giving you as an allotment and you take possession of it and live in it,<verse eid="DEU 26:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:2"/>that you shall take from the first fruit of the fruits of your land that the Lord your God is giving you and put in a basket and go to the place that the Lord your God may choose for his name to be called there.<verse eid="DEU 26:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:3"/>And you shall go to the priest who shall be in those days and say to him, "Today I declare to the Lord my God that I have come into the land that the Lord swore to our fathers to give us."<verse eid="DEU 26:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:4"/>And the priest shall take the basket from your hands and set it down before the altar of the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 26:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:5"/>And in reply, you shall say before the Lord your God: "My ancestor abandoned Syria and went down into Egypt and sojourned there, few in number, and there he became a nation, great and numerous, many and great.<verse eid="DEU 26:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:6"/>And the Egyptians did us ill and humbled us and imposed hard work on us,<verse eid="DEU 26:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:7"/>and we cried to the Lord, the God of our fathers, and the Lord listened to our voice and saw our humiliation and our toil and our oppression.<verse eid="DEU 26:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:8"/>And the Lord brought us out of Egypt with great strength and with a strong hand and a high arm and with great spectacles and with signs and with wonders,<verse eid="DEU 26:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:9"/>and he brought us into this place and gave us this land, a land flowing with milk and honey.<verse eid="DEU 26:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:10"/>And now look, I have brought the first fruit of the produce of the land that you, O Lord, have given me, a land flowing with milk and honey." And you shall leave them before the Lord your God and do obeisance before the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 26:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:11"/>And you shall rejoice in all the goods that the Lord your God gave to you and to your house and the Leuite and the guest who is among you.<verse eid="DEU 26:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:12"/>Now if you finish paying all the tithe of your produce in the third year, you shall give the second tithe to the Leuite and the guest and the orphan and the widow, and they shall eat within your cities and be filled.<verse eid="DEU 26:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:13"/>And you shall say before the Lord your God: "I have cleansed the sacred portions from my house, and I gave them to the Leuite and the guest and the orphan and the widow, in accordance with all the commandments that you commanded me; I have not transgressed your commandment, nor have I forgotten,<verse eid="DEU 26:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:14"/>and I have not eaten from them in my grief; I have not enjoyed the fruits from them for something unclean; I have not given any of them to the dead. I have obeyed the voice of the Lord my God; I did just as you commanded me.<verse eid="DEU 26:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:15"/>Look down from your holy house, from the sky, and bless your people Israel and the land that you gave them, as you swore to our fathers to give us-- a land flowing with milk and honey."<verse eid="DEU 26:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:16"/>This very day the Lord your God is commanding you to do all these statutes and judgments, and you shall keep and do them with the whole of your heart and with the whole of your soul.<verse eid="DEU 26:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:17"/>Today you have chosen God to be your god and to walk in his ways and to keep his statutes and his judgments and to obey his voice.<verse eid="DEU 26:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:18"/>Today also the Lord has chosen you to be his exceptional people, as he said, to keep all his commandments,<verse eid="DEU 26:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 26:19"/>and that you be high above all nations, as he has made you renowned and a boast and glorified, that you be a people holy to the Lord your God, as he spoke.<verse eid="DEU 26:19"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 27"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:1"/>And Moyses and the council of elders of Israel gave orders, saying: Keep all these commandments that I command you today.<verse eid="DEU 27:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:2"/>And it shall be, on the day when you cross over the Jordan into the land that the Lord your God is giving you, that you shall set up for yourself large stones and plaster them with plaster.<verse eid="DEU 27:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:3"/>And you shall write on the stones all the words of this law when you cross over the Jordan, when you enter the land that the Lord, the God of your fathers, is giving you, a land flowing with milk and honey, as the Lord, the God of your fathers, said to you.<verse eid="DEU 27:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:4"/>And it shall be, when you cross over the Jordan, that you shall set up these stones about which I command you today, on Mount Gaibal, and you shall plaster them with plaster.<verse eid="DEU 27:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:5"/>And you shall build an altar there to the Lord your God, an altar of stones. You shall not place an iron tool on them.<verse eid="DEU 27:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:6"/>You shall build the altar to the Lord your God of whole stones, and you shall offer up whole burnt offerings on it to the Lord your God<verse eid="DEU 27:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:7"/>and sacrifice a sacrifice of deliverance and eat and be filled there and be joyful before the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 27:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:8"/>And you shall write on the stones all of this law very clearly.<verse eid="DEU 27:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:9"/>And Moyses and the priests, the Leuites, spoke to all Israel, saying: Keep silence, and hear, O Israel! This day you have become a people to the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 27:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:10"/>And you shall listen to the voice of the Lord your God and do all his commandments and his statutes that I command you today.<verse eid="DEU 27:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:11"/>And Moyses commanded the people in that day, saying:<verse eid="DEU 27:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:12"/>When you have crossed over the Jordan, these shall stand to bless the people on Mount Garizin: Symeon, Leui, Ioudas, Issachar, Ioseph and Beniamin.<verse eid="DEU 27:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:13"/>And these shall stand upon the curse on Mount Gaibal: Rouben, Gad and Aser, Zaboulon, Dan and Nephthali.<verse eid="DEU 27:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:14"/>And the Leuites, in reply, shall say in a loud voice to all Israel:<verse eid="DEU 27:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:15"/>"Cursed be the person who shall make a carved and a cast image, an abomination to the Lord, a work of the hands of an artisan and shall set it up in secret." And all the people, in reply, shall say, "May it be!"<verse eid="DEU 27:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:16"/>"Cursed be he who dishonors his father or his mother." And all the people shall say, "May it be!"<verse eid="DEU 27:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:17"/>"Cursed be he who moves a neighbor's boundaries." And all the people shall say, "May it be!"<verse eid="DEU 27:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:18"/>"Cursed be he who misleads a blind person on the road." And all the people shall say, "May it be!"<verse eid="DEU 27:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:19"/>"Cursed be he if he deprive guest and orphan and widow of justice." And all the people shall say, "May it be!"<verse eid="DEU 27:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:20"/>"Cursed be he who lies with his father's wife, because he has uncovered the cover of his father." And all the people shall say, "May it be!"<verse eid="DEU 27:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:21"/>"Cursed be he who lies with any animal." And all the people shall say, "May it be!"<verse eid="DEU 27:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:22"/>"Cursed be he who lies with his sister, whether from his father or from his mother." And all the people shall say, "May it be!"<verse eid="DEU 27:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:23"/>"Cursed be he who lies with his mother-in-law." And all the people shall say, "May it be!"<verse eid="DEU 27:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:24"/>"Cursed be he who strikes down a neighbor with treachery." And all the people shall say, "May it be!"<verse eid="DEU 27:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:25"/>"Cursed be he if he take gifts to strike a soul of innocent blood." And all the people shall say, "May it be!"<verse eid="DEU 27:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 27:26"/>"Cursed be any person who does not remain in all the words of this law to do them." And all the people shall say, "May it be!"<verse eid="DEU 27:26"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 28"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:1"/>And it shall be, if by hearing you hear the voice of the Lord your God, to be watchful and to perform all his commandments that I command you today, that the Lord your God will render you high above all the nations of the earth,<verse eid="DEU 28:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:2"/>and all these blessings shall come upon you and find you, if you hear the voice of the Lord your God:<verse eid="DEU 28:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:3"/>Blessed be you in the city, and blessed be you in the field.<verse eid="DEU 28:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:4"/>Blessed be the progeny of your belly and the produce of your land, the herds of your cows and the flocks of your sheep.<verse eid="DEU 28:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:5"/>Blessed be your storehouses and your reserves.<verse eid="DEU 28:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:6"/>Blessed be you when you come in, and blessed be you when you go out.<verse eid="DEU 28:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:7"/>May the Lord your God hand over your enemies who have risen against you, when they have been crushed before you; they shall come out against you by one way and flee from before you by seven ways.<verse eid="DEU 28:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:8"/>May the Lord send the blessing upon you in your storerooms and in all things to which you put your hand in the land that the Lord your God is giving you.<verse eid="DEU 28:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:9"/>May the Lord raise you up for himself as a holy people, as he has sworn to your fathers, if you listen to the voice of the Lord your God and walk in his ways.<verse eid="DEU 28:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:10"/>And all the nations of the earth shall see you that the name of the Lord has been surnamed to you, and they shall be afraid of you.<verse eid="DEU 28:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:11"/>And the Lord your God will make you abound with good things, in the progeny of your belly and in the progeny of your livestock and in the produce of your land in the land that the Lord swore to your fathers to give you.<verse eid="DEU 28:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:12"/>May the Lord open for you his good treasury, the sky, to give the rain to your land in its season, to bless all the works of your hands. And you will lend to many nations, but you will not borrow. And you will rule over many nations, but they shall not rule over you.<verse eid="DEU 28:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:13"/>May the Lord your God set you up as a head and not as a tail, and you shall then be on top, and you shall not be underneath-- if you hear the commandments of the Lord your God, which I command you today, to guard and to perform.<verse eid="DEU 28:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:14"/>You shall not turn aside from all of the words that I command you today, right or left, to go after other gods to serve them.<verse eid="DEU 28:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:15"/>And it shall be, if you do not listen to the voice of the Lord your God to keep and to do all his commandments, which I command you today, that all these curses shall come upon you and overtake you:<verse eid="DEU 28:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:16"/>Cursed be you in the city, and cursed be you in the field.<verse eid="DEU 28:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:17"/>Cursed be your storehouses and your reserves.<verse eid="DEU 28:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:18"/>Cursed be the progeny of your belly and the produce of your land, the herds of your cows and the flocks of your sheep.<verse eid="DEU 28:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:19"/>Cursed be you when you come in, and cursed be you when you go out.<verse eid="DEU 28:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:20"/>May the Lord send you lack and hunger and exhaustion in everything to which you may put your hand, whatever you might do until he utterly destroys you and until he ruins you quickly, on account of your evil deeds, because you have forsaken me.<verse eid="DEU 28:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:21"/>May the Lord make death cling to you until it consumes you off the land that you are entering there to inherit it.<verse eid="DEU 28:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:22"/>May the Lord strike you with difficulty and fever and cold and irritation and murder and with blight and paleness<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'mildew'</char></note>, and they shall pursue you until they destroy you.<verse eid="DEU 28:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:23"/>And the sky over your head shall be bronze for you, and the earth under you iron.<verse eid="DEU 28:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:24"/>May the Lord render the rain of your land as powder, and dust from the sky shall come down upon you until it wipes you out and until it destroys you.<verse eid="DEU 28:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:25"/>May the Lord give you slaughter before your enemies; you shall go out against them by one way and flee from them by seven ways. And you shall be in dispersion in all the kingdoms of the earth.<verse eid="DEU 28:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:26"/>And your corpses will be food for the birds of the sky and for the wild animals of the earth, and there shall be no one to frighten them away.<verse eid="DEU 28:26"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:27"/>May the Lord strike you with an Egyptian festering sore in the seats and with severe itch and scratching so that you cannot be healed.<verse eid="DEU 28:27"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:28"/>May the Lord strike you with derangement and blindness and distraction of mind,<verse eid="DEU 28:28"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:29"/>and you shall be groping about at midday as a blind person would grope in the darkness, and he will not prosper your ways, and you will then be wronged and plundered all the days, and there shall be none to help you.<verse eid="DEU 28:29"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:30"/>You shall take a wife<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:30</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'woman'</char></note>, but another man shall have her. You shall build a house, and you shall not live in it. You shall plant a vineyard and not harvest it.<verse eid="DEU 28:30"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:31"/>Your bull calf is butchered before you, but you shall not eat of it. Your donkey is seized from you, and it shall not be given back to you. Your sheep is given to your enemies, and there shall be none to help you.<verse eid="DEU 28:31"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:32"/>Your sons and daughters are given to another nation, and your eyes, being purulent, shall look for them<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:32</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'sons and daughters'</char></note>, and your hand shall not be strong.<verse eid="DEU 28:32"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:33"/>A nation whom you do not know shall eat up the produce of your land and all your labors, and you shall be wronged and shattered all the days.<verse eid="DEU 28:33"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:34"/>And you shall be driven mad because of the sights of your eyes, which you shall see.<verse eid="DEU 28:34"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:35"/>May the Lord strike you on the knees and on the legs with a grievous festering sore so that you cannot be healed, from the sole of your feet to your crown.<verse eid="DEU 28:35"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:36"/>May the Lord lead away you and your rulers whom you may set over yourself to a nation that you and your fathers do not know, and you shall serve there other gods, of wood and stone.<verse eid="DEU 28:36"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:37"/>And there you shall become an enigma and an illustration<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:37</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'parable'</char></note> and a tale among all the nations into which the Lord may lead you away there.<verse eid="DEU 28:37"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:38"/>You shall carry out much seed into the field and shall bring in few, for the grasshopper shall consume them.<verse eid="DEU 28:38"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:39"/>You shall plant and work a vineyard, but you shall neither drink the wine nor be joyful from it, for the worm shall devour them.<verse eid="DEU 28:39"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:40"/>Olive trees you shall have throughout all your borders, but you shall not anoint yourself with oil, for your olive tree shall shed.<verse eid="DEU 28:40"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:41"/>You shall bear sons and daughters, but they shall not remain yours, for they shall go away in captivity.<verse eid="DEU 28:41"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:42"/>All your wood products<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:42</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'wood products':  I.e. 'things made from wood'</char></note> and the produce of your land the rust shall devour.<verse eid="DEU 28:42"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:43"/>The guest who is among you shall ascend up and up above you, but you shall descend down, down.<verse eid="DEU 28:43"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:44"/>He shall lend to you, but you shall not lend to him; he shall be the head, and you shall be the tail.<verse eid="DEU 28:44"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:45"/>And all these curses shall come upon you and pursue you and overtake you until it utterly destroy you and until it ruin you, because you did not listen to the voice of the Lord your God, to keep his commandments and his statutes that he commanded you.<verse eid="DEU 28:45"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:46"/>And there shall be signs and wonders among you and among your offspring forever,<verse eid="DEU 28:46"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:47"/>because you did not serve the Lord your God with rejoicing and with a good heart for the abundance of everything.<verse eid="DEU 28:47"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:48"/>And you shall serve your enemies whom the Lord will send against you, with famine and with thirst and with nakedness and with lack of everything. And he will put an iron collar on your neck until he utterly destroys you.<verse eid="DEU 28:48"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:49"/>The Lord will bring upon you a nation from far away, from the end of the earth, like the swoop of an eagle, a nation whose speech you will not hear,<verse eid="DEU 28:49"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:50"/>a nation shameless in face, which will not marvel at the face of an elder and have no mercy on the young.<verse eid="DEU 28:50"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:51"/>And it shall consume the progeny of your livestock and the produce of your land so that there remains for you no grain, wine, oil, the herds of your cows and the flocks of your sheep, until it destroys you.<verse eid="DEU 28:51"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:52"/>And it shall wipe you out in all your cities until your high and fortified walls, in them in which you trusted, be pulled down in all your land, and it shall afflict you in all your cities that the Lord your God has given you.<verse eid="DEU 28:52"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:53"/>And in your desperate straits and in your affliction with which your enemy shall afflict you, you will eat the progeny of your belly, the flesh of your sons and your daughters whom the Lord has given you.<verse eid="DEU 28:53"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:54"/>The gentle among you and the very soft will begrudge with his eye his brother and the wife in his bosom and the remaining children who are left,<verse eid="DEU 28:54"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:55"/>so as to give to one of them from the flesh of his children whom he may be eating, because nothing remains to him in your desperate straits and affliction by which your enemies afflict you in all your cities.<verse eid="DEU 28:55"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:56"/>And she who is gentle among you and soft, the foot of whom did not make an attempt to tread on the ground, because of delicacy and gentleness, will begrudge with her eye her husband, who is in her bosom, and her son and daughter,<verse eid="DEU 28:56"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:57"/>even her afterbirth that comes out from between her thighs, and the child that she might bear. For she will devour them in secret for want of all things, in desperate straits and in affliction with which your enemy will afflict you in your cities.<verse eid="DEU 28:57"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:58"/>If you do not listen to perform all the words of this law that are written in this book, to fear this honorable and marvelous name, the Lord your God,<verse eid="DEU 28:58"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:59"/>then the Lord will make exceptional your plagues and the plagues upon your offspring, great and marvelous plagues and evil and constant maladies.<verse eid="DEU 28:59"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:60"/>And he will bring back upon you all the evil pains of Egypt of which you were in dread before them, and they shall cling to you.<verse eid="DEU 28:60"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:61"/>And every malady and every plague not recorded in the book of this law the Lord will bring on you until he utterly destroys you.<verse eid="DEU 28:61"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:62"/>And you shall be left few in number, instead of the fact that you were as the stars of the sky in multitude, because you did not listen to the voice of the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 28:62"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:63"/>And it shall be, just as the Lord took delight in you that you might do well and that you multiply, so the Lord will take delight in you to destroy you utterly, and you shall be removed from the land that you are entering there to inherit it.<verse eid="DEU 28:63"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:64"/>And the Lord your God will disperse you to all nations, from an end of the earth to an end of the earth, and there you shall be subject to other gods, of wood and stone, which you and your fathers did not know.<verse eid="DEU 28:64"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:65"/>But also among those nations he shall not give you rest, nor will there be a station for the trace of your foot. And there the Lord will give you a discouraged heart and failing eyes and a molten soul.<verse eid="DEU 28:65"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:66"/>And your life shall be hanging before your eyes, and night and day you shall be afraid, and you shall not be sure of your life.<verse eid="DEU 28:66"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:67"/>In the morning you shall say, "If only evening might come!" and at evening you shall say, "If only morning might come!"-- because of the fear of your heart with which you shall fear and because of the sights of your eyes which you shall see.<verse eid="DEU 28:67"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 28:68"/>And the Lord will bring you back in ships to Egypt by a route that I said: You shall never see it again, and there you shall be put up for sale to your enemies as male and female slaves, and there will be no buyer.<verse eid="DEU 28:68"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 29"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:1"/>These are the words of the covenant, which<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">29:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the words'</char></note> the Lord commanded Moyses to establish for the sons of Israel in the land of Moab, besides the covenant that he had made with them at Choreb.<verse eid="DEU 29:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:2"/>And Moyses called all the sons of Israel and said to them: You have seen all that the Lord did before you in the land of Egypt, to Pharao and to his attendants and to all his land,<verse eid="DEU 29:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:3"/>the great trials that your eyes saw, the signs and those great wonders.<verse eid="DEU 29:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:4"/>But to this day the Lord God has not given you a heart to know and eyes to see and ears to hear.<verse eid="DEU 29:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:5"/>And he led you forty years in the wilderness. Your garments have not grown old, and your sandals have not worn from your feet;<verse eid="DEU 29:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:6"/>you have not eaten bread, you have not drunk wine and sikera<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">29:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Aramaic = 'strong drink'</char></note>-- so that you may know that he is the Lord your God.<verse eid="DEU 29:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:7"/>And you came as far as this place, and King Seon of Hesebon and King Og of Basan came out to meet us for battle, and we struck them down.<verse eid="DEU 29:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:8"/>And we took their land, and I gave it as an allotment to Rouben and to Gaddi and to the half-tribe of Manasse.<verse eid="DEU 29:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:9"/>And you shall be watchful to perform all the words of this covenant in order that you may understand everything that you shall do.<verse eid="DEU 29:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:10"/>You stand today, all of you, before the Lord your God-- the leaders of your tribes and your council of elders and your judges and your recorders, every man of Israel,<verse eid="DEU 29:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:11"/>your women and your progeny and the guest who is in the midst of your camp, from your woodcutter even up to your water bearer--<verse eid="DEU 29:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:12"/>so that you may enter in the covenant of the Lord your God, and in his imprecations, which the Lord your God is making with you today<verse eid="DEU 29:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:13"/>in order that he may establish you for himself as a people, and he in turn shall be your god, as he said to you and as he swore to your fathers Abraam and Isaak and Iakob.<verse eid="DEU 29:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:14"/>And I am establishing this covenant and this imprecation, not with you alone<verse eid="DEU 29:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:15"/>but also with those who are here with us today before the Lord our God (15) and with those who are not here with us today,<verse eid="DEU 29:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:16"/>because you know how we lived in the land of Egypt and how we passed through the midst of the nations through which you passed.<verse eid="DEU 29:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:17"/>And you have seen their abominations and their idols, wood and stone, silver and gold, that were among them.<verse eid="DEU 29:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:18"/>Who is there among you, man or woman or family or tribe, whose mind has turned away from the Lord our God, to go to serve the gods of those nations? Who among you is a root growing up with gall and bitterness?<verse eid="DEU 29:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:19"/>And it shall be, if he hears the words of this imprecation and declares in his heart, saying: "May holy things become mine, because I shall walk in the wandering of my heart," lest the sinner destroy the sinless as well,<verse eid="DEU 29:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:20"/>God will not want to pardon him, but the Lord's anger and his zeal will then blaze out against that person. And all the imprecations of this covenant, written in the book of this law will attach themselves to him, and the Lord will blot out his name from the earth beneath the sky.<verse eid="DEU 29:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:21"/>And the Lord will single him out for evil from all the sons of Israel, in accordance with all the imprecations of the covenant, which are written in the book of this law.<verse eid="DEU 29:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:22"/>And the next generation will say, your sons who will rise up after you and the stranger who may come from a land far away, and they will see the plagues of that land and its diseases which the Lord has sent upon it:<verse eid="DEU 29:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:23"/>sulfur and burnt salt; its whole land shall not be sown, nor shall it sprout, neither will any vegetation spring up on it, just as Sodoma was overturned, and Gomorra, Adama and Seboim, which the Lord overturned in wrath and anger.<verse eid="DEU 29:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:24"/>And all the nations will say, "Why has the Lord done thus to this land? What was this great vehemence of anger?"<verse eid="DEU 29:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:25"/>And they will say, "Because they abandoned the covenant of the Lord, the God of their fathers, which he made with their fathers when he brought them out of the land of Egypt.<verse eid="DEU 29:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:26"/>And having gone, they served other gods and did obeisance to them whom they had not known, neither had he allotted to them,<verse eid="DEU 29:26"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:27"/>and the Lord became angry with wrath against that land, to bring on it according to all the curses written in this book.<verse eid="DEU 29:27"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:28"/>And the Lord removed them from their land in wrath and anger and very great provocation and cast them into another land, as it is now."<verse eid="DEU 29:28"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 29:29"/>The secret things belong to the Lord our God, but the revealed things belong to us and to our children forever, to do all the words of this law.<verse eid="DEU 29:29"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 30"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:1"/>And it shall be, when all these words come upon you, the blessing and the curse that I gave before you, that you shall receive them into your heart among all the nations wherever the Lord may scatter you there,<verse eid="DEU 30:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:2"/>and you shall return to the Lord your God and obey his voice regarding everything I command you today, with the whole of your heart and with the whole of your soul.<verse eid="DEU 30:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:3"/>And the Lord will heal your sins and have mercy on you and gather you again from all the nations among whom the Lord has scattered you there.<verse eid="DEU 30:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:4"/>If your dispersion be from an end of the sky to an end of the sky, from there the Lord your God will gather you, and from there he will take you.<verse eid="DEU 30:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:5"/>And the Lord your God will bring you into the land that your fathers inherited, and you will inherit it, and he will make you well, and he will make you numerous beyond your fathers.<verse eid="DEU 30:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:6"/>And the Lord will purge your heart and the heart of your offspring, to love the Lord your God with the whole of your heart and with the whole of your soul in order that you may live.<verse eid="DEU 30:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:7"/>And the Lord your God will give these imprecations on your enemies and on those who hate you, who pursued you.<verse eid="DEU 30:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:8"/>And you shall turn and listen to the voice of the Lord your God, and you shall do his commandments that I command you today,<verse eid="DEU 30:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:9"/>and the Lord your God will treat you with care in every work of your hands, in the progeny of your belly and in the produce of your land and in the progeny of your livestock. For the Lord your God will turn to be joyful toward you for good things, just as he was joyful over your fathers,<verse eid="DEU 30:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:10"/>if you listen to the voice of the Lord your God, to keep his commandments and his statutes and his judgments that are written in the book of this law, if you turn to the Lord your God with the whole of your heart and with the whole of your soul,<verse eid="DEU 30:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:11"/>because this commandment that I command you today is not excessive nor is it far from you.<verse eid="DEU 30:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:12"/>It is not in the sky, saying, "Who will go up to the sky and get it for us? And when we hear it, we shall do it."<verse eid="DEU 30:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:13"/>Neither is it beyond the sea, saying, "Who will cross to the other side of the sea for us and get it for us? And when we hear it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">30:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'when we hear it':  Wevers Ed. = 'he shall make it heard to us'</char></note>, we shall also do it."<verse eid="DEU 30:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:14"/>The word is very near to you, in your mouth and in your heart and in your hands, to do it.<verse eid="DEU 30:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:15"/>See, I have given before you today life and death, good and evil.<verse eid="DEU 30:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:16"/>Now if you listen to the commandments of the Lord your God that I command you today, to love the Lord your God, to walk in his ways, to keep his statutes and his commandments and his judgments, then you shall live and become many, and the Lord your God will bless you in all the land into which you are entering there to inherit it.<verse eid="DEU 30:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:17"/>And if your heart turns away and you do not listen but having been led astray you do obeisance to other gods and serve them,<verse eid="DEU 30:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:18"/>I declare to you today that by destruction you shall perish, and you shall not have many days in the land into which you are crossing the Jordan there to inherit it.<verse eid="DEU 30:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:19"/>I call both sky and earth to witness against you today: I have given before you life and death, blessing and curse. And choose life so that you and your offspring may live,<verse eid="DEU 30:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 30:20"/>to love the Lord your God, to listen to his voice and to hold fast to him, for this is life for you and the length of your days so that you may live in the land that the Lord swore to your fathers Abraam and Isaak and Iakob to give to them.<verse eid="DEU 30:20"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 31"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:1"/>And Moyses finished speaking all these words to all the sons of Israel,<verse eid="DEU 31:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:2"/>and he said to them: "I am today one hundred twenty years old. I shall not be able any more to come in and to go out. Now the Lord said to me, 'You shall not cross over this Jordan.'<verse eid="DEU 31:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:3"/>The Lord your God who goes before you, he will utterly destroy these nations from before you, and you shall dispossess them. Iesous also is the one crossing over before you, as the Lord spoke.<verse eid="DEU 31:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:4"/>And the Lord will do to them as he did to Seon and Og, the two kings of the Amorrites who were beyond the Jordan, and to their land, as he utterly destroyed them.<verse eid="DEU 31:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:5"/>And the Lord has delivered them before you, and you shall do to them as I have commanded you.<verse eid="DEU 31:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:6"/>Be manly and strong; have no fear, nor be frightened, nor be terrified from before them, because the Lord your God, he who goes with you among you, will not forsake you or abandon you."<verse eid="DEU 31:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:7"/>And Moyses called Iesous and said to him before all Israel: "Be manly and strong, for you will go before this people into the land that the Lord has sworn to our fathers to give to them, and you will take possession of it for them.<verse eid="DEU 31:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:8"/>And the Lord, the one who goes with you, will not forsake you or abandon you. Do not fear, nor be frightened."<verse eid="DEU 31:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:9"/>And Moyses wrote down the words of this law in a book and gave to the priests, the sons of Leui, who carry the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and to the elders of the sons of Israel.<verse eid="DEU 31:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:10"/>And Moyses commanded them in that day, saying: "After seven years, in the time of the year of release, during the feast of tent pitching,<verse eid="DEU 31:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:11"/>when all Israel comes together to appear before the Lord your God at the place that the Lord may choose, you shall read this law before all Israel in their ears,<verse eid="DEU 31:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:12"/>having assembled the people-- men and women and progeny and the guest in your cities-- so that they may hear and so that they may learn to fear the Lord your God, and they shall listen to perform all the words of this law,<verse eid="DEU 31:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:13"/>and their sons, who do not know, shall hear and learn to fear the Lord your God, all the days which they themselves live in the land into which you are crossing over the Jordan there to inherit it."<verse eid="DEU 31:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:14"/>And the Lord said to Moyses, "Look, the days of your death have come near; call Iesous, and stand by the entrance of the tent of witness, and I will command him." And Moyses went, and Iesous, into the tent of witness, and they stood by the entrance of the tent of witness,<verse eid="DEU 31:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:15"/>and the Lord descended in a cloud, and he stood at the entrance of the tent of witness, and the pillar of cloud stood at the entrance of the tent.<verse eid="DEU 31:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:16"/>And the Lord said to Moyses, "Look, you are lying down with your fathers. And this people, having risen up, will prostitute after foreign gods of the land into which it is going there into it, and they will forsake me and break my covenant that I have established with them.<verse eid="DEU 31:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:17"/>And I shall be angry with wrath against them in that day, and I will abandon them and turn away my face from them, and it will become food, and many evils and afflictions will find it. And in that day it will say, 'Because the Lord my God is not with me, these evils have found me.'<verse eid="DEU 31:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:18"/>But I by turning will turn my face from them on that day, on account of all the evils they have done, because they turned to foreign gods.<verse eid="DEU 31:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:19"/>And now write the words of this song, and teach it to the sons of Israel, and put it in their mouth in order that this song may be to me a witness among the sons of Israel.<verse eid="DEU 31:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:20"/>For I will bring them into the good land which I swore to their fathers, a land flowing with milk and honey, and they shall eat and, filled, shall be sated and will turn to foreign gods and serve them and provoke me and break my covenant.<verse eid="DEU 31:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:21"/>And this song will confront them, by witnessing contrariwise, for it will not be forgotten from the mouth of their offspring. For I know their evil, what they are doing here today, before I have brought them into the good land that I swore to their fathers."<verse eid="DEU 31:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:22"/>And on that day Moyses wrote this song and taught it to the sons of Israel.<verse eid="DEU 31:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:23"/>And he commanded Iesous and said, "Be manly and strong, for you shall bring the sons of Israel into the land that the Lord swore to them, and he will be with you."<verse eid="DEU 31:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:24"/>Now when Moyses had finished writing down in a book all the words of this law, to the very end,<verse eid="DEU 31:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:25"/>then he commanded the Leuites, who carry the ark of the covenant of the Lord, saying,<verse eid="DEU 31:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:26"/>"Having taken the book of this law, you shall put it beside the ark of the covenant of the Lord your God, and it shall be there as a witness against you.<verse eid="DEU 31:26"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:27"/>For I know your rebelliousness and your hard neck. For, while I am still alive among you today, you are being fractious concerning the things of God, how not also after my death?<verse eid="DEU 31:27"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:28"/>Assemble to me all the leaders of your tribes and your elders and your judges and your recorders so that I may speak all these words in their ears and call sky and earth to witness against them.<verse eid="DEU 31:28"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:29"/>For I know that, after my demise, with lawlessness you will act lawlessly and turn aside from the way that I have commanded you. And the evils will come upon you at the end of days, because you will do what is evil in the sight of the Lord, to provoke him through the works of your hands."<verse eid="DEU 31:29"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 31:30"/>And Moyses spoke the words of this song, to the very end, in the ears of the whole assembly of Israel:<verse eid="DEU 31:30"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 32"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:1"/>Give heed, O sky, and I will speak, and let the earth hear words from my mouth.<verse eid="DEU 32:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:2"/>Let my utterance be awaited like rain, and let my words come down like dew, like a rainstorm on dog's tooth grass, and like a snowstorm on grass.<verse eid="DEU 32:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:3"/>For I have called out the name of the Lord; ascribe greatness to our God!<verse eid="DEU 32:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:4"/>God-- his works are genuine, and all his ways are justice. A faithful god, and there is no injustice, a righteous and holy Lord<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">32:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'a righteous and holy Lord':  Or 'righteous and holy is the Lord'</char></note>;<verse eid="DEU 32:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:5"/>blemished children, not his, have sinned, a generation, crooked and perverse.<verse eid="DEU 32:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:6"/>Do you thus repay the Lord these things, O people, foolish and not wise? Did not he himself, your father, acquire you and make you and create you?<verse eid="DEU 32:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:7"/>Remember days of old; consider years of a generation of generations; ask your father, and he will inform you, your elders, and they will tell you.<verse eid="DEU 32:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:8"/>When the Most High was apportioning nations, as he scattered Adam's sons, he fixed boundaries of nations according to the number of divine sons,<verse eid="DEU 32:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:9"/>and his people Iakob became the Lord's portion, Israel a measured part of his inheritance.<verse eid="DEU 32:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:10"/>He made him self-sufficient in a desert land, in thirst of heat, in a waterless place; he encircled him and educated him and guarded him as the apple of his eye.<verse eid="DEU 32:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:11"/>Like an eagle to protect his brood, he too yearned for his young; spreading his wings, he received them and bore them aloft on his back;<verse eid="DEU 32:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:12"/>the Lord alone was leading them, and no foreign god was with them.<verse eid="DEU 32:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:13"/>He made them ascend onto the strength of the land, fed them with produce of the fields; they sucked honey from a rock and oil from solid rock,<verse eid="DEU 32:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:14"/>butter of cows and milk of sheep, with fat of lambs and rams; of the sons of bulls and of goats, with fat of kidneys of wheat-- and they drank wine, blood of grapes.<verse eid="DEU 32:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:15"/>And Iakob ate and was filled, and the beloved one kicked. He grew fat; he became heavy; he became broad! And he abandoned God who made him, and he departed from God his savior.<verse eid="DEU 32:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:16"/>They provoked me with foreign things; by their abominations they embittered me.<verse eid="DEU 32:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:17"/>They sacrificed to demons and not to God, to gods they did not know. New, recent ones have come, whom their fathers did not know.<verse eid="DEU 32:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:18"/>You abandoned God who bore you, and you forgot God who nurtures you.<verse eid="DEU 32:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:19"/>And the Lord saw it and was jealous, and he was provoked on account of the wrath of his sons and daughters.<verse eid="DEU 32:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:20"/>And he said: I will turn away my face from them, and I will show what will happen to them at the end, for it is a perverse generation, sons who have no faithfulness in them.<verse eid="DEU 32:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:21"/>They made me jealous with what is no god, provoked me with their idols. So I will make them jealous with what is no nation, provoke them with a nation lacking understanding.<verse eid="DEU 32:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:22"/>For a fire has lit up from my anger and will burn as far as Hades below; it will devour earth and its produce and will light up foundations of mountains.<verse eid="DEU 32:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:23"/>I will gather evils against them and will spend my arrows against them:<verse eid="DEU 32:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:24"/>when they are being wasted by famine and by devouring of birds-- and recurvation beyond cure. Teeth of beasts I will send against them, with rage of things that drag on the ground.<verse eid="DEU 32:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:25"/>From outside a dagger shall bereave them, and from the inner chambers fear, young man together with maiden, nursing child with one grown old.<verse eid="DEU 32:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:26"/>I said, I will disperse them; indeed, I will cause their memory to cease from among humans;<verse eid="DEU 32:26"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:27"/>were it not for wrath of the enemies so that they may not last long and so that their adversaries not collaborate, let them not say, "Our hand is high, and it was not the Lord who did all these things."<verse eid="DEU 32:27"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:28"/>For it is a nation that has lost counsel, and there is no understanding in them.<verse eid="DEU 32:28"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:29"/>They had no sense to understand these things. Let them accept them for the time to come.<verse eid="DEU 32:29"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:30"/>How shall one pursue thousands and two remove myriads unless God sold them and the Lord delivered them up?<verse eid="DEU 32:30"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:31"/>For not like our God are their gods, but our enemies are without understanding.<verse eid="DEU 32:31"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:32"/>For their vine is from the vine of Sodoma, and their branch from Gomorra; their cluster is a cluster of bile; it is a bunch of bitterness to them;<verse eid="DEU 32:32"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:33"/>their wine is the wrath of dragons, and the wrath of asps beyond cure.<verse eid="DEU 32:33"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:34"/>Look, have not these things been gathered with me and sealed up in my treasuries?<verse eid="DEU 32:34"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:35"/>In a day of vengeance, I will repay, in a time when their foot slips, because near is the day of their destruction and things prepared for you are at hand.<verse eid="DEU 32:35"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:36"/>For the Lord will judge his people and be comforted over his slaves. For he saw them paralyzed, both failed under attack and enfeebled.<verse eid="DEU 32:36"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:37"/>And the Lord said: Where are their gods, they in whom they trusted,<verse eid="DEU 32:37"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:38"/>the fat of whose sacrifices you were eating and were drinking the wine of their libations? Let them rise up and help you, and let them be protectors for you!<verse eid="DEU 32:38"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:39"/>See, see that I am, and there is no god except me. I will kill, and I will make alive; I will strike, and I will heal, and there is no one who will deliver from my hands.<verse eid="DEU 32:39"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:40"/>For I will lift up my hand to the sky, and I will swear by my right hand, and I will say: I live forever,<verse eid="DEU 32:40"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:41"/>because I will sharpen my dagger like lightning, and my hand will take hold on judgment, and I will repay my enemies with a sentence, and those who hate me I will repay.<verse eid="DEU 32:41"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:42"/>I will make my arrows drunk with blood-- and my dagger shall devour flesh-- with the blood of the wounded and of captives, from the head of the commanders of the enemies.<verse eid="DEU 32:42"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:43"/>Be glad, O skies, with him, and let all the divine sons do obeisance to him. Be glad, O nations, with his people, and let all the angels of God prevail for him. For he will avenge the blood of his sons and take revenge and repay the enemies with a sentence, and he will repay those who hate, and the Lord shall cleanse the land of his people.<verse eid="DEU 32:43"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:44"/>And Moyses wrote this song in that day and taught it to the sons of Israel. And Moyses entered and spoke all the words of this law in the ears of the people, he and Iesous the son of Naue.<verse eid="DEU 32:44"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:45"/>And Moyses finished speaking to all Israel,<verse eid="DEU 32:45"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:46"/>and he said to them: "Pay heed with your heart to all these words that I am testifying against you today, which things you shall command your sons, to guard and to perform all the words of this law.<verse eid="DEU 32:46"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:47"/>Because this is not an empty word for you, since it is your very life, and through this word you shall live long in the land into which you are crossing over the Jordan there to inherit."<verse eid="DEU 32:47"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:48"/>And on this day the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="DEU 32:48"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:49"/>"Ascend the mountain, this Abarim, Mount Nabau, which is in the land of Moab, across from Iericho, and view the land of Chanaan, which I am giving to the sons of Israel as a possession,<verse eid="DEU 32:49"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:50"/>and die on the mountain upon which you are ascending there, and be added to your people as your brother Aaron died on Hor the mountain and was added to his people,<verse eid="DEU 32:50"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:51"/>because you both disobeyed my word among the sons of Israel at the water of dispute at Kades in the wilderness of Sin, because you both did not sanctify me among the sons of Israel.<verse eid="DEU 32:51"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 32:52"/>Because you shall view the land from a distance, but you shall not enter there.<verse eid="DEU 32:52"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 33"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:1"/>And this is the blessing with which Moyses, man of God, blessed the sons of Israel before his death.<verse eid="DEU 33:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:2"/>And he said: The Lord has come from Sina and appeared to us from Seir and hasted from Mount Pharan with myriads of Kades; at his right, angels with him.<verse eid="DEU 33:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:3"/>And he spared his people, and all of the sanctified ones were under your hands-- even these are under you, and it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">33:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the people'</char></note> accepted from his words<verse eid="DEU 33:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:4"/>a law, which Moyses commanded us, an inheritance for the congregations of Iakob.<verse eid="DEU 33:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:5"/>And he shall be a ruler in<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">33:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'by means of'</char></note> the beloved one, when rulers of peoples have been gathered together with the tribes of Israel.<verse eid="DEU 33:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:6"/>Let Rouben live and not die out, and let him be many in number.<verse eid="DEU 33:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:7"/>And this<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">33:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'this blessing'</char></note> of Ioudas: Listen, O Lord, to the voice of Ioudas, and you could enter into his people; his hands will decide<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">33:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'distinguish'</char></note> for him, and you will be a helper from his enemies.<verse eid="DEU 33:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:8"/>And to Leui he said: Give Leui his clear ones<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">33:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'clear ones':  Possibly 'explaining devices'</char></note> and his truth to the devout man, whom they tempted him with temptation. They reviled him at the water of dispute.<verse eid="DEU 33:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:9"/>He who was saying to his father and his mother, "I have not seen you," and he did not acknowledge his brothers and did not acknowledge his sons-- he guarded your oracles and kept your covenant.<verse eid="DEU 33:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:10"/>They shall show Iakob your statutes and Israel your law; they shall place incense <note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">33:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'on your wrath' or 'when you are angry'</char></note>in your wrath<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">33:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the people'</char></note> continually on your altar.<verse eid="DEU 33:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:11"/>Bless, O Lord, his strength, and accept the works of his hands; shatter the loins of his enemies that have risen up against him, and those that hate him, let them not rise up.<verse eid="DEU 33:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:12"/>And to Benjamin he said: Beloved by the Lord he shall encamp in confidence-- and God overshadows him all the days-- and he rested between his shoulders.<verse eid="DEU 33:12"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:13"/>And to Ioseph he said: His land is from the Lord's blessing, from the seasons of the sky and of dew and from unfathomable springs below<verse eid="DEU 33:13"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:14"/>and in a season of produce of the sun's changes and from conjunctions of months<verse eid="DEU 33:14"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:15"/>and from the top of mountains of yore and from the top of the everlasting hills<verse eid="DEU 33:15"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:16"/>and in a season of earth's fullness. And may the things acceptable to him who appeared in the bush come on the head of Ioseph and on his crown, when he was glorified among brothers.<verse eid="DEU 33:16"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:17"/>A firstborn of a bull-- his beauty! His horns are horns of a unicorn; with them he will gore nations, all at once as far as earth's end. These are the myriads of Ephraim; these the thousands of Manasse.<verse eid="DEU 33:17"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:18"/>And to Zaboulon he said: Be glad, Zaboulon, in your going out, and, Issachar, in his coverts.<verse eid="DEU 33:18"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:19"/>They shall utterly destroy nations, and you<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">33:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = plural</char></note> shall invoke there, and you<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">33:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = plural</char></note> shall sacrifice a sacrifice of righteousness, for the riches of the sea will suckle you and the trade of those living by the seacoast.<verse eid="DEU 33:19"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:20"/>And to Gad he said: Blessed be the one who expands Gad! He rested like a lion, having broken arm and ruler.<verse eid="DEU 33:20"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:21"/>And he saw his first fruit, for there was apportioned a land of rulers, gathered together with chiefs of peoples, the Lord executed righteousness and his judgment with Israel.<verse eid="DEU 33:21"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:22"/>And to Dan he said: Dan is a lion's whelp, and he shall leap forth from Basan.<verse eid="DEU 33:22"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:23"/>And to Nephthali he said: Nephthali has a fullness of things acceptable, and let him be filled with blessing from the Lord; he shall inherit the sea and the southwest.<verse eid="DEU 33:23"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:24"/>And to Aser he said: Blessed of children be Aser, and he shall be acceptable to his brothers; he shall dip his foot in oil.<verse eid="DEU 33:24"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:25"/>His sandal will be iron and bronze, and as your days, so is your strength.<verse eid="DEU 33:25"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:26"/>There is none like the God of the beloved; he who rides upon the sky is your helper and the magnificent one of the firmament.<verse eid="DEU 33:26"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:27"/>And there is divine protection of yore and under the strength of the everlasting arms, and he will drive out the enemy before you, saying, "May you perish!"<verse eid="DEU 33:27"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:28"/>And Israel will encamp in confidence, alone in Iakob's land with grain and wine, and the sky is cloudy with dew for him.<verse eid="DEU 33:28"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 33:29"/>Happy are you, O Israel! Who is like you, a people saved by the Lord? Your helper will shield you, and the dagger will be your boast! And your enemies shall speak falsely to you, and you shall tread on their neck.<verse eid="DEU 33:29"/>



  <chapter sid="DEU 34"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 34:1"/>And Moyses went up from Araboth of Moab to Mount Nabau, to the top of Phasga, which is opposite Iericho, and the Lord showed him all the land: Galaad as far as Dan<verse eid="DEU 34:1"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 34:2"/>and all the land of Nephthali and all the land of Ephraim and Manasse and all the land of Ioudas as far as the last sea<verse eid="DEU 34:2"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 34:3"/>and the wilderness and the environs of Iericho, a city of palm trees-- as far as Segor.<verse eid="DEU 34:3"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 34:4"/>And the Lord said to Moyses, "This is the land of which I swore to Abraam and Isaak and Iakob, saying, 'I will give it to your offspring, I showed it to your eyes, but you shall not enter there."<verse eid="DEU 34:4"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 34:5"/>And Moyses, the domestic of the Lord, died there in the land of Moab, through the word of the Lord.<verse eid="DEU 34:5"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 34:6"/>And they buried him in Gai, in the land of Moab, near the house of Phogor, but no one knows his grave to this day.<verse eid="DEU 34:6"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 34:7"/>Now Moyses was one hundred twenty years old when he died; his eyes were neither dimmed nor were they ruined.<verse eid="DEU 34:7"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 34:8"/>And the sons of Israel wept for Moyses in Araboth of Moab, near the Jordan, opposite Iericho, thirty days, and the days of mourning of the weeping for Moyses were ended.<verse eid="DEU 34:8"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 34:9"/>And Iesous son of Naue was filled with the spirit of understanding, because Moyses had laid his hands on him, and the sons of Israel listened to him and did as the Lord had commanded Moyses.<verse eid="DEU 34:9"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 34:10"/>And there has not again arisen a prophet in Israel like Moyses whom the Lord knew face-to-face,<verse eid="DEU 34:10"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 34:11"/>with all the signs and wonders, whom the Lord sent to do them in the land of Egypt, against Pharao and his attendants and his entire land<verse eid="DEU 34:11"/>
    <verse sid="DEU 34:12"/>and the great wonders and the strong hand which Moyses exhibited before all Israel.<verse eid="DEU 34:12"/>
</usx>
