<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- SourceFormat: VL.  Converted to USX by the STEP project: 2023-08-18 -->
<usx version="2.0">
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <book code="MAN"/>



  <chapter sid="MAN 1"/>
    <verse sid="MAN 1:1"/>O Lord Almighty, God of our fathers, of Abraam and Isaak and Iakob and of their righteous offspring,<verse eid="MAN 1:1"/>
    <verse sid="MAN 1:2"/>you who made the sky and the earth together with all their order, you who shackled the sea by the word of your ordinance,<verse eid="MAN 1:2"/>
    <verse sid="MAN 1:3"/>you who shut up the deep and sealed it with your awesome and notable name,<verse eid="MAN 1:3"/>
    <verse sid="MAN 1:4"/>at whom all things shudder and tremble from before your power,<verse eid="MAN 1:4"/>
    <verse sid="MAN 1:5"/>because the magnificence of your glory cannot be borne, and the wrath of your threat against sinners cannot be withstood;<verse eid="MAN 1:5"/>
    <verse sid="MAN 1:6"/>both immeasurable and inscrutable is the mercy of your promise,<verse eid="MAN 1:6"/>
    <verse sid="MAN 1:7"/>because you are Lord Most High, compassionate, slow to anger and abounding in mercy and repenting at ills of human beings.<verse eid="MAN 1:7"/>
    <verse sid="MAN 1:8"/>So you, O Lord God of the righteous, you did not appoint repentance for righteous ones, for Abraam and Isaak and Iakob, who had not sinned against you, but you appointed repentance for me, the sinner,<verse eid="MAN 1:8"/>
    <verse sid="MAN 1:9"/>because I sinned beyond the number of the sand of the sea. My acts of lawlessness multiplied, O Lord, they multiplied, and I am not worthy to gaze at and see the height of the sky, due to the multitude of my injustices.<verse eid="MAN 1:9"/>
    <verse sid="MAN 1:10"/>Bent down I am by many a fetter of iron, for me to say, "No," over my sins. And I find no relief, because I provoked your anger and did what was evil before you, having set up abominations and having multipied objects of wrath.<verse eid="MAN 1:10"/>
    <verse sid="MAN 1:11"/>And now I bend my heart's knee, begging for kindness from you.<verse eid="MAN 1:11"/>
    <verse sid="MAN 1:12"/>I have sinned, O Lord; I have sinned, and my lawless acts I know.<verse eid="MAN 1:12"/>
    <verse sid="MAN 1:13"/>I plead, begging you; relieve me, O Lord; relieve me! Do not destroy me together with my acts of lawlessness nor be angry forever and retain evil for me nor condemn me in the deepest places of the earth, because you, O Lord, are the God of those who repent,<verse eid="MAN 1:13"/>
    <verse sid="MAN 1:14"/>and in me show your goodness, because, though unworthy, you will save me according to your abundant mercy,<verse eid="MAN 1:14"/>
    <verse sid="MAN 1:15"/>and I will praise you always throughout the days of my life, because all the host of the heavens will sing a hymn to you, and yours is the glory forever. Amen.<verse eid="MAN 1:15"/>
</usx>
