<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<_X_usx version="2.0">
<para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
<_X_book code="AMO">





<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="AMO 1">
<verse sid="AMO 1:1"/>Words of Amos that came in Nakkarim out of Thekoue, which he saw concerning Ierou-salem in the days of King Ozias of Ioudas and in the days of King Ieroboam son of Ioas of Israel, two years before the earthquake.<verse eid="AMO 1:1"/>

<verse sid="AMO 1:2"/>And he said: The Lord uttered sounds from Sion and gave his voice from Ierousalem, and the pastures of the shepherds mourned, and the top of Carmel dried up.<verse eid="AMO 1:2"/>

<verse sid="AMO 1:3"/>And the Lord said: For three impious acts of Damascus, and for four, I will not turn away from<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'I will not turn away from':  Perhaps 'I will not let ... go unpunished'</char></note> him, because they were sawing pregnant women of those in Galaad asunder with iron saws.<verse eid="AMO 1:3"/>

<verse sid="AMO 1:4"/>And I will send forth a fire on the house of Hazael, and it shall devour the foundations of the son of Hader.<verse eid="AMO 1:4"/>

<verse sid="AMO 1:5"/>And I will break the gate bars of Damascus and utterly destroy inhabitants from the plain of On, and I will cut to pieces a tribe from the men of Charran, and the important people of Syria will be taken captive, says the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 1:5"/>

<verse sid="AMO 1:6"/>This is what the Lord says: For three impious acts of Gaza, and for four, I will not turn away from<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'I will not turn away from':  Perhaps 'I will not let ... go unpunished'</char></note> them, because of their capturing a captivity of Salomon, to shut them up in Idumea.<verse eid="AMO 1:6"/>

<verse sid="AMO 1:7"/>And I will send forth a fire against the walls of Gaza, and it shall devour its foundations.<verse eid="AMO 1:7"/>

<verse sid="AMO 1:8"/>And I will utterly destroy inhabitants from Azotus, and a tribe shall be removed from Ascalon, and I will bring my hand against Akkaron, and those remaining of the allophyles shall perish, says the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 1:8"/>

<verse sid="AMO 1:9"/>This is what the Lord says: For three impious acts of Tyre, and for four, I will not turn away from<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'I will not turn away from':  Perhaps 'I will not let ... go unpunished'</char></note> it, because they shut up a captivity of Salomon in Idumea and did not remember a covenant of brothers.<verse eid="AMO 1:9"/>

<verse sid="AMO 1:10"/>And I will send forth a fire against the walls of Tyre, and it shall devour its foundations.<verse eid="AMO 1:10"/>

<verse sid="AMO 1:11"/>This is what the Lord says: For three impious acts of Idumea, and for four, I will not turn away from<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'I will not turn away from':  Perhaps 'I will not let ... go unpunished'</char></note> them, because they pursued his brother with a sword and he spoiled a womb upon the ground and seized his shivering fright for a testimony and kept his onslaught unto victory<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'unto victory':  Perhaps 'forever'</char></note>.<verse eid="AMO 1:11"/>

<verse sid="AMO 1:12"/>And I will send forth a fire on Thaiman, and it shall devour the foundations of its walls.<verse eid="AMO 1:12"/>

<verse sid="AMO 1:13"/>This is what the Lord says: For three impious acts of the sons of Ammon, and for four, I will not turn away from<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'I will not turn away from':  Perhaps 'I will not let ... go unpunished'</char></note> him, because they were ripping up the pregnant women of the Galaadites in order to enlarge their borders.<verse eid="AMO 1:13"/>

<verse sid="AMO 1:14"/>And I will kindle a fire against the walls of Rabba, and it shall devour its foundations, with a cry on the day of battle, and it will be shaken on the day of its destruction.<verse eid="AMO 1:14"/>

<verse sid="AMO 1:15"/>And its kings shall go into captivity, their priests and their rulers together, says the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 1:15"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="AMO 2">
<verse sid="AMO 2:1"/>This is what the Lord says: For three impious acts of Moab, and for four, I will not turn away from<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'I will not turn away from':  Perhaps 'I will not let ... go unpunished'</char></note> him, because they burned to lime the bones of the king of Idumea.<verse eid="AMO 2:1"/>

<verse sid="AMO 2:2"/>And I will send forth a fire against Moab, and it shall devour the foundations of its cities, and Moab shall die in debility, with shouting and with the sound of a trumpet.<verse eid="AMO 2:2"/>

<verse sid="AMO 2:3"/>And I will utterly destroy a judge from it and kill all its rulers with him, says the Lord<verse eid="AMO 2:3"/>

<verse sid="AMO 2:4"/>This is what the Lord says: For three impious acts of the sons of Ioudas, and for four, I will not turn away from<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'I will not turn away from':  Perhaps 'I will not let ... go unpunished'</char></note> him, because they rejected the law of the Lord and did not keep his ordinances, and their vain things which they made, which their fathers followed after, led them astray.<verse eid="AMO 2:4"/>

<verse sid="AMO 2:5"/>And I will send forth a fire against Ioudas, and it shall devour the foundations of Ierousalem.<verse eid="AMO 2:5"/>

<verse sid="AMO 2:6"/>This is what the Lord says: For three impious acts of Israel, and for four, I will not turn away from<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'I will not turn away from':  Perhaps 'I will not let ... go unpunished'</char></note> him, because they sold the just for silver and the needy for the sake of sandals--<verse eid="AMO 2:6"/>

<verse sid="AMO 2:7"/>things that tread on the dust of the earth, and they were buffeting the heads of the poor, and they turned aside the way of the humble, and a son and his father were going to the same female servant in order to profane the name of their God.<verse eid="AMO 2:7"/>

<verse sid="AMO 2:8"/>And binding their garments with cords, they were making curtains beside the altar, and in the house of their God they were drinking wine obtained through extortion.<verse eid="AMO 2:8"/>

<verse sid="AMO 2:9"/>But I removed the Amorrite from before them, whose height was as the height of a cedar, and who was as strong as an oak, and I removed his fruit above and his roots beneath.<verse eid="AMO 2:9"/>

<verse sid="AMO 2:10"/>Also I brought you up out of the land of Egypt and led you around for forty years in the wilderness, to inherit the land of the Amorrites.<verse eid="AMO 2:10"/>

<verse sid="AMO 2:11"/>And I took some of your sons to be prophets and some of your youths for consecration. Is this not so, O sons of Israel? says the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 2:11"/>

<verse sid="AMO 2:12"/>But you were making the consecrated ones drink wine and were commanding the prophets, saying, "You shall not prophesy."<verse eid="AMO 2:12"/>

<verse sid="AMO 2:13"/>Therefore, behold, I roll under you like a wagon full of straw is rolled.<verse eid="AMO 2:13"/>

<verse sid="AMO 2:14"/>And flight shall perish from the runner, and the strong shall not retain his strength, and the fighter shall not save his soul,<verse eid="AMO 2:14"/>

<verse sid="AMO 2:15"/>and the archer shall not stand, and he who is swift on his feet shall not escape, nor shall the horseman save his soul<verse eid="AMO 2:15"/>

<verse sid="AMO 2:16"/>and shall find his heart in acts of dominance; the naked shall pursue on that day, says the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 2:16"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="AMO 3">
<verse sid="AMO 3:1"/>Hear this word that the Lord has spoken against you, O house of Israel, and against the whole tribe that I brought up out of the land of Egypt, saying,<verse eid="AMO 3:1"/>

<verse sid="AMO 3:2"/>Only you have I known of all the tribes of the earth; therefore I will avenge upon you all your sins.<verse eid="AMO 3:2"/>

<verse sid="AMO 3:3"/>Will two in any way walk together unless they be acquainted with each other?<verse eid="AMO 3:3"/>

<verse sid="AMO 3:4"/>Will a lion roar from its thicket, when it has no prey? Will a whelp utter its voice from his den at all, if he has caught nothing?<verse eid="AMO 3:4"/>

<verse sid="AMO 3:5"/>Will a bird fall upon the ground without a fowler? Will a snare on the ground spring without catching something?<verse eid="AMO 3:5"/>

<verse sid="AMO 3:6"/>Will a trumpet sound in a city, and the people not be terrified? Will there be evil in a city, which the Lord did not do?<verse eid="AMO 3:6"/>

<verse sid="AMO 3:7"/>For the Lord God will not do a thing unless he reveals instruction to his slaves the prophets.<verse eid="AMO 3:7"/>

<verse sid="AMO 3:8"/>A lion will roar, and who will not fear? The Lord God has spoken, and who will not prophesy?<verse eid="AMO 3:8"/>

<verse sid="AMO 3:9"/>Proclaim to the districts among the Assyrians, and to the districts of Egypt, and say, "Assemble on the mountain of Samaria, and see many marvels in its midst and oppression within it."<verse eid="AMO 3:9"/>

<verse sid="AMO 3:10"/>And it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'Samaria'</char></note> was unaware of what would be before it, says the Lord, those who store up injustice and wretchedness in their districts.<verse eid="AMO 3:10"/>

<verse sid="AMO 3:11"/>Therefore this is what the Lord God says: Tyre and your land round about shall be made desolate, and he shall bring down your might out of you, and your districts shall be plundered.<verse eid="AMO 3:11"/>

<verse sid="AMO 3:12"/>This is what the Lord says: As when the shepherd pulls from the mouth of the lion two legs or a lobe of an ear, so shall the sons of Israel be pulled out, those who live in Samaria before a tribe and in Damascus as priests.<verse eid="AMO 3:12"/>

<verse sid="AMO 3:13"/>Hear, and testify to the house of Iakob, says the Lord God the Almighty:<verse eid="AMO 3:13"/>

<verse sid="AMO 3:14"/>For in the day when I take vengeance on the impious acts of Israel against him, I will also take vengeance against the altars of Baithel, and the horns of the altar shall be demolished and fall to the ground.<verse eid="AMO 3:14"/>

<verse sid="AMO 3:15"/>I will demolish the house encircled by columns onto the summer house, and the houses of ivory shall perish, and many other houses shall be added, says the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 3:15"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="AMO 4">
<verse sid="AMO 4:1"/>Hear this word, you heifers of Basanitis, who are in the mountain of Samaria, who oppress the poor and trample the needy, who say to their lords, "Give to us that we might drink."<verse eid="AMO 4:1"/>

<verse sid="AMO 4:2"/>The Lord swears by his holy ones: For behold, days are coming upon you, and they shall take you with weapons, and fiery pests shall cast those with you into cauldrons heated from underneath.<verse eid="AMO 4:2"/>

<verse sid="AMO 4:3"/>And you shall be carried out naked before each other, and you shall be flung out into Mount Remman, says the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 4:3"/>

<verse sid="AMO 4:4"/>You came to Baithel and committed lawlessness, and in Galgala you multiplied to commit impiety, and you brought your sacrifices in the morning, your tithes on the third day.<verse eid="AMO 4:4"/>

<verse sid="AMO 4:5"/>They read the law outside and called for confessions. Announce that the sons of Israel have loved these things, says the Lord God.<verse eid="AMO 4:5"/>

<verse sid="AMO 4:6"/>And I will give you an aching of the teeth in all your cities, and lack of bread in all your places, and you did not return to me, says the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 4:6"/>

<verse sid="AMO 4:7"/>I also withheld the rain from you three months before the harvest, and I will rain on one city, and on one city I will not rain; one part will be rained upon, and a part which I will not rain on will wither,<verse eid="AMO 4:7"/>

<verse sid="AMO 4:8"/>and two or three cities will come together to one city to drink water and will not be satisfied; even so you did not return to me, says the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 4:8"/>

<verse sid="AMO 4:9"/>I struck you with fever and jaundice; you multiplied your gardens; the caterpillar devoured your vineyards and fig yards and olive yards; even so you did not return to me, says the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 4:9"/>

<verse sid="AMO 4:10"/>I sent you death in the way of Egypt, and I killed your young men with the sword, along with the captivity of your horses, and I brought up your camps with fire in your wrath; even so you did not return to me, says the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 4:10"/>

<verse sid="AMO 4:11"/>I overthrew you as God overthrew Sodoma and Gomorra, and you were like a firebrand snatched from the fire; even so you did not return to me, says the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 4:11"/>

<verse sid="AMO 4:12"/>Therefore, thus I will do to you, O Israel, but because I will do thus to you, prepare to call upon your God, O Israel.<verse eid="AMO 4:12"/>

<verse sid="AMO 4:13"/>For behold, I am the one who makes the thunder strong and creates a wind and announces his anointed to humans, makes dawn and mist and treads on the heights of the earth-- the Lord God the Almighty is his name!<verse eid="AMO 4:13"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="AMO 5">
<verse sid="AMO 5:1"/>Hear this word of the Lord that I take up over you in lamentation, O house of Israel:<verse eid="AMO 5:1"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:2"/>She has fallen, no more to rise, the maiden Israel; she slipped upon her land; there is no one to raise her up.<verse eid="AMO 5:2"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:3"/>For this is what the Lord says: The city out of which a thousand were going forth, there shall be left a hundred, and out of which a hundred were going forth, there shall be left ten to the house of Israel.<verse eid="AMO 5:3"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:4"/>For this is what the Lord says to the house of Israel: Seek me, and you shall live,<verse eid="AMO 5:4"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:5"/>and stop seeking Baithel, and stop entering Galgala, and stop crossing over to the well of the oath, because Galgala, taken captive, will be taken captive, and Baithel shall be as not existing.<verse eid="AMO 5:5"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:6"/>Seek the Lord, and live, lest the house of Ioseph should flame up like fire, and it will devour him, and there will be no one to quench for the house of Israel.<verse eid="AMO 5:6"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:7"/>The Lord is the one who makes judgment on high and has established justice on earth,<verse eid="AMO 5:7"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:8"/>who makes all things and transforms and turns the shadow of death into the morning and darkens day into night, who calls to the water of the sea and pours it out upon the face of the earth-- the Lord God the Almighty is his name--<verse eid="AMO 5:8"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:9"/>who dispenses destruction against strength and brings misery to the fortress.<verse eid="AMO 5:9"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:10"/>They have hated the one who reproves in the gates and have despised holy speech.<verse eid="AMO 5:10"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:11"/>Therefore, because you were buffeting the poor and have taken from them choice gifts, you have built houses of hewn stone, but you shall not live in them; you have planted desirable vineyards, but you shall not drink the wine from them.<verse eid="AMO 5:11"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:12"/>For I have known your many impious acts -- your sins are mighty-- trampling the just, taking rewards and turning aside the needy in the gates.<verse eid="AMO 5:12"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:13"/>Therefore the prudent will keep silent in that time, for it is an evil time.<verse eid="AMO 5:13"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:14"/>Seek the good thing and not the evil thing, that you may live, and so the Lord God the Almighty will be with you, just as you have said,<verse eid="AMO 5:14"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:15"/>"We have hated evil things and loved the good things." Restore judgment in the gates, that the Lord God the Almighty might have mercy on the remnant of Ioseph.<verse eid="AMO 5:15"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:16"/>Therefore this is what the Lord God the Almighty says: In all the streets there shall be wailing, and in all the roads it shall be said, Alas! Alas! The farmer shall be called to mourning and lamentation and to those knowing a dirge;<verse eid="AMO 5:16"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:17"/>in all the roads there shall be wailing, for I will pass through the midst of you, said the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 5:17"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:18"/>Woe, you who desire the day of the Lord! Why is this the day of the Lord to you? And it is darkness, not light,<verse eid="AMO 5:18"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:19"/>as if someone should flee from a lion, and a bear attacks him, or he should leap into his house, place his hands on the wall, and a snake should bite him.<verse eid="AMO 5:19"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:20"/>Is not the day of the Lord darkness and not light, and gloom with no brightness in it?<verse eid="AMO 5:20"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:21"/>I have hated, I have despised your feasts, and I will not smell at your festivals.<verse eid="AMO 5:21"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:22"/>For if you should bring to me your whole burnt offerings and sacrifices, I will not accept them, and your conspicuous acts for deliverance<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Perhaps 'offering for deliverance'</char></note> I will not look upon.<verse eid="AMO 5:22"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:23"/>Take away from me the noise of your songs; I will not listen to a strumming of your instruments.<verse eid="AMO 5:23"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:24"/>And judgment will roll down like water, and justice like an unfordable wadi.<verse eid="AMO 5:24"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:25"/>Surely you did not bring me victims and sacrifices forty years, O house of Israel?<verse eid="AMO 5:25"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:26"/>You even took up the tent of Moloch and the star of your god Raiphan, models of them which you made for yourselves.<verse eid="AMO 5:26"/>

<verse sid="AMO 5:27"/>And I will deport you beyond Damascus, says the Lord-- God the Almighty is his name.<verse eid="AMO 5:27"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="AMO 6">
<verse sid="AMO 6:1"/>Alas for those who count Sion as nothing and for those who trust in the mountain of Samaria. They have harvested the rule of the nations and entered for themselves.<verse eid="AMO 6:1"/>

<verse sid="AMO 6:2"/>Cross over, O house of Israel, all of you, and see, and from there pass on to Hemath Rabba, and go down to Geth of allophyles, the most excellent ones of all these kingdoms. See<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> if their borders are greater than your borders.<verse eid="AMO 6:2"/>

<verse sid="AMO 6:3"/>Those who pray for an evil day, who draw near and hold fast to false sabbaths,<verse eid="AMO 6:3"/>

<verse sid="AMO 6:4"/>who sleep on beds of ivory and live lewdly on their couches and eat kids from the flocks and suckling calves from the midst of the herds,<verse eid="AMO 6:4"/>

<verse sid="AMO 6:5"/>who applaud at the sound of the instruments-- since they considered them as permanent and not as fleeting--<verse eid="AMO 6:5"/>

<verse sid="AMO 6:6"/>who drink thoroughly filtered wine and anoint themselves with the finest oils, they were not even suffering anything over the ruin of Ioseph.<verse eid="AMO 6:6"/>

<verse sid="AMO 6:7"/>Therefore they shall now be captives of the powerful from the beginning, and the neighing of horses shall be removed from Ephraim.<verse eid="AMO 6:7"/>

<verse sid="AMO 6:8"/>Because the Lord has sworn by himself: For I abhor all the pride of Iakob and have hated his lands. And I will remove a city with all who inhabit it.<verse eid="AMO 6:8"/>

<verse sid="AMO 6:9"/>And it shall be, if ten men are left in one house, they shall also die-- and the remaining ones shall be left--<verse eid="AMO 6:9"/>

<verse sid="AMO 6:10"/>and the members of their household shall take them and forcibly bring their bones out of the house, and he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'one'</char></note> will say to those in charge of the house, "Might there still be one with you?" And he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'one'</char></note> will say, "No more." And he will say, "Silence, so as not to name the name of the Lord!"<verse eid="AMO 6:10"/>

<verse sid="AMO 6:11"/>For behold, the Lord commands, and he shall strike the great house with bruises and the little house with lacerations.<verse eid="AMO 6:11"/>

<verse sid="AMO 6:12"/>Will horses pursue on rocks? Will they be silent among mares? Because you have turned judgment into wrath and the fruit of justice into bitterness,<verse eid="AMO 6:12"/>

<verse sid="AMO 6:13"/>you who are glad at no word, who say, "Did we not have horns in our strength?"<verse eid="AMO 6:13"/>

<verse sid="AMO 6:14"/>For behold, I am raising up against you a nation, O house of Israel, and they shall oppress you, that you may not enter Hemath and as far as the wadi of the west.<verse eid="AMO 6:14"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="AMO 7">
<verse sid="AMO 7:1"/>Thus the Lord showed me and behold, an early offspring of grasshoppers coming, and behold, one locust larva, Gog the king.<verse eid="AMO 7:1"/>

<verse sid="AMO 7:2"/>And it will be, if they finish to devour the grass of the land-- and I said, "O Lord, O Lord, be gracious. Who will raise up Iakob, because he is very small?<verse eid="AMO 7:2"/>

<verse sid="AMO 7:3"/>Repent, O Lord, at this." "Even this shall not be," says the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 7:3"/>

<verse sid="AMO 7:4"/>Thus the Lord showed me, and behold, the Lord called for a sentence by fire. And it devoured the voluminous deep and devoured the portion.<verse eid="AMO 7:4"/>

<verse sid="AMO 7:5"/>And I said, "O Lord, O Lord, do cease! Who will raise up Iakob, because he is very small?<verse eid="AMO 7:5"/>

<verse sid="AMO 7:6"/>Repent, O Lord, at this." "Even this shall not come about," says the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 7:6"/>

<verse sid="AMO 7:7"/>Thus the Lord showed me, and behold, one that stood on an adamantine wall, and adamant was in his hand.<verse eid="AMO 7:7"/>

<verse sid="AMO 7:8"/>And the Lord said to me, "Amos, what do you see?" And I said, "Adamant." And the Lord said to me, "Behold, I am inserting adamant in the midst of my people, Israel. I will no longer add to pass them by,<verse eid="AMO 7:8"/>

<verse sid="AMO 7:9"/>and altars<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = 'bômos'</char></note> of laughter shall be annihilated, and the mystic rites of Israel shall be laid waste, and I will rise against the house of Ieroboam with a sword."<verse eid="AMO 7:9"/>

<verse sid="AMO 7:10"/>And Amasias, the priest of Baithel, sent to King Ieroboam of Israel, saying, "Amos is conducting seditious meetings against you in the midst of the house of Israel. The land shall not be able to bear all his words.<verse eid="AMO 7:10"/>

<verse sid="AMO 7:11"/>For this is what Amos says, 'Ieroboam shall die by the sword, and Israel shall be led captive from his land.' "<verse eid="AMO 7:11"/>

<verse sid="AMO 7:12"/>And Amasias said to Amos, "You that see, go, be-take you to the land of Ioudas, and live there, and you shall prophesy there,<verse eid="AMO 7:12"/>

<verse sid="AMO 7:13"/>but do no longer add to prophesy at Baithel, for it is the king's holy precinct and it is the house of the kingdom."<verse eid="AMO 7:13"/>

<verse sid="AMO 7:14"/>And Amos answered and said to Amasias, "I was no prophet nor a prophet's son, but I was a goatherd and a scratcher of sycamore figs,<verse eid="AMO 7:14"/>

<verse sid="AMO 7:15"/>and the Lord took me from the sheep, and the Lord said to me, 'Go, prophesy against my people, Israel.'<verse eid="AMO 7:15"/>

<verse sid="AMO 7:16"/>"And now, hear a word of the Lord. You say, 'Do not prophesy against Israel, and you shall not incite a mob against the house of Iakob.'<verse eid="AMO 7:16"/>

<verse sid="AMO 7:17"/>Therefore this is what the Lord says, 'Your wife shall become a whore in the city, and your sons and your daughters shall fall by the sword, and your land shall be measured by line, and you yourself shall die in an unclean land, and Israel shall be led captive from its land.' "<verse eid="AMO 7:17"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="AMO 8">
<verse sid="AMO 8:1"/>Thus the Lord showed me, and behold, a fowler's basket. And he said, "What do you see, Amos?" And I said, "A fowler's basket."<verse eid="AMO 8:1"/>

<verse sid="AMO 8:2"/>And the Lord said to me, "The end has come upon my people Israel; I will no longer add to pass them by,<verse eid="AMO 8:2"/>

<verse sid="AMO 8:3"/>and the compartments of the shrine shall wail in that day," says the Lord; "the fallen one shall be numerous in every place. I will inflict silence."<verse eid="AMO 8:3"/>

<verse sid="AMO 8:4"/>Do hear this, you who rub out the needy in the morning and oppress the poor from the land,<verse eid="AMO 8:4"/>

<verse sid="AMO 8:5"/>who say, "When will the month pass and we will do business, and the sabbaths, and we will open storehouses, to make a measure small, to enlarge weights and to make the balance unfair,<verse eid="AMO 8:5"/>

<verse sid="AMO 8:6"/>to acquire the poor with silver and the humble for sandals, and we will trade in every kind of produce?"<verse eid="AMO 8:6"/>

<verse sid="AMO 8:7"/>The Lord swears by the pride of Iakob: If all your deeds shall be forgotten successfully!<verse eid="AMO 8:7"/>

<verse sid="AMO 8:8"/>And due to this shall not the land be troubled and everyone mourn who lives in it and consummation rise up like a river and sink like the river of Egypt?<verse eid="AMO 8:8"/>

<verse sid="AMO 8:9"/>And it will come to pass on that day, says the Lord, and the sun will go down at noon, and the light will become dark upon the earth in the daytime.<verse eid="AMO 8:9"/>

<verse sid="AMO 8:10"/>And I will turn your feasts into mourning and all your songs into lamentation. And I will bring sackcloth on every loin and baldness on every head. And I will make him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Antecedent uncertain</char></note> like the mourning for a loved one and those with him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Antecedent uncertain</char></note> like a day of suffering.<verse eid="AMO 8:10"/>

<verse sid="AMO 8:11"/>Behold, days are coming, says the Lord, and I will send a famine on the land, not a famine of bread or a thirst for water, but a famine of hearing a word of the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 8:11"/>

<verse sid="AMO 8:12"/>And the waters will be shaken as far as the sea, and from north to east they shall run to and fro, seeking the word of the Lord, and they shall not find it.<verse eid="AMO 8:12"/>

<verse sid="AMO 8:13"/>In that day, the beautiful maidens and the young men shall faint for thirst,<verse eid="AMO 8:13"/>

<verse sid="AMO 8:14"/>those who swear by the atonement of Samaria, and say, "Your god lives, O Dan," and, "Your god lives, O Bersabee"-- and they shall fall and never rise again.<verse eid="AMO 8:14"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="AMO 9">
<verse sid="AMO 9:1"/>I saw the Lord standing on the altar, and he said: Strike the propitiatory, and the gateways shall be shaken, and cut through the heads of all, and those who are left I will kill with the sword; not one of them fleeing shall escape, and not one of them attempting to return safe will come through safely.<verse eid="AMO 9:1"/>

<verse sid="AMO 9:2"/>If they be buried in Hades, from there my hand shall draw them up; even if they ascend to heaven, from there I will bring them down.<verse eid="AMO 9:2"/>

<verse sid="AMO 9:3"/>If they hide on the top of Carmel, from there I will search out and take them; even if they sink from my eyes to the depths of the sea, there I will command the dragon, and it shall bite them.<verse eid="AMO 9:3"/>

<verse sid="AMO 9:4"/>Even if they go into captivity in front of their enemies, there I will command the sword, and it shall kill them, and I will fix my eyes on them for harm and not for good.<verse eid="AMO 9:4"/>

<verse sid="AMO 9:5"/>And the Lord God the Almighty, who touches the earth and shakes it, and all who inhabit it will mourn, and its consummation will rise up like a river and sink like the river of Egypt;<verse eid="AMO 9:5"/>

<verse sid="AMO 9:6"/>who builds his ascent to heaven and founds his promise upon the earth, who calls for the water of the sea and pours it out upon the face of the earth-- the Lord God the Almighty is his name.<verse eid="AMO 9:6"/>

<verse sid="AMO 9:7"/>Are you not like sons of Ethiopians to me, O sons of Israel? says the Lord. Did I not bring Israel up from the land of Egypt and the allophyles from Cappadocia and the Syrians from a hole?<verse eid="AMO 9:7"/>

<verse sid="AMO 9:8"/>Behold, the eyes of the Lord God are upon the kingdom of sinners, and I will remove it from the face of the earth-- except that I will not utterly remove the house of Iakob, says the Lord.<verse eid="AMO 9:8"/>

<verse sid="AMO 9:9"/>For behold, I am commanding, and I will winnow the house of Israel among all the nations as one winnows with a winnowing-fan, and nothing crushed<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'nothing crushed':  Perhaps 'no crushed grain'</char></note> shall fall to the ground.<verse eid="AMO 9:9"/>

<verse sid="AMO 9:10"/>All the sinners of my people shall die by the sword, who say, "Evil shall not draw near or be against us."<verse eid="AMO 9:10"/>

<verse sid="AMO 9:11"/>On that day I will raise up the tent of Dauid that is fallen and rebuild its ruins and raise up its destruction, and rebuild it as the days of old<verse eid="AMO 9:11"/>

<verse sid="AMO 9:12"/>in order that those remaining of humans and<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'even'</char></note> all the nations upon whom my name has been called might seek out me<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note>, says the Lord who does these things.<verse eid="AMO 9:12"/>

<verse sid="AMO 9:13"/>Behold days are coming, says the Lord, and the grain harvest shall overtake the vintage, and the grape shall ripen at seedtime, and the mountains shall drip sweetness, and all the hills shall be thickly grown.<verse eid="AMO 9:13"/>

<verse sid="AMO 9:14"/>And I will return the captivity of my people Israel, and they shall build the annihilated cities and inhabit them, and they shall plant vineyards and drink their wine, and they shall plant gardens and eat their fruit.<verse eid="AMO 9:14"/>

<verse sid="AMO 9:15"/>And I will plant them upon their land, and they shall never again be plucked from their land that I have given them, says the Lord God the Almighty.<verse eid="AMO 9:15"/>
</_X_chapter></_X_book></_X_usx>