<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<_X_usx version="2.0">
<para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
<_X_book code="BAR">





<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="BAR 1">
<verse sid="BAR 1:1"/>And these are the words of the book which Barouch son of Nerias son of Maasaias son of Sedekias son of Hasadias son of Chelkias wrote in Babylon,<verse eid="BAR 1:1"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:2"/>in the fifth year, on the seventh of the month, at the time when the Chaldeans took Ierousalem and set it on fire.<verse eid="BAR 1:2"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:3"/>And Barouch read the words of this book in the ears of Iechonias son of Ioakim, king of Iouda, and in the ears of all the people, those who came to the book,<verse eid="BAR 1:3"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:4"/>and in the ears of the mighty and the sons of the kings and in the ears of the elders and in the ears of all the people, from small to great, all who lived in Babylon by the river Soud.<verse eid="BAR 1:4"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:5"/>And they kept weeping and fasting and praying before the Lord,<verse eid="BAR 1:5"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:6"/>and they collected silver as the hand of each was able<verse eid="BAR 1:6"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:7"/>and sent it to Ierou-salem to the priest Ioakim son of Chelkias son of Salom and to the priests and to all the people who were found with him in Ierousalem<verse eid="BAR 1:7"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:8"/>when he took the vessels of the house of the Lord which were carried out of the shrine to return to the land of Iouda on the tenth of Siouan-- the silver vessels that King Sedekias of Iouda son of Iosias had made,<verse eid="BAR 1:8"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:9"/>after Nabouchodonosor, king of Babylon, exiled Iechonias and the magistrates and the prisoners and the mighty and the people of the land from Ierousalem, and he brought him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'them'</char></note> to Babylon.<verse eid="BAR 1:9"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:10"/>And they said: Look, we sent you silver; and buy with the silver whole burnt offerings and for sin and incense, and make manaa<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'grain offering'</char></note>, and offer them on the altar of the Lord our God;<verse eid="BAR 1:10"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:11"/>and pray concerning the life of King Nabouchodonosor of Babylon and regarding the life of his son Baltasar so that their days on the earth may be like the days of the sky.<verse eid="BAR 1:11"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:12"/>And the Lord will give strength to us, and he will illuminate our eyes, and we shall live under the shadow of King Nabouchodonosor of Babylon and under the shadow of his son Baltasar, and we shall be subject to them many days, and we shall find favor before them.<verse eid="BAR 1:12"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:13"/>And pray concerning us to the Lord our God, for we have sinned against the Lord our God, and the anger of the Lord and his wrath have not turned away from us until this day.<verse eid="BAR 1:13"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:14"/>And you shall read aloud this book, which we sent to you to declare in the house of the Lord on a feast day and on days of a season.<verse eid="BAR 1:14"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:15"/>And you shall say: To the Lord, our God, belongs righteousness but to us shame of faces as this day, to a person of Iouda, to the inhabitants of Ierousalem,<verse eid="BAR 1:15"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:16"/>to our kings and to our magistrates and to our priests and to our prophets and to our fathers,<verse eid="BAR 1:16"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:17"/>for which things we have sinned before the Lord,<verse eid="BAR 1:17"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:18"/>and we disobeyed him and have not listened to the voice of the Lord, our God, to walk by the decrees of the Lord that he gave before us.<verse eid="BAR 1:18"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:19"/>From the day when the Lord brought our fathers out of the land of Egypt even until this day, we were being disobedient to the Lord our God, and we were acting carelessly so as not to listen to his voice.<verse eid="BAR 1:19"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:20"/>And there have clung to us the bad things and the curse that the Lord instructed to his servant Moyses in the day he brought out our ancestors from the land of Egypt, to give to us a land flowing with milk and honey, as this day.<verse eid="BAR 1:20"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:21"/>And we did not listen to the voice of the Lord our God according to all the words of the prophets whom he sent to us,<verse eid="BAR 1:21"/>

<verse sid="BAR 1:22"/>and each of us went off in the intent of his evil heart to work for other gods, to do evil things in the eyes of the Lord our God.<verse eid="BAR 1:22"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="BAR 2">
<verse sid="BAR 2:1"/>And the Lord established his word which he spoke to us and to our judges who judged Israel and to our kings and to our magistrates and to a person of Israel and Iouda.<verse eid="BAR 2:1"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:2"/>It was not done under the whole sky as he did in Ierousalem, according to that which is written in the law of Moyses--<verse eid="BAR 2:2"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:3"/>that we should eat, a person the flesh of his son and a person the flesh of his daughter.<verse eid="BAR 2:3"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:4"/>And he gave them as subjects to all the kingdoms around us as a disgrace and as something untrodden, among all the peoples around us there where the Lord scattered them.<verse eid="BAR 2:4"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:5"/>And they became beneath and not above, because we sinned against the Lord, our God, so as not to listen to his voice.<verse eid="BAR 2:5"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:6"/>To the Lord, our God, belongs righteousness but to us and to our fathers shame of faces, as this day.<verse eid="BAR 2:6"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:7"/>All these bad things which the Lord spoke to us have come upon us.<verse eid="BAR 2:7"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:8"/>And we did not entreat the face of the Lord to turn away, each from the designs of their wicked heart.<verse eid="BAR 2:8"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:9"/>And the Lord kept watch over the bad things, and the Lord brought them upon us, for the Lord is just in all his works, which he commanded us.<verse eid="BAR 2:9"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:10"/>And we have not listened to his voice to walk by the decrees of the Lord that he gave before us.<verse eid="BAR 2:10"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:11"/>And now, O Lord God of Israel, you who brought out your people from the land of Egypt by a mighty hand and with signs and with wonders and with great power and with a high arm and you made yourself a name, as this day.<verse eid="BAR 2:11"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:12"/>We have sinned; we have been impious; we have done wrong, O Lord our God, against all of your requirements.<verse eid="BAR 2:12"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:13"/>Let your anger turn away from us, for few of us have been left behind among the nations, there where you scattered us.<verse eid="BAR 2:13"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:14"/>Listen, O Lord, to our prayer and our petition, and deliver us for your sake, and give us favor before the face of those who carried us off to exile<verse eid="BAR 2:14"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:15"/>in order that all the earth may know that you are the Lord our God, for your name has been called upon Israel and upon his family.<verse eid="BAR 2:15"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:16"/>O Lord, look down from your holy house, and think of us. Incline, O Lord, your ear, and listen.<verse eid="BAR 2:16"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:17"/>Open your eyes, and see, for the dead in Hades, those whose spirit has been taken from their inward parts, will not give glory and justification to the Lord.<verse eid="BAR 2:17"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:18"/>But the soul who is grieving over the magnitude<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'great mass of people'</char></note>, that walks bowed and is weak, and the eyes that are failing and the soul that is hungry-- they shall give you glory and righteousness, O Lord.<verse eid="BAR 2:18"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:19"/>For it is not because of acts deemed righteous of our fathers and our kings that we throw down our<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'for us'</char></note> mercy before you, O Lord, our God.<verse eid="BAR 2:19"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:20"/>For you have brought your anger and your wrath against us, as you had spoken by the hand of your servants the prophets, saying:<verse eid="BAR 2:20"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:21"/>Thus did the Lord say: Incline your shoulder, and work for the king of Babylon, and sit upon the land which I gave to your fathers.<verse eid="BAR 2:21"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:22"/>And if you do not obey the voice of the Lord to work for the king of Babylon,<verse eid="BAR 2:22"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:23"/>I will make to fail from the towns of Iouda and from outside of Ierousalem a voice of merriment and a voice of delight, a voice of bridegroom and a voice of bride, and all the land will become untrodden by inhabitants.<verse eid="BAR 2:23"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:24"/>And we did not obey your voice to work for the king of Babylon, and you have established your words which you spoke by the hands of your servants the prophets, that the bones of our kings and the bones of our fathers may be carried out from their place.<verse eid="BAR 2:24"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:25"/>And look, they<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the bones'</char></note> are cast out in the heat of the day and the frost of the night, and they died in wicked pains, by famine and by sword and by dispatch.<verse eid="BAR 2:25"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:26"/>And you made the house, where your name was called over it, as this day because of the wickedness of the house of Israel and the house of Iouda.<verse eid="BAR 2:26"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:27"/>And you have done to us, O Lord, our God, according to all your fairness and according to all your great compassion<verse eid="BAR 2:27"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:28"/>as you spoke by the hand of your servant Moyses in the day when you commanded him to write your law before the sons of Israel, saying,<verse eid="BAR 2:28"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:29"/>"If you do not obey my voice, surely this great, voluminous buzzing<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:29</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'of people'</char></note> will turn into a small one among the nations, there where I will scatter them.<verse eid="BAR 2:29"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:30"/>For I knew that they would not obey me, because the people are stiff-necked. And they will return to their heart in the land of their exile,<verse eid="BAR 2:30"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:31"/>and they will know that I am the Lord their God. And I will give them a heart and hearing ears,<verse eid="BAR 2:31"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:32"/>and they will praise me in the land of their exile, and they will remember my name,<verse eid="BAR 2:32"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:33"/>and they will turn away from their hard back and from their wicked deeds, because they will remember the way of their fathers who sinned before the Lord.<verse eid="BAR 2:33"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:34"/>And I will return them to the land, which I swore to their fathers, to Abraam and to Isaak and to Iakob, and they will rule over it, and I will multiply them, and they will not diminish.<verse eid="BAR 2:34"/>

<verse sid="BAR 2:35"/>I will establish with them an everlasting covenant, that I be god to them and they be a people to me, and I will not disturb again my people Israel from the land that I have given them."<verse eid="BAR 2:35"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="BAR 3">
<verse sid="BAR 3:1"/>O Lord Almighty, God of Israel, a soul in straits and a weary spirit calls out to you.<verse eid="BAR 3:1"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:2"/>Listen, O Lord, and show mercy, for we have sinned before you.<verse eid="BAR 3:2"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:3"/>For you are seated forever, and we are perishing forever.<verse eid="BAR 3:3"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:4"/>O Lord Almighty, God of Israel, listen now to the prayer of those of Israel who have died and of the sons of those who kept sinning before you, who did not listen to the voice of the Lord, their God, and bad things have clung to us.<verse eid="BAR 3:4"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:5"/>Do not remember the injustices of our ancestors; rather, remember your hand and your name in this season.<verse eid="BAR 3:5"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:6"/>For you are the Lord, our God, and we will praise you, O Lord.<verse eid="BAR 3:6"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:7"/>For because of this you have given your fear in our heart in order that we call upon your name, and we will praise you in our exile, for we have put away from our heart all the injustice of our fathers who sinned before you.<verse eid="BAR 3:7"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:8"/>Look, we are today in our exile, there where you have scattered us for a reproach and for a curse and for a penalty according to all the injustices of our fathers who departed from the Lord our God.<verse eid="BAR 3:8"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:9"/>Hear, O Israel, commandments of life; give ear to learn insight.<verse eid="BAR 3:9"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:10"/>Why is it, O Israel, why is it that you are in the enemies' land, that you became old in a foreign land;<verse eid="BAR 3:10"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:11"/>you were defiled with corpses, you were counted among those in Hades?<verse eid="BAR 3:11"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:12"/>You have forsaken the spring of wisdom.<verse eid="BAR 3:12"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:13"/>If in the way of God you had gone, you would be living in peace forever.<verse eid="BAR 3:13"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:14"/>Learn where there is insight, where there is strength, where there is intelligence, to know at the same time where there is longevity and life, where there is light for eyes and peace.<verse eid="BAR 3:14"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:15"/>Who has found her place, and who entered into her treasuries?<verse eid="BAR 3:15"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:16"/>Where are the magistrates of the nations and those who have dominion over the beasts that are on the earth,<verse eid="BAR 3:16"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:17"/>those who make sport among the birds of the sky and who store up silver and gold, in which humans have trusted, and there is no end to their acquisition,<verse eid="BAR 3:17"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:18"/>those who scheme for silver and are anxious, and there is no trace of their works?<verse eid="BAR 3:18"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:19"/>They have vanished and gone down to Hades, and others have arisen in their place.<verse eid="BAR 3:19"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:20"/>Younger ones saw light, and they lived upon the earth, but they did not know the way of knowledge<verse eid="BAR 3:20"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:21"/>nor understood her paths, nor did they take hold of her. Their sons ended up far away from their way.<verse eid="BAR 3:21"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:22"/>She has neither been heard of in Chanaan nor been seen in Thaiman--<verse eid="BAR 3:22"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:23"/>nor the sons of Hagar who seek out intelligence upon the earth, the merchants of Merran and Thaiman and the storytellers and the seekers for intelligence. But they did not know the way of wisdom nor remembered her paths.<verse eid="BAR 3:23"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:24"/>Ah Israel, how great is the house of God, and how extensive is the place of its<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'his'</char></note> estate!<verse eid="BAR 3:24"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:25"/>It is great and has no end; it is high and immeasurable.<verse eid="BAR 3:25"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:26"/>The giants were born there, those renowned, those of old, seeing that they were large, experts in war.<verse eid="BAR 3:26"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:27"/>Not these did God choose, nor did he give them the way of knowledge,<verse eid="BAR 3:27"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:28"/>and they perished because they had no insight; they perished through their recklessness.<verse eid="BAR 3:28"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:29"/>Who has gone up into the sky and taken her and brought her down from the clouds?<verse eid="BAR 3:29"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:30"/>Who has crossed over the sea and found her and will bring her in exchange for choice gold?<verse eid="BAR 3:30"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:31"/>There is no one who is familiar with her way, nor one who thinks much about her path.<verse eid="BAR 3:31"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:32"/>But he who knows all things is familiar with her; he discovered her by his intelligence; he who equipped the earth for all time, he filled it with quadrupeds.<verse eid="BAR 3:32"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:33"/>He who sends the light, and it goes-- he summoned it and it obeyed him, with a shudder,<verse eid="BAR 3:33"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:34"/>but the stars shone in their watches and were glad;<verse eid="BAR 3:34"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:35"/>he called them, and they said, "We are present!" They shone with gladness for him who made them.<verse eid="BAR 3:35"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:36"/>This is our God; no other will be reckoned with him.<verse eid="BAR 3:36"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:37"/>He discovered the whole way of knowledge and gave her to his servant Iakob and to Israel who was loved by him.<verse eid="BAR 3:37"/>

<verse sid="BAR 3:38"/>After this she appeared on earth and associated among humans.<verse eid="BAR 3:38"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="BAR 4">
<verse sid="BAR 4:1"/>She<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'way of knowledge'</char></note> is the book of the decrees of God and the law that remains forever. All who seize her are for life, but those who forsake her will die.<verse eid="BAR 4:1"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:2"/>Turn, O Iakob, and take hold of her; pass through toward the shining in the presence of her light.<verse eid="BAR 4:2"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:3"/>Do not give your glory to another and your benefits to a foreign nation.<verse eid="BAR 4:3"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:4"/>Happy are we, O Israel, because what is pleasing to God is known to us.<verse eid="BAR 4:4"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:5"/>Take courage, my people, reminder of Israel!<verse eid="BAR 4:5"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:6"/>You were sold to the nations not for destruction, but because you angered God you were delivered to your adversaries.<verse eid="BAR 4:6"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:7"/>For you provoked the one who made you by sacrificing to demons and not to God.<verse eid="BAR 4:7"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:8"/>And you forgot the one who nursed you, God everlasting, and you even grieved Ierousalem who reared you.<verse eid="BAR 4:8"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:9"/>For she saw the anger that came upon you from God, and she said: Listen, you neighbors of Sion, God has brought great mourning upon me;<verse eid="BAR 4:9"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:10"/>for they saw the captivity of my sons and daughters, which the Everlasting brought upon them.<verse eid="BAR 4:10"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:11"/>For I reared them with gladness, but I sent them away with weeping and grief.<verse eid="BAR 4:11"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:12"/>Let no one rejoice against me, the widow and one forsaken by many; I was left desolate because of the sins of my children, because they turned away from God's law.<verse eid="BAR 4:12"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:13"/>And they did not recognize his statutes; neither did they walk in the ways of God's commandments nor tread on the paths of instruction by his righteousness.<verse eid="BAR 4:13"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:14"/>Let the neighbors of Sion come. And remember the captivity of my sons and daughters, which the Everlasting brought upon them.<verse eid="BAR 4:14"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:15"/>For he brought against them a far off nation, a shameless nation and one speaking an alien tongue, who did not respect an old man nor showed mercy to a child.<verse eid="BAR 4:15"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:16"/>And they led away the beloved sons of the widow and isolated the lonely woman from her daughters.<verse eid="BAR 4:16"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:17"/>But I<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Ierousalem'</char></note>, how am I able to help you?<verse eid="BAR 4:17"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:18"/>For he who brought these bad things upon you will deliver you from the hand of your enemies.<verse eid="BAR 4:18"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:19"/>Walk, children, walk, for I have been left desolate.<verse eid="BAR 4:19"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:20"/>I have taken off the robe of peace and put on sackcloth for my petition; I will cry out to the Everlasting in all my days.<verse eid="BAR 4:20"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:21"/>Take courage, O children; call out to God, and he will deliver you from domination, from the hand of enemies.<verse eid="BAR 4:21"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:22"/>For I have hoped in the Everlasting for your salvation, and joy has come to me from the Holy One because of the mercy that will soon come to you from your everlasting savior.<verse eid="BAR 4:22"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:23"/>For I dispatched out with mourning and weeping, but God will give you back to me with delight and merriment forever.<verse eid="BAR 4:23"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:24"/>For as the neighbors of Sion have seen your captivity now, so they will quickly see your salvation from God, which will come to you with the great glory and splendor of the Everlasting.<verse eid="BAR 4:24"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:25"/>O children, bear patiently the wrath that has come upon you from God. The enemy has pursued you, but you will quickly see their destruction and will tread upon their necks.<verse eid="BAR 4:25"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:26"/>My pampered children have traveled rough roads; they were taken away like a flock carried off by enemies.<verse eid="BAR 4:26"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:27"/>Take courage, O children, and call out to God, for there will be mention of you by the one who brought this.<verse eid="BAR 4:27"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:28"/>For just as your intention became to go astray from God, multiply by ten when you return to seek him.<verse eid="BAR 4:28"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:29"/>For the one who brought these bad things upon you will bring you everlasting merriment with your salvation.<verse eid="BAR 4:29"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:30"/>Take courage, O Ierousalem; he who named you will comfort you.<verse eid="BAR 4:30"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:31"/>Wretched will be those who have harmed you and who have rejoiced at your fall.<verse eid="BAR 4:31"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:32"/>Wretched will be the cities that your children served as slaves; wretched will be the one<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:32</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Babylon'</char></note> that received your sons.<verse eid="BAR 4:32"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:33"/>For just as she rejoiced at your fall and was glad for your ruin, so she will be grieved at her own desolation.<verse eid="BAR 4:33"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:34"/>And I will take away her rejoicing of her great population, and her insolence will be turned to mourning.<verse eid="BAR 4:34"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:35"/>For fire will come upon her from the Everlasting for long days, and for a rather long time she will be inhabited by demons.<verse eid="BAR 4:35"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:36"/>Look around toward the east, O Ierousalem, and see the merriment that is coming to you from God.<verse eid="BAR 4:36"/>

<verse sid="BAR 4:37"/>Behold, your sons are coming, whom you sent away; they are coming, gathered from east until west, at the word of the Holy One, rejoicing in the glory of God.<verse eid="BAR 4:37"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="BAR 5">
<verse sid="BAR 5:1"/>Take off your robe of mourning and affliction, O Ierousalem, and put on the dignity of the glory from God forever.<verse eid="BAR 5:1"/>

<verse sid="BAR 5:2"/>Put on the double-cloak<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'double-cloak':  a style of garment</char></note> of the righteousness that is from God; put on your head the headband of the glory of the Everlasting.<verse eid="BAR 5:2"/>

<verse sid="BAR 5:3"/>For God will show your splendor in the whole earth beneath heaven.<verse eid="BAR 5:3"/>

<verse sid="BAR 5:4"/>For your name will be called by God forever, "Peace of righteousness and glory of piety."<verse eid="BAR 5:4"/>

<verse sid="BAR 5:5"/>Arise, O Ierousalem, and stand upon the height, and look around toward the east, and see your children gathered from the setting of the sun until its rising at the word of the Holy One, rejoicing at God's remembering.<verse eid="BAR 5:5"/>

<verse sid="BAR 5:6"/>For they went out from you on foot, led away by enemies, but God will bring them to you, taken up with glory, as on a royal throne.<verse eid="BAR 5:6"/>

<verse sid="BAR 5:7"/>For God has instructed that every high mountain and the everlasting mounds be made low and the valleys be filled to make level the ground so that Israel may walk safely by the glory of God.<verse eid="BAR 5:7"/>

<verse sid="BAR 5:8"/>And even the woods and every fragrant tree have shaded Israel at God's ordinance.<verse eid="BAR 5:8"/>

<verse sid="BAR 5:9"/>For God will lead Israel with merriment, by the light of his glory, together with the mercy and righteousness that is from him.<verse eid="BAR 5:9"/>
</_X_chapter></_X_book></_X_usx>