<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<_X_usx version="2.0">
<para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
<_X_book code="DAN">





<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="DAN 1">
<verse sid="DAN 1:1"/><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Translation based on Old Greek text with versification based on fuller Theodotion text</char></note>During the third year of King Ioakim of Judea, when Nabouchodonosor, king of Babylon, arrived at Ierousalem, he besieged it.<verse eid="DAN 1:1"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:2"/>And the Lord delivered it into his hands as well as Ioakim, king of Judea, and some part of the sacred vessels of the Lord. And taking them to Babylonia, he deposited them in his idol temple.<verse eid="DAN 1:2"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:3"/>And the king told Abiesdri, his own chief eunuch, to bring to him some of the sons of the nobles of Israel and of royal descent and of the aristocracy:<verse eid="DAN 1:3"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:4"/>young men without physical defect and good-looking and knowledgeable in all wisdom and educated and wise and strong to be in the king's house, and to teach them letters and Chaldean speech<verse eid="DAN 1:4"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:5"/>and that they be given a prescribed portion from the king each day, both from the royal table and of the wine, which the king drank, and to educate them for three years and to place some of them before the king.<verse eid="DAN 1:5"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:6"/>And there were of the race of the sons of Israel who were from Judea: Daniel, Hananias, Misael, Azarias.<verse eid="DAN 1:6"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:7"/>And the chief eunuch assigned them names: to Daniel, Baltasar, but to Hananias, Sedrach and to Misael, Misach and to Azarias, Abdenago.<verse eid="DAN 1:7"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:8"/>And Daniel was determined in his heart that he not [... .....]<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Munnich = 'be defiled'</char></note> with the king's dinner and the wine that he drank, and he petitioned the chief eunuch so that he not be contaminated.<verse eid="DAN 1:8"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:9"/>And the Lord gave Daniel honor and favor before the chief eunuch.<verse eid="DAN 1:9"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:10"/>And the chief eunuch said to Daniel, "I am distressed because of my lord the king who appointed your food and drink that he should not see your face more drawn<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'thinner'</char></note> and sickly than the young men from aliens with whom you are being reared; I will risk my own neck!"<verse eid="DAN 1:10"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:11"/>And Daniel said to Abiesdri, the chief eunuch, who was assigned to Daniel, Hananias, Misael, Azarias:<verse eid="DAN 1:11"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:12"/>"Do test your servants over a period of ten days, and let us be given some pulse from the earth to <note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Munnich = 'eat'</char></note>gulp down and water to drink.<verse eid="DAN 1:12"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:13"/>And if our appearance seems more pale than the other young men who are eating of the royal dinner, as you observe so deal with your servants."<verse eid="DAN 1:13"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:14"/>And he dealt with them in this manner and tested them for ten days.<verse eid="DAN 1:14"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:15"/>Now, after ten days their appearance and physical condition was shown to be better than that of the other young men who were eating the royal dinner.<verse eid="DAN 1:15"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:16"/>And Abiesdri continued to withhold their dinner and their wine and would give them some pulse instead.<verse eid="DAN 1:16"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:17"/>And the Lord gave the young men knowledge and clever insight in every literary art. And to Daniel he gave insight into every vision and dreams and in all wisdom.<verse eid="DAN 1:17"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:18"/>Then after these days, the king ordered them to be brought in, and they were led by the chief eunuch to Nabouchodonosor the king.<verse eid="DAN 1:18"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:19"/>And the king conversed with them, and no one was found among the wise like Daniel and Hananias and Misael and Azarias, and they were in the king's presence.<verse eid="DAN 1:19"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:20"/>And in every topic and understanding and education, which the king inquired of them, he took them to be ten times wiser, surpassing the savants and scholars that were in the whole kingdom. And the king glorified them and appointed them in affairs in his whole kingdom.<verse eid="DAN 1:20"/>

<verse sid="DAN 1:21"/>And Daniel lasted until the first year of the reign of Cyrus.<verse eid="DAN 1:21"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="DAN 2">
<verse sid="DAN 2:1"/>And in the twelfth year of Nabouchodonosor's reign, it happened that visions and dreams befell him, and he was disturbed in his sleep.<verse eid="DAN 2:1"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:2"/>And the king ordered that the enchanters and the magicians and sorcerers of the Chaldeans be brought in to tell the king his dreams. And when they arrived, they stood in front of the king.<verse eid="DAN 2:2"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:3"/>And the king said to them, "I have seen a dream, and my spirit was shaken. Therefore, I want to find out about the dream."<verse eid="DAN 2:3"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:4"/>And the Chaldeans spoke to the king in Syrian, "O lord, you shall live forever! Tell the dream to your servants, and we will explain it."<verse eid="DAN 2:4"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:5"/>Then the king said in reply to the Chaldeans, "Unless you tell me the dream with certainty and disclose its sense, you will be made an example, and your possessions will be expropriated into the royal treasury.<verse eid="DAN 2:5"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:6"/>But if you make plain to me the dream and tell its sense, you will receive all kinds of gifts, and you will be glorified by me. Therefore, disclose the dream, and interpret."<verse eid="DAN 2:6"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:7"/>Then they answered a second time, saying, "O king, state the vision, so your servants will interpret regarding these matters."<verse eid="DAN 2:7"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:8"/>And the king said to them, "It is certain you are trying to buy time; therefore, as I have commanded:<verse eid="DAN 2:8"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:9"/>unless you render to me the dream and disclose its meaning, you will meet up with death. For you have agreed to make lying words in my presence until the occasion changes. Now, therefore, if you state the vision, which I saw during the night, I shall know that you can also disclose its sense."<verse eid="DAN 2:9"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:10"/>And the Chaldeans answered in the presence of the king, "Nobody on earth can say to the king what he has seen as you are asking! And, no king or dynast has asked<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Munnich = requested</char></note> such a matter of any sage or magician or Chaldean.<verse eid="DAN 2:10"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:11"/>And the thing that you seek, O king, is difficult and important. And there is no one who can disclose these things except some angel, whose habitation is not with any flesh; therefore, it is not possible that it happen, as you imagine."<verse eid="DAN 2:11"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:12"/>Then the king, being anxious and very sad, ordered to bring forth all the savants of Babylonia.<verse eid="DAN 2:12"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:13"/>And it was decreed to execute all of them, but Daniel and all those who were with him were sought in order to be killed as well.<verse eid="DAN 2:13"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:14"/>Then Daniel spoke counsel and knowledge to Arioch, the king's chief cook, who was ordered to bring forward the savants of Babylonia.<verse eid="DAN 2:14"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:15"/>And he inquired of him, saying, "Why is it being decreed so harshly by the king?" Then Arioch made the ordinance clear to Daniel.<verse eid="DAN 2:15"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:16"/>Now Daniel immediately went in to the king and petitioned that time might be given to him, and he would disclose everything in the presence of the king.<verse eid="DAN 2:16"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:17"/>Then Daniel, departing to his own home, declared everything in detail to Hananias and Misael and Azarias, his companions.<verse eid="DAN 2:17"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:18"/>And he proclaimed a fast and supplication and that help be sought from the Lord Most High about this mystery so that Daniel and those who were with him might not be delivered to destruction together with the savants of Babylon.<verse eid="DAN 2:18"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:19"/>Then the mystery of the king was disclosed to Daniel. In the night in a vision the matter was clearly brought to light. Then Daniel blessed the Lord Most High and crying out he said,<verse eid="DAN 2:19"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:20"/>"Let the name of the great Lord be blessed forever, because wisdom and majesty are his.<verse eid="DAN 2:20"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:21"/>And he changes seasons and times, deposing kings and setting up, giving to the sages wisdom and understanding to those who have knowledge<verse eid="DAN 2:21"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:22"/>and revealing deep and obscure things and knowing what is in the darkness and in the light, and with him there is release.<verse eid="DAN 2:22"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:23"/>You, Lord of my ancestors, I acknowledge and praise, because you gave me wisdom and intelligence, and now you have shown as much as I petitioned in order to disclose regarding these things to the king."<verse eid="DAN 2:23"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:24"/>So when Daniel went in to Arioch, who had been appointed by the king to execute all the savants of Babylonia, he said to him, "Do not destroy the savants of Babylon, but bring me in to the king, and I will disclose everything in detail to the king."<verse eid="DAN 2:24"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:25"/>Then Arioch quickly brought Daniel in to the king and said to him: "I have found a wise person among the captives of the sons of Judea who will disclose everything in detail to the king."<verse eid="DAN 2:25"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:26"/>So having answered, the king said to Daniel, but called Baltasar in Chaldean, "Are you able to disclose to me the vision that I have seen and its sense?"<verse eid="DAN 2:26"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:27"/>So Daniel spoke aloud in the presence of the king and said, "That which the king has seen: the explanation is not of the sages and enchanters and sorcerers and Gazarenes,<verse eid="DAN 2:27"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:28"/>but there is a Lord in heaven illumining mysteries who has disclosed to King Nabouchodonosor what must happen at the end of days. O King, you shall live forever! The dream and the vision of your head upon your bed is this:<verse eid="DAN 2:28"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:29"/>You, O king, after you reclined upon your couch, saw everything that must happen at the end of the days, and he that reveals mysteries has disclosed to you what is about to happen.<verse eid="DAN 2:29"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:30"/>But as for me, this mystery was not brought to light because of wisdom that I have beyond all persons, but it was shown to me what you pondered in your heart by knowledge in order that it might be disclosed to the king.<verse eid="DAN 2:30"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:31"/>"And you saw, O king. And lo! There was one image. And that image was exceedingly great. And its appearance, being extraordinary, stood in front of you, and the appearance of the image was frightening.<verse eid="DAN 2:31"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:32"/>And the head was of good gold, the chest and the arms silver, the belly and the thighs bronze,<verse eid="DAN 2:32"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:33"/>and the legs iron, the feet partly of iron and partly of earthenware.<verse eid="DAN 2:33"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:34"/>And you saw until when a stone was cut from a mountain, without hands, and it struck the image on the iron and earthenware feet and crushed them.<verse eid="DAN 2:34"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:35"/>Then the iron as well as the earthenware and the bronze and the silver and the gold became powdery together and became more powdery, as it were, than the chaff on a threshing floor, and the wind threw them so that nothing remained of them. And the stone that struck the image became a great mountain, and it struck the whole earth.<verse eid="DAN 2:35"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:36"/>"This was the vision. Now we will also tell the meaning in the presence of the king.<verse eid="DAN 2:36"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:37"/>You, O king, are king of kings, and to you the Lord of heaven has given the kingdom and power and honor and glory.<verse eid="DAN 2:37"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:38"/>In the whole world from humans and wild animals and birds of the air and fish of the sea, he has delivered them into your hands to rule over all-- you are the gold head.<verse eid="DAN 2:38"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:39"/>And after you will rise a kingdom smaller than yours and another kingdom of bronze, which will rule over the whole earth,<verse eid="DAN 2:39"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:40"/>and another kingdom, strong as iron, which saws everything and cuts down every tree, and the whole earth will be shaken.<verse eid="DAN 2:40"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:41"/>And as you saw its feet partly of iron and partly of potter's ware: there will be another kingdom in two parts, and some of the iron base will be in it; just as you saw the iron commixed with the clay ware,<verse eid="DAN 2:41"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:42"/>part of the kingdom will be strong, and part of it will be broken.<verse eid="DAN 2:42"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:43"/>And as you saw the iron admixed with the clay ware, they will be commixed in races of humans, but they will not be in agreement or well disposed to one another, even as iron is not able to be blended with earthenware.<verse eid="DAN 2:43"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:44"/>And in the times of these kings the God of heaven will set up another kingdom that will be forever and will not be corrupted. And this kingdom will never permit another nation, but it will crush and abolish those kingdoms, and it will stand forever,<verse eid="DAN 2:44"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:45"/>just as you have seen a stone cut out of a mountain, without hands, and it ground the earthenware and the iron and bronze and silver and gold. The great God has shown the king what will be at the end of the days, and the vision is precise, and the meaning of it trustworthy."<verse eid="DAN 2:45"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:46"/>Then Nabouchodonosor the king, falling facedown on the ground, did obeisance to Daniel and ordered that sacrifices and libations be carried out to him.<verse eid="DAN 2:46"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:47"/>And the king cried out to Daniel and said, "It is certain; your God is God of gods and Lord of lords and Lord of kings who alone brings to light hidden mysteries, because you have been able to disclose this mystery!"<verse eid="DAN 2:47"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:48"/>Then King Nabouchodonosor, after he magnified Daniel and bestowed many great presents, appointed him over the affairs of Babylonia and designated him ruler and leader of all the savants of Babylon.<verse eid="DAN 2:48"/>

<verse sid="DAN 2:49"/>And Daniel petitioned the king that Sedrach, Misach, Abdenago might be appointed over the affairs of the kingdom of Babylon. And Daniel was in the royal court.<verse eid="DAN 2:49"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="DAN 3">
<verse sid="DAN 3:1"/>In the eighteenth year of Nabouchodonosor, when he was managing cities and regions and all who lived from India to Ethiopia, he also made a golden image. Its height was sixty cubits, and its width was twelve cubits. And he set it up on the plain of the enclosure of the region of Babylonia.<verse eid="DAN 3:1"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:2"/>And Nabouchodonosor, king of kings and ruling the whole inhabited world, sent to gather all the nations and tribes and languages, satraps and generals, local rulers and magistrates, administrators and the authorities by region and all those in the inhabited world to come to the dedication of the golden image, which King Nabouchodonosor had established<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Munnich = 'set up'</char></note>,<verse eid="DAN 3:2"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:3"/>and the aforementioned stood in front of the image.<verse eid="DAN 3:3"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:4"/>And the herald heralded to the crowds, "I tell you, O nations, peoples and languages,<verse eid="DAN 3:4"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:5"/>whenever you hear the sound of the horn, pipe, lyre, trigon, harp and a symphony of all kinds of musical instruments, you should fall down and do obeisance to the gold image, which King Nabouchodonosor has set up.<verse eid="DAN 3:5"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:6"/>And anyone who does not fall down and do obeisance, they will throw him into the furnace of fire."<verse eid="DAN 3:6"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:7"/>And at that time when all the nations heard the horn and all the sounds of musical instruments, all the nations, tribes and languages, falling down they did obeisance to the gold image that Nabouchodonosor had set up.<verse eid="DAN 3:7"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:8"/>At that time, when Chaldean men came forward, they denounced the Judeans.<verse eid="DAN 3:8"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:9"/>And they answered and said, "O lord king, live forever!<verse eid="DAN 3:9"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:10"/>You, O king, have ordered and decided that every person who hears the horn and all the sounds of musical instruments should fall down and do obeisance to the gold image,<verse eid="DAN 3:10"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:11"/>and whoever does not do obeisance will be thrown into the furnace blazing with fire.<verse eid="DAN 3:11"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:12"/>But there are certain Judean men whom you have appointed over the region of Babylonia-- Sedrach, Misach, Abdenago-- these people do not fear your command, and they do not serve your idol, and they do not do obeisance to your gold image, which you have set up."<verse eid="DAN 3:12"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:13"/>Then Nabouchodonosor, being angered, in a rage ordered that Sedrach, Misach, Abdenago be brought in. Then the men were brought to the king.<verse eid="DAN 3:13"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:14"/>So when King Nabouchodonosor saw them, he said to them, "O Sedrach, Misach, Abdenago, for what reason do you not serve my gods and do not do obeisance to the gold image, which I have set up?<verse eid="DAN 3:14"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:15"/>And now, if you are now prepared, as soon as you hear the horn and all the sounds of musical instruments to fall down and do obeisance to the gold image that I set up .... But if not-- know that if you do not do obeisance, you will be thrown immediately into the furnace blazing with fire, and what god will deliver you out of my hands?"<verse eid="DAN 3:15"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:16"/>But Sedrach, Misach, Abdenago answered and said to King Nabouchodonosor, "O king, we have no need to answer you about this command,<verse eid="DAN 3:16"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:17"/>for there is God who is in heaven, our one Lord, whom we fear, who is able to deliver us from the furnace of fire, and out of your hands, O king, he will deliver us.<verse eid="DAN 3:17"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:18"/>And then it will be clear to you, that we will neither serve your idol nor will we do obeisance to your gold image, which you have set up."<verse eid="DAN 3:18"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:19"/>Then Nabouchodonosor was filled with anger, and the form of his face was distorted against them. And he ordered that the furnace be heated sevenfold more than it was necessary for it to be heated<verse eid="DAN 3:19"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:20"/>and ordered very strong men, who were in his command, after they had tied those with Azarias, to throw them into the furnace blazing with fire.<verse eid="DAN 3:20"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:21"/>Then these men were tied with their sandals on and their hats on their heads in their clothing, and they were thrown into the furnace of fire.<verse eid="DAN 3:21"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:22"/>Because the king's command was insistent, the furnace was also heated sevenfold more than before, and the men who had been selected, after they had tied and brought them to the furnace, threw them into it.<verse eid="DAN 3:22"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:23"/>Then the flame coming<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:23</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Munnich = 'burning'</char></note> out from the furnace burned and killed the men who tied those with Azarias, but they were preserved.<verse eid="DAN 3:23"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:24"/>So, therefore, Hananias and Azarias and Misael prayed and sang hymns to the Lord, when the king ordered them to be thrown into the furnace.<verse eid="DAN 3:24"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:25"/>Then Azarias stood and prayed in this way. And he opened his mouth, and he acknowledged the Lord together with his companions in the middle of the fire, while the furnace was being heated exceedingly by the Chaldeans, and he said:<verse eid="DAN 3:25"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:26"/>Blessed are you, O Lord, God of our ancestors, and praiseworthy and glorified is your name forever!<verse eid="DAN 3:26"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:27"/>For you are just in all you have done for us, and all your works are genuine and your ways right, and all your judgments are genuine.<verse eid="DAN 3:27"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:28"/>And you have executed true judgments in all you have brought upon us and upon Ierousalem, your holy city of our ancestors, because in truth and judgment you have done all these things because of our sins.<verse eid="DAN 3:28"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:29"/>For we have sinned in everything and broken your law in turning away from you, and in all matters we have sinned grievously.<verse eid="DAN 3:29"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:30"/>And we have not heeded the commandments of your law, and we have not kept them or done as you have commanded us so that it might go well for us.<verse eid="DAN 3:30"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:31"/>And now all that you have brought upon us you have done by a true judgment.<verse eid="DAN 3:31"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:32"/>And you have handed us over into the power of our enemies, lawless and hateful rebels, and to an unjust king, the most wicked in the world.<verse eid="DAN 3:32"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:33"/>And now we cannot open our mouth: it has become a shame and a reproach for your slaves and those who worship you.<verse eid="DAN 3:33"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:34"/>For your name's sake do not give us up completely, and do not annul your covenant.<verse eid="DAN 3:34"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:35"/>And do not withdraw your mercy from us, for the sake of Abraam beloved by you and your slave Isaak and Israel your holy one,<verse eid="DAN 3:35"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:36"/>as you spoke to them saying that their offspring would be multiplied like the stars of heaven in multitude and like the sand on the shore of the sea.<verse eid="DAN 3:36"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:37"/>For we, O Master, have become fewer than any other nation and are brought low this day in all the earth because of our sins.<verse eid="DAN 3:37"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:38"/>And in this time there is no ruler and prophet and leader, no whole burnt offering or sacrifice or oblation or incense, no place to make an offering before you and to find mercy.<verse eid="DAN 3:38"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:39"/>But rather with a broken life and a humbled spirit may we be accepted,<verse eid="DAN 3:39"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:40"/>as though it were with whole burnt offering of rams and bulls and with tens of thousands of fat lambs; thus let our sacrifice come before you today, because no shame will come to those who trust in you, and may it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:40</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'sacrifice'</char></note> come to maturity behind you.<verse eid="DAN 3:40"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:41"/>And now with our whole heart we follow, and we fear you and seek your face.<verse eid="DAN 3:41"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:42"/>Do not put us to shame, but deal with us in your fairness and in your abundant mercy.<verse eid="DAN 3:42"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:43"/>And deliver us in accordance with your marvelous works, and bring glory to your name, O Lord.<verse eid="DAN 3:43"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:44"/>And may all who display evil to your slaves also be put to shame, and may they be disgraced by all dominance and their strength be broken.<verse eid="DAN 3:44"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:45"/>Let them know that you alone are the Lord and glorious over the whole world.<verse eid="DAN 3:45"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:46"/>And when they cast the three in all at once into the furnace, the furnace was red hot, sevenfold in its heat. And when they threw them in, those who threw them in were over them, and those below them kept on stoking from underneath with naptha and pitch and tow and brushwood.<verse eid="DAN 3:46"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:47"/>And the flame poured out above the furnace forty-nine cubits<verse eid="DAN 3:47"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:48"/>and flared out and burned those of the Chaldeans who were caught near the furnace.<verse eid="DAN 3:48"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:49"/>But an angel of the Lord came down into the furnace to be with Azarias and his companions and shook the flame of the fire out of the furnace<verse eid="DAN 3:49"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:50"/>and made the inside of the furnace as if a moist breeze were whistling through. And the fire did not touch them at all and caused them no pain or distress.<verse eid="DAN 3:50"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:51"/>Now, the three resuming, as though from one mouth, were singing hymns and glorifying and blessing and exalting God in the furnace, saying:<verse eid="DAN 3:51"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:52"/>Blessed are you, O Lord, God of our ancestors, and to be praised and highly exalted forever. And blessed is your glorious holy name, and to be highly praised and highly exalted forever and ever.<verse eid="DAN 3:52"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 3:53"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:53</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 3:53"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:54"/>Blessed are you upon the throne of your kingdom, and to be greatly hymned and highly glorified forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:54"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:55"/>Blessed are you who view the depths sitting upon cheroubin, and to be praised and glorified forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:55"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:56"/>Blessed are you in the firmament, and to be hymned and glorified forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:56"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:57"/>Bless the Lord, all you works of the Lord; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:57"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:58"/>Bless the Lord, you angels of the Lord; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:58"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:59"/>Bless the Lord, you heavens; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:59"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:60"/>Bless the Lord, all you waters above the heavens; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:60"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:61"/>Bless the Lord, all you powers of the Lord; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:61"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:62"/>Bless the Lord, sun and moon; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:62"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:63"/>Bless the Lord, stars of heaven; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:63"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:64"/>Bless the Lord, all rain and dew; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:64"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:65"/>Bless the Lord, all you winds<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:65</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'spirits'</char></note>; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:65"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:66"/>Bless the Lord, fire and heat; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:66"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:67"/>Bless the Lord, chill and winter cold; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:67"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:68"/>Bless the Lord, dews and falling snow; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:68"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:69"/>Bless the Lord, ice and cold; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:69"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:70"/>Bless the Lord, snows and hoarfrosts; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:70"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:71"/>Bless the Lord, nights and days; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:71"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:72"/>Bless the Lord, darkness and light; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:72"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:73"/>Bless the Lord, lightnings and clouds; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:73"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:74"/>Let the earth bless the Lord; let it sing hymns and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:74"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:75"/>Bless the Lord, mountains and hills; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:75"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:76"/>Bless the Lord, all that grows in the ground; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:76"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:77"/>Bless the Lord, rain storms and springs; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:77"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:78"/>Bless the Lord, seas and rivers; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:78"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:79"/>Bless the Lord, you sea-monsters and all that move in the waters; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:79"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:80"/>Bless the Lord, all birds of the air; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:80"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:81"/>Bless the Lord, four-footed and wild animals of the land; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:81"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:82"/>Bless the Lord, all humans on earth; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:82"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:83"/>Bless the Lord, O Israel; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:83"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:84"/>Bless the Lord, you priests, slaves of the Lord; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:84"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 3:85"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:85</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 3:85"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:86"/>Bless the Lord, spirits and righteous souls; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:86"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:87"/>Bless the Lord, you who are holy and humble in heart; sing hymns and highly exalt him forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:87"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:88"/>Bless the Lord, Hananias, Azarias, Misael; sing hymns, and highly exalt him forever. For he has rescued us from Hades and saved us from the hand of death and delivered us from the midst of the burning flame and released us from the fire.<verse eid="DAN 3:88"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:89"/>Acknowledge the Lord, for he is kind, for his mercy is forever.<verse eid="DAN 3:89"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:90"/>All who worship the Lord, bless the God of gods; sing hymns, and acknowledge him, for his mercy is forever and ever and ever.<verse eid="DAN 3:90"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:91"/>(24) And it happened that when the king heard them singing hymns and when he stood, he saw them alive. Then Nabouchodonosor the king was astonished. And he rose quickly and said to his friends,<verse eid="DAN 3:91"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:92"/>(25) "Lo, I see four men unbound and walking in the fire, and no ruin has come to them, and the appearance of the fourth is the likeness of a divine angel."<verse eid="DAN 3:92"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:93"/>(26) And approaching the door of the still blazing furnace, the king called them by name, "Sedrach, Misach, Abdenago, servants of the Most High God, come out of the fire!" So then, the men came out from the middle of the fire.<verse eid="DAN 3:93"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:94"/>(27) And the governors, the local rulers, the heads of families and the king's Friends gathered together and looked at these men, that the fire had not touched their body, and their hair was not burned, and their trousers were not changed, nor was a smell of fire on them.<verse eid="DAN 3:94"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:95"/>(28) Then, in response Nabouchodonosor the king said, "Blessed be the Lord, the God of Sedrach, Misach, Abdenago, who has sent his angel and saved his servants who hope in him; for they disregarded the king's order and yielded up their body for burning in order that they might not serve or do obeisance to another god except to their God.<verse eid="DAN 3:95"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:96"/>(29) And now, I decide that any nation and all tribes and languages-- whoever blasphemes the Lord, God of Sedrach, Misach, Abdenago will be dismembered<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:96</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or Munnich = 'dissected'</char></note>, and his possessions confiscated, because there is no other god who is able to deliver in this way."<verse eid="DAN 3:96"/>

<verse sid="DAN 3:97"/>(30) So then, after the king gave authority to Sedrach, Misach, Abdenago over his whole region, he appointed them rulers.<verse eid="DAN 3:97"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="DAN 4">
<verse sid="DAN 4:1"/>(4) In the eighteenth year of his reign, Nabouchodonosor said, "I was living at peace in my home and prospering on my throne.<verse eid="DAN 4:1"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:2"/>(5) I saw a dream, and I was alarmed, and fear fell upon me<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">+ Munnich = 'on my bed'</char></note><verse eid="DAN 4:2"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 4:3"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 4:3"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 4:4"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 4:4"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 4:5"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 4:5"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 4:6"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 4:6"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:7"/>(10) I was sleeping, and lo, a tall tree was growing on the earth. Its appearance was huge, and there was no other like it.<verse eid="DAN 4:7"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:8"/>(11) And its appearance was great. Its crown came close to heaven, and its span to the clouds, filling the area under heaven. The sun and the moon dwelled in it and illuminated the whole earth.<verse eid="DAN 4:8"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:9"/>(12) Its branches were about thirty stadia long, and all the animals of the earth found shade under it, and the birds of the air hatched their brood in it. Its fruit was abundant and good, and it sustained all living creatures.<verse eid="DAN 4:9"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:10"/>(13) I continued looking in my sleep; lo, an angel was sent in power out of heaven.<verse eid="DAN 4:10"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:11"/>(14) And he called and said: 'Cut it down, and destroy it, for it has been decreed by the Most High to uproot and render it useless.'<verse eid="DAN 4:11"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:12"/>(15) And thus he said: 'Spare one of its roots in the ground so that he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'it'</char></note> may feed on grass like an ox with the animals of the earth in the mountains,<verse eid="DAN 4:12"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:13"/>(16) and his<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'it'</char></note> body may be changed from the dew of heaven, and he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'it'</char></note> may graze with them for seven years<verse eid="DAN 4:13"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:14"/>until he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'it'</char></note> acknowledges that the Lord of heaven has authority over everything which is in heaven and which is on the earth and does with them whatever he wishes.' (14a) It was cut down before me in one day, and its destruction was in one hour of the day. And its branches were given to every wind, and it was dragged and thrown away. He<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'it'</char></note> ate grass with the animals of the earth. And he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'it'</char></note> was delivered into prison and was bound by them with shackles and bronze manacles. I marveled exceedingly at all these things, and my sleep escaped from my eyes.<verse eid="DAN 4:14"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:15"/>(18) And when I arose in the morning from my bed, I called Daniel, the ruler of the savants and the leader of those who decide dreams, and I described the dream for him, and he showed me its entire interpretation.<verse eid="DAN 4:15"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:16"/>(19) But since Daniel was greatly amazed and since foreboding pressed him and since he was afraid, as trembling seized him and his appearance changed, having shaken his head, having marveled for one hour, he answered me in a quiet voice: 'O king, may this dream be for those who hate you, and its interpretation come upon your enemies!<verse eid="DAN 4:16"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:17"/>(20) The tree that was planted in the earth, whose appearance was great-- it is you, O king,<verse eid="DAN 4:17"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:18"/>(21) and all the birds of the air which nest in it. The strength of the earth and the nations and all the languages unto the ends of the earth and all countries are slaves to you.<verse eid="DAN 4:18"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:19"/>(22) Furthermore, the fact that that tree was exalted and neared heaven and that its span touched the clouds is: You, O king, have been exalted above all humans who are upon the face of the whole earth. Your heart was exalted with pride and power vis-à-vis the holy one and his angels. Your works were seen, how you ravaged the house of the living God pertaining to the sins of the sanctified people.<verse eid="DAN 4:19"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:20"/>(23) And the vision, which you saw, that an angel was sent in power by the Lord and that he said to destroy and cut down the tree: the verdict of the great God will come upon you,<verse eid="DAN 4:20"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:21"/>(24) and the Most High and his angels are pursuing you.<verse eid="DAN 4:21"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:22"/>(25) They will take you away to prison and send you away into a desert place.<verse eid="DAN 4:22"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:23"/>(26) And the root of the tree, which was spared, since it was not uprooted: the place of your throne will be kept for you for a season and an hour. Lo, they are being prepared against you, and they will whip you, and they will bring the judgments against you. The Lord lives in heaven, and his authority is over the whole earth.<verse eid="DAN 4:23"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:24"/>(27) Entreat him concerning sins, and atone for all your iniquities with alms<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'acts of mercy'</char></note> so that equity might be given to you and you might be long-lived on the throne of your kingdom and not be destroyed. Gladly receive these words, for my word is accurate and your time is complete.'"<verse eid="DAN 4:24"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:25"/>(28) And at the completion of the words, Nabouchodonosor, as he heard the verdict of the vision, kept the words in his heart.<verse eid="DAN 4:25"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:26"/>(29) And after twelve months the king was walking on the walls of the city in all his glory and going through its towers,<verse eid="DAN 4:26"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:27"/>(30) and answering he said, "This is the great Babylon, which I have built by the might of my power, and it will be called my royal house."<verse eid="DAN 4:27"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:28"/>(31) And at the completion of his word, he heard a voice from heaven: "O King Nabouchodonosor, to you it is said: The kingdom of Babylon has been taken away from you and is being given to another, a contemned person in your house. Lo, I establish him over your kingdom, and he will receive your authority and your glory and your luxury so that you may recognize that the God of heaven has authority in the kingdom of humans and he will give it to whomever he desires. Now, by sunrise, another king will rejoice in your house and will take your glory and your power and your authority.<verse eid="DAN 4:28"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:29"/>(32) And the angels will pursue you for seven years, and you will never be seen, nor will you ever speak with any person. They will feed you grass like an ox, and your pasture will be from the tender grass of the earth. Lo, instead of your glory they will tie you, and another will have your luxurious house and the kingdom.<verse eid="DAN 4:29"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:30"/>(33) Now, by morning everything will be completed concerning you. O King Nabouchodonosor of Babylon, and none of all these things will fail." <para style="p"/><verse eid="DAN 4:30"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:30a"/>(30a) "I, Nabouchodonosor, king of Babylon, was bound seven years. They fed me grass like an ox, and I would eat the tender grass of the earth. And after seven years I gave my soul to supplication, and I petitioned before the Lord, the God of heaven, concerning my sins, and I entreated the great God of gods concerning my ignorance.<verse eid="DAN 4:30a"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:30b"/>(30b) And my hair became like wings of an eagle, my nails like those of a lion. My flesh and my heart were changed. I would walk about naked with the animals of the field. I saw a dream and forebodings gripped me, and after a while a great sleep overtook me, and drowsiness fell upon me.<verse eid="DAN 4:30b"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:30c"/>(30c) And at the completion of seven years my time of redemption came, and my sins and my ignorances were fulfilled before the God of heaven, and I entreated the great God of gods concerning my ignorances, and lo, one angel called me from heaven: 'Nabouchodonosor, be subject to the holy God of heaven, and give glory to the Most High. The dominion of your nation is being given back to you.'<verse eid="DAN 4:30c"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 4:31"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:31</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 4:31"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 4:32"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:32</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 4:32"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:33"/>(36) "On that day my kingdom was restored to me, and my glory was given back to me.<verse eid="DAN 4:33"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:34"/>(37) I acknowledge the Most High, and I praise the one who created the heaven and the earth and the seas and the rivers and everything that is in them. I acknowledge, and I praise, because he is God of gods and Lord of lords and Lord of kings, because he does signs and wonders and changes seasons and times, removing the reign of kings and setting others in their place.<verse eid="DAN 4:34"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:34a"/>(34a) From now on I will serve him, and trembling has gripped me from fear of him, and I praise all his holy ones, for the gods of the nations do not have power in them to give away the kingdom of a king to another king and to kill and to make alive and to do signs and great and terrible marvels and to change very great matters as the God of heaven has done with me. And he changed great things about me. I will offer sacrifices to the Most High as an odor of fragrance to the Lord for my life every day of my reign, and I will do what is pleasing before him, I and my people, [my nation] and my lands that are in my authority. And as many as have spoken against the God of heaven and as many as should be caught speaking anything, I will condemn these to death."<verse eid="DAN 4:34a"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:34b"/>(34b) Then King Nabouchodonosor wrote a circular letter to all the nations in each place and to countries and languages who live in all the countries, generations and generations. "Praise the Lord, God of heaven. Bring sacrifice and offering to him gloriously. I, the king of kings, acknowledge him gloriously, because he has done thus with me. In the same day he established me on my throne, and I took possession of my authority and my kingdom among my people, and my greatness was restored to me.<verse eid="DAN 4:34b"/>

<verse sid="DAN 4:34c"/>(34c) King Nabouchodonosor to all nations and all countries and all the inhabitants in them: May peace be multiplied to you at every time. And now, I will show to you the deeds that the great God has done with me. Moreover, it seemed good to me to show you and your savants that God is one, and his marvels are great; his rule is forever; his authority is from generation to generation." And he sent letters about everything that happened to him during his reign to all the nations which were under his reign.<verse eid="DAN 4:34c"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="DAN 5">
<verse sid="DAN 5:1"/>[King Baltasar gave a great reception on the day of the dedication of his palace, and he invited two thousand men of his nobles. On that day, Baltasar, in high spirits from the wine and boasting in his drink, praised all the molten and carved gods of the nations, and he did not give praise to the Most High God. On that same night, fingers, as though of a human, came forth and inscribed on the wall of his house, on the plaster, opposite the light: MANE PHARES THEKEL. Their translation is: MANE, it has been numbered; PHARES, it has been taken away; THEKEL, it has been established.] (1) King Baltasar made a great feast for his associates.<verse eid="DAN 5:1"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:2"/>And he was drinking wine, and his heart was exalted, and he said to bring the gold and silver vessels of the house of God that his father Nabouchodonosor had brought from Ierousalem and to pour wine in them for his associates.<verse eid="DAN 5:2"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:3"/>And they were brought, and they were drinking with them.<verse eid="DAN 5:3"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:4"/>And they blessed their handmade idols, and they did not bless the eternal God who had authority over their spirit.<verse eid="DAN 5:4"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:5"/>In that very same hour fingers, as though of a human hand, came forth and wrote on the wall of his house, on the plaster opposite the light, facing King Baltasar. And he saw a hand writing,<verse eid="DAN 5:5"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:6"/>and his appearance was changed, and foreboding pressed him. Therefore, the king hastened and stood up and kept looking at that writing, and his companions spoke loudly around him.<verse eid="DAN 5:6"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:7"/>And the king called in a loud voice that the enchanters and sorcerers and Chaldeans and Gazarenes be summoned to tell the meaning of the writing. And they came to the spectacle to see the writing, and they were unable to interpret the meaning of the writing for the king. Then the king published a declaration, saying: Anyone who can explain the meaning of the writing-- he will dress him in purple, and the gold torque he will put on him, and authority over a third of the kingdom will be given to him.<verse eid="DAN 5:7"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:8"/>And the enchanters and sorcerers and Gazarenes came in, and none was able to tell the meaning of the writing.<verse eid="DAN 5:8"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:9"/>Then the king summoned the queen about the sign, and he explained to her how large it was and that no person was able to tell the king the meaning of the writing.<verse eid="DAN 5:9"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:10"/>Then the queen reminded him concerning Daniel who was among the captives of Judea.<verse eid="DAN 5:10"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:11"/>And she said to the king, "That person was prudent and wise and surpassed all the sages of Babylon,<verse eid="DAN 5:11"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:12"/>and a holy spirit is in him. And in the days of your father the king he explained difficult meanings to Nabouchodonosor your father."<verse eid="DAN 5:12"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:13"/>Then Daniel was brought in to the king. And answering the king said to him,<verse eid="DAN 5:13"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 5:14"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 5:14"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 5:15"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 5:15"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:16"/>"O Daniel, are you able to explain to me the interpretation of the writing? And I shall dress you in purple, and a gold torque I shall put on you, and you will have authority over a third part of my kingdom."<verse eid="DAN 5:16"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:17"/>Then Daniel stood in front of the writing and read, and thus he answered the king, "This is the writing: it has been numbered; it has been reckoned; it has been taken away. And the writing hand ceased, and this is their interpretation.<verse eid="DAN 5:17"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 5:18"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 5:18"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 5:19"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 5:19"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 5:20"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 5:20"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 5:21"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 5:21"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 5:22"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 5:22"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:23"/>O King, you made a feast for your Friends, and you were drinking wine, and the vessels of the house of the living God were brought to you, and you were drinking with them, you and your nobles. And you praised all the idols made by human hands, and you did not bless the living God. And your spirit is in his hand, and he himself gave to you your reign, and you did not bless him nor praise him.<verse eid="DAN 5:23"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 5:24"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 5:24"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 5:25"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 5:25"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:26"/>This is the meaning of the writing: the time of your kingdom has been reckoned; your kingdom is coming to an end.<verse eid="DAN 5:26"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:27"/>It has been cut short, and it has finished.<verse eid="DAN 5:27"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:28"/>Your kingdom is being given to the Medes and to the Persians."<verse eid="DAN 5:28"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:29"/>Then Baltasar the king clothed Daniel in purple, and he put a gold torque on him, and he gave him authority over a third part of his kingdom.<verse eid="DAN 5:29"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:30"/>And the meaning came upon Baltasar the king, and the rule was taken away from the Chaldeans and was given to the Medes and to the Persians,<verse eid="DAN 5:30"/>

<verse sid="DAN 5:31"/>(6.1) and Xerxes, who was king of the Medes, received the kingdom.<verse eid="DAN 5:31"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="DAN 6">
<verse sid="DAN 6:1"/>And when Darius was full of days and esteemed in old age, he set one hundred twenty-seven satraps over his whole kingdom<verse eid="DAN 6:1"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:2"/>and over them three men their leaders, and Daniel was one of the three men,<verse eid="DAN 6:2"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:3"/>since he had authority over everyone in the kingdom. And Daniel was clothed in purple and was great and esteemed before King Darius, as he was knowledgeable and intelligent and a holy spirit was in him, and he prospered in the affairs of the king that he performed. [Then the king decided to set Daniel over all his kingdom, and the two men whom he had appointed with him and the one hundred twenty-seven satraps.]<verse eid="DAN 6:3"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:4"/>Now, when the king decided to appoint Daniel over all his kingdom, then the two young men, speaking to each other, agreed to a plan and resolve among themselves, since they found neither sin nor ignorance against Daniel for which they could accuse him to the king.<verse eid="DAN 6:4"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:5"/>And they said, "Come, let us establish an interdict by ourselves that no one will present a petition and never pray a prayer to any god for thirty days, except from King Darius, otherwise he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the one committing the offense'</char></note> will die," so that they might vanquish Daniel before the king and he might be cast into the lions' pit. For they knew that Daniel prayed to and entreated the Lord, his God, three times a day.<verse eid="DAN 6:5"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:6"/>Then those men went and said before the king,<verse eid="DAN 6:6"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:7"/>"We have established an interdict and stipulation that any person who prays a prayer or requests some request from any god, for thirty days, except from King Darius, will be cast into the lions' pit."<verse eid="DAN 6:7"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:8"/>And they requested the king so that he would establish and not change the interdict (as they knew Daniel prayed and entreated three times a day) so that he might be vanquished at the hands of the king and thrown into the lions' pit.<verse eid="DAN 6:8"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:9"/>And thus King Darius established and confirmed it.<verse eid="DAN 6:9"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:10"/>But although Daniel was aware of the interdict, which they established against him, he opened windows in his upper room opposite Ierousalem and would fall on his face thrice a day, just as he had been doing previously and kept entreating.<verse eid="DAN 6:10"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:11"/>And they watched Daniel and caught him praying three times a day each day.<verse eid="DAN 6:11"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:12"/>Then these men met with the king and said, "O King Darius, did you not make an interdict that no person will pray a prayer nor request a request from any god for thirty days, except from you, O king, otherwise the person will be cast into the lions' pit?" Then, the king answered and said to them, "The word is accurate, and the interdict will remain." (12a) And they said to him, "We adjure you; swear by the decrees of the Medes and Persians that you not change the matter nor that you respect the person nor that you reduce anything of the things said and you punish the person who did not abide by the this interdict." And he said, "Thus I will do as you say, and this has been established for me."<verse eid="DAN 6:12"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:13"/>And they said, "Lo, we have found Daniel, your Friend, praying and entreating the face of his God thrice a day.<verse eid="DAN 6:13"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:14"/>And grieving, the king said that Daniel be cast into the lions' pit according to the interdict, [which he established against him]. Then the king grieved exceedingly for Daniel, and he kept assisting to deliver him until sunset from the hands of the satraps.<verse eid="DAN 6:14"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:15"/>And he was unable to deliver him from them.<verse eid="DAN 6:15"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:16"/>Now Darius the king cried out and said to Daniel, "Your God, whom you continually serve thrice a day, he will deliver you from the power of lions! Have courage until morning."<verse eid="DAN 6:16"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:17"/>Then Daniel was thrown into the lions' pit, and a stone was brought and laid on the mouth of the pit, and the king sealed it with his signet and with the signets of his nobles so that Daniel might not be removed by them or the king pull him up from the pit.<verse eid="DAN 6:17"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:18"/>Then the king returned to his palace and passed the night without eating and was grieving for Daniel. But the God of Daniel, having taken forethought for him, shut the mouths of the lions, and they did not bother Daniel.<verse eid="DAN 6:18"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:19"/>And King Darius rose early in the morning and took the satraps with him. And he went and stood at the opening of the lions' pit.<verse eid="DAN 6:19"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:20"/>Then the king called Daniel in a loud voice with wailing, saying, "O Daniel, are you still alive, and has your God whom you continually serve saved you from the lions, and have they not injured you?"<verse eid="DAN 6:20"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:21"/>Then Daniel heeded the loud voice and said,<verse eid="DAN 6:21"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:22"/>"O king, I am still alive, and the Lord has saved me from the lions, because righteousness was found in me in his presence, and also in your presence, O king, neither ignorance nor sin was found in me. But you listened to people who deceive kings, and you cast me into the lions' pit for destruction."<verse eid="DAN 6:22"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:23"/>Then all the authorities gathered and saw Daniel, how the lions had not bothered him.<verse eid="DAN 6:23"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:24"/>Then these two men who testified falsely against Daniel-- they and their wives and their children were cast to the lions. And the lions killed them and shattered their bones, and Daniel was appointed over the whole kingdom of Darius.<verse eid="DAN 6:24"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:25"/>Then Darius wrote to all nations and countries and languages who inhabited his whole earth, saying: 26"Let all people who are in my kingdom do obeisance and worship Daniel's God, for he is an enduring and living God for generations and generations, forever.<verse eid="DAN 6:25"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 6:26"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:26</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 6:26"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:27"/>I, Darius, will do obeisance and be subject to him all my days, for the handmade idols are not able to save as God redeemed Daniel."<verse eid="DAN 6:27"/>

<verse sid="DAN 6:28"/>And King Darius was added to his fathers, and Cyrus the Persian received his kingdom.<verse eid="DAN 6:28"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="DAN 7">
<verse sid="DAN 7:1"/>During the first year of Baltasar's reign over the land of Babylonia, Daniel saw a vision from his head upon his bed. Then Daniel wrote down the vision that he saw. He wrote as a summary of the account:<verse eid="DAN 7:1"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:2"/>On my bed I was watching in my sleep during the night, and lo, the four winds of heaven fell upon a great sea,<verse eid="DAN 7:2"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:3"/>and four beasts were coming up out of the sea, each one differing from the other.<verse eid="DAN 7:3"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:4"/>The first was like a lioness, having as though wings of an eagle. I kept watching until its wings were plucked out, and it was lifted from the ground and was set upon human feet, and a human heart was given to it.<verse eid="DAN 7:4"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:5"/>And lo, another beast was after it, having the likeness of a bear. And it was placed on one side, and three ribs were in its mouth. And thus it said, "Rise, devour much flesh!"<verse eid="DAN 7:5"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:6"/>And after this, I was watching another beast like a leopard. And four wings of a bird were on it, and the beast had four heads, and language was given to it.<verse eid="DAN 7:6"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:7"/>But after this, I was watching in a vision by night a terrifying fourth beast, and the fear of it was surpassing in strength. It had great iron teeth, devouring and pounding; it was trampling with its feet round about, and it behaved differently from all the beasts before it, and it had ten horns.<verse eid="DAN 7:7"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:8"/>And many designs were in its horns, and lo, one horn grew up among them, a little one among its horns, and three of the earlier horns were removed by it. And lo, eyes like human eyes were in this horn, and a mouth speaking great things. And it made war against the holy ones.<verse eid="DAN 7:8"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:9"/>I kept watching until thrones were set, and an ancient of days sat, having a cloak like snow, and the tuft of hair on his head was like pure wool. The throne was like a flame of fire shooting out,<verse eid="DAN 7:9"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:10"/>and a stream of fire went out from before him. A thousand thousands were waiting on him, and ten thousand times ten thousand stood attending him. And books were opened, and a court sat in judgment.<verse eid="DAN 7:10"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:11"/>I was then watching the noise of the great words, which the horn kept speaking, and the beast was beaten to death, and its body perished and was given over to burning with fire.<verse eid="DAN 7:11"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:12"/>And he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'ancient of days'</char></note> removed those around him from their authority, and time of life was granted to them for a season and a time.<verse eid="DAN 7:12"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:13"/>I was watching in the night visions, and lo, as it were a son of man was coming upon the clouds of heaven. And he came as far as the ancient of days, and the attendants were present with him.<verse eid="DAN 7:13"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:14"/>And royal authority was given to him, and all the nations of the earth according to posterity, and all honor was serving him. And his authority is an everlasting authority, which shall never be removed-- and his kingship, which will never perish.<verse eid="DAN 7:14"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:15"/>And as for me, Daniel, since I was exhausted by these things, by the night vision,<verse eid="DAN 7:15"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:16"/>I approached one of those standing and was seeking the truth from him about all these things. So answering, he spoke to me and disclosed to me the meaning of the words:<verse eid="DAN 7:16"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:17"/>"These great beasts are four kingdoms, which shall perish from the earth.<verse eid="DAN 7:17"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:18"/>And holy ones of the Most High will receive the kingdom and possess the kingdom forever-- forever and ever."<verse eid="DAN 7:18"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:19"/>Then I wanted to learn accurately concerning the fourth beast, which was different from all others and extremely terrible. And lo, its teeth were iron, and its claws were bronze, consuming all round about and trampling with the feet.<verse eid="DAN 7:19"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:20"/>And concerning its ten horns that were upon its head, and the one, which was growing, and three fell out because of it-- and that horn had eyes and a mouth speaking great things, and its looks surpassed the others,<verse eid="DAN 7:20"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:21"/>And I was observing that horn preparing for war against the holy ones and routing them<verse eid="DAN 7:21"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:22"/>until the ancient of days came, and he gave the verdict for<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'in favor of'</char></note> the holy ones of the Most High, and the time was given, and the holy ones gained possession of the seat of empire.<verse eid="DAN 7:22"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:23"/>And it was said to me concerning the fourth beast: "There shall be a fourth kingdom upon the earth, which shall excel over the whole earth and disturb it and grind it down.<verse eid="DAN 7:23"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:24"/>And as for the ten horns of the kingdom, ten kings shall rise, and another king shall rise after these. And he shall excel more than the former ones in evil, and he shall humble three kings.<verse eid="DAN 7:24"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:25"/>And he shall speak words against the Most High and shall wear down the holy ones of the Most High and shall expect to change seasons and law, and everything shall be delivered into his hands for a time and times and until half a time.<verse eid="DAN 7:25"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:26"/>And the trial shall sit, and they shall destroy authority, and they shall resolve to defile and destroy completely.<verse eid="DAN 7:26"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:27"/>And he shall give the authority and the kingdom and the magnitude of all the kingdoms, which are under heaven, to the holy people of the Most High, to reign over an everlasting kingdom, and all authorities will be subjected to him and obey him until the conclusion of the word."<verse eid="DAN 7:27"/>

<verse sid="DAN 7:28"/>As for me, Daniel, I was seized with great dismay, and my condition spread within me, and I fixed the matter in my heart.<verse eid="DAN 7:28"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="DAN 8">
<verse sid="DAN 8:1"/>During the third year, when Baltasar was king, there was a vision, which I, Daniel, saw after I saw the first one.<verse eid="DAN 8:1"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:2"/>And I saw in the vision of my dream. When I was in Sousa the city, which is in the region of Elymais, while I was still by the gate of Olam,<verse eid="DAN 8:2"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:3"/>when I looked up, I saw one large ram standing in front of the gate, and it had stately horns. And the one was more stately, and the stately one came up.<verse eid="DAN 8:3"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:4"/>But after this I saw the ram charging [to the east and] to the north and to the west and to the south. And no beasts stood after<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'behind'</char></note> it, and no one could rescue from its hands. And it was doing as it wanted and became exalted.<verse eid="DAN 8:4"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:5"/>And I was pondering, and lo, a male goat of goats was coming from the west, over the face of the earth, and it did not touch the ground. And one horn of the male goat was between its eyes.<verse eid="DAN 8:5"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:6"/>And it came at the ram, which had the horns, which I had seen standing by the gate, and it ran against it in a furious rage.<verse eid="DAN 8:6"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:7"/>And I saw it approaching toward the ram. And it was inflamed against it, and it struck and crushed its two horns. And there was no longer power in the ram to stand against the male goat, and it rent it asunder on the ground and crushed it, and there was no one who could rescue the ram from the male goat.<verse eid="DAN 8:7"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:8"/>And the male goat of the goats prevailed exceedingly, and when it prevailed, its great horn was crushed, and another four horns came up behind it toward the four winds of heaven.<verse eid="DAN 8:8"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:9"/>And out of one of them sprang one strong horn, and it prevailed, and it struck against the south and against the east and against the north.<verse eid="DAN 8:9"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:10"/>And it was raised unto the stars of the sky. And it was thrown down upon the earth from the stars and was trodden upon by them<verse eid="DAN 8:10"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:11"/>until the commander in chief delivers the captives. And the mountains, which were from eternity, were overthrown on account of it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the male goat'</char></note> and their place and sacrifice were taken away. And he put it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the horn'</char></note> to the ground [upon the earth], and it prospered, and it emerged<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'it happened'</char></note>, and the sanctuary will be desolated.<verse eid="DAN 8:11"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:12"/>And sins were on the offering, and justice was thrown to the ground, and it acted, and it prospered.<verse eid="DAN 8:12"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:13"/>And I kept hearing another holy one speaking, and the other one said to the Phelmouni who was speaking, "How long will this vision continue: even the sacrifice, which has been taken away, and the sin of desolation that has been given and the sanctuaries<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'holy things'</char></note> will be desolated unto trampling?"<verse eid="DAN 8:13"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:14"/>And he said to him, "Two thousand three hundred days, evenings and mornings, and the sanctuary will be purified."<verse eid="DAN 8:14"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:15"/>And it happened that when I, Daniel, was seeing, I was seeking to comprehend the vision. And lo, one having the appearance of a human stood in front of me,<verse eid="DAN 8:15"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:16"/>and I heard a human voice in the midst of the Olam<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Munnich = + [and it called, "Gabriel, help this one understand the vision."]</char></note>, and after the human cried out he said, "The vision is for<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'with a view to'</char></note> this ordinance."<verse eid="DAN 8:16"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:17"/>And he came and stood near where I stood, and when he came, I became bewildered and fell on my face. And he said to me, "Consider, O son of man, for this vision is yet for an appropriate time."<verse eid="DAN 8:17"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:18"/>And while he spoke with me, I slept facedown on the ground, and as he touched me, he roused me on the spot.<verse eid="DAN 8:18"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:19"/>And he said to me, "Lo, I am telling you what will take place at the end of the wrath against the sons of the people, for yet will remain the appropriate time of consummation.<verse eid="DAN 8:19"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:20"/>The ram that you saw, which had the horns, is the king of the Medes and Persians.<verse eid="DAN 8:20"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:21"/>And the male goat of the goats is the king of the Greeks, and the great horn that is between its eyes, this one is the first king.<verse eid="DAN 8:21"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:22"/>And as for the four horns that were crushed and came up after it: four kings will arise from his nation, not in accordance with their power.<verse eid="DAN 8:22"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:23"/>And at the last of their reign, when their sins are full, a king shameless of countenance will arise who understands obscure sayings.<verse eid="DAN 8:23"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:24"/>And his power will be established, and he will destroy terribly. And he will prosper and will accomplish, and he will destroy the powerful and the common people of the holy ones.<verse eid="DAN 8:24"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:25"/>And his thought will be against the holy ones. And the lie will prosper by his hands, and his heart will be exalted. And by deceit he will annihilate many, and he will rise by the destruction of men. And he will make a gathering by hand and will repay.<verse eid="DAN 8:25"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:26"/>The evening and morning vision was told truthfully. And now, the vision is closed, for it is yet for many days."<verse eid="DAN 8:26"/>

<verse sid="DAN 8:27"/>I, Daniel, having been weak many days and having risen, again was conducting the royal affairs. And I was continually upset by the vision, and there was no one who comprehended it.<verse eid="DAN 8:27"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="DAN 9">
<verse sid="DAN 9:1"/>During the first year of Darius son of Xerxes, of Median lineage, who were reigning over the kingdom of the Chaldeans,<verse eid="DAN 9:1"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:2"/>in the first year of his reign, I, Daniel, pondered in the books the number of the days when the ordinance of the Lord came to the prophet Ieremias to arise for the fulfillment of the reproach of Ierousalem-- seventy years.<verse eid="DAN 9:2"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:3"/>And I gave my face to the Lord God, to find prayer and compassion with fasting and with ashes and sackcloth.<verse eid="DAN 9:3"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:4"/>And I prayed to the Lord God and acknowledged him and said, "O Lord, lo, you are the great and powerful God and the fear-inspiring one in maintaining the covenant and mercy with those who love you and keep your ordinance<verse eid="DAN 9:4"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:5"/>we have sinned, acted wickedly, done wrong and rebelled and passed over your commandments and your ordinances.<verse eid="DAN 9:5"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:6"/>And we have not obeyed your servants the prophets, what they spoke in your name to our kings and sovereigns and our ancestors and to every nation on the earth.<verse eid="DAN 9:6"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:7"/>"Righteousness belongs to you, O Lord, and the shame of our face belongs to us, on this day, to the people of Iouda and the settlers in Ierousalem and to all the people of Israel, those who are near and those who are farther off, in all the regions into which you have dispersed them there, because of the trespasses that they have perpetrated before you.<verse eid="DAN 9:7"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:8"/>O Master, the shame of our face belongs to us and to our kings and sovereigns and to our ancestors, because we have sinned against you.<verse eid="DAN 9:8"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:9"/>To the Lord belongs justice and mercy, for we have rebelled against you<verse eid="DAN 9:9"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:10"/>and have not obeyed the voice of the Lord our God by following your law, which you gave before Moyses and us through your servants the prophets.<verse eid="DAN 9:10"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:11"/>"And all Israel has forsaken your law and turned away in order not to hear your voice. And the curse and the oath written in the law of Moyses, the servant of God, have come upon us, because we have sinned against him.<verse eid="DAN 9:11"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:12"/>And he has established his ordinances for us, what he spoke against us and against our judges who judged, by bringing great evils upon us such as have not happened under heaven as they have happened in Ierousalem.<verse eid="DAN 9:12"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:13"/>According to what is written in the covenant of Moyses, all the evils have come upon us. And we did not seek the face of the Lord our God, to turn away from our sins and to consider your righteousness, O Lord.<verse eid="DAN 9:13"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:14"/>And the Lord God kept watch over the evils and brought them upon us, for the Lord God is right in everything that he does, and we have not obeyed his voice.<verse eid="DAN 9:14"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:15"/>"And now, O Master<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">+ Munnich = 'Lord'</char></note>, our God, that brought your people out of Egypt by your uplifted arm and you made a name for yourself at this day-- we have sinned; we have failed to understand.<verse eid="DAN 9:15"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:16"/>O Master, according to your righteousness, let your anger turn away from us, and your wrath from your city Ierou-salem, the holy mountain. Because by our sins and by the ignorance of our ancestors, Ierousalem and your common people, O Lord, became a disgrace among all our neighbors.<verse eid="DAN 9:16"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:17"/>And now, O Master<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">+ Munnich = 'Lord'</char></note>, heed the prayer of your servant even for my supplications; for the sake of your slaves, O Master, let your face look upon your desolated holy mountain.<verse eid="DAN 9:17"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:18"/>Give your ear attention, O Lord, and heed me. Open your eyes, and see the desolation of us and of your city where your name has been called upon it, for we do not make requests in our prayers before you on the ground of our righteous acts, but because of your mercy, O Lord. O Master, heed your people; O Lord, do be gracious.<verse eid="DAN 9:18"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:19"/>O Lord, do heed, and act, and do not delay for your own sake, O Master, because your name is called upon your city, Sion, and upon your people, Israel!"<verse eid="DAN 9:19"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:20"/>And as I kept speaking, praying and acknowledging my sins and the sins of my people Israel and entreating with prayers before the Lord, my God, and on behalf of the holy mountain of our God<verse eid="DAN 9:20"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:21"/>and while I was still speaking in my prayer, and lo, the man whom I had seen at first in my sleep, Gabriel, being carried swiftly approached me at the time of the evening sacrifice.<verse eid="DAN 9:21"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:22"/>And he came and spoke with me and said, "Daniel, I have just come out to show you intelligence.<verse eid="DAN 9:22"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:23"/>At the beginning of your supplication an ordinance went out from the Lord, and I have come to explain to you, for you are shown mercy. And think about the ordinance:<verse eid="DAN 9:23"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:24"/>"Seventy weeks have been decided for your people and for the city, Sion: for sin to be consummated and to make iniquities scarce and to blot out iniquities and to comprehend the vision and for everlasting righteousness to be given and for the vision to be consummated and to gladden a holy of holies.<verse eid="DAN 9:24"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:25"/>And you shall understand and will rejoice and will discover ordinances to respond, and you will build Ierousalem as a city for the Lord.<verse eid="DAN 9:25"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:26"/>And after seven and seventy and sixty-two weeks, an anointing will be removed and will not be. And a king of nations will demolish the city and the sanctuary along with the anointed one, and his consummation will come with wrath even until the time of consummation. He will be attacked through war.<verse eid="DAN 9:26"/>

<verse sid="DAN 9:27"/>And the covenant will prevail for many, and it will return again and be rebuilt broad and long. And at the consummation of times [even after seven years and seventy times and sixty-two times] [until the time of the consummation of the war even desolation will be removed] [when the covenant prevails for many weeks]. And in half of the week the sacrifice and the libation will cease, and in the temple there will be an abomination of desolations until the consummation of a season, and a consummation will be given for the desolation."<verse eid="DAN 9:27"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="DAN 10">
<verse sid="DAN 10:1"/>In the first year of King Cyrus of the Persians a decree was shown to Daniel, whose name was called Baltasar. And [the vision and] the decree was true. And the forceful multitude will understand the decree, and I understood it by means of a vision.<verse eid="DAN 10:1"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:2"/>In those days I, Daniel, was in mourning.<verse eid="DAN 10:2"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:3"/>I had not eaten food of desire, and no meat or wine had entered my mouth. I had not anointed myself with oil until I completed three weeks of days.<verse eid="DAN 10:3"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:4"/>And it happened on the twenty-fourth day of the first month, and as I was on the bank of the great river, which is the Tigris,<verse eid="DAN 10:4"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:5"/>and I raised my eyes and saw, and lo, there was one person clothed in linen and girded with gold around the waist and a phas<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'pure gold'</char></note> from his middle.<verse eid="DAN 10:5"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:6"/>And his body was like tharsis<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = a precious stone (possibly 'chrysolite')</char></note>, and his face like an appearance of lightning, and his eyes like torches of fire, and his arms and feet like dazzling bronze, and the sound of his talking like the sound of a throng.<verse eid="DAN 10:6"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:7"/>And I, Daniel, saw this great vision, and the persons who were with me saw this vision, and a mighty fear fell on them, and they ran away in haste.<verse eid="DAN 10:7"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:8"/>And I remained alone, and I saw this great vision. And no strength remained in me, and I saw a spirit turned toward me in order to corrupt, and I did not prevail.<verse eid="DAN 10:8"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:9"/>And as I heard the sound of his talking, I fell on my face to the ground.<verse eid="DAN 10:9"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:10"/>And lo, he reached out a hand to me and roused me on my knees to the soles of my feet.<verse eid="DAN 10:10"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:11"/>And he said to me, "Daniel, you are a person shown mercy. Ponder the ordinances that I am going to speak to you. And stand in your place, for I have just been sent to you." And while he spoke this decree to me, I stood trembling.<verse eid="DAN 10:11"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:12"/>And he said to me, "Do not fear, Daniel, for from the first day that you gave your mind to gain knowledge and to be humble before your Lord, your word has been heeded, and I have come because of your word.<verse eid="DAN 10:12"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:13"/>And the general of the king of the Persians opposed me twenty and one day. Lo<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Munnich = + ['one of the chief rulers']</char></note>, one of the holy angels approached to help me, and I left him there with the general of the king of the Persians."<verse eid="DAN 10:13"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:14"/>And he said to me, "I have come to explain to you that it will come upon your people at the end of days, for a vision is yet for days."<verse eid="DAN 10:14"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:15"/>And as he spoke with me these decrees, I gave my face toward the ground and was silent.<verse eid="DAN 10:15"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:16"/>And lo, as it were a likeness of a human hand touched my lips, and I opened my mouth, and I spoke and said to the one who stood in front of me, "Sir, as the vision turned to me, to my flank, there was not even strength in me.<verse eid="DAN 10:16"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:17"/>And how will the servant be able to talk with his lord?" And as for me, I became weak, and no strength stayed in me, and no breath remained in me.<verse eid="DAN 10:17"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:18"/>And a specter of a human continued and touched me and gave me strength.<verse eid="DAN 10:18"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:19"/>And he said to me, "You are a person shown mercy. Do not fear; be well. Be courageous and strong!" And when he spoke with me, I was strengthened and said, "Let my lord speak, for he has strengthened me."<verse eid="DAN 10:19"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:20"/>And he said to me, "Do you understand why I have come to you? And now I will return to contend with the general of the king of the Persians. And I was leaving, and lo, the commander of the Greeks was entering.<verse eid="DAN 10:20"/>

<verse sid="DAN 10:21"/>And the more I will explain to you the chief things that are in the register of truth. And there was no one with me who helped concerning these things except Michael, the mighty angel."<verse eid="DAN 10:21"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="DAN 11">
<verse sid="DAN 11:1"/>In the first year of King Cyrus, he told me to be strong and be courageous.<verse eid="DAN 11:1"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:2"/>"And now I have come to explain the truth to you. Lo, three kings have risen in opposition in Persia. And the fourth will be rich with great riches beyond all, and when he is empowered by his riches, he will rise up against every king of the Greeks.<verse eid="DAN 11:2"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:3"/>And a mighty king will arise, and he will be lord over a great dominion and will act just as he wishes.<verse eid="DAN 11:3"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:4"/>And when he rises, his kingdom will be broken and distributed toward the four winds of heaven, not according to his strength nor according to his dominion which he dominated, for his kingdom will be removed and he will teach others these things.<verse eid="DAN 11:4"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:5"/>"And the king of Egypt will grow strong, and one of the sovereigns will overpower him and will dominate a large domain.<verse eid="DAN 11:5"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:6"/>And at the completion of the years he will lead them, and the king of Egypt will enter the northern kingdom to ratify an agreement. And he will never prevail, because his arm will not establish strength. And the arm of him and of those associating with him will grow numb, and he will continue for a season.<verse eid="DAN 11:6"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:7"/>"And a plant from his root will arise against himself. And the king of the north will come upon his idleness with his strength, and he will cause turmoil and will prevail.<verse eid="DAN 11:7"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:8"/>And he will overthrow their gods with their cast images and their crowds with their precious vessels. They will carry off the silver and gold to Egypt in captivity, and the king of the north will have a year.<verse eid="DAN 11:8"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:9"/>And he will enter into the kingdom of Egypt for days, and he will return to his own land.<verse eid="DAN 11:9"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:10"/>"And his son will both be irritated and will gather a gathering of a great crowd. And he will march against it, ravaging. He will pass through and will return and will be greatly provoked.<verse eid="DAN 11:10"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:11"/>And the king of Egypt will be inflamed and will do battle against the king of the north, and the gathering will be given into his hands.<verse eid="DAN 11:11"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:12"/>And he will carry off the gathering, and his heart will be exalted, and he will trouble many, and he will never be afraid.<verse eid="DAN 11:12"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:13"/>And the king of the north will return and will gather [from the city] a gathering, greater than the previous, according to the completion of the time of the year. And he will advance into it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'gathering'</char></note> with a large crowd and many goods.<verse eid="DAN 11:13"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:14"/>"And in those times thoughts will rise against the king of Egypt. And he will rebuild the fallen<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'ruins'</char></note> of your nation, and he will rise in order to restore prophecy, and they will take offense.<verse eid="DAN 11:14"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:15"/>And the king of the north will attack and will turn his spears and will take the fortified city. And the arms of the king of Egypt will not stand with his mighty ones, and he will not have the strength to oppose him.<verse eid="DAN 11:15"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:16"/>And he who comes upon him will act according to his will, and no one will oppose him. And he will stand in the land of desires,<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the land he wanted'</char></note> and everything will be completed by his hands.<verse eid="DAN 11:16"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:17"/>And he will give his face to attack all of his work with force, and he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the king of the north'</char></note> will make an agreement with him. And in order to corrupt him, he will give him a daughter of man, and she will not stand and will not be.<verse eid="DAN 11:17"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:18"/>And he will give his face to the sea and will take many. And he will return wrath for their insult, with an oath, according to his insult.<verse eid="DAN 11:18"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:19"/>He will turn his face in order to strengthen his country, and he will stumble and will fall and will not be found.<verse eid="DAN 11:19"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:20"/>"And a royal plant will arise from his root for rising up, a man striking the honor of the king. And in the last days he will be broken, and not in anger or in battle.<verse eid="DAN 11:20"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:21"/>And a contemptible person will arise in his place, and the royal honor will not be granted to him, and he will come without warning, and the king will prevail by his lot.<verse eid="DAN 11:21"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:22"/>And he will break the broken arms before his face.<verse eid="DAN 11:22"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:23"/>And he will perpetrate a lie with the covenant and the people drawn up with him and come against a strong nation with a very small nation.<verse eid="DAN 11:23"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:24"/>Without warning he will desolate a city and will do what none of his ancestors nor his ancestors' ancestors had ever done; he will give plunder and spoil and money to them. And he will take thought against the strong city, and his deliberations will be in vain.<verse eid="DAN 11:24"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:25"/>And his power and his heart will be roused against the king of Egypt with a great crowd, and the king of Egypt will be provoked into battle with an exceedingly strong crowd. And he will not succeed, because a plot will be devised against him.<verse eid="DAN 11:25"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:26"/>And his worries will consume him and will bring him back. And he will depart and will carry off, and many casualties will fall.<verse eid="DAN 11:26"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:27"/>And the two kings will dine alone [in the same place] and [will eat] at one table and will speak falsely. And they will not prosper, for there is yet a consummation at the appointed time.<verse eid="DAN 11:27"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:28"/>And he will return to his country with much money, and his heart will be against the covenant of the holy one. He will act and will return to his country<verse eid="DAN 11:28"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:29"/>at a set time. "And he will enter into Egypt, and as the first so the last will not be.<verse eid="DAN 11:29"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:30"/>And the Romans will come and will expel him and rebuke him. And he will turn back [and will be angered] against the covenant of the holy one. And he will take action and will turn back and will be minded against them, because they abandoned the covenant of the holy one.<verse eid="DAN 11:30"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:31"/>And arms from him will rise and will defile the sanctuary of fear. And they will remove the sacrifice and will give an abomination of desolation.<verse eid="DAN 11:31"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:32"/>And with sins against the covenant they will defile by means of a distributed portion, and the common people who know these things will stand firm and will take action.<verse eid="DAN 11:32"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:33"/>And thoughtful ones of the nation will understand for many, and they will stumble by sword and will become old by it and by captivity, and they will be soiled by pillaging for days.<verse eid="DAN 11:33"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:34"/>And when they are broken, they will gather a little strength. And many will be gathered to them [-- in the city also many-- ] as by an allotment.<verse eid="DAN 11:34"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:35"/>And some of the intelligent will be minded to purify themselves and be chosen and be purified until the time of consummation, for there is yet a time. "In that hour<verse eid="DAN 11:35"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:36"/>the king will act according to his will. And he will be enraged and will be exalted over every god and will speak strange things against the God of gods. And he will succeed until the wrath is completed, for completion pertaining to him is coming.<verse eid="DAN 11:36"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:37"/>And he will in no way have regard for the gods of his ancestors, and he will give no thought to the desire of a woman. He will be exalted in everything, [and strong nations will be subject to him].<verse eid="DAN 11:37"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:38"/>And he will honor a strong god in his place; even a god whom his ancestors did not know he will honor with gold and silver and valuable stone. And with desirable things<verse eid="DAN 11:38"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:39"/>[of cities] he will act and will come into a strong fortress. With a foreign god whom he acknowledges he will increase honor, and he will rule over it far and wide, and he will divide the area freely.<verse eid="DAN 11:39"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:40"/>"And according to the time of consummation the king of Egypt will lock horns with him. And the king of the north will be angry with him with chariots and with many horses and with many ships. And he will advance into the country of Egypt.<verse eid="DAN 11:40"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="DAN 11:41"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:41</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="DAN 11:41"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:42"/>And there will be no one that is delivered in it.<verse eid="DAN 11:42"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:43"/>And he will seize the place of gold and the place of silver and all the desire of Egypt, and Libyans and Ethiopians will be in his crowd.<verse eid="DAN 11:43"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:44"/>And a rumor from the east and north will alarm him, and he will go out with mighty fury both to annihilate by sword and to kill many.<verse eid="DAN 11:44"/>

<verse sid="DAN 11:45"/>And he will set up his tent then between the seas and the mountain of the will of the holy one. And the hour of his consummation will come, and there will be no one who helps him.<verse eid="DAN 11:45"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="DAN 12">
<verse sid="DAN 12:1"/>"And at that hour Michael, the great angel who stands over the sons of your people, will pass by. That is a day of affliction, which will be such as has not occurred since they were born until that day. And on that day the whole people will be exalted<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Munnich = 'saved'</char></note>, whoever is found inscribed in the book.<verse eid="DAN 12:1"/>

<verse sid="DAN 12:2"/>And many of those who sleep in the flat of the earth will arise, some to everlasting life but others to shame and others to dispersion [and contempt] everlasting.<verse eid="DAN 12:2"/>

<verse sid="DAN 12:3"/>And those who are intelligent will light up like the luminaries of heaven, and those who strengthen my words will be as the stars of heaven forever and ever.<verse eid="DAN 12:3"/>

<verse sid="DAN 12:4"/>And you, Daniel, hide the ordinances, and seal the book until the time of consummation<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'time of consummation':  Perhaps 'consummation of time'</char></note>, until the many rage violently and the earth is filled with injustice."<verse eid="DAN 12:4"/>

<verse sid="DAN 12:5"/>And I, Daniel, saw, and lo, two others stood, one on this side of the stream and one on the other.<verse eid="DAN 12:5"/>

<verse sid="DAN 12:6"/>And they said to the one wearing linen, "O, O Sir, when then will you do the consummation of the wonders and the purification of these things which you have told?"<verse eid="DAN 12:6"/>

<verse sid="DAN 12:7"/>And I heard the one wearing linen, who was above the water of the stream: "Until the <note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Perhaps 'consummation of time'</char></note>time of the consummation." And he raised the right hand and left hand toward heaven, and he swore by God, who lives forever, "The consummation of the power<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Perhaps 'hands'</char></note> for the release of the holy people will be at a time and times and half a time, and all these things will be accomplished."<verse eid="DAN 12:7"/>

<verse sid="DAN 12:8"/>And I heard and did not comprehend regarding the time itself, and I said, "Sir, what is the interpretation of this word [and what are these illustrations]?"<verse eid="DAN 12:8"/>

<verse sid="DAN 12:9"/>And he said to me, "Run along, Daniel, for the ordinances have been hidden and sealed until many are tested and sanctified,<verse eid="DAN 12:9"/>

<verse sid="DAN 12:10"/>and the sinners sin. And no sinners will ever comprehend, and those who understand will pay heed.<verse eid="DAN 12:10"/>

<verse sid="DAN 12:11"/>From the time that the [perpetual] sacrifice was taken away and the abomination of desolation was prepared to be given, there are one thousand two hundred ninety days.<verse eid="DAN 12:11"/>

<verse sid="DAN 12:12"/>Happy is the one who continues, because he will gather one thousand three hundred thirty-five days.<verse eid="DAN 12:12"/>

<verse sid="DAN 12:13"/>And you, go! Be off! For there are yet days and hours until the fulfillment of the consummation. [And you will rest and will rise upon your glory at the consummation of days.]<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Munnich = Omit [ ]</char></note>"<verse eid="DAN 12:13"/>
</_X_chapter></_X_book></_X_usx>