<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<_X_usx version="2.0">
<para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
<_X_book code="EZR">





<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="EZR 1">
<verse sid="EZR 1:1"/>And in the first year of Cyrus, king of the Persians, in order that the word of the Lord from the mouth of Ieremias might be fulfilled, the Lord stirred up the spirit of Cyrus, king of the Persians, and he commanded an utterance<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'proclamation'</char></note> in all his kingdom, indeed in written form, saying:<verse eid="EZR 1:1"/>

<verse sid="EZR 1:2"/>"Thus said Cyrus, king of the Persians: the Lord, the God of heaven, has given me all the kingdoms of the earth, and he himself has visited upon me to build him a house in Ierousalem, which is in Judea.<verse eid="EZR 1:2"/>

<verse sid="EZR 1:3"/>Who is there among you from all his people? And his God will be with him, and he will go up to Ierousalem, which is in Judea, and let him build the house of Israel's God; he is the God who is in Ierousalem.<verse eid="EZR 1:3"/>

<verse sid="EZR 1:4"/>And every one left shall go up from all the places where he resides there, and the men of his place shall receive them with silver and gold and with goods and animals, besides the freewill offering for the house of the God who is in Ierousalem."<verse eid="EZR 1:4"/>

<verse sid="EZR 1:5"/>And the chiefs of the paternal families of Iouda and Beniamin and the priests and the Leuites got up, all of whom God had stirred up their spirit, to go up to build the Lord's house, which is in Ierousalem.<verse eid="EZR 1:5"/>

<verse sid="EZR 1:6"/>And all from round about prevailed with their hands with vessels of silver, with gold and with goods and with livestock and with presents, besides the things that were freely offered.<verse eid="EZR 1:6"/>

<verse sid="EZR 1:7"/>And King Cyrus brought out the vessels of the house of the Lord, which Nabouchodonosor took from Ierousalem and placed them in the house of his god.<verse eid="EZR 1:7"/>

<verse sid="EZR 1:8"/>And Cyrus, king of the Persians, brought them out onto the hand of Mithridates Garbarenos<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Cf. Hebrew = 'treasurer'</char></note>, and he counted them for Sasabassar, the ruler of Iouda.<verse eid="EZR 1:8"/>

<verse sid="EZR 1:9"/>And this was their number: gold wine coolers, thirty, and silver wine coolers, one thousand, assorted items, twenty-nine,<verse eid="EZR 1:9"/>

<verse sid="EZR 1:10"/>gold chephoure<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'bowls'</char></note>, thirty, and silver ones and other vessels, one thousand,<verse eid="EZR 1:10"/>

<verse sid="EZR 1:11"/>All the vessels in gold and silver: five thousand four hundred, every one of which went up with Sasabassar from the exile out of Babylon to Ierousalem.<verse eid="EZR 1:11"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="EZR 2">
<verse sid="EZR 2:1"/>And these are the sons of the country, who went up from the captivity of the exile, which Nabouchodonosor, king of Babylon, had exiled to Babylon, and they returned to Ierousalem and Iouda, a man to his city,<verse eid="EZR 2:1"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:2"/>who went with Zorobabel: Iesous, Neemias, Saraias, Reelias, Mardochaios, Balasan, Masphar, Bagouai, Reoum, Baana. Number of the men of the people of Israel:<verse eid="EZR 2:2"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:3"/>sons of Phoros, two thousand one hundred seventy-two;<verse eid="EZR 2:3"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:4"/>sons of Saphatia, three hundred seventy-two;<verse eid="EZR 2:4"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:5"/>sons of Ares, seven hundred seventy-five;<verse eid="EZR 2:5"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:6"/>sons of Phaathmoab-- in reference to the sons of Iesou, of Ioab<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'Iesous Ioab'</char></note>-- two thousand eight hundred twelve;<verse eid="EZR 2:6"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:7"/>sons of Ailam, one thousand two hundred fifty-four;<verse eid="EZR 2:7"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:8"/>sons of Zaththoua, nine hundred forty-five;<verse eid="EZR 2:8"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:9"/>sons of Zakchai, seven hundred sixty;<verse eid="EZR 2:9"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:10"/>sons of Banoui, six hundred forty-two;<verse eid="EZR 2:10"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:11"/>sons of Babai, six hundred twenty-three;<verse eid="EZR 2:11"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:12"/>sons of Azgad, one thousand two hundred twenty-two;<verse eid="EZR 2:12"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:13"/>sons of Adonikam, six hundred sixty-six;<verse eid="EZR 2:13"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:14"/>sons of Bagouai, two thousand fifty-six;<verse eid="EZR 2:14"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:15"/>sons of Addin, four hundred fifty-four;<verse eid="EZR 2:15"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:16"/>sons of Ater-- in reference to Hezekias-- ninety-eight;<verse eid="EZR 2:16"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:17"/>sons of Bassou, three hundred twenty-three;<verse eid="EZR 2:17"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:18"/>sons of Iora, one hundred twelve;<verse eid="EZR 2:18"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:19"/>sons of Hasoum, two hundred twenty-three;<verse eid="EZR 2:19"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:20"/>sons of Gaber, ninety-five;<verse eid="EZR 2:20"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:21"/>sons of Baithleem, one hundred twenty-three;<verse eid="EZR 2:21"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:22"/>sons of Netopha, fifty-six;<verse eid="EZR 2:22"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:23"/>sons of Anathoth, one hundred twenty-eight;<verse eid="EZR 2:23"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:24"/>sons of Azmoth, forty-two;<verse eid="EZR 2:24"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:25"/>sons of Kariathiarim, Chaphira and Beroth, seven hundred forty-three;<verse eid="EZR 2:25"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:26"/>sons of the Rama and of Gabaa, six hundred twenty-one;<verse eid="EZR 2:26"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:27"/>men of Machmas, one hundred twenty-two;<verse eid="EZR 2:27"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:28"/>men of Baithel and Aia, four hundred twenty-three;<verse eid="EZR 2:28"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:29"/>sons of Nabo, fifty-two;<verse eid="EZR 2:29"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:30"/>sons of Magebis, one hundred fifty-six;<verse eid="EZR 2:30"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:31"/>sons of Elamar, one thousand two hundred fifty-four;<verse eid="EZR 2:31"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:32"/>sons of Heram, three hundred twenty;<verse eid="EZR 2:32"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:33"/>sons of Lod, Hadid and Ono, seven hundred twenty-five;<verse eid="EZR 2:33"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:34"/>sons of Iericho, three hundred forty-five;<verse eid="EZR 2:34"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:35"/>sons of Senaa, three thousand six hundred thirty.<verse eid="EZR 2:35"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:36"/>And the priests: sons of Iedoua-- in reference to the house of Iesous-- nine hundred seventy-three;<verse eid="EZR 2:36"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:37"/>sons of Emmer, one thousand fifty-two;<verse eid="EZR 2:37"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:38"/>sons of Phasour, one thousand two hundred forty-seven;<verse eid="EZR 2:38"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:39"/>sons of Herem, one thousand seven.<verse eid="EZR 2:39"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:40"/>And the Leuites: sons of Iesous and Kadmiel-- in reference to the sons of Hodouia-- seventy-four.<verse eid="EZR 2:40"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:41"/>The singers: sons of Asaph, one hundred twenty-eight.<verse eid="EZR 2:41"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:42"/>Sons of the gatekeepers: sons of Selloum; sons of Ater; sons of Telmon; sons of Akoub; sons of Hatita; sons of Sobai, in all one hundred thirty-nine.<verse eid="EZR 2:42"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:43"/>The nathineans<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:43</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'temple servants'</char></note>: sons of Souaa; sons of Hasoupha; sons of Tabbaoth;<verse eid="EZR 2:43"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:44"/>sons of Keraos; sons of Siaa; sons of Phadon;<verse eid="EZR 2:44"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:45"/>sons of Labano; sons of Hagaba; sons of Akoub;<verse eid="EZR 2:45"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:46"/>sons of Hagab; sons of Selami; sons of Hanan;<verse eid="EZR 2:46"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:47"/>sons of Geddel; sons of Gaar; sons of Raia;<verse eid="EZR 2:47"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:48"/>sons of Rason; sons of Nekoda; sons of Gazam;<verse eid="EZR 2:48"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:49"/>sons of Aza; sons of Phase; sons of Basi;<verse eid="EZR 2:49"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:50"/>sons of Asena; sons of Mooünim; sons of Nephousim;<verse eid="EZR 2:50"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:51"/>sons of Bakkouk; sons of Hakoupha; sons of Harour;<verse eid="EZR 2:51"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:52"/>sons of Basaloth; sons of Meida; sons of Harsa;<verse eid="EZR 2:52"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:53"/>sons of Barkos; sons of Sisara; sons of Thema;<verse eid="EZR 2:53"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:54"/>sons of Nasie; sons of Hatipha.<verse eid="EZR 2:54"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:55"/>Sons of Abdeselma: sons of Sotai; sons of Hasepherath; sons of Phadoura;<verse eid="EZR 2:55"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:56"/>sons of Ieala; sons of Kerkon; sons of Geddel;<verse eid="EZR 2:56"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:57"/>sons of Saphatia; sons of Hattil; sons of Phacherath of Hasaboim; sons of Emei.<verse eid="EZR 2:57"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:58"/>All the nathinim and sons of Abdeselma were three hundred ninety-two.<verse eid="EZR 2:58"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:59"/>And the following were those who went up from Thelmelech, Thelaresa, Cheroub, Edan, Emmer and were not able to proclaim their paternal house and their offspring, whether they were from Israel:<verse eid="EZR 2:59"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:60"/>sons of Dalaia; sons of Boua; sons of Tobia; sons of Nekoda, six hundred fifty-two.<verse eid="EZR 2:60"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:61"/>And from sons of the priests: sons of Hobaia; sons of Hakkous; sons of Berzellai (who took as wife one of the daughters of Berzellai the Galaadite and was called by their name).<verse eid="EZR 2:61"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:62"/>These, the methoesim<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:62</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'genealogical records'</char></note>, looked for their registration, and they were not found, and they were made near kin from the priesthood,<verse eid="EZR 2:62"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:63"/>and Hathersatha spoke to them so that they would not eat from the holy of holies until a priest should arise for<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:63</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'to pronounce on'</char></note> the things that enlighten and the things that are flawless.<verse eid="EZR 2:63"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:64"/>Now the whole assembly, as one, was forty-two thousand three hundred sixty,<verse eid="EZR 2:64"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:65"/>besides their male slaves and their servant girls-- these were seven thousand three hundred thirty-seven. And these, there were two hundred male singers and female singers.<verse eid="EZR 2:65"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:66"/>Their horses seven hundred thirty-six; their mules two hundred forty-five;<verse eid="EZR 2:66"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:67"/>their camels four hundred thirty-five, and their donkeys six thousand seven hundred twenty.<verse eid="EZR 2:67"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:68"/>And some from the chiefs of the ancestral families, when they came to the Lord's house, which is in Ierousalem, made freewill offerings to the house of God in order to erect it on its prepared basis.<verse eid="EZR 2:68"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:69"/>According to their ability they gave to the treasury for the work sixty-one thousand drachmas of gold and five thousand minas<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:69</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek 1 mina = 100 drachmas = 0.6 kg</char></note> of silver and one hundred priests' robes.<verse eid="EZR 2:69"/>

<verse sid="EZR 2:70"/>And the priests and the Leuites and those from the people and the singers and the gatekeepers and the nathinim settled in their cities, and all Israel in their cities.<verse eid="EZR 2:70"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="EZR 3">
<verse sid="EZR 3:1"/>And the seventh month arrived, and Israel was in their cities, and the people gathered as one man to Ierousalem.<verse eid="EZR 3:1"/>

<verse sid="EZR 3:2"/>And Iesous the son of Iosedek and his brothers the priests and Zorobabel the son of Salathiel and their brothers got ready and built the altar of the God of Israel in order to offer up whole burnt offerings on it, according to the things written in the law of Moyses the man of God.<verse eid="EZR 3:2"/>

<verse sid="EZR 3:3"/>And they prepared the altar on its prepared basis, because they had dread upon them from the peoples of the countries, and a whole burnt offering to the Lord was mounted upon it, in the morning and at evening.<verse eid="EZR 3:3"/>

<verse sid="EZR 3:4"/>And they observed the feast of tents, according to what was written, and the whole burnt offerings day by day, by number, according to decision, a matter of a day for its day,<verse eid="EZR 3:4"/>

<verse sid="EZR 3:5"/>and after that the whole burnt offerings of perpetuity and those for the new moons and for all the consecrated feasts to the Lord and the freewill offering of everyone who was making a freewill offering to the Lord.<verse eid="EZR 3:5"/>

<verse sid="EZR 3:6"/>On day one of the seventh month they began to offer up whole burnt offerings to the Lord, and the foundation of the Lord's house was not laid.<verse eid="EZR 3:6"/>

<verse sid="EZR 3:7"/>And they gave silver to the stonecutters and the carpenters and food and drink and oil to the Sidonians and the Tyrians, to bring cedar trees from the Lebanon to the sea of Joppe, according to the grant of Cyrus, king of the Persians, to them.<verse eid="EZR 3:7"/>

<verse sid="EZR 3:8"/>And in the second year of their going to the house of God at Ierousalem, in the second month, Zorobabel the son of Salathiel and Iesous the son of Iosedek and the rest of their brothers, the priests and the Leuites and all who were coming to Ierousalem from the captivity made a beginning and appointed the Leuites, from twenty years old and upward, over those who were doing the projects in the Lord's house.<verse eid="EZR 3:8"/>

<verse sid="EZR 3:9"/>And Iesous and his sons and his brothers, Kadmiel and his sons, sons of Iouda, sons of Henadad, their sons and their brothers the Leuites supervised those doing the projects in the house of God.<verse eid="EZR 3:9"/>

<verse sid="EZR 3:10"/>And they laid the foundation to build the house of the Lord, and the priests stood in their vestments with trumpets, and the Leuites, sons of Asaph, with cymbals, to praise the Lord upon the hands of Dauid, king of Israel,<verse eid="EZR 3:10"/>

<verse sid="EZR 3:11"/>and they responded with praise and confession to the Lord, "For it is good, for his mercy is forever upon Israel." And all the people signaled with a loud voice to praise the Lord for the foundation of the house of the Lord.<verse eid="EZR 3:11"/>

<verse sid="EZR 3:12"/>And many from the priests and the Leuites and chiefs of the paternal families, the old people, who had seen the first house on its foundation and this house with their eyes, were weeping with a loud voice, also the crowd at a signal with merriment to raise up a song.<verse eid="EZR 3:12"/>

<verse sid="EZR 3:13"/>And the people were not distinguishing the sound of the signal of merriment from the sound of the people's weeping, for the people shouted with a loud voice and the sound was being heard even at great distance.<verse eid="EZR 3:13"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="EZR 4">
<verse sid="EZR 4:1"/>And those who were afflicting Iouda and Beniamin heard that the sons of the exile were building a house to the Lord, God of Israel,<verse eid="EZR 4:1"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:2"/>and they approached Zorobabel and the chiefs of the paternal families and said to them, "Let us build with you, for we seek your God as you do, and we have been sacrificing to him since the days of Asaraddon, king of Assour, who brought us here."<verse eid="EZR 4:2"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:3"/>And Zorobabel and Iesous and the rest of the chiefs of the paternal families of Israel said to them: "It is not for us and for you to build a house for our God, because we ourselves together will build for the Lord, our God, as Cyrus, the king of the Persians, commanded us."<verse eid="EZR 4:3"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:4"/>And the people of the land were weakening the hands of the people of Iouda, and they were trying to hinder them from building<verse eid="EZR 4:4"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:5"/>and were hiring people against them, plotting to scatter their council all the days of Cyrus, king of the Persians, and until the reign of Darius, king of the Persians.<verse eid="EZR 4:5"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:6"/>And in the reign of Asoueros, in the beginning of his reign, they wrote a letter against those inhabiting Iouda and Ierousalem.<verse eid="EZR 4:6"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:7"/>And in the days of Arthasastha, they wrote in peace-- Mithridates, Tabeel<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'Mithridates, Tabeel':  Or 'Mithridates Tabeel' or 'Mithridates of Tabeel'</char></note> with also the rest of his fellow-slaves-- to Arthasastha, king of the Persians; the tribute collector wrote in Syrian<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Aramaic'</char></note> a document, also having been translated.<verse eid="EZR 4:7"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:8"/>Reoum, Baaltam and Samsai the scribe wrote one letter against Ierousalem to Arthasastha the king.<verse eid="EZR 4:8"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:9"/>"Reoum, Baaltam and Samsai the scribe and the rest of our fellow-slaves, the Dinians, Apharsathachians, Tarphallians, Apharsians, Archyians, Babylonians, Sousanachians, Dauians;<verse eid="EZR 4:9"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:10"/>the rest of the nations, whom the great and honorable Asennaphar deported and whom he settled in the cities of Somoron, and the rest beyond the river<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'beyond the river':  Perhaps 'Beyond the River'</char></note> have rendered judgment as follows."<verse eid="EZR 4:10"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:11"/>This is the commandment<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'disposition'</char></note> of the letter that they sent to him: "To Arthasastha the king. Your servants, men beyond the river<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'beyond the river':  Perhaps 'Beyond the River'</char></note>.<verse eid="EZR 4:11"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:12"/>Let it be known to the king that the Judeans, having come up from you to us, went to Ierousalem, the rebellious and wicked city, which they are building, and its walls have been finished, and they raised up its foundations.<verse eid="EZR 4:12"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:13"/>Now then, let it be known to the king that, if that city is rebuilt and its walls finished, tributes will not accrue to you, nor will they give, and this is detrimental to kings.<verse eid="EZR 4:13"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:14"/>And it is not fitting for us to see the king's dishonor; therefore we have sent and informed the king<verse eid="EZR 4:14"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:15"/>so that he might look in the book of the record of your fathers, and you will discover and know that that is a rebellious city and detrimental to kings and territories, and groups of fugitive slaves from long ago are in its midst. On that account this city was laid waste.<verse eid="EZR 4:15"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:16"/>Therefore, we are making it known to the king that, if that city is built and its walls are finished, you do not have peace."<verse eid="EZR 4:16"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:17"/>And the king sent peace and tidings to Reoum, Baaltam and Samsai the scribe and the rest of their fellow-slaves who live in Samaria and to the rest of those from beyond the river<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'beyond the river':  Perhaps 'Beyond the River'</char></note>:<verse eid="EZR 4:17"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:18"/>"The tribute collector whom you sent to us was summoned before me.<verse eid="EZR 4:18"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:19"/>And a decision was made by me, and we searched and discovered that that city, from days of old, rises up against kings, and that rebellions and banishments occur in it,<verse eid="EZR 4:19"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:20"/>and kings became strong in Ierousalem and ruled over the whole west of the river, and full tributes and a share were given to them.<verse eid="EZR 4:20"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:21"/>And now, make a decision that those men stop. And the city will no longer be built due to the decision,<verse eid="EZR 4:21"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:22"/>since you have been on guard against being slack in this matter, lest<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Göttingen Ed. = 'in order that no'</char></note> damage might perchance multiply to the detriment of kings."<verse eid="EZR 4:22"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:23"/>Then the tribute collector of Arthasastha the king read before Reoum, Baaltam and Samsai the scribe, his own fellow-slaves. And they went quickly to Ierousalem and in Iouda and stopped them with horses<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:23</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'cavalry'</char></note> and a force.<verse eid="EZR 4:23"/>

<verse sid="EZR 4:24"/>Then the work in Ierousalem on the house of God stopped and remained stopped until the second year of the reign of Darius, the king of the Persians.<verse eid="EZR 4:24"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="EZR 5">
<verse sid="EZR 5:1"/>And Haggaios the prophet and Zacharias the son of Addo prophesied a prophecy to the Judeans who were in Iouda and Ierousalem, in the name of Israel's God, who was over them.<verse eid="EZR 5:1"/>

<verse sid="EZR 5:2"/>At that time Zorobabel the son of Salathiel and Iesous son of Iosedek set out and began to build the house of God, which is in Ierousalem, and with them were the prophets of God, helping them.<verse eid="EZR 5:2"/>

<verse sid="EZR 5:3"/>At the same time Thaththanai, the commander beyond the river<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'beyond the river':  Perhaps 'Beyond the River'</char></note>, and Satharbouzanai, and their fellow-slaves came to them and spoke to them like this, "Who gave you a decision to build this house and to supply these materials?"<verse eid="EZR 5:3"/>

<verse sid="EZR 5:4"/>Then they said to them this: "What are the names of the men who are building this city?"<verse eid="EZR 5:4"/>

<verse sid="EZR 5:5"/>And the eyes of God were upon the captivity of Iouda, and they did not stop them until the advice was delivered to Darius. And then an answer about the matter was sent to the tribute collector.<verse eid="EZR 5:5"/>

<verse sid="EZR 5:6"/>The explanation of the letter that Thaththanai, the commander of the area beyond the river<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'the area beyond the river': Perhaps 'Beyond the River'</char></note>, Satharbouzanes and their fellow-slaves, the Apharsachians, who were in the area<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'beyond the river, Satharbouzanes and their fellow-slaves, the Apharsachians, who were in the area': Lacking in Greek</char></note> beyond the river<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'the area beyond the river': Perhaps 'Beyond the River'</char></note>, sent to Darius the king.<verse eid="EZR 5:6"/>

<verse sid="EZR 5:7"/>They sent him a report and in it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Antecedent unclear</char></note> these things were written: "To Darius the king, all peace!<verse eid="EZR 5:7"/>

<verse sid="EZR 5:8"/>Let it be known to the king that we went to the Judean region, to the house of the great God, and it is being built with choice stones, and timbers are laid in the walls, and that work is prosperous and going well in their hands.<verse eid="EZR 5:8"/>

<verse sid="EZR 5:9"/>Then we asked those elders and spoke to them thus, 'Who gave you a decision to build this house and to supply these materials?'<verse eid="EZR 5:9"/>

<verse sid="EZR 5:10"/>And we asked them their names, to inform you, so we could record for you the names of the men who are their rulers.<verse eid="EZR 5:10"/>

<verse sid="EZR 5:11"/>And they replied to us with a speech like this, saying: 'We are slaves of the God of heaven and earth, and we are building the house that had been built many years before now (and a great king of Israel built it and finished it for them).<verse eid="EZR 5:11"/>

<verse sid="EZR 5:12"/>But after that our fathers angered the God of heaven; he gave them into the hands of Nabouchodonosor, king of Babylon, the Chaldean, and he destroyed this house and exiled the people to Babylon.<verse eid="EZR 5:12"/>

<verse sid="EZR 5:13"/>But in the first year of Cyrus the king, Cyrus the king had a decision made that this house of God should be built.<verse eid="EZR 5:13"/>

<verse sid="EZR 5:14"/>And, as for the gold and silver vessels of the house of God, which Nabouchodonosor brought out from the house, which is in Ierousalem, and brought away into the shrine of the king, Cyrus the king brought them out of the shrine of the king and gave them to Sanabassaros, the treasurer who was over the treasury<verse eid="EZR 5:14"/>

<verse sid="EZR 5:15"/>and said to him, "Take all the vessels, and go; put them in the house, which is in Ierousalem, in their place."<verse eid="EZR 5:15"/>

<verse sid="EZR 5:16"/>Then this Sanabassar came and laid the foundations of the house of God in Ierousalem, and from then until now it was built and was not finished.'<verse eid="EZR 5:16"/>

<verse sid="EZR 5:17"/>And now, if it seems good to the king, have a search made in the house of the treasure of the king of Babylon, so you might know that a decision was issued from King Cyrus to build that house of God, which is in Ierousalem. And when the king knows about this, let him send notification to us."<verse eid="EZR 5:17"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="EZR 6">
<verse sid="EZR 6:1"/>Then Darius the king made a decision, and he searched in the libraries where the treasure is deposited in Babylon.<verse eid="EZR 6:1"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:2"/>And in the city of Amatha, in the bastion of the city of the Medes, one scroll was found, and this had written in it: "A record:<verse eid="EZR 6:2"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:3"/>In the first year of Cyrus the king, Cyrus the king issued a decision concerning the house of God, which is in Ierousalem: Let a house and a place where they sacrifice sacrifices be built, (and he made an elevation sixty cubits in height and its width sixty cubits,<verse eid="EZR 6:3"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:4"/>and there were three courses of hard stones and one course of timber) , and the cost will be paid from the house of the king.<verse eid="EZR 6:4"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:5"/>And, as for the silver and gold vessels of the house of God, which Nabouchodonosor brought out of the house, which was in Ierousalem, and carried off to Babylon, let them also be given, and let them go to the shrine, which is in Ierousalem, to the place where they were put in the house of God."<verse eid="EZR 6:5"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:6"/>"Now, commanders beyond the river<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'beyond the river': Perhaps '(of) Beyond the River'</char></note>, Satharbouzanai and their fellow-slaves, the Apharsacheans, who are in the area<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'in the area': Lacking in Greek</char></note> beyond the river<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'beyond the river': Perhaps '(of) Beyond the River'</char></note>, you will give these things, though being far away from there.<verse eid="EZR 6:6"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:7"/>And now permit the work of the house of God. Let the leaders of the Judeans and the elders of the Judeans build that house of God on its site.<verse eid="EZR 6:7"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:8"/>And a decision has been issued by me, lest you do anything with the elders of the Judeans to build that house of God. And let the cost diligently be paid to those men from the king's possessions, the tributes from beyond the river<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'beyond the river':  Perhaps '(of) Beyond the River'</char></note>, so that they are not delayed.<verse eid="EZR 6:8"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:9"/>And whatever the need-- in a case of<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'in a case of':  Lacking in Greek</char></note> both the offspring of cattle and rams and male lambs for whole burnt offerings to the God of heaven, wheat, salt, wine, oil, according to the word of the priests who are in Ierousalem-- let it be given to them day by day, whatever they request,<verse eid="EZR 6:9"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:10"/>so that they may be offering fragrances to the God of heaven and be praying for the life of the king and his sons.<verse eid="EZR 6:10"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:11"/>And a decision has been issued from me that, as for any person who alters this word, a beam shall be taken down out of his house, and he will be raised up and impaled on it, and his home made my possession.<verse eid="EZR 6:11"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:12"/>And may the God whose name encamps there overthrow any king and people that shall put forth its hand to alter or to destroy that house of God which is in Ierousalem. I, Darius, have issued a decision; it shall be done with all diligence."<verse eid="EZR 6:12"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:13"/>Then Thaththanai, governor beyond the river<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'beyond the river':  Perhaps '(of) Beyond the River'</char></note>, Satharbouzanai and his fellow slaves in this way acted with all diligence toward what Darius the king had sent.<verse eid="EZR 6:13"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:14"/>And the elders of the Judeans and the Leuites kept building during the prophesying of Haggaios the prophet and Zacharias son of Addo, and they rebuilt and finished it due to the decision of the God of Israel and due to the decision of Cyrus and Darius and Arthasastha, kings of the Persians.<verse eid="EZR 6:14"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:15"/>And they completed this house until the third day of the month of Adar, which was the sixth year of the reign of Darius the king.<verse eid="EZR 6:15"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:16"/>And sons of Israel-- the priests and the Leuites and the rest of the sons of the exile-- celebrated the rededication of the house of God with joy.<verse eid="EZR 6:16"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:17"/>And for the rededication of the house of God they offered one hundred calves, two hundred rams, four hundred male lambs, twelve male goats for sin on behalf of all Israel, for the number of the tribes of Israel.<verse eid="EZR 6:17"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:18"/>And they set the priests in their divisions and the Leuites in their orders for the service of the God who is in Ierousalem, in accordance with the scripture of the book of Moyses.<verse eid="EZR 6:18"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:19"/>And on the fourteenth of the first month the sons of the exile kept the pascha.<verse eid="EZR 6:19"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:20"/>Because the priests were purified and the Leuites pure, one and all, they also slaughtered the pascha for all the sons of the exile and for their brothers the priests and for themselves.<verse eid="EZR 6:20"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:21"/>And sons of Israel-- those from the exile and every one who was separating himself from the impurity of the nations of the land, joining them, in order to seek after the Lord, God of Israel-- ate the pascha<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Passover'</char></note>.<verse eid="EZR 6:21"/>

<verse sid="EZR 6:22"/>And they celebrated the feast of unleavened bread for seven days with joy, because the Lord made them joyful, and the Lord turned the heart of the king of Assour to them, to strengthen their hands in the projects of the house of the God of Israel.<verse eid="EZR 6:22"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="EZR 7">
<verse sid="EZR 7:1"/>And after these matters, in the reign of Arthasastha, king of the Persians, Esdras went up-- son of Saraias son of Azarias son of Helkia<verse eid="EZR 7:1"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:2"/>son of Selloum son of Saddouk son of Achitob<verse eid="EZR 7:2"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:3"/>son of Amaria son of Ezria son of Maraioth<verse eid="EZR 7:3"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:4"/>son of Zaraia son of Ozios son of Bokki<verse eid="EZR 7:4"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:5"/>son of Abisoue son of Phinees son of Eleazar son of Aaron the first priest.<verse eid="EZR 7:5"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:6"/>Esdras himself went up from Babylon, and he was a scribe quick in the law of Moyses that the Lord God of Israel had given. And the king gave to him, for the hand of the Lord, his God, was upon him in all that he himself was seeking.<verse eid="EZR 7:6"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:7"/>And some of the sons of Israel and some of the priests and some of the Leuites and the singers and the gatekeepers and the nathinim<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew (Aramaic) = 'temple servants'</char></note> went up to Ierousalem in the seventh year of Arthasastha the king.<verse eid="EZR 7:7"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:8"/>And they came to Ierousalem in the fifth month, that is, the seventh year of the king--<verse eid="EZR 7:8"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:9"/>because on the first of the first month he himself founded the ascent from Babylon, but on the first of the fifth month they came to Ierousalem, for the hand of his God was good upon him--<verse eid="EZR 7:9"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:10"/>because Esdras proposed in his heart to seek the law and to practice and to teach the ordinances and judgments in Israel.<verse eid="EZR 7:10"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:11"/>And this is the clear statement of the edict that Arthasastha gave to Esdras the priest, the scribe of the book of words of the commandments of the Lord and his ordinances for Israel:<verse eid="EZR 7:11"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:12"/>"Arthasastha, king of kings, to Esdras, the scribe of the law of the Lord the God of heaven. The message and its answer have been completed.<verse eid="EZR 7:12"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:13"/>A decision was issued from me that any from the people of Israel and priests and Leuites in my kingdom who freely offer to go to Ierousalem are to go with you.<verse eid="EZR 7:13"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:14"/>It<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the decision'</char></note> was sent from before the king and the seven counselors that you conduct an inspection of Judea and of Ierousalem in accordance with the law of their God, which is in your hand--<verse eid="EZR 7:14"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:15"/>and <note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note>that you inspect the silver and gold for the house of the Lord that the king and counselors freely offered to the God of Israel who encamps in Ierousalem<verse eid="EZR 7:15"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:16"/>and any silver and gold that you might find in the whole country of Babylon besides the freewill offering of the people and the priests who are giving willingly to the house of God, which is in Ierousalem;<verse eid="EZR 7:16"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:17"/>and everything that comes in, readily enter this one in this book: calves, rams, lambs and their offerings and their libations, and you shall offer them on the altar of the house of your God, which<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'who'</char></note> is in Ierousalem.<verse eid="EZR 7:17"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:18"/>And if something seems good to you and your brothers to do with the rest of the silver and gold, do as is pleasing to your God.<verse eid="EZR 7:18"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:19"/>And the vessels that are being given you for the service of the house of God, deliver them before God in Ierousalem.<verse eid="EZR 7:19"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:20"/>And as for the rest of the requirements for the house of your God-- whatever you think you should provide, you will provide out of the houses of the king's treasure.<verse eid="EZR 7:20"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:21"/>"And I, Arthasastha the king, have issued a decision from me for all the treasures in the area<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> beyond the river<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'the area beyond the river': Perhaps 'Beyond the River'</char></note> that everything that Esdras, the priest and scribe of the law of the God of heaven, asks you, let it be done with all diligence,<verse eid="EZR 7:21"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:22"/>up to one hundred talents of silver and up to one hundred kors<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew 1 kor = 220 liters</char></note> of wheat and up to one hundred baths<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew 1 bath = 22 liters</char></note> of wine and one hundred bathsh of oil and salt for which there is no writ.<verse eid="EZR 7:22"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:23"/>Everything that is in the decision of the God of heaven, let it be done. Beware of someone attacking the house of the God of heaven, lest wrath come upon the realm of the king and his sons.<verse eid="EZR 7:23"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:24"/>And this has been made known to you<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = plural</char></note> among all the priests and Leuites, singers, door keepers, nathinim<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew (Aramaic) = 'temple servants'</char></note> and ministers of God's house. Let there be no tribute for you<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = singular</char></note>, you will not have the power to enslave them.<verse eid="EZR 7:24"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:25"/>"And you, Esdras, in keeping with the wisdom of God in your hand, appoint scribes and judges so that they may be judging in the interest of all the people who are in the area<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> beyond the river<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'the area beyond the river': Perhaps 'Beyond the River'</char></note>, all who know the law of your God, and you shall make it known to the one who does not know it.<verse eid="EZR 7:25"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:26"/>And any who does not observe the law of God and the law of the king, readily the judgment will be one that issues from it, whether for death or whether for discipline or whether for loss of livelihood or whether for bonds."<verse eid="EZR 7:26"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:27"/>Blessed be the Lord the God of our fathers, who in this way put it in the heart of the king to glorify the house of the Lord, which is in Ierousalem;<verse eid="EZR 7:27"/>

<verse sid="EZR 7:28"/>and has inclined mercy upon me in the eyes of the king and his counselors and all the king's exalted rulers. And I was strengthened, for the good hand of God was upon me, and I gathered rulers from Israel to go up with me.<verse eid="EZR 7:28"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="EZR 8">
<verse sid="EZR 8:1"/>And these are the chiefs of their paternal families, the guides who went up with me in the reign of Arthasastha, the king of Babylon:<verse eid="EZR 8:1"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:2"/>of Phinees' sons, Gersom; of Ithamar's sons, Daniel; of Dauid's sons, Hattous;<verse eid="EZR 8:2"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:3"/>of Sachania's sons; of Phoros' sons, Zacharias, and with him the company of one hundred fifty;<verse eid="EZR 8:3"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:4"/>of Phaathmoab's sons, Eliana son of Saraia, and with him two hundred males;<verse eid="EZR 8:4"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:5"/>of Zathoes' sons, Sechenias son of Haziel, and with him three hundred males.<verse eid="EZR 8:5"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:6"/>And of Adin's sons, Obeth son of Ionathan, and with him fifty males.<verse eid="EZR 8:6"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:7"/>And of Elam's sons, Isaia son of Athelia, and with him seventy males.<verse eid="EZR 8:7"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:8"/>And of Saphatia's sons, Zabdias son of Michael, and with him the eighty males.<verse eid="EZR 8:8"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:9"/>And of Ioab's sons, Abadia-- he being son of Ieiel-- and with him were the two hundred eighteen males.<verse eid="EZR 8:9"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:10"/>And of Baani's sons, Selimouth son of Iosephia, and with him the one hundred sixty males.<verse eid="EZR 8:10"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:11"/>And of Babi's sons, Zacharias son of Babi, and with him the twenty-eight males.<verse eid="EZR 8:11"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:12"/>And of Azgad's sons, Ioanan-- he being son of Hakkatan-- and with him the one hundred ten males.<verse eid="EZR 8:12"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:13"/>And of Adonikam's sons-- they were last-- and these were their names: Eliphalath, Ieiel and Samaia, and with them the sixty males.<verse eid="EZR 8:13"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:14"/>And of Bagouai's sons, Outhai and Zaboud, and with them the seventy males.<verse eid="EZR 8:14"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:15"/>And I gathered them to the river that runs to Eui, and there we camped three days. And I took notice among the people and among the priests, and I did not find there any of Leui's sons.<verse eid="EZR 8:15"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:16"/>And I sent intelligent people to Eleazar, to Ariel, to Samaia and to Maonam and to Iarib and to Elnathan and to Nathan and to Zacharia and to Mesoulam and to Ioarib and to Elnathan,<verse eid="EZR 8:16"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:17"/>and I brought them out to the ruler with the silver of the place, and I placed words in their mouths to say to the brothers of them, of the nathinim<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'temple servants'</char></note>, so that they would bring for us, with the silver of the place, singers for the house of our God.<verse eid="EZR 8:17"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:18"/>And since the good hand of our God was upon us, there came to us a man of Sachol<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'sachol'</char></note>, some of Mooli's sons, son of Leui son of Israel (and his sons and his brothers, eighteen of them, came at the beginning) ,<verse eid="EZR 8:18"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:19"/>and Hasebia and Isaia of Merari's sons, his brothers and their sons, twenty,<verse eid="EZR 8:19"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:20"/>and of the nathinim<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'temple servants'</char></note> whom Dauid and his rulers had given into slavery to the Leuites, two hundred twenty nathinim<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'temple servants'</char></note>. They were all gathered together by name.<verse eid="EZR 8:20"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:21"/>And I proclaimed a fast there at the river Aoue, so that we might be humbled before our God, to seek from him a straight journey for ourselves and our children and all our property.<verse eid="EZR 8:21"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:22"/>Because I was ashamed to request from the king a force and horses to save us from an enemy on the journey, because we had spoken to the king, saying, "The hand of our God is upon all who seek him for good, and his power and his wrath are upon all who forsake him."<verse eid="EZR 8:22"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:23"/>And we fasted and sought from our God about this, and he listened to us.<verse eid="EZR 8:23"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:24"/>And I set apart twelve from the leaders of the priests, in reference to Saraia, in reference to Hasabia, and ten from their brothers with them,<verse eid="EZR 8:24"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:25"/>and I weighed out for them the silver and the gold and the vessels of the first fruit of the house of our God, which the king and his counselors and his rulers and all Israel who were found had lifted up.<verse eid="EZR 8:25"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:26"/>And I weighed onto their hands six hundred fifty talents of silver and one hundred silver vessels and one hundred talents of gold;<verse eid="EZR 8:26"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:27"/>and for the journey twenty gold chaphoure<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:27</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'bowls'</char></note> worth a thousand drachmas and excellent, desirable vessels of fine polished bronze in gold.<verse eid="EZR 8:27"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:28"/>And I said to them, "You are holy to the Lord God, and the vessels are holy, and the silver and the gold are freewill offerings to the Lord, God of our fathers.<verse eid="EZR 8:28"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:29"/>Be vigilant, and keep them until you weigh<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:29</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'set'</char></note> them before the rulers of the priests and the Leuites and the chiefs of paternal families in Ierousalem, at the tents of the house of the Lord."<verse eid="EZR 8:29"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:30"/>And the priests and the Leuites took the weight of the silver and the gold and the vessels, to bring to Ierousalem to the house of our God.<verse eid="EZR 8:30"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:31"/>And we started out from the river Aoue on the twelfth of the first month, to go to Ierousalem, and the hand of our God was upon us, and he delivered us from the hand of the enemy and hostility on the journey.<verse eid="EZR 8:31"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:32"/>And we came to Ierousalem and settled there three days.<verse eid="EZR 8:32"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:33"/>And it happened on the fourth day, in the house of our God, we weighed the silver and the gold and the vessels into the hand of Marimoth son of Ouria the priest (and with him was Eleazar son of Phinees, and with them Iozabad son of Iesous and Noadia son of Banaia, the Leuites) ,<verse eid="EZR 8:33"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:34"/>everything by number and by weight, and the total weight was recorded. At that time<verse eid="EZR 8:34"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:35"/>those who had come from captivity, sons of the exiles, offered as whole burnt offerings to the God of Israel twelve calves for all Israel, ninety-six rams, seventy-seven lambs, twelve male goats for sin; these were all the burnt offerings to the Lord.<verse eid="EZR 8:35"/>

<verse sid="EZR 8:36"/>And they gave the king's currency to the administrators of the king and to the commanders beyond the river<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:36</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'beyond the river':  Perhaps 'of Beyond the River'</char></note>, and they extolled the people and the house of God.<verse eid="EZR 8:36"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="EZR 9">
<verse sid="EZR 9:1"/>And after these things had been done, the rulers approached me, saying, "The people of Israel and the priests and the Leuites were not separated from the peoples of the lands with their things put far away<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'things put far away':  Possibly 'abominations'</char></note>, in reference to the Chanani-- the Heththi, the Pherezi, the Iebousi, the Ammoni, the Moab, the Mosri and the Amori--<verse eid="EZR 9:1"/>

<verse sid="EZR 9:2"/>because they have taken from their daughters for themselves and for their sons, and the holy seed was influenced by the peoples of the lands, and the hand of the rulers was in this faithlessness in the beginning."<verse eid="EZR 9:2"/>

<verse sid="EZR 9:3"/>And when I heard this word, I tore my garments and was quivering and was pulling out some of the hair of my head and some of my beard and was sitting in silence.<verse eid="EZR 9:3"/>

<verse sid="EZR 9:4"/>And everyone who pursued the word of Israel's God, because of the faithlessness of the exile-- they gathered to me, and I kept sitting in silence until the evening sacrifice.<verse eid="EZR 9:4"/>

<verse sid="EZR 9:5"/>And at the evening sacrifice I got up from my humiliation. And when I had torn my garments, and I was quivering and was getting down on my knees and spreading out my hands to the Lord God<verse eid="EZR 9:5"/>

<verse sid="EZR 9:6"/>and said, "O Lord, I was ashamed and hesitated to lift, O my God, my face to you, because our acts of lawlessness have multiplied above our heads, and our errors have been increased up to heaven.<verse eid="EZR 9:6"/>

<verse sid="EZR 9:7"/>From the days of our fathers to this day we are in error, and for our acts of lawlessness we and our kings and our sons have been handed over in the hand of the kings of the nations, by sword and by captivity and by plundering and by shame of our face, as this day.<verse eid="EZR 9:7"/>

<verse sid="EZR 9:8"/>And now the Lord, our God, was fair with us to leave us for salvation and give us support in the place of his holiness<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'holy precinct'</char></note> in order that he might brighten our eyes and grant us a little vitality in our slavery.<verse eid="EZR 9:8"/>

<verse sid="EZR 9:9"/>Because we are slaves, the Lord, our God, has not forsaken us even in our slavery and inclined mercy upon us before the kings of the Persians, to give us vitality that they might raise up the house of our God and to repair its ruins and to give us a fence<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'fortification'</char></note> in Iouda and in Ierousalem.<verse eid="EZR 9:9"/>

<verse sid="EZR 9:10"/>"Our God, what shall we say after this? Because we have forsaken your commandments,<verse eid="EZR 9:10"/>

<verse sid="EZR 9:11"/>which you gave us by the hand of your slaves the prophets, saying, 'The land that you are entering to possess it is a land undergoing change by the changing of the peoples of the nations, with their things put far away<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'things put far away':  Possibly 'abominations'</char></note>, who they have filled it from mouth to mouth with their impurities.<verse eid="EZR 9:11"/>

<verse sid="EZR 9:12"/>And now do not give your daughters to their sons, and do not take some of their daughters for your sons, and never seek out their peace and their prosperity so that you may be strong and eat the good of the land and distribute it to your sons forever.'<verse eid="EZR 9:12"/>

<verse sid="EZR 9:13"/>And after all that is coming upon us for our evil deeds and for our great error-- because there is none like our God, because you canceled our acts of lawlessness and gave us salvation,<verse eid="EZR 9:13"/>

<verse sid="EZR 9:14"/>because we returned to scatter your commandments and to intermarry with the peoples of the lands, do not be provoked at us until destruction so that there is no remnant and survivor.<verse eid="EZR 9:14"/>

<verse sid="EZR 9:15"/>O Lord, God of Israel, you are just, because we have been left over as survivors, as this day. Behold, we are before you with our errors, because it is not possible to stand before you because of this."<verse eid="EZR 9:15"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="EZR 10">
<verse sid="EZR 10:1"/>And as Esdras prayed and as he declared, weeping and praying before the house of God, a very great assembly-- men and women and young men-- gathered to him from Israel, because the people wept and lifted up while weeping.<verse eid="EZR 10:1"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:2"/>And Sechenias son of Ieiel, of Elam's sons, answered and said to Esdras, "We were faithless with our God and set up<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'set up':  I.e. 'married'</char></note> foreign women from the peoples of the land, and now there is endurance for Israel in this.<verse eid="EZR 10:2"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:3"/>And now let us make a covenant with our God to cast out all the women and the issue from them, however you want. Arise, and scare them with the commandments of our God, and let it be done according to the law.<verse eid="EZR 10:3"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:4"/>Arise! The word is upon you, and we are with you; be strong, and act."<verse eid="EZR 10:4"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:5"/>And Esdras arose and made the rulers, the priests and Leuites and all Israel swear to act according to this word. And they swore.<verse eid="EZR 10:5"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:6"/>And Esdras arose from before the house of God and went to the treasure chamber of Ioanan son of Elisoub, and he went there. He did not eat bread and did not drink water, because he was mourning over the faithlessness of the exile.<verse eid="EZR 10:6"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:7"/>And they presented an utterance<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'proclamation'</char></note> in Iouda and in Ierousalem to all sons of the exile that they should assemble in Ierousalem:<verse eid="EZR 10:7"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:8"/>"Anyone who does not come within three days, as the council of the rulers and the elders demands<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note>-- all his property will be anathematized, and he himself banned from the assembly of the exile."<verse eid="EZR 10:8"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:9"/>And all the men of Iouda and Beniamin assembled to Ierousalem within the three days; this was the ninth month. On the twentieth of the month, all the people sat in the open square of the house of God, from their tumult about<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'tumult about':  Or 'clamor after'</char></note> the word and because of the winter.<verse eid="EZR 10:9"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:10"/>And Esdras the priest arose and said to them, "You have been faithless and set up<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'set up':  I.e. 'married'</char></note> foreign women, increasing the error of Israel.<verse eid="EZR 10:10"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:11"/>And now give praise to the Lord God of our fathers, and do what is pleasing before him, and separate from the peoples of the land and from the foreign women."<verse eid="EZR 10:11"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:12"/>And all the assembly answered with a loud voice and said, "This word of yours is a big thing for us to do.<verse eid="EZR 10:12"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:13"/>But the people are many, and it is the winter season, and there is no ability to stand outside, and the task is not for one day and not for two, because we have multiplied in doing wrong in this matter.<verse eid="EZR 10:13"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:14"/>Let now our rulers stand fast for the whole assembly and for all those in our cities. As for him who has set up<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'set up':  I.e. 'married'</char></note> foreign women-- let them come at appropriate times as instructed, and with them the elders of city by city and judges, in order to turn away from us the anger of the wrath of our God concerning this matter."<verse eid="EZR 10:14"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:15"/>Only Ionathan son of Asael and Iazias son of Thekoue are with me in this, and Mesoulam and Sabbathai the Leuite supporting them.<verse eid="EZR 10:15"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:16"/>And sons of the exile did so. And Esdras the priest and men ruling the paternal houses were set apart<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'were set apart':  Or 'given express orders'</char></note>, and all by name, because on the first day of the tenth month they turned to investigate the matter.<verse eid="EZR 10:16"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:17"/>And they finished with all the men who had set up<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'set up':  I.e. 'married'</char></note> foreign women by the first day of the first month.<verse eid="EZR 10:17"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:18"/>And there were found some sons of the priests who had set up<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'set up':  I.e. 'married'</char></note> foreign women: some sons of Iesous son of Iosedek and his brothers: Maaseia and Eliezer and Iarib and Gadalia.<verse eid="EZR 10:18"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:19"/>And they gave their hand<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'gave their hand':  I.e. 'pledged'</char></note> to put away their wives and errors-- a ram of the flock for their error.<verse eid="EZR 10:19"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:20"/>And of Emmer's sons: Hanania and Zabdia.<verse eid="EZR 10:20"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:21"/>And of Heram's sons: Masias and Elia and Samaia and Ieiel and Ozia.<verse eid="EZR 10:21"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:22"/>And of Phasour's sons: Elioenai, Maasia and Ismael and Nathanael and Iozabad and Elasa.<verse eid="EZR 10:22"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:23"/>And of the Leuites: Iozabad and Samou and Kolia (that is, Kolitas) and Phetheia and Ioudas and Eliezer.<verse eid="EZR 10:23"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:24"/>And of the singers: Elisab. And of the gatekeepers: Solmen and Telmen and Odoue.<verse eid="EZR 10:24"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:25"/>And of Israel: of Phoros' sons: Ramia and Iazia and Melchia and Meamin and Eleazar and Hasabia and Banaia.<verse eid="EZR 10:25"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:26"/>And of Elam's sons: Maththania and Zacharia and Iaiel and Abdia and Ieri-moth and Elia.<verse eid="EZR 10:26"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:27"/>And of Zaththoua's sons: Elioenai, Elisoub, Maththanai and Iarmoth and Zabad and Oziza.<verse eid="EZR 10:27"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:28"/>And of Babi's sons: Ioanan, Hanania and Zabou, Othali.<verse eid="EZR 10:28"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:29"/>And of Bani's sons: Mesoulam, Malouch, Adaias, Iasoub and Saal and Re-moth.<verse eid="EZR 10:29"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:30"/>And of Phaathmoab's sons: Edne and Chalel and Banaia, Maasea, Maththania, Beselel and Banoui and Manasse.<verse eid="EZR 10:30"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:31"/>And of Heram's sons: Eliezer, Ieseia, Melchia, Samaias, Semeon,<verse eid="EZR 10:31"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:32"/>Beniamin, Malouch, Samaria.<verse eid="EZR 10:32"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:33"/>And of Hasem's sons: Maththanai, Maththatha, Zabad, Eliphalet, Ieremi, Manasse and Semei.<verse eid="EZR 10:33"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:34"/>And of Bani's sons: Mood-ia, Amram and Ouel,<verse eid="EZR 10:34"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:35"/>Banaia, Badaia, Chelia,<verse eid="EZR 10:35"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:36"/>Ououania, Marimoth, Eliasib,<verse eid="EZR 10:36"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:37"/>Maththania, Maththanai, and so did<verse eid="EZR 10:37"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:38"/>Banoui's sons and Semei's sons<verse eid="EZR 10:38"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:39"/>and Selemia and Nathan and Adaias,<verse eid="EZR 10:39"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:40"/>Machnadaabou, Sesei, Arou,<verse eid="EZR 10:40"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:41"/>Ezriel and Selemia and Samarias,<verse eid="EZR 10:41"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:42"/>Selloum, Amarias, Ioseph.<verse eid="EZR 10:42"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:43"/>And of Nabou's sons: Ieiel, Maththathias, Zabad, Zebinnas, Iadai and Ioel and Banaia.<verse eid="EZR 10:43"/>

<verse sid="EZR 10:44"/>All these had married foreign women, and they fathered sons by them.<verse eid="EZR 10:44"/>
</_X_chapter></_X_book></_X_usx>