<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<_X_usx version="2.0">
<para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
<_X_book code="HAB">





<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="HAB 1">
<verse sid="HAB 1:1"/>The issue that the prophet Habbakoum<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = 'Hambakoum'</char></note> saw.<verse eid="HAB 1:1"/>

<verse sid="HAB 1:2"/>O Lord, how long shall I cry out, and you will not listen? Being wronged shall I cry to you, and you will not save?<verse eid="HAB 1:2"/>

<verse sid="HAB 1:3"/>Why did you show me toils and hardships, to look at wretchedness and impiety? Justice has come before me, and the judge is receiving.<verse eid="HAB 1:3"/>

<verse sid="HAB 1:4"/>Therefore, law has been dispersed, and judgment is not administered at all, because an impious person oppresses the just-- on this account, judgment will come forth perverted.<verse eid="HAB 1:4"/>

<verse sid="HAB 1:5"/>Look, you despisers, and watch! And marvel at marvelous things, and be annihilated! For I am working a work in your days that you would not believe if someone should tell it.<verse eid="HAB 1:5"/>

<verse sid="HAB 1:6"/>For behold I am rousing [the Chaldeans,] the fighters, the bitter and swift nation that goes over the breadths of the earth to possess dwellings not his own.<verse eid="HAB 1:6"/>

<verse sid="HAB 1:7"/>He is frightening and conspicuous; his judgment will be from himself, and his unjust gain will come from himself.<verse eid="HAB 1:7"/>

<verse sid="HAB 1:8"/>And his horses will leap beyond leopards and will be swifter than the wolves of Arabia. His horsemen will ride forth and charge from far away; they will fly like an eagle eager to devour.<verse eid="HAB 1:8"/>

<verse sid="HAB 1:9"/>Consummation will come to the impious, who stand with their faces in opposition, and he will gather a captivity like the sand.<verse eid="HAB 1:9"/>

<verse sid="HAB 1:10"/>And at kings he will scoff, and tyrants will be his toys. He will jest at every fortress and heap up earth and take it.<verse eid="HAB 1:10"/>

<verse sid="HAB 1:11"/>Then he will have a change of spirit and pass through and will appease. This strength belongs to my God.<verse eid="HAB 1:11"/>

<verse sid="HAB 1:12"/>Are you not from the beginning, O Lord, my holy God? So we shall not die. O Lord, you have appointed him for judgment, and he has formed me to examine his chastening.<verse eid="HAB 1:12"/>

<verse sid="HAB 1:13"/>A pure eye is not for seeing evil things, and you cannot look upon sufferings. Why do you look on those who despise? Will you keep silence while the impious swallows up the just?<verse eid="HAB 1:13"/>

<verse sid="HAB 1:14"/>And you will make people like the fish of the sea and like crawling things that have no leader!<verse eid="HAB 1:14"/>

<verse sid="HAB 1:15"/>He drew up consummation with a fish hook and dragged him with a fishing net and gathered him in his seines.<verse eid="HAB 1:15"/>

<verse sid="HAB 1:16"/>On this account he will be glad, and his heart will rejoice. On this account he will sacrifice to his seine and burn incense to his fishing net, because by them he made his portion fat and his food choice.<verse eid="HAB 1:16"/>

<verse sid="HAB 1:17"/>Therefore he will cast his fishing net and never spare killing the nations.<verse eid="HAB 1:17"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="HAB 2">
<verse sid="HAB 2:1"/>I will stand at my watch post and station myself on a rock. And I will keep watch to see what he will say to me and what I should answer to my reproof.<verse eid="HAB 2:1"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:2"/>And the Lord answered me and said, Write a vision, and clearly on a tablet, so that the reader might pursue them.<verse eid="HAB 2:2"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:3"/>For there is still a vision for an appointed time, and it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'appointed time'</char></note> will rise up at the end and not in vain. If it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'appointed time'</char></note> should tarry, wait for it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'appointed time'</char></note>, for when it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'appointed time'</char></note> comes it will come and not delay.<verse eid="HAB 2:3"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:4"/>If it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'appointed time'</char></note> draws back, my soul is not pleased in it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'appointed time'</char></note>. But the just shall live by my faith<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'faithfulness'</char></note>.<verse eid="HAB 2:4"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:5"/>But he who is drunk with wine and a despiser -- a boastful man-- will complete nothing, who widened his soul like Hades, and he, like death, not being satisfied, will also gather to himself all nations and will welcome to himself all peoples.<verse eid="HAB 2:5"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:6"/>Shall not all these things take up a parable against him and a riddle as a narrative of him? And they will say, "Woe to him who increases for himself things not his own-- how long?-- and who weighs down his collar<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly as an ornament</char></note> strongly,"<verse eid="HAB 2:6"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:7"/>because when they bite him they will suddenly rise. And those who plot against you will become sober, and you will be booty for them.<verse eid="HAB 2:7"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:8"/>For you have despoiled many nations, all the peoples that survive shall despoil you-- on account of human bloodshed and impieties of the earth, of the city and of all who live in it.<verse eid="HAB 2:8"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:9"/>"Ah he who gains an evil gain for his house, to set his nest on high, to be pulled out from the reach of evil ones!"<verse eid="HAB 2:9"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:10"/>You have devised shame for your house; you have put an end to many peoples, and your soul has sinned.<verse eid="HAB 2:10"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:11"/>For a stone shall cry out from a wall, and a beetle shall utter them from wood.<verse eid="HAB 2:11"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:12"/>"Woe to him who builds a city by bloodshed and prepares a city with injustices!"<verse eid="HAB 2:12"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:13"/>Are these not from the Lord Almighty? And enough peoples have expired in fire, and many nations have become faint-hearted.<verse eid="HAB 2:13"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:14"/>Because the earth will be filled with knowing the glory of the Lord, like water it will cover them.<verse eid="HAB 2:14"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:15"/>"Ah he who by turbid upset gives his neighbor to drink and intoxicates him in order to gaze on their caverns<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Perhaps 'private parts'</char></note>."<verse eid="HAB 2:15"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:16"/>Drink, you too, an abundance of dishonor from glory, and shake, and quake! A cup in the Lord's right hand has gone around to you, and dishonor has been gathered to your glory!<verse eid="HAB 2:16"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:17"/>For the impiety of Lebanon will cover you, and the misery of wild animals will terrify you-- on account of human bloodshed and impieties of the earth, of the city and of all who live in it.<verse eid="HAB 2:17"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:18"/>What use is a carved image, because one carved it? He shaped it a molten image, a deceptive representation, because its shaper trusts in his shape, to make idols dumb!<verse eid="HAB 2:18"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:19"/>Woe to him who says to the wood, "Be sober! Wake up!" and to the stone, "Be exalted!" And it is a representation, that is, a beaten- out piece of gold and silver, and there is no breath in it.<verse eid="HAB 2:19"/>

<verse sid="HAB 2:20"/>But the Lord is in his holy shrine; let all the earth do reverence before him!<verse eid="HAB 2:20"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="HAB 3">
<verse sid="HAB 3:1"/>A prayer of the prophet Habbakoum<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = Hambakoum</char></note> with a song.<verse eid="HAB 3:1"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:2"/>O Lord, I have heard of your renown and feared; I considered your works and was astonished. You will be known in the midst of two living creatures; you will be recognized when the years draw near; you will be displayed when the right time comes; you will remember mercy when my soul is troubled in wrath.<verse eid="HAB 3:2"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:3"/>God will come out of Thaiman, and the Holy One from a shady, densely wooded mountain. Interlude on strings His virtue has covered heavens, and the earth is full of his praise.<verse eid="HAB 3:3"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:4"/>And his brightness will be like light; horns are in his hands. And he has established a strong love of his strength.<verse eid="HAB 3:4"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:5"/>A report shall proceed before him, and he shall go forth, his feet in sandals.<verse eid="HAB 3:5"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:6"/>He stopped, and the earth shook; he looked, and nations dissolved; the mountains were broken to pieces in violence; everlasting hills of his eternal passage melted.<verse eid="HAB 3:6"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:7"/>I saw the encampments of the Ethiopians instead of troubles; they shall be terrified, even the tents of the land of Madiam.<verse eid="HAB 3:7"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:8"/>Surely, you were not angry with rivers, O Lord? Or was your wrath against rivers, or your onslaught against a sea? Because you will mount your horses, and your cavalry is deliverance.<verse eid="HAB 3:8"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:9"/>Stretching, you will stretch your bow; seven scepters, says the Lord. Interlude on strings A land of rivers will be torn asunder.<verse eid="HAB 3:9"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:10"/>Peoples will see you and writhe as you scatter the waters of a course. The deep gave forth its voice, the height of its representation.<verse eid="HAB 3:10"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:11"/>The sun was raised up, and the moon stood still in its course. Your missiles will go into the light, into the brightness of the lightning of your weapons.<verse eid="HAB 3:11"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:12"/>With a threat you will diminish the earth, and with wrath you will bring down nations.<verse eid="HAB 3:12"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:13"/>You came forth for the salvation of your people, to save your anointed ones. You cast death on the heads of the lawless; you raised fetters up to the neck. Interlude on strings<verse eid="HAB 3:13"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:14"/>In a frenzy you cut through the heads of the mighty; they shall quake at this<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'frenzy'</char></note>. They shall open their bridles like a poor man eating in secret.<verse eid="HAB 3:14"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:15"/>And you caused your horses to go up into the sea, as they were stirring up much water.<verse eid="HAB 3:15"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:16"/>I watched, and my belly was terrified by the sound of the prayer of my lips. And trembling entered into my bones, and my posture was stirred beneath me. I will rest on a day of affliction to go up to a people of my sojourning.<verse eid="HAB 3:16"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:17"/>For a fig tree shall bear no fruit, and no produce shall be on the vines; the work of the olive will deceive, and the plains will yield no food; sheep have run out of food, and cows are not at the mangers.<verse eid="HAB 3:17"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:18"/>But I will exult in the Lord; I will rejoice in God my savior.<verse eid="HAB 3:18"/>

<verse sid="HAB 3:19"/>The Lord God is my power, and he shall establish my feet unto the end. He causes me to mount the heights, to be victorious in his song.<verse eid="HAB 3:19"/>
</_X_chapter></_X_book></_X_usx>