<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<_X_usx version="2.0">
<para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
<_X_book code="HAG">





<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="HAG 1">
<verse sid="HAG 1:1"/>In the second year of King Darius, in the sixth month, on the first of the month, a word of the Lord came by the hand of the prophet Haggaios, saying, Speak to Zorobabel the son of Salathiel, from the tribe of Ioudas, and to Iesous the son of Iosedek, the great priest, saying,<verse eid="HAG 1:1"/>

<verse sid="HAG 1:2"/>This is what the Lord Almighty says, saying, These people say, The time has not come to build the Lord's house.<verse eid="HAG 1:2"/>

<verse sid="HAG 1:3"/>And a word of the Lord came by the hand of the prophet Haggaios, saying,<verse eid="HAG 1:3"/>

<verse sid="HAG 1:4"/>Is it time for you to live in your paneled houses, but this house is in ruins?<verse eid="HAG 1:4"/>

<verse sid="HAG 1:5"/>And now, this is what the Lord Almighty says, Focus now your hearts on your ways.<verse eid="HAG 1:5"/>

<verse sid="HAG 1:6"/>You have sown much and taken in little; you have eaten, and not to satiety; you have drunk, and not unto drunkenness; you have clothed yourselves and have not been warmed by them, and he who gathers wages gathered them for a purse with holes.<verse eid="HAG 1:6"/>

<verse sid="HAG 1:7"/>This is what the Lord Almighty says, Set your hearts on your ways.<verse eid="HAG 1:7"/>

<verse sid="HAG 1:8"/>Go up to the mountain, and cut trees, and build the house, and I will take pleasure in it and be honored, said the Lord.<verse eid="HAG 1:8"/>

<verse sid="HAG 1:9"/>You have looked for much, and little has come, and it was brought home, and I blew it away. Therefore this is what the Lord Almighty says, Because my house is a wilderness but you run off each one to his own house,<verse eid="HAG 1:9"/>

<verse sid="HAG 1:10"/>therefore the sky shall withhold the dew, and the earth shall withdraw its produce.<verse eid="HAG 1:10"/>

<verse sid="HAG 1:11"/>And I will bring a sword on the land and on the mountains and on the grain and on the wine and on the oil, and what the soil produces, and on human beings and on animals and on all the labors of their hands.<verse eid="HAG 1:11"/>

<verse sid="HAG 1:12"/>And Zorobabel the son of Salathiel, from the tribe of Ioudas, and Iesous the son of Iosedek, the great priest, and all the remnant of the people listened to the voice of the Lord their God and the words of the prophet Haggaios, as the Lord had sent him to them, and the people feared before the Lord.<verse eid="HAG 1:12"/>

<verse sid="HAG 1:13"/>And Haggaios, the messenger of the Lord, said to the people, I am with you, says the Lord.<verse eid="HAG 1:13"/>

<verse sid="HAG 1:14"/>And the Lord stirred up the spirit of Zorobabel son of Salathiel, from the tribe of Ioudas, and the spirit of Iesous son of Iosedek, the great priest, and the spirit of the remnant of all the people, and they entered and were doing work in the house of the<verse eid="HAG 1:14"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="HAG 2">
<verse sid="HAG 2:1"/>Lord Almighty, their God, (1) on the twenty-fourth of the sixth month, in the second year of King Darius. In the seventh month, on the twenty-first of the month, the Lord spoke by the hand of the prophet Haggaios, saying,<verse eid="HAG 2:1"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:2"/>Speak now to Zorobabel the son of Salathiel, from the tribe of Ioudas, and to Iesous the son of Iosedek, the great priest, and to all the remnant of the people, saying,<verse eid="HAG 2:2"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:3"/>Who is left among you that saw this house in its former glory? And how do you see it now? As though it does not exist before you?<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'you.'</char></note><verse eid="HAG 2:3"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:4"/>And now, be strong, O Zorobabel, says the Lord, and be strong, O Iesous the son of Iosedek, the great priest, and let all the people of the land be strong, says the Lord, and act, for I am with you, says the Lord Almighty,<verse eid="HAG 2:4"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:5"/>and my spirit is present among you; have courage.<verse eid="HAG 2:5"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:6"/>For this is what the Lord Almighty says, Once again I will shake the sky and the earth and the sea and the dry land,<verse eid="HAG 2:6"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:7"/>and I will shake all the nations, and the choice things of all the nations shall come, and I will fill this house with splendor, says the Lord Almighty.<verse eid="HAG 2:7"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:8"/>The silver is mine, and the gold is mine, says the Lord Almighty.<verse eid="HAG 2:8"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:9"/>For the last splendor of this house shall be great beyond the first, says the Lord Almighty, and in this place I will give peace, says the Lord Almighty, even peace of mind for an acquisition to everyone who creates, to raise up this shrine.<verse eid="HAG 2:9"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:10"/>On the twenty-fourth of the ninth month of the second year of Darius, a word of the Lord came to the prophet Haggaios, saying:<verse eid="HAG 2:10"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:11"/>This is what the Lord Almighty says: Ask the priests for a ruling, saying:<verse eid="HAG 2:11"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:12"/>If a person should take consecrated meat in the skirt of his garment and the skirt of his garment should touch bread or stew or wine or oil or any kind of food-- whether it will become holy? And the priests answered and said, "No."<verse eid="HAG 2:12"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:13"/>And Haggaios said, "If one who is defiled by a soul<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'departed soul' tantamount to 'corpse'</char></note> should touch any of these, will it become defiled?" And the priests answered and said, "It will become defiled."<verse eid="HAG 2:13"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:14"/>And Haggaios answered and said, So is this people, and so is this nation before me, says the Lord, and so are all the works of their hands, and whoever comes near there will be defiled on account of their early gains<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'early gains':  I.e. 'earlier income'</char></note>; they will suffer because of their toils. And you used to hate those who reprove in the gates.<verse eid="HAG 2:14"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:15"/>And now, do place it in your hearts from this day and beyond, before laying one stone upon another in the Lord's shrine,<verse eid="HAG 2:15"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:16"/>who you were; when you threw twenty sata<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew 1 seah = ca. 7 liters</char></note> of barley into the grain bin and it became ten sata<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew 1 seah = ca. 7 liters</char></note> of barley, and you entered the wine vat to draw fifty measures<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek 1 metretes = ca. 22 liters</char></note> and they became twenty.<verse eid="HAG 2:16"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:17"/>I struck you with dearth and wind-damage, and all the works of your hands with hail, and you did not return to me, says the Lord.<verse eid="HAG 2:17"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:18"/>Subject now your hearts from this day forward; from the twenty-fourth of the ninth month, even from the day when the Lord's shrine was founded, place it in your hearts,<verse eid="HAG 2:18"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:19"/>whether still there will be anything recognized on the threshing floor and whether still the vine and the fig and the pomegranate and the trees of the olive that fail to bear fruit will be recognized<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'will be recognized':  Lacking in Greek</char></note>; from this day on I will bless you.<verse eid="HAG 2:19"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:20"/>And a word of the Lord came a second time to the prophet Haggaios on the twenty-fourth of the month, saying:<verse eid="HAG 2:20"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:21"/>Say to Zorobabel the son of Salathiel, from the tribe of Ioudas, saying, I am shaking the sky and the earth and the sea and the dry land,<verse eid="HAG 2:21"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:22"/>and I will overthrow thrones of kings and destroy power of kings of the nations and overthrow chariots and riders, and the horses and their riders will descend each one with a sword against his brother.<verse eid="HAG 2:22"/>

<verse sid="HAG 2:23"/>On that day, says the Lord Almighty, I will take you, O Zorobabel the son of Salathiel, my slave, says the Lord, and I will make you like a signet, for I have chosen you, says the Lord Almighty.<verse eid="HAG 2:23"/>
</_X_chapter></_X_book></_X_usx>