<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<_X_usx version="2.0">
<para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
<_X_book code="JER">





<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 1">
<verse sid="JER 1:1"/>The dictum of God which came to Ieremias the son of Chelkias of the priests, who was living in Anathoth in the land of Beniamin;<verse eid="JER 1:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:2"/>a word of God which came to him in the days of King Iosias son of Amos of Iouda, in the thirteenth year of his reign.<verse eid="JER 1:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:3"/>And it came in the days of King Ioakim son of Iosias of Iouda, until the eleventh year of King Sedekias son of Iosias of Iouda, until the captivity of Ierousalem in the fifth month.<verse eid="JER 1:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:4"/>And a word of the Lord came to him, saying<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = Omit</char></note>,<verse eid="JER 1:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:5"/>"Before I formed you in the belly, I knew you, and before you came forth from the womb, I had consecrated you; a prophet to nations I had made you."<verse eid="JER 1:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:6"/>And I said, "You That Are, Sovereign, Lord! Behold, I do not know how to speak, because I am rather young."<verse eid="JER 1:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:7"/>And the Lord said to me, "Do not say, 'I am rather young,' because you shall go to all to whom I send you, and you shall speak according to all I command you.<verse eid="JER 1:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:8"/>Do not be afraid before them, because I am with you to deliver you, says the Lord."<verse eid="JER 1:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:9"/>And the Lord stretched out his hand to me and touched my mouth, and the Lord said to me, "Behold, I have given my words to your mouth.<verse eid="JER 1:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:10"/>Behold, today I have appointed you over nations and over kingdoms, to uproot and to pull down and to destroy and to rebuild and to plant.<verse eid="JER 1:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:11"/>And a word of the Lord came to me, saying, "Ieremiasa, what do you see?" And I said, "A staff of nut wood."<verse eid="JER 1:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:12"/>And the Lord said to me, "You have seen well, for I am watchful over my words to perform them."<verse eid="JER 1:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:13"/>And a word of the Lord came to me a second time, saying, "What do you see?" And I said, "A cauldron being heated, and its face<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'opening'</char></note> is from the north."<verse eid="JER 1:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:14"/>And the Lord said to me: From the face of the north evil shall flare up against all the inhabitants of the land,<verse eid="JER 1:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:15"/>for behold, I am summoning all the kingdoms from the north of the earth, says the Lord, and they shall come, and they shall set, each his throne against the entrances of the gates of Ierousalem and against all its surrounding walls and against all the cities of Iouda.<verse eid="JER 1:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:16"/>And I will speak to them with judgment about all their wickedness, how they forsook me and burned incense to foreign gods and did obeisance to the works of their own hands.<verse eid="JER 1:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:17"/>And you, gird up your loins, and stand up, and tell them everything that I command you. Do not be afraid by their presence, nor be terrified before them, because I am with you to deliver you, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 1:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:18"/>Behold, I have made you in this very day like a strong city and like a strong bronze wall, to all the kings of Iouda and its rulers and the people of the land.<verse eid="JER 1:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 1:19"/>And they will fight you, and they shall not prevail against you, for I am with you to deliver you, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 1:19"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 2">
<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 2:1"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 2:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:2"/>And he said, This is what the Lord says: I remembered the mercy of your youth and the love of your growing up, how you followed the holy one of Israel, says the Lord. and the love of your growing up, how you followed the holy one of Israel, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 2:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:3"/>[Israel was holy to the Lord,] the firstfruit of his products. All who eat him will err; evil will come upon them, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 2:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:4"/>Hear a word of the Lord, O house of Iakob and the whole paternal family of the house of Israel.<verse eid="JER 2:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:5"/>This is what the Lord says: What error did your fathers find in me that they stood far from me and went after worthless things and became worthless themselves?<verse eid="JER 2:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:6"/>And they did not say, "Where is the Lord who brought us up out of the land of Egypt, who led us in the wilderness, in a land boundless and trackless, in a land waterless and fruitless, in a land that nothing passed in it and no person settled there?"<verse eid="JER 2:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:7"/>And I brought you into Carmel that you eat its fruit and its good things. And you entered, and you defiled my land and made my heritage an abomination.<verse eid="JER 2:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:8"/>The priests did not say, "Where is the Lord?" and those who hold fast to the law did not know me, and the shepherds would act impiously toward me, and the prophets would prophesy by the goddess Baal and went after what does not profit.<verse eid="JER 2:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:9"/>Therefore once more I will go to law with you, says the Lord. and I will go to law with your sons' sons,<verse eid="JER 2:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:10"/>for cross to islands of Chettiim and see, and send to Kedar and examine with care, and see if such things have happened:<verse eid="JER 2:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:11"/>Will nations change their gods? And these are no gods. But my people have changed their glory for one from which they will not profit.<verse eid="JER 2:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:12"/>The sky was appalled at this and shuddered more and more, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 2:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:13"/>because my people in fact committed two evils: they forsook me, fountain of living water, and they dug out cracked cisterns for themselves that will not be able to hold water.<verse eid="JER 2:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:14"/>Surely Israel is not a slave or a homebred one? Why has he become plunder?<verse eid="JER 2:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:15"/>Lions would roar against him and gave forth their voice, who turned his land into a wilderness, and his cities were torn down, to the point that they are not inhabited.<verse eid="JER 2:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:16"/>And sons of Memphis and Taphnas knew you and used to mock you.<verse eid="JER 2:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:17"/>(17) Has not your abandoning of me brought about these things for you? (17) says the Lord, your God.<verse eid="JER 2:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:18"/>And now, what do you have to do with the road to Egypt, to drink the water of Geon? And what do you have to do with the road to the Assyrians, to drink the water of rivers?<verse eid="JER 2:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:19"/>Your apostasy will discipline you, and your wickedness will convict you. Both know and see that it is bitter for you to forsake me, says the Lord, your God, and I took no pleasure in you, says the Lord, your God.<verse eid="JER 2:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:20"/>because long ago you shattered your yoke and burst your bonds, and you said, "I will not be a slave, but I will go on every high hill and under every shady tree; there I will sprawl in my whoredom."<verse eid="JER 2:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:21"/>Yet I planted you as a fruitful vine, from pure stock. How did you turn to bitterness, you foreign vine?<verse eid="JER 2:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:22"/>Though you wash yourself with nitre and multiply herbs<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'with medicinal qualities'</char></note> for yourself, you have become stained by your injustices before me, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 2:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:23"/>How will you say, "I was not defiled, and I did not go after the goddess Baal"? Look at your ways in the common burial place and know what you did. Her voice cried out in the evening.<verse eid="JER 2:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:24"/>She widened her ways to the waters of the wilderness; she was wind-borne<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'wind-borne':  Possibly 'inspired'</char></note> by the cravings of her soul. She was handed over. Who will turn her back? None who seek her will toil hard; in her humiliation they will find her.<verse eid="JER 2:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:25"/>Turn your foot from a rough way and your throat from thirst. But she said, "I will play the man," because she had loved foreigners and would go after them.<verse eid="JER 2:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:26"/>Like a thief's shame when he is caught, so the sons of Israel shall be shamed, they and their kings and their rulers and their priests and their prophets.<verse eid="JER 2:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:27"/>They said to the tree, "You are my father," and to the stone, "You gave me birth." And they turned backs to me, and not their faces. And in the time of their trouble they will say, "Rise up, and save us!"<verse eid="JER 2:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:28"/>And where are your gods that you made for yourself, if they will rise up and save you in your time of trouble?-- because according to the number of your cities were your gods, O Iouda, and according to the number of Ierousalem's streets they were sacrificing to the goddess Baal.<verse eid="JER 2:28"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:29"/>Why do you speak to me? You all acted impiously, and you all acted lawlessly against me, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 2:29"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:30"/>In vain I have struck your children; discipline you did not accept. A dagger devoured your prophets like a ravening lion, and you did not fear.<verse eid="JER 2:30"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:31"/>Hear a word of the Lord! This is what the Lord says: Surely I have not become a wilderness to Israel or a dried-out land? Why did my people say, "We will not be ruled, and we will come to you no more"?<verse eid="JER 2:31"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:32"/>Surely a bride will not forget her adornment, and a virgin her breast band? Yet my people forgot me, days without number.<verse eid="JER 2:32"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:33"/>Why is it that you will take exceptional care in your ways to seek affection? Not so, but in fact you acted wickedly to defile your ways.<verse eid="JER 2:33"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:34"/>Also on your hands was found blood of innocent souls. I did not find them in trenches but at every oak.<verse eid="JER 2:34"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:35"/>And you said, "I am innocent; only let his anger be turned from me." Behold, I am going to law with you for saying, "I did not sin."<verse eid="JER 2:35"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:36"/>Whatever did you greatly despise so as to repeat your ways? And you shall be put to shame by Egypt as you were put to shame by Assour,<verse eid="JER 2:36"/>

<verse sid="JER 2:37"/>because also from there you will come away, and your hands will be on your head, because the Lord has rejected your hope, and you will not prosper through it.<verse eid="JER 2:37"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 3">
<verse sid="JER 3:1"/>If a man dismisses his wife and she goes from him and becomes another man's, surely, if she returns, she will not return any more to him? Surely when she becomes polluted, that woman will be polluted? And you have played the whore with many shepherds, and would you return to me? says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 3:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:2"/>Raise your eyes straight ahead, and see! Where have you not been contaminated? By the ways you have sat for them like a desolate crow. And you polluted the land with your whoring and wickedness.<verse eid="JER 3:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:3"/>And you had many shepherds as an obstacle to yourself; you got a harlot's look; you behaved shamelessly toward all.<verse eid="JER 3:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:4"/>Did you not, as it were, call me Home and Father and Originator of your maidenhood?<verse eid="JER 3:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:5"/>Surely, it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'maidenhood'</char></note> will not remain forever, nor will it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'maidenhood'</char></note> be maintained to victory? Behold, you spoke, and you did these evils, and you prevailed.<verse eid="JER 3:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:6"/>And the Lord said to me in the days of King Iosias: Have you seen what the settlement<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'colony'</char></note> of Israel did to me? They went to every high mountain and under every woodland tree and played the whore there.<verse eid="JER 3:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:7"/>And I said after she did all these things, "Return to me," but she did not return, and faithless Iouda saw her faithlessness.<verse eid="JER 3:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:8"/>And I saw that for everything in which the settlement<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'colony'</char></note> of Israel was caught, [in which she committed adultery], and I sent her away and gave her a document of dismissal, and faithless Iouda did not fear, but she too went and played the whore.<verse eid="JER 3:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:9"/>And her whoredom came to nothing, and she committed adultery with tree and stone.<verse eid="JER 3:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:10"/>And in all these things faithless Iouda did not return to me with her whole heart, but only in pretense.<verse eid="JER 3:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:11"/>And the Lord said to me: Israel has justified his soul vis-à-vis faithless Iouda.<verse eid="JER 3:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:12"/>Go, and read these words toward the north, and you will say: Return to me, settlement<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'colony'</char></note> of Israel, says the Lord, and I will not set my face against you, because merciful am I, says the Lord, and I will not cherish wrath against you forever.<verse eid="JER 3:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:13"/>Only acknowledge your injustice, that you acted impiously against the Lord your God and poured out your ways to foreigners under every woodland tree, but you did not obey my voice, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 3:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:14"/>Return, O apostate sons, says the Lord, for I will be your lord, and I will take you, one from a city and two from a paternal family, and I will bring you into Sion.<verse eid="JER 3:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:15"/>And I will give you shepherds after my own heart, and in shepherding they will shepherd you with skill.<verse eid="JER 3:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:16"/>And it will be, if you multiply and increase in the land, in those days, says the Lord, they shall no longer say, "Ark of the covenant of the holy one of Israel." It shall not come up in the heart; it shall not be named nor be considered, and it shall not be made again.<verse eid="JER 3:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:17"/>In those days and at that time they shall call Ierousalem "The Lord's throne," and all the nations shall be gathered into her, and they shall no longer walk after the notions of their own evil heart.<verse eid="JER 3:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:18"/>In those days the house of Iouda shall join the house of Israel, and they shall come to the same place from a land of the north and from all the countries to the land that I gave their fathers for a heritage.<verse eid="JER 3:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:19"/>And I said, "May it be, O Lord," because I will make you as children and will give you a choice land as a heritage of God Almighty of nations and I said, "You will call me Father and will not be turned away from me."<verse eid="JER 3:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:20"/>Instead, as a woman is faithless toward her mate, so the house of Israel was faithless toward me, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 3:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:21"/>From lips was heard a voice of weeping and of pleading of Israel's sons, because they did wrong in their ways, they forgot their holy God.<verse eid="JER 3:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:22"/>Return, O sons who are given to turning, and I will heal your fractures. "We here will be yours, because you are the Lord, our God.<verse eid="JER 3:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:23"/>Truly the hills and the power of the mountains were a delusion, but through the Lord, our God, is the salvation of Israel.<verse eid="JER 3:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:24"/>"But from our youth Shame has devoured the labors of our fathers, their sheep and their bull calves and their sons and their daughters.<verse eid="JER 3:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 3:25"/>We lay down in our shame, and our dishonor covered us; for we have sinned against our God, we and our fathers, from our youth until this day, and we have not obeyed the voice of the Lord our God."<verse eid="JER 3:25"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 4">
<verse sid="JER 4:1"/>If Israel returns, says the Lord, to me he shall return, if he removes his abominations from his mouth and shows reverence because of my presence<verse eid="JER 4:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:2"/>and if he swears, "The Lord lives!" with truth in judgment and in uprightness, nations shall also bless in him, and in him they shall praise God in Ierousalem,<verse eid="JER 4:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:3"/>because this is what the Lord says to the men of Iouda and to the inhabitants of Ierousalem: Renew for yourselves what has been made new, and do not sow among thorns.<verse eid="JER 4:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:4"/>Be circumcised to your God, and remove the foreskin of your heart, O men of Iouda and inhabitants of Ierousalem, or else my anger goes forth like fire and will blaze forth, and there will be no one to quench because of the evil of your doings.<verse eid="JER 4:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:5"/>Declare in Iouda, and let it be heard in Ierou-salem; say: Give a sign with a trumpet in the land, and cry greatly; say: "Gather together, and let us enter into the walled cities!"<verse eid="JER 4:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:6"/>Take up, and flee to Sion; hurry, do not stop, because I am bringing evil from the north, and a great destruction.<verse eid="JER 4:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:7"/>A lion has gone up from its lair; an utter destroyer of nations has set out, and he has gone out from his place to make the land a desolation, and cities will be ruined, to the point they are not inhabited.<verse eid="JER 4:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:8"/>For these things put on sackcloth, and lament and wail, for the anger of the Lord has not turned away from us.<verse eid="JER 4:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:9"/>And it shall be on that day, says the Lord, that the heart of the king shall perish, and the heart of the rulers, and the priests shall be amazed, and the prophets astounded.<verse eid="JER 4:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:10"/>And I said, "You That Are, O Sovereign, Lord! So then, when misleading you misled this people and Ierousalem, saying, 'There shall be peace.' And behold, the dagger reached as far as their life."<verse eid="JER 4:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:11"/>At that time they will say to this people and to Ierousalem: There is a spirit of wandering in the wilderness, a way of the daughter of my people not to what is clean nor to what is holy.<verse eid="JER 4:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:12"/>A spirit of filling<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'satisfaction'</char></note> will come to me, but now I speak judgments against them.<verse eid="JER 4:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:13"/>Behold, he will come up like a cloud, and his chariots like a whirlwind; his horses are swifter than eagles-- woe to us, because we are wretched.<verse eid="JER 4:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:14"/>O Ierousalem, wash your heart of wickedness so that you may be saved. How long are thoughts of your trouble within you?--<verse eid="JER 4:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:15"/>for a voice of one declaring will come from Dan, and trouble will be heard from Mount Ephraim.<verse eid="JER 4:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:16"/>Remind nations, "Behold, they have come!" Proclaim in Ierousalem, "Bands come from a land far away, and they gave forth their voice against the cities of Iouda.<verse eid="JER 4:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:17"/>They came against her all round like watchers of a field, because you neglected me, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 4:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:18"/>Your ways and your doings have done these things to you. This is your wickedness, because it is bitter, because it reached your heart."<verse eid="JER 4:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:19"/>My belly, I feel pain in my belly and in the faculties of my heart. My soul quivers with excitement! My heart is beating wildly; I cannot keep silent, because my soul heard a trumpet sound, a cry of war.<verse eid="JER 4:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:20"/>And distress calls upon disaster, because the whole land has become distressed. Suddenly the tent has become distressed, my skins torn up.<verse eid="JER 4:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:21"/>How long will I see people fleeing, while I hear the sound of trumpets?--<verse eid="JER 4:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:22"/>"for the leaders of my people did not know me; they are stupid sons, and they have no understanding. They are skilled in doing evil but did not know how to do good."<verse eid="JER 4:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:23"/>I looked on the earth, and behold, there was nothing, and to the sky, and it had no lights.<verse eid="JER 4:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:24"/>I saw the mountains, and they were trembling, and all the hills were being disturbed.<verse eid="JER 4:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:25"/>I looked, and behold, there was no human, and all the birds of the air were being terrified.<verse eid="JER 4:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:26"/>I saw, and behold, Carmel was a wilderness, and all the cities burned up before the Lord, and before the wrath of his anger they were annihilated.<verse eid="JER 4:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:27"/>This is what the Lord says: The whole land shall be a wilderness; yet I will not make a full end.<verse eid="JER 4:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:28"/>For these things let the earth mourn, and let the sky above grow black, for I have spoken, and I will not repent; I rushed out, and I will not turn back from it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:28</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the earth'</char></note>.<verse eid="JER 4:28"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:29"/>At the noise of horseman and bent bow every country withdrew; they crawled into the caves, and they hid in groves, and they climbed upon rocks; every city was forsaken; no person lives in them.<verse eid="JER 4:29"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:30"/>And you, what will you do if you dress in scarlet and you deck yourself with gold ornaments and if you anoint your eyes with antimony? In vain is your adorning. Your lovers rejected you; they will seek your soul,<verse eid="JER 4:30"/>

<verse sid="JER 4:31"/>because I heard a sound of your groaning, as of one in labor, as of one bringing forth her first child; the sound of daughter Sion will be dissolved, and she will let fall her hands; "Woe is me, for my soul is failing for those killed!"<verse eid="JER 4:31"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 5">
<verse sid="JER 5:1"/>Run about in the streets of Ierousalem, and see, and take note, and search in its squares, if there be found one who practices justice and seeks faithfulness, and I will be gracious to them, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 5:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:2"/>They say, "The Lord lives." Are they therefore not swearing lies?<verse eid="JER 5:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:3"/>O Lord, your eyes-- are they not on faithfulness? You have struck them, but they were not in trouble; you have consumed them, but they did not want to take correction. They have made their faces harder than rock, and they did not want to turn back.<verse eid="JER 5:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:4"/>And I said, "Perhaps they are poor; that's why they were not able, because they did not know the way of the Lord and divine judgment."<verse eid="JER 5:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:5"/>I will go to the prominent and speak to them, because they were acquainted with the way of the Lord and divine judgment, and behold, they all alike had broken the yoke; they had burst the bonds.<verse eid="JER 5:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:6"/>Therefore a lion from the forest struck them, and a wolf right up to the houses destroyed them, and a leopard watched against their cities; all who go out of them shall be hunted-- because they multiplied their impieties, they prevailed in their digressions.<verse eid="JER 5:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:7"/>For which of these should I be merciful to you? Your sons have forsaken me and would swear by those who are no gods. And I fed them, and they were committing adultery and would lodge in houses of prostitutes.<verse eid="JER 5:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:8"/>They were lusty stallions, each neighing for his fellow's wife.<verse eid="JER 5:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:9"/>Surely I shall not fail to visit for these things? says the Lord, or shall my soul not take vengeance on such a nation?<verse eid="JER 5:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:10"/>Go up upon her battlements, and raze, but do not make a full end; leave behind her under-props, because they are the Lord's,<verse eid="JER 5:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:11"/>because in breaking faith, the house of Israel and the house of Iouda broke faith with me.<verse eid="JER 5:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:12"/>They lied to their Lord and said, "These things are not so. No evil will come upon us, and we shall not see dagger and famine.<verse eid="JER 5:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:13"/>Our prophets became wind, and a word of the Lord was not in them. Thus shall it be to them!"<verse eid="JER 5:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:14"/>Therefore this is what the Lord Almighty says: Because you spoke this utterance, behold, I have given my words in your mouth as a fire and this people as wood, and it shall devour them.<verse eid="JER 5:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:15"/>Behold, I am bringing upon you a nation from far away, O house of Israel, says the Lord, a nation [the sound of] whose language you will not understand.<verse eid="JER 5:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:16"/>All are strong,<verse eid="JER 5:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:17"/>and they shall devour your harvest and your food, and they shall devour your sons and your daughters, and they shall devour your sheep and your bull calves, and they shall devour your vineyards and your fig groves and your olive groves, and they shall thresh by sword your fortified cities in which you trust in them.<verse eid="JER 5:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:18"/>And it shall be in those days, says the Lord, your<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = singular</char></note> God, I will not make a full end of you.<verse eid="JER 5:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:19"/>And it shall be when you say, "Why has the Lord our God done all these things to us?" then you shall say to them, "Because you were a slave to foreign gods in your land, so you shall be a slave to foreigners in a land that is not yours."<verse eid="JER 5:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:20"/>Declare these things to the house of Iakob, and let it be heard in Iouda:<verse eid="JER 5:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:21"/>Do hear these things, O foolish and heartless people; eyes they have and do not see, ears they have and do not hear.<verse eid="JER 5:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:22"/>Will you not fear me? says the Lord, or will you not show reverence before me who sets sand as boundary for the sea? A perpetual ordinance, and it will not transgress it, and it will toss and will not be able, and its waves will roar, and it will not transgress it.<verse eid="JER 5:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:23"/>But this people had a noncompliant and disobedient heart; they have turned aside and gone away.<verse eid="JER 5:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:24"/>And they did not say in their heart, "Do let us fear the Lord our God, who gives us rain, early rain and late rain, according to the season of the satisfaction of the ordinance of harvesting, and he kept it for us."<verse eid="JER 5:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:25"/>Your acts of lawlessness have turned these away, and your sins have distanced good things from you,<verse eid="JER 5:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:26"/>because impious ones were found among my people, and they set traps to ruin men, and they would catch them.<verse eid="JER 5:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:27"/>As a trap, when set up, is full of birds, so their houses are full of treachery; therefore they have become great and rich,<verse eid="JER 5:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:28"/>and they transgressed justice, they did not judge the cause of the orphan, and the cause of the widow they would not judge.<verse eid="JER 5:28"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:29"/>Surely I shall not fail to visit for these things? says the Lord. or shall my soul not take vengeance on such a nation?<verse eid="JER 5:29"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:30"/>Astonishment and horrible things have occurred in the land:<verse eid="JER 5:30"/>

<verse sid="JER 5:31"/>the prophets prophesy what is wrong, and the priests seized with their hands, and my people loved to have it so. And what will you do hereafter?<verse eid="JER 5:31"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 6">
<verse sid="JER 6:1"/>Prevail, O sons of Beniamin, from the midst of Ierousalem! And in Thekoue signal with the trumpet, and over Baiththacharma raise a signal, because evil has popped up from the north and it is becoming a great destruction.<verse eid="JER 6:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:2"/>And your loftiness, O daughter Sion, shall be removed.<verse eid="JER 6:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:3"/>Shepherds and their flocks shall come into her. And they shall pitch tents at her all around, and they shall pasture, each with his hand.<verse eid="JER 6:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:4"/>"Prepare for war against her; rise up, and let us go up against her at noon!" "Woe to us, for the day has declined, because the shadows of the evening fail!"<verse eid="JER 6:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:5"/>"Rise up, and let us go up by night and destroy her foundations!"--<verse eid="JER 6:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:6"/>because this is what the Lord says: Cut down her trees; pour out a force against Ierousalem. Ah false city, there is nothing but oppression within her.<verse eid="JER 6:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:7"/>As a cistern keeps water fresh, so she keeps fresh her wickedness; impiety and distress will be heard within her, before her always. With toil and whip<verse eid="JER 6:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:8"/>you will be disciplined, O Ierousalem, lest my soul stand away from you, lest I make you an untrodden land which will not be inhabited,<verse eid="JER 6:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:9"/>because this is what the Lord says: Glean, glean like a vine the remnants of Israel; turn back like the grape gatherer to his basket.<verse eid="JER 6:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:10"/>To whom should I speak and give warning, and he will hear? Behold, their ears are uncircumcised, and they cannot hear. Behold, the dictum of the Lord was to them an object of scorn; they will not want it at all.<verse eid="JER 6:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:11"/>And I filled my anger, and I held back and did not finish them. I will pour it out on infants outside and on a gathering of young men as well, because husband and wife shall be seized, an older person with fullness of days.<verse eid="JER 6:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:12"/>And their houses shall be turned over to others, fields and their wives together, because I will stretch out my hand against the inhabitants of this land, says the Lord,<verse eid="JER 6:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:13"/>because from their small even to their great, all carried out lawless deeds; from priest even to pseudo-prophet, all produced lies.<verse eid="JER 6:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:14"/>And they were doctoring the fracture of my people with contempt and saying, "Peace, peace," and where is peace?<verse eid="JER 6:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:15"/>They were put to shame, because they failed; yet they were not ashamed like people being put to shame, and they did not know their disgrace. Therefore they shall fall in their fall, and they shall perish in a time of visitation, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 6:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:16"/>This is what the Lord says: Stand at the roads, and see, and ask for the ancient paths of the Lord, and see what the good way is, and walk in it, and you will find purification for your souls. And they said, "We will not walk in it."<verse eid="JER 6:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:17"/>I have appointed sentinels for you: "Hear the sound of the trumpet!" And they said, "We will not hear."<verse eid="JER 6:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:18"/>Therefore, the nations heard, and those that were shepherding their flocks.<verse eid="JER 6:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:19"/>Hear, O earth; behold, I am bringing evil on this people, the fruit of their turning away, because they did not hold on to my words and they rejected my law.<verse eid="JER 6:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:20"/>Why do you bring me frankincense from Saba and cinnamon from a land far away? Your whole burnt offerings are not acceptable, and your sacrifices did not gratify me.<verse eid="JER 6:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:21"/>Therefore this is what the Lord says: Behold, I am giving to this people weakness, and they shall be weak with it, fathers and sons together; a neighbor and his fellow shall perish.<verse eid="JER 6:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:22"/>This is what the Lord says: Behold, a people is coming from the north, and nations will stir from the farthest part of the earth.<verse eid="JER 6:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:23"/>They will grasp bow and spear; bold it is and will show no mercy; its sound is like a roaring sea; on horses and chariots it will draw up in battle order like a fire, for battle against you, O daughter Sion!<verse eid="JER 6:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:24"/>"We have heard news of them; our hands fell helpless; anguish took hold of us, pains as of one giving birth.<verse eid="JER 6:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:25"/>Do not go out into a field, and do not walk on the roads, because a sword of the enemies sojourns on every side."<verse eid="JER 6:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:26"/>O daughter of my people, put on sackcloth; sprinkle with ashes; make for yourself a mourning for a beloved, a most pitiable lamentation: because suddenly distress will come upon us.<verse eid="JER 6:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:27"/>I have given you as a tester<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:27</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'a tester':  Or 'one tested'</char></note> among tested peoples, and you will know me when I test their way.<verse eid="JER 6:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:28"/>All are noncompliant, going about with slanders; bronze and iron, all of them have been corrupted.<verse eid="JER 6:28"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:29"/>Bellows failed from a fire; lead failed; in vain does a silversmith coin silver; their wickedness did not melt.<verse eid="JER 6:29"/>

<verse sid="JER 6:30"/>Call them "rejected silver," because the Lord has rejected them.<verse eid="JER 6:30"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 7">
<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 7:1"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 7:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:2"/>Hear a word of the Lord, all Judea.<verse eid="JER 7:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:3"/>This is what the Lord, the God of Israel says: Amend your ways and your doings, and I will cause you to dwell in this place.<verse eid="JER 7:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:4"/>Do not trust in yourselves with deceptive words, because they will not benefit you at all, when you say: "A shrine of the Lord, a shrine of the Lord it is."<verse eid="JER 7:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:5"/>Because if in amending, you amend your ways and your doings, and in acting you act with justice between a man and between his fellow<verse eid="JER 7:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:6"/>and do not oppress guest and orphan and widow and do not shed innocent blood in this place and do not go after foreign gods to your own hurt,<verse eid="JER 7:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:7"/>I will also cause you to dwell in this place, in the land that I gave of old to your fathers and forever.<verse eid="JER 7:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:8"/>But if you trust in deceptive words, whereby you will not benefit,<verse eid="JER 7:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:9"/>and murder and commit adultery and steal and swear wrongly and offer incense to the goddess Baal and go after foreign gods that you do not know,<verse eid="JER 7:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:10"/>so that it be ill for you, and if you came and stood before me in the house, where my name has been called on it, and you said, "We have kept away from doing all these abominations"--<verse eid="JER 7:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:11"/>surely my house, there where my name has been called on it, has not become a den of robbers before you? And I, behold, I have seen it, says the Lord,<verse eid="JER 7:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:12"/>because go to my place which was in Selo, there where I made my name encamp formerly, and see what I did to it because of the wickedness of my people Israel.<verse eid="JER 7:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:13"/>And now, because you have done all these deeds and I spoke to you and you did not hear me and I called you and you did not answer,<verse eid="JER 7:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:14"/>I will also do to the house, where my name is called on it, in which you trust in it, and to the place that I gave to you and to your fathers, just what I did to Selo.<verse eid="JER 7:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:15"/>And I will cast out you from before me, just as I cast out your kinsfolk, all the offspring of Ephraim.<verse eid="JER 7:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:16"/>And as for you, do not keep praying about this people, and do not request to petition about them, and do not keep making vows, and do not approach me concerning them, because I will not listen.<verse eid="JER 7:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:17"/>Or do you not see what they themselves are doing in the cities of Iouda and in the streets of Ierousalem?<verse eid="JER 7:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:18"/>Their sons gather wood, and their fathers burn a fire, and their women knead dough to make cakes for the host of the sky, and they poured out libations to foreign gods in order to provoke me to anger.<verse eid="JER 7:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:19"/>Are they not provoking me? says the Lord. Is it not themselves so that their faces may be ashamed?<verse eid="JER 7:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:20"/>Therefore this is what the Lord says: Behold, my wrath and anger are being poured on this place, both on human beings and on animals and on every tree of the field and on the produce of the ground, and it will burn and not be quenched.<verse eid="JER 7:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:21"/>This is what the Lord says: Gather your whole burnt offerings with your sacrifices, and eat meat,<verse eid="JER 7:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:22"/>because in the day that I brought your fathers up out of the land of Egypt, I did not speak to them and did not command them concerning whole burnt offerings and sacrifices.<verse eid="JER 7:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:23"/>But this dictum I commanded them, saying, "Obey my voice, and I will become a god to you, and you shall become a people to me, and walk in all my ways, which I command you, so that it may be well with you."<verse eid="JER 7:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:24"/>And they did not obey me, and they did not turn their ear, but they walked by the notions of their evil heart, and they became backward and not forward.<verse eid="JER 7:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:25"/>From the day that their fathers came out of the land of Egypt even until this day, I have also sent out all my slaves the prophets to you by day, and early in the morning I also sent,<verse eid="JER 7:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:26"/>and they did not obey me, and they did not turn their ear, and they stiffened their necks worse than their fathers.<verse eid="JER 7:26"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 7:27"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:27</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 7:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:28"/>And you shall speak this word to them: This is the nation that did not obey the voice of the Lord and did not accept discipline; faithfulness has failed from their mouth.<verse eid="JER 7:28"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:29"/>Shear your head, and throw away<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:29</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the hair'</char></note>, and take a lamentation on your lips, because the Lord has discarded and rejected the generation that did these things,<verse eid="JER 7:29"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:30"/>because the sons of Iouda have done evil<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:30</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'the wicked'</char></note> before me, says the Lord; they have arrayed their abominations in the house where my name is called on it, to defile it.<verse eid="JER 7:30"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:31"/>And they built the altar<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:31</char><char closed="false" style="ft">e'ed' dGk = bômos</char></note> of Tapheth, which is in the valley of Hennom's son, to burn their sons and their daughters with fire-- which I did not command them, and I did not intend it in my heart.<verse eid="JER 7:31"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:32"/>Therefore, behold, days are coming, says the Lord, and they shall no longer say Altar<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:32</char><char closed="false" style="ft">e'ed' dGk = bômos</char></note> of Tapheth and Valley of Hennom's Son, but Valley of the Slain, and they will bury in Tapheth, because there is no room.<verse eid="JER 7:32"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:33"/>And the corpses of this people will be food for the birds of the air and for the animals of the earth, and there will not be one to frighten them away.<verse eid="JER 7:33"/>

<verse sid="JER 7:34"/>And I will abolish a sound of people making mirth and a sound of people rejoicing, a voice of bridegroom and a voice of bride from the cities of Iouda and from the streets of Ierousalem, because all the land shall become a desolation.<verse eid="JER 7:34"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 8">
<verse sid="JER 8:1"/>At that time, says the Lord, they shall bring the bones of the kings of Iouda and the bones of its rulers and the bones of the priests and the bones of the prophets and the bones of the inhabitants of Ierousalem out of their tombs,<verse eid="JER 8:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:2"/>and they shall air them to the sun and to the moon [and to all the stars] and to all the host of the sky, which things they have loved and been slaves to and which they have followed after them and which they have clung to and which they did obeisance to them. They shall not be mourned and shall not be buried, and they shall be an example on the surface of the ground,<verse eid="JER 8:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:3"/>because they chose death over life, even for all the remnants that remain of that generation in every place, there where I have driven them--<verse eid="JER 8:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:4"/>because this is what the Lord says: He that falls, does he not rise up, and he that turns away, does he not return?<verse eid="JER 8:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:5"/>Why has my people turned away in a shameless turning away and were in the grip of their preference and did not want to return?<verse eid="JER 8:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:6"/>Do give ear, and hear. Will they not speak in this manner; "There is no person that repents of his wickedness, saying, 'What have I done?' " The runner stopped from his own course, like a sweating horse in his neighing.<verse eid="JER 8:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:7"/>Even the hasida<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'stork'</char></note> in the sky knew its time; turtledove and swallow, agour<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'thrush'?</char></note> [sparrows] observe the times of their arrival, but my people did not know the judgments of the Lord.<verse eid="JER 8:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:8"/>How will you say, "We are wise, and the law of the Lord is with us?" A false pen has become of no use to scribes.<verse eid="JER 8:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:9"/>Wise were put to shame and were terrified and caught, because they have discarded the word of the Lord. What wisdom is in them?<verse eid="JER 8:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:10"/>Therefore I will give their wives to others and their fields to heirs.<verse eid="JER 8:10"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 8:11"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 8:11"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 8:12"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 8:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:13"/>And they will gather their produce, says the Lord; there are no grapes on the vines, and there are no figs on the fig trees; even the leaves have fallen off.<verse eid="JER 8:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:14"/>For what do we sit still? Gather together, and let us go into the fortified cities and be cast out, because God has cast us out and has given us water with gall to drink, because we have sinned before him.<verse eid="JER 8:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:15"/>We gathered for peace, and there was no good, for a time of healing, and behold, exertion.<verse eid="JER 8:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:16"/>From Dan we will hear the sound of the speed of his horses; at the sound of the neighing of his cavalry the whole land quaked. And he will come and devour land and all that fills it, city and those who live in it.<verse eid="JER 8:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:17"/>For behold, I am sending out against you deadly snakes that cannot be charmed, and they shall bite you.<verse eid="JER 8:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:18"/>Incurable things with the pain of your puzzled heart.<verse eid="JER 8:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:19"/>Behold, a voice of the daughter of my people from a land far away: "Is the Lord not in Sion? Or is there no king there?"("Why have they provoked me to anger with their carved images) and with strange vanities?")<verse eid="JER 8:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:20"/>"Summer ended; harvest passed, and we were not saved."<verse eid="JER 8:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:21"/>Because of a fracture of the daughter of my people I was made dizzy<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'blind'</char></note>; dismay has taken hold of me, pains as one giving birth.<verse eid="JER 8:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 8:22"/>Is there no pine resin in Galaad, or is a physician not there? Why has the healing of the daughter of my people not come about?<verse eid="JER 8:22"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 9">
<verse sid="JER 9:1"/>Who will give my head water and my eyes a fountain of tears, and I shall bewail my people day and night, the slain of the daughter of my people?<verse eid="JER 9:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:2"/>Who would give me in the wilderness a remote lodging place, and I shall leave my people and go away from them? Because they all commit adultery, a band of faithless they are.<verse eid="JER 9:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:3"/>And they bent their tongue like a bow; falsehood and not faith grew strong in the land, because they proceeded from evil to evil, and me they did not know.<verse eid="JER 9:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:4"/>Each of you, beware of his fellow, and put no trust in their kin, because every brother will trip up with the heel and every friend will go around deceitfully.<verse eid="JER 9:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:5"/>Each will mock at his friend; truth they will never speak; their tongue has learned to speak lies; they committed injustice and did not pause so as to return.<verse eid="JER 9:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:6"/>Usury upon usury, deceit upon deceit! They did not want to know me.<verse eid="JER 9:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:7"/>Therefore this is what the Lord says: Behold, I will refine them and test them, because I will act in the face of the wickedness of the daughter of my people.<verse eid="JER 9:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:8"/>Their tongue is a wounding arrow; the words of their mouth are deceitful. He speaks peaceably to his fellow but inwardly has enmity.<verse eid="JER 9:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:9"/>Surely I shall not fail to visit for these things? says the Lord, or shall my soul not take vengeance on such a people?<verse eid="JER 9:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:10"/>Take up wailing for the mountains, and a lamentation regarding the paths of the wilderness, because they failed to the point that there are no people; they did not hear a sound of existence; from the birds of the air even to animals they departed; they went away.<verse eid="JER 9:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:11"/>And I will render Ierousalem a settlement of migrants and a lair of dragons, and I will make the cities of Iouda an annihilation, to the point that it is uninhabited.<verse eid="JER 9:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:12"/>Who is the intelligent person? Let him also understand this, and him to whom a word of the mouth of the Lord has come, let him declare it to you. For what reason did the land perish, was kindled like a wilderness, to the point that nothing passes through it?<verse eid="JER 9:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:13"/>And the Lord said to me: Because they forsook my law that I gave before them, they also have not obeyed my voice<verse eid="JER 9:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:14"/>but have gone after what pleases their own evil heart and after the idols, which their fathers taught them.<verse eid="JER 9:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:15"/>Therefore this is what the Lord, the God of Israel, says: Behold, I will feed them anguish and will give them water with gall to drink.<verse eid="JER 9:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:16"/>And I will scatter them among the nations [to] whom they and their fathers did not know, and I will send the dagger upon them until I have consumed them with it,<verse eid="JER 9:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:17"/>says the Lord. Call the mourning women, and let them come, and send for the skilled women, and let them speak loudly,<verse eid="JER 9:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:18"/>and let them raise a lament over us, and let our eyes bring down tears, and let our eyelids flow with water,<verse eid="JER 9:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:19"/>because a sound of pity was heard in Sion: "How we have suffered hardship! We were utterly shamed, because we have abandoned the land and we have cast down our quarters."<verse eid="JER 9:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:20"/>Do hear, O women, a divine word, and let your ears accept words of his mouth, and teach to your daughters a dirge, and a woman to her companion a lament<verse eid="JER 9:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:21"/>"because death has come up through our windows, has entered into our land, to destroy infants outside and young men from the squares.<verse eid="JER 9:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:22"/>And human corpses shall become an example upon the surface of the plain of the land, and like grass behind a mower, and there shall be no one to gather."<verse eid="JER 9:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:23"/>This is what the Lord says: Let not the wise boast in his wisdom, and let not the mighty boast in his might, and let not the wealthy boast in his wealth,<verse eid="JER 9:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:24"/>but let him who boasts boast in this: that he understands and knows that I am the Lord when I do mercy and justice and righteousness in the earth, because in these things is my will, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 9:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:25"/>Behold, days are coming, says the Lord, and I will visit on all circumcised their foreskin<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'uncircumcision'</char></note>:<verse eid="JER 9:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 9:26"/>on Egypt and on Judea and on Edom and on the sons of Ammon and on the sons of Moab and on every one who shaves all around what is on his face, those who live in the wilderness, because all the nations are uncircumcised in the flesh and all the house of Israel are uncircumcised in their heart.<verse eid="JER 9:26"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 10">
<verse sid="JER 10:1"/>Hear a word of the Lord that he spoke to you, O house of Israel.<verse eid="JER 10:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:2"/>This is what the Lord says: Do not learn according to the ways of the nations, and do not be afraid of the signs of the sky, because they are afraid of them to their faces<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'to their faces':  I.e. 'when they see them'</char></note>,<verse eid="JER 10:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:3"/>because the precepts of the nations are vain: there is a tree from the forest, cut down, a work of a craftsman, and a molten image.<verse eid="JER 10:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:4"/>They have been beautified with silver and gold; they fastened them with hammers and nails, and they shall not be moved.<verse eid="JER 10:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:5"/>Wrought silver it is-- they will not walk.<verse eid="JER 10:5"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 10:6"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 10:6"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 10:7"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 10:7"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 10:8"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 10:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:9"/>Beaten silver will come from Tharsis, gold of Mophas and a hand of goldsmiths-- works of craftsmen all; they will clothe them in blue and purple. (5b) Raised they will be carried, because they will not walk. Do not be afraid of them, because they shall not do evil, and there is no good in them.<verse eid="JER 10:9"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 10:10"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 10:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:11"/>Thus shall you say to them: Let gods who did not make the sky and the earth perish from the earth and from under this sky.<verse eid="JER 10:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:12"/>It is the Lord who made the earth by his strength, who set upright the world by his wisdom, and by his prudence he stretched out the sky,<verse eid="JER 10:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:13"/>and a quantity of water was in the sky, and he brought up clouds from the end of the earth. Lightnings he made into rain, and he brought out light from his storehouses.<verse eid="JER 10:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:14"/>Every person was stupid, apart from<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'apart from':  I.e. 'without'</char></note> knowledge; every goldsmith was put to shame at his carved images, because they<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'goldsmiths'</char></note> cast lies; there is no breath in them.<verse eid="JER 10:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:15"/>Worthless they are, works of mockery; at the time of their visitation they shall perish.<verse eid="JER 10:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:16"/>Such a portion is not Iakob's; because he who formed all things, he is his inheritance; the Lord is his name.<verse eid="JER 10:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:17"/>He gathered your substance from outside, when it was residing in choice places--<verse eid="JER 10:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:18"/>because this is what the Lord says: Behold, I am tripping up the inhabitants of this land with affliction so that your plague may be discovered.<verse eid="JER 10:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:19"/>Woe because of your fracture! Your plague is painful. So I said, "Truly this is my wound, and it seized me."<verse eid="JER 10:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:20"/>My tent endured hardship, and all my skins were torn; my sons and my sheep are no more; there is no longer a place for my tent, a place for my curtains.<verse eid="JER 10:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:21"/>Because the shepherds played the fool and did not seek out the Lord, therefore the whole pasture did not comprehend, and they were scattered.<verse eid="JER 10:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:22"/>A sound of a report! Behold, it is coming-- and a great commotion from a land of the north, to make the cities of Iouda an annihilation and a nesting place for sparrows.<verse eid="JER 10:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:23"/>I know, O Lord, that a human being's way is not his own, nor shall a man journey and direct his journey.<verse eid="JER 10:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:24"/>Correct us, O Lord, but in just measure and not in anger so that you may not make us few.<verse eid="JER 10:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 10:25"/>Pour out your anger on nations that do not know you and on generations that did not call on your name, because they have devoured Iakob and they have consumed him and his pasture they have made desolate.<verse eid="JER 10:25"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 11">
<verse sid="JER 11:1"/>The word that came from the Lord to Ieremias, saying:<verse eid="JER 11:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:2"/>Hear the words of this covenant. And you shall speak to the men of Iouda and to the inhabitants of Ierousalem.<verse eid="JER 11:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:3"/>And you shall say to them, This is what the Lord, the God of Israel, says: Cursed be the person who will not heed the words of this covenant,<verse eid="JER 11:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:4"/>which I commanded your fathers in the day that I brought them up out of the land of Egypt, out of the iron smelter, saying, Hear my voice, and do all that I command you. And you shall become a people to me, and I will become a god to you,<verse eid="JER 11:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:5"/>that I may establish my oath that I swore to your fathers, to give them a land flowing with milk and honey, as this day. And I answered and said, "May it be, Lord."<verse eid="JER 11:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:6"/>And the Lord said to me: Read these words in the cities of Iouda and outside of Ierousalem, saying: Hear the words of this covenant and do them.<verse eid="JER 11:6"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 11:7"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 11:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:8"/>And they did not.<verse eid="JER 11:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:9"/>And the Lord said to me: A bond of union was found among the men of Iouda and among the inhabitants of Ierousalem.<verse eid="JER 11:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:10"/>They have turned back to the injustices of their fathers of former times, who did not want to listen to my words, and behold, they are walking after foreign gods to be slaves to them, and the house of Israel and the house of Iouda have scattered the covenant that I made with their fathers.<verse eid="JER 11:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:11"/>Therefore, this is what the Lord says, Behold, I am bringing evil upon this people from which they will not be able to escape from it, and they will cry out to me, and I will not listen to them.<verse eid="JER 11:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:12"/>And the cities of Iouda and the inhabitants of Ierousalem will go and will cry out to the gods to whom they are burning incense to them. Surely, they will save them in the time of their troubles?--<verse eid="JER 11:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:13"/>because your gods were according to the number of your cities, O Iouda, and according to the number of exits of Ierousalem you have set up altars<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = bômos</char></note> to burn incense to the goddess Baal.<verse eid="JER 11:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:14"/>And as for you, do not keep praying for this people, and do not keep making a request with petition and prayer on their behalf, because I will not listen at the time they call to me in the time of their trouble.<verse eid="JER 11:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:15"/>Why has the beloved<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Ierousalem'</char></note> done an abomination in my house? Surely vows and holy flesh will not remove from you your wickedness, or will you escape by means of these things?<verse eid="JER 11:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:16"/>The Lord called your name a beautiful olive tree, well shaded in appearance; at the sound of its pruning<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'circumcision'</char></note> the affliction was great on you; its branches were rendered useless.<verse eid="JER 11:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:17"/>And the Lord, who planted you, pronounced evil against you, in return for the evil of the house of Israel and the house of Iouda, because they have done this to themselves to provoke me to anger by offering incense to the goddess Baal.<verse eid="JER 11:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:18"/>O Lord, make it known to me, and I will know; then I saw their doings.<verse eid="JER 11:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:19"/>But I, like an innocent lamb led to be slaughtered, did not know. They devised an evil scheme against me, saying, "Come, and let us throw wood into his bread, and let us wipe him out from the land of the living, and his name will no longer be remembered!"<verse eid="JER 11:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:20"/>O Lord, when you judge righteously, when you test kidneys<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'emotions'</char></note> and heart, may I see your avenging on them, because to you I have revealed my plea of right.<verse eid="JER 11:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:21"/>Therefore this is what the Lord says in reference to the men of Anathoth, who seek my soul, who say, "You shall not prophesy in the name of the Lord; otherwise you will die by our hands"--<verse eid="JER 11:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:22"/>Behold, I will visit upon them; their young men shall die by dagger, and their sons and their daughters shall come to their end by famine,<verse eid="JER 11:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 11:23"/>and there shall be no remnant of them, because I will bring evil upon the inhabitants of Anathoth, in the year of their visiting.<verse eid="JER 11:23"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 12">
<verse sid="JER 12:1"/>You are in the right, O Lord, because I will make my defense to you, but let me<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'let me':  Or 'I will'</char></note> speak of judgments to you. Why is it that the way of the impious prospers? Why did all who commit acts of faithlessness thrive?<verse eid="JER 12:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 12:2"/>You planted them, and they took root; they bred children and produced fruit; you are near to their mouths and far from their kidneys<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'emotions'</char></note>.<verse eid="JER 12:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 12:3"/>And you, O Lord, you know me; you have tested my heart before you. Purify them for a day of their slaughter!<verse eid="JER 12:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 12:4"/>How long will the land mourn, and all the grass of the field wither from the wickedness of those who live in it? Animals and birds were annihilated, because they said, "God will not see our ways."<verse eid="JER 12:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 12:5"/>Your feet are running, and they undo you; how will you prepare for horses? And you trusted in a land of peace; how will you fare in the roaring of the Jordan?--<verse eid="JER 12:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 12:6"/>because even your kinsfolk and the household of your father, even they have dealt faithlessly with you; they too shouted; they were gathered behind you; do not believe them, because they will speak good things to you.<verse eid="JER 12:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 12:7"/>I have forsaken my house; I have let go of my heritage; I have given my beloved soul into the hands of her enemies.<verse eid="JER 12:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 12:8"/>My heritage has become to me like a lion in a forest; she has given forth her voice against me-- therefore I hated her.<verse eid="JER 12:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 12:9"/>Surely my heritage is not a hyena's cave to me or a cave all around her? Go, assemble all the animals of the field, and let them come to eat her.<verse eid="JER 12:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 12:10"/>Many shepherds have destroyed my vineyard; they have defiled my portion; they rendered my desired portion an untrodden wilderness.<verse eid="JER 12:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 12:11"/>It was made into an annihilation of destruction; on my account the whole land was annihilated with annihilation, because there is not a man who lays it to heart.<verse eid="JER 12:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 12:12"/>Upon every trail in the wilderness spoilers have come, because a dagger of the Lord will devour from one end of the land to the other end of the land; there is no peace for any flesh.<verse eid="JER 12:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 12:13"/>Sow wheat, and reap thorns. Their farms will not profit them. Be ashamed of your boasting, of reproaching before the Lord--<verse eid="JER 12:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 12:14"/>because this is what the Lord says concerning all the evil neighbors who touch my heritage that I have allotted to my people Israel: Behold, I am tearing them from their land, and Iouda I will cast out from among them.<verse eid="JER 12:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 12:15"/>And it shall be after I have cast them out, I will turn and have mercy on them, and I will settle them, each in his heritage and each in his land.<verse eid="JER 12:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 12:16"/>And it shall be, if when learning they learn the way of my people, to swear by my name, "The Lord lives," as they taught my people to swear by the goddess Baal, and they shall be built up in the midst of my people.<verse eid="JER 12:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 12:17"/>But if they do not turn, I will even remove that nation with removal and destruction.<verse eid="JER 12:17"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 13">
<verse sid="JER 13:1"/>This is what the Lord says, "Go, and acquire for yourself a linen loincloth, and put it on your loins, and it shall not pass through water."<verse eid="JER 13:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:2"/>And I acquired the loincloth according to the word of the Lord and put it on my loins.<verse eid="JER 13:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:3"/>And a word of the Lord came to me, saying,<verse eid="JER 13:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:4"/>"Take the loincloth that is on your loins, and rise up, and go to the Euphrates, and hide it there in a hole of the rock."<verse eid="JER 13:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:5"/>And I hid it by the Euphrates, as the Lord commanded me.<verse eid="JER 13:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:6"/>And it happened after many days that the Lord said to me, "Rise up, go to the Euphrates, and take from there the loincloth that I commanded you to hide there."<verse eid="JER 13:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:7"/>And I went to the Euphrates river and dug, and I took the loincloth from the place, there where I had hidden it. And behold, it had been utterly destroyed-- which will be good for nothing.<verse eid="JER 13:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:8"/>And a word of the Lord came to me saying: This is what the Lord says:<verse eid="JER 13:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:9"/>Just so I will destroy the pride of Iouda and the pride of Ierousalem,<verse eid="JER 13:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:10"/>this great pride, those who refuse to obey my words and have gone after foreign gods to be slaves to them and to do obeisance to them, and they shall be like this loincloth, which shall be good for nothing,<verse eid="JER 13:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:11"/>because as the loincloth clings to a person's loins, so I made the whole house of Israel and the whole house of Iouda cling to myself in order that they might be for me a people of name, both as a boast and as a glory. And they did not listen to me.<verse eid="JER 13:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:12"/>And you shall say to this people: Every wineskin shall be filled with wine. And it shall be if they say to you, "Surely, in knowing shall we not know that every wine-skin will be filled with wine?"<verse eid="JER 13:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:13"/>And you shall say to them: This is what the Lord says: Behold, I am filling the inhabitants of this land-- both their kings, the sons of Dauid who sit on their throne and the priests and the prophets and Iouda and all the inhabitants of Ierousalem-- with drunkenness.<verse eid="JER 13:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:14"/>And I will scatter them, a man and his brother, and their fathers and their sons in the same manner; I will not yearn after, says the Lord, and I will not spare or have compassion at their destruction.<verse eid="JER 13:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:15"/>Hear, and give ear, and do not be lifted up, because the Lord has spoken.<verse eid="JER 13:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:16"/>Give glory to the Lord your God before he brings darkness and before your feet stumble on dark mountains, and you will wait for light, and a shadow of death is there, and they shall be placed in darkness.<verse eid="JER 13:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:17"/>If you do not hear, your soul will weep in secret due to pride, and your eyes will bring down tears, because the Lord's flock has been smashed.<verse eid="JER 13:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:18"/>Say to the king and to those in power: "Be humbled, and sit down, because your crown of glory has been removed from your head."<verse eid="JER 13:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:19"/>The cities toward the south were shut up, and there was no one to open; Iouda<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = 'Ioudas'</char></note> was exiled; he completed a complete exile.<verse eid="JER 13:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:20"/>Lift up your eyes, O Ierousalem, and see those who come from the north. Where is the flock that was given you, sheep of your glory?<verse eid="JER 13:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:21"/>What will you say when they visit you? And it was you who taught them lessons for rule over you. Will not pangs take hold of you, like a woman giving birth?<verse eid="JER 13:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:22"/>And if you say in your heart, "Why have these things come against me?" it is for the greatness of your injustice that your hind parts were uncovered, that your heels were made a spectacle of.<verse eid="JER 13:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:23"/>Will an Ethiopian change his skin, and a leopard her spots? And will you be able to do good, though you have learned evil?<verse eid="JER 13:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:24"/>And I scattered them like firewood driven by the wind into the wilderness.<verse eid="JER 13:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:25"/>This is your lot and portion for your disobeying of me, says the Lord, because you have forgotten me and hoped in lies.<verse eid="JER 13:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:26"/>It is I that will reveal your hindquarters to your face, and your dishonor will be seen,<verse eid="JER 13:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 13:27"/>both your adultery and your neighing and the estranging of your prostitution; on the hills and in the fields I have seen your abominations. Woe to you, O Ierousalem! Because you were not cleansed behind<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:27</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'after'</char></note> me, how long will it yet be?<verse eid="JER 13:27"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 14">
<verse sid="JER 14:1"/>And a word of the Lord came to Ieremias concerning the drought:<verse eid="JER 14:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:2"/>Judea mourned, and her gates were emptied, and they were darkened in the land, and the cry of Ierousalem went up.<verse eid="JER 14:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:3"/>And her nobles sent their young men for water; they came to the cisterns and found no water, and they returned their vessels empty.<verse eid="JER 14:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:4"/>And the labors of the land failed, because there was no rain; farmers were put to shame; they covered their head.<verse eid="JER 14:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:5"/>Even does in the field gave birth and forsook their young<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">14:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'their young':  Lacking in Greek</char></note>, because there was no herbage.<verse eid="JER 14:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:6"/>Wild asses stood by wooded valleys; they snuffed up wind; their eyes failed, because there was no grass.<verse eid="JER 14:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:7"/>If our sins withstood us, O Lord, act for us for your sake, because our sins are many before you, because we have sinned.<verse eid="JER 14:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:8"/>You are Israel's endurance, O Lord, and you save in time of trouble; why have you become like a resident alien in the land and like an indigenous person turning aside for lodging?<verse eid="JER 14:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:9"/>Surely you shall not be like a person asleep or like a man not able to save? And you are among us, O Lord, and your name has been called upon us; do not forget us!<verse eid="JER 14:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:10"/>Thus says the Lord with reference to this people: They have loved to move their feet, and they have not spared, and God found no pleasure in them; now he will remember their injustice.<verse eid="JER 14:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:11"/>And the Lord said to me: Do not pray concerning this people for good,<verse eid="JER 14:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:12"/>because if they fast, I will not hear their petition, and if they offer whole burnt offerings and sacrifices, I will not have pleasure in them, because by dagger and by famine and by death I will make an end of them.<verse eid="JER 14:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:13"/>And I said: "You That Are, Lord! Behold, their prophets are prophesying and saying, 'You shall not see a dagger, nor shall famine be among you, because I bestow truth and peace on the land and in this place.' "<verse eid="JER 14:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:14"/>And the Lord said to me: The prophets are prophesying lies in my name; I did not send them, and I did not command them and did not speak to them, because they are prophesying to you lying visions and divinations and omens and preferences of their own heart.<verse eid="JER 14:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:15"/>Therefore this is what the Lord says concerning the prophets who prophesy lies in my name, and I did not send them, who say, "Dagger and famine shall not come on this land": By a sickly death they shall die, and by famine the prophets shall come to an end.<verse eid="JER 14:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:16"/>And the people, to them to whom they prophesy, they also shall be thrown out in the streets of Ierousalem, before the dagger and the famine, and there shall be no one to bury them-- and their wives and their sons and their daughters<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">14:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'and their wives and their sons and their daughters':  I.e. 'these shall fare likewise'</char></note>. And I will pour out their evil upon them.<verse eid="JER 14:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:17"/>And you shall say to them this word: Bring down upon your eyes tears day and night, and let them not cease, because the daughter of my people was shattered with a fracture and with a very grievous blow.<verse eid="JER 14:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:18"/>If I go out into the plain, and behold, casualties of a dagger! And if I enter into the city, and behold, hardship of famine, because priest and prophet went to a land of which they had no knowledge!<verse eid="JER 14:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:19"/>Surely when rejecting, you did not reject Iouda? And has your soul departed from Sion? Why did you strike us, and there is no healing for us? We waited for peace, and there was no good, for a time of healing, and behold, disturbance.<verse eid="JER 14:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:20"/>We were aware of our sins, O Lord, injustices of our fathers, because we have sinned before you.<verse eid="JER 14:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:21"/>Stop for your name's sake; do not destroy the throne of your glory; remember, do not scatter your covenant with us.<verse eid="JER 14:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 14:22"/>Surely, there is no one among idols of the nations that brings rain? And whether the sky will give its abundance ...? Is it not you yourself? And we will wait on you, because it is you who did all these things.<verse eid="JER 14:22"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 15">
<verse sid="JER 15:1"/>And the Lord said to me: If Moyses and Samouel stood before me, my soul would not be toward them. Send this people away, and let them go!<verse eid="JER 15:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:2"/>And it shall be, if they say to you, "Where shall we go?" you shall also say to them: This is what the Lord says: Those destined for death, to death, and those destined for a dagger, to a dagger; and those destined for famine, to famine, and those destined for captivity, to captivity.<verse eid="JER 15:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:3"/>And I will avenge on them four kinds, says the Lord: the dagger for slaughter and the dogs for tearing and the wild animals of the earth and the birds of the air for eating and for corruption.<verse eid="JER 15:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:4"/>And I will hand them over for anguish to all the kingdoms of the earth on account of King Manasse son of Hezekias of Iouda concerning all he did in Ierousalem.<verse eid="JER 15:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:5"/>Who will be sparing over you, O Ierousalem, and who will be in dread over you, or who will double back for peace for you?<verse eid="JER 15:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:6"/>It is you that have turned away from me, says the Lord; you will go backward, and I will stretch out my hand and destroy you, and I will let them off no more.<verse eid="JER 15:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:7"/>And I will disperse them in a dispersion in the gates of my people. I was made childless; I destroyed my people because of their evils.<verse eid="JER 15:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:8"/>Their widows became more numerous than the sand of the sea; I have brought against the mother of a youth wretchedness at noonday; I threw trembling and haste upon her suddenly.<verse eid="JER 15:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:9"/>She who bore seven was depleted; her soul became miserable; the sun set for her while it was yet midday; she has been shamed and disgraced. The rest of them I will give to a dagger before their enemies.<verse eid="JER 15:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:10"/>Woe is me, O mother! As whom did you bear me? A man being condemned and at variance with the whole land! I neither owed nor did any one owe me; my strength failed amongst those that curse me.<verse eid="JER 15:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:11"/>May it be so, O Sovereign, while they succeed; otherwise I stood before you in a time of their troubles and in a time of their distress for good against the enemy.<verse eid="JER 15:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:12"/>Will iron be known? And your strength is a bronze wrap.<verse eid="JER 15:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:13"/>And your treasures I will give as plunder, as a payment for all your sins, and in all your borders.<verse eid="JER 15:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:14"/>And I will make you a slave to your enemies all around in the land that you did not know, because from my anger a fire has blazed forth; it shall burn against you.<verse eid="JER 15:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:15"/>O Lord, remember me, and visit me, and hold me guiltless before my persecutors; do not incline to forbearance. Know how on your account I received insult<verse eid="JER 15:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:16"/>by those who reject your words. Make an end of them, and your word will be to me gladness and the joy of my heart, because your name is called upon me, O Lord Almighty.<verse eid="JER 15:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:17"/>I did not sit in the council of them when they were making sport, but I was cautious before your hand; I sat alone, because I was filled with bitterness.<verse eid="JER 15:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:18"/>Why do those who pain me prevail over me? My wound is severe; how shall I be healed? As it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">15:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'wound'</char></note> came, it became to me like fake water not having credence.<verse eid="JER 15:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:19"/>Therefore this is what the Lord says: If you return, I will also restore you, and you shall stand before me. And if you bring out what is precious from what is worthless, you shall be as my mouth. And it is they who will turn to you, and not you who will turn to them.<verse eid="JER 15:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:20"/>And I will give you to this people as a fortified bronze wall, and they will fight against you, and they shall not prevail against you, for I am with you to save you<verse eid="JER 15:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 15:21"/>and to deliver you out of the hand of the wicked and from the hand of the pestilent.<verse eid="JER 15:21"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 16">
<verse sid="JER 16:1"/>And you, do not take a wife, says the Lord God of Israel,<verse eid="JER 16:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:2"/>and no son or daughter shall be born to you in this place,<verse eid="JER 16:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:3"/>because this is what the Lord says concerning the sons and concerning the daughters who are born in this place and concerning their mothers who bore them and their fathers who begot them in this land:<verse eid="JER 16:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:4"/>They shall die by a sickly death. They shall not be lamented, and they shall not be buried; they shall become an example on the surface of the ground, both for the wild animals of the earth and for the birds of the air. By dagger they shall fall, and by famine they shall be brought to an end.<verse eid="JER 16:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:5"/>This is what the Lord says: Do not enter into their revel, and do not go to lament, and do not bemoan them, because I have removed my peace from this people.<verse eid="JER 16:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:6"/>They shall not lament for them, nor shall they make incisions, and they shall not be shaved.<verse eid="JER 16:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:7"/>And bread shall not be broken in their mourning, for comfort over the dead; they shall not make him drink a cup for comfort over his father and mother.<verse eid="JER 16:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:8"/>You shall not enter into a house of feasting, to sit with them to eat and drink,<verse eid="JER 16:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:9"/>for this is what the Lord says, the God of Israel: Behold, I am banishing from this place, before your eyes and in your days, a voice of joy and a voice of gladness, a voice of bridegroom and a voice of bride.<verse eid="JER 16:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:10"/>And it shall be when you tell this people all these dicta, and they say to you, "Why has the Lord spoken all these evil things against us? What is our injustice? And what is our sin that we have committed before the Lord our God?"<verse eid="JER 16:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:11"/>And you shall say to them: It is because your fathers have forsaken me, says the Lord, and were going after foreign gods and have been subject to them and did obeisance to them and have forsaken me and have not kept my law,<verse eid="JER 16:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:12"/>and you have behaved worse than your fathers, and behold, every one of you is following after the things that please your evil heart so as not to obey me.<verse eid="JER 16:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:13"/>And I will hurl you from this land into a land that you and your fathers have not known, and there you shall be slaves to other gods who will show you no mercy.<verse eid="JER 16:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:14"/>Therefore, behold, days are coming, says the Lord, and they shall no longer say, "The Lord lives who brought the sons of Israel up out of the land of Egypt,"<verse eid="JER 16:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:15"/>but "The Lord lives who brought the house of Israel up out of the land of the north and out of all the countries, there where they had been driven." For I will restore them to their own land that I gave to their fathers.<verse eid="JER 16:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:16"/>Behold, I am sending many fishermen, says the Lord, and they shall catch them, and afterward I will send many hunters, and they shall hunt them on every mountain and on every hill and out of the clefts of the rocks,<verse eid="JER 16:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:17"/>because my eyes were on all their ways and their acts of injustice were not concealed from my sight.<verse eid="JER 16:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:18"/>And I will doubly repay their injustices and their sins with which they have polluted my land with the carcasses of their abominations and with their lawless acts, by which they erred against my inheritance.<verse eid="JER 16:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:19"/>O Lord, my strength and my help and my refuge in a day of troubles, to you shall nations come from the end of the earth and say: How have our fathers acquired false idols, and there is no profit in them!<verse eid="JER 16:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:20"/>Will a person make for himself gods? But these are no gods!<verse eid="JER 16:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 16:21"/>"Therefore, behold, I will make clear to them at this time my hand and make known to them my power, and they shall know that my name is the Lord."<verse eid="JER 16:21"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 17">
<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 17:1"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">17:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 17:1"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 17:2"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">17:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 17:2"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 17:3"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">17:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 17:3"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 17:4"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">17:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 17:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:5"/>Cursed is the person who has his hope in a human and will steady the flesh of his arm on him, and his heart will stand away from the Lord.<verse eid="JER 17:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:6"/>And he shall be like a wild tamarisk in the wilderness; he shall not see when good things come. And he shall encamp by the seaside, in a wilderness, in a salt land that is not inhabited.<verse eid="JER 17:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:7"/>And blessed is the person who trusts in the Lord, and the Lord shall be his hope.<verse eid="JER 17:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:8"/>And he shall be like a tree thriving beside waters, and it shall send out its roots to moisture. And it shall not fear when heat comes, and the trunks on it shall be grove-like; in a year of drought it shall not fear, and it shall not cease to produce fruit.<verse eid="JER 17:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:9"/>The heart is deep above all else, and so<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">17:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> is man, and who shall understand him?<verse eid="JER 17:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:10"/>I, the Lord, am one who tests hearts and examines kidneys<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">17:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'emotions'</char></note>, to give to each according to his ways and according to the fruit of his doings.<verse eid="JER 17:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:11"/>A partridge gathered what she did not hatch. When one produces his wealth not with discretion-- at the midpoint of his days they will leave him, and at his end he will be a fool.<verse eid="JER 17:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:12"/>O exalted throne of glory, our sanctity<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">17:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'holy precinct'</char></note>!<verse eid="JER 17:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:13"/>O endurance of Israel! O Lord! Let all who forsake you be put to shame; let those who have turned away be recorded on the earth, because they have forsaken the fountain of life, the Lord.<verse eid="JER 17:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:14"/>Heal me, O Lord, and I shall be healed; save me, and I shall be saved, because you are my boast.<verse eid="JER 17:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:15"/>Behold, it is they that say to me, "Where is the word of the Lord? Let it come!"<verse eid="JER 17:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:16"/>But I have not tired of following after you, and man's day I have not desired; you understand; what came from my lips is before you.<verse eid="JER 17:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:17"/>Do not become an alienation to me when you spare me in an evil day.<verse eid="JER 17:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:18"/>Let my persecutors be shamed, and may I not be shamed; may they be terrified, and may I not be terrified; bring on them an evil day; smash them with a double fracture!<verse eid="JER 17:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:19"/>This is what the Lord says: Go, and stand in the gates of the sons of your people, by them by which kings of Iouda enter and by them by which they go out and in all the gates of Ierousalem,<verse eid="JER 17:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:20"/>and you will say to them: Hear a word of the Lord, you kings of Iouda, and all Judea and all Ierousalem, who enter by these gates.<verse eid="JER 17:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:21"/>This is what the Lord says: Watch your souls, and do not bear burdens on the day of the sabbaths, and do not go in by the gates of Ierousalem.<verse eid="JER 17:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:22"/>And do not carry burdens out of your houses on the day of the sabbaths, and you shall not do any work; keep the day of the sabbaths holy, as I commanded your fathers. (23) And they did not hear and did not incline their ear,<verse eid="JER 17:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:23"/>and they stiffened their neck more than their fathers so as not to hear me and not to receive instruction.<verse eid="JER 17:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:24"/>And it shall be if you hear me by hearing, says the Lord, so as not to bring in burdens through the gates of this city on the day of the sabbaths and to keep the day of the sabbaths holy so as not to do any work,<verse eid="JER 17:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:25"/>then there shall enter through the gates of this city kings and rulers sitting on the throne of Dauid, and mounted on chariots and horses, they and their rulers, men of Iouda and the inhabitants of Ierousalem, and this city shall be settled forever.<verse eid="JER 17:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:26"/>And they shall come from the cities of Iouda and all around Ierousalem and from the land of Beniamin and from the plain and from the mountain and from the southern land, bringing whole burnt offerings and sacrificial victims and manaa<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">17:26</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'grain offering'</char></note> and frankincense, bringing praise into the house of the Lord.<verse eid="JER 17:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 17:27"/>And it shall be, if you do not listen to me, to keep the day of the sabbaths holy, so as not to carry in burdens and not to enter by the gates of Ierousalem on the day of the sabbaths, I will also kindle a fire in its gates, and it shall devour the quarters of Ierousalem and shall not be quenched.<verse eid="JER 17:27"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 18">
<verse sid="JER 18:1"/>The word that came from the Lord to Ieremias, saying:<verse eid="JER 18:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:2"/>"Get up, and go down to the potter's house, and there you will hear my words."<verse eid="JER 18:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:3"/>And I went down to the potter's house, and behold, he was doing a job on the stones.<verse eid="JER 18:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:4"/>And the vessel he was making failed in his hands, and again he made it into another vessel, as seemed good to him to do.<verse eid="JER 18:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:5"/>And a word of the Lord came to me, saying:<verse eid="JER 18:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:6"/>Shall I not have the power to do with you, O house of Israel, just as this potter did? Behold, you are in my hands like the clay of the potter.<verse eid="JER 18:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:7"/>At last let me<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">18:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'let me':  Or 'I will'</char></note> speak with reference to a nation or with reference to a kingdom, to remove them and to destroy,<verse eid="JER 18:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:8"/>and let that nation turn from all their evil, and I will change my mind about the evils that I devised to do to them.<verse eid="JER 18:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:9"/>And at last let me<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">18:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'let me':  Or 'I will'</char></note> speak in reference to a nation and in reference to a kingdom to rebuild and to plant it,<verse eid="JER 18:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:10"/>and let them do evil before me so as not to hear my voice, and I will change my mind about the good things that I had spoken to do to them.<verse eid="JER 18:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:11"/>And now, say to the men of Iouda and to the inhabitants of Ierousalem: Behold, I am shaping evil against you and devising a plan against you. Let each now turn from his evil way and make your doings more noble.<verse eid="JER 18:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:12"/>And they said, "We will play the man, because we will go after our own aversions, and each of us will do what pleases his evil heart!"<verse eid="JER 18:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:13"/>Therefore this is what the Lord says: Do ask among nations: Who has heard such horrible things which Virgin Israel did exceedingly?<verse eid="JER 18:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:14"/>Surely, breasts<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">18:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'breast-shaped crags'</char></note> will not fail from a rock, or snow from the Lebanon? Surely water violently carried by wind will not change course?<verse eid="JER 18:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:15"/>Because my people forgot me, they burned incense in vain, and they will become weak in their ways, to tread for miles<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">18:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek schoinos = a land measure equal to ca. 11 km</char></note> on ancient paths, since they have no road for travel,<verse eid="JER 18:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:16"/>to render their land an annihilation and a thing to be hissed at forever. All who pass through it will be astonished and shake their head.<verse eid="JER 18:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:17"/>I will disperse them before their enemies like a scorching wind. I will show them a day of their ruin.<verse eid="JER 18:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:18"/>And they said, "Come, let us devise a scheme against Ieremias-- because law shall not perish from a priest, and counsel from an intelligent person, and a word from a prophet. Come, and let us strike him with the tongue, and we will hear all his words."<verse eid="JER 18:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:19"/>Listen to me, O Lord, and listen to the sound of my vindication!<verse eid="JER 18:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:20"/>Is evil a recompense for good that together they spoke utterances against my soul and hid their punishment for me? Remember me when I stood before you to speak good on their behalf, to turn away your anger from them.<verse eid="JER 18:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:21"/>Therefore give their sons over to famine, and gather them to a dagger's power; let their wives become childless and widows, and let their men become destroyed by death and their youths become felled by dagger in battle.<verse eid="JER 18:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:22"/>Let there be a cry in their houses! You will bring marauders suddenly upon them, because they undertook a plan for catching me and hid snares for me!<verse eid="JER 18:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 18:23"/>And you, O Lord, knew all their plotting against me for death. Do not excuse their injustices, and do not blot out their sins from your sight. Let their weakness be before you; in a time of your anger deal with them.<verse eid="JER 18:23"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 19">
<verse sid="JER 19:1"/>Then the Lord said to me: Go, and acquire a fashioned earthenware jug, and you will bring some of the elders of the people and some of the priests,<verse eid="JER 19:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 19:2"/>and you shall go out to the common burial ground of the sons of their children which is at the entry of the gate Charsith<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">19:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'potsherds'</char></note> and read there all the words that I tell you.<verse eid="JER 19:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 19:3"/>And you shall say: Hear a word of the Lord, O kings of Iouda and men of Iouda and inhabitants of Ierousalem and those who enter in these gates. This is what the Lord, the God of Israel, says: Behold, I am bringing evil upon this place so that the ears of everyone who hears of it will tingle.<verse eid="JER 19:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 19:4"/>Because they have forsaken me and have made this place foreign and offered incense in it to foreign gods whom they did not know, they nor their fathers, and the kings of Iouda have filled this place with innocent blood<verse eid="JER 19:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 19:5"/>and built high places of the goddess Baal to burn their sons with fire, which things I did not command nor intended in my heart.<verse eid="JER 19:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 19:6"/>Therefore behold, days are coming, says the Lord, and this place will no longer be called Fall and Burial Ground of Hennom's Son, but Burial Ground of Slaughter.<verse eid="JER 19:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 19:7"/>And I will slaughter the plan of Iouda and the plan of Ierousalem in this place and will make them fall by dagger before their enemies and by the hands of people who seek their souls. And I will give their corpses for food to the birds of the air and to the wild animals of the earth.<verse eid="JER 19:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 19:8"/>And I will make this city into an annihilation and into a hissing; everyone who passes by it will look sullen and will hiss because of all its blow.<verse eid="JER 19:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 19:9"/>And they shall eat the flesh of their sons and the flesh of their daughters, and each shall eat the flesh of his fellow in the blockade and in the siege with which their enemies besiege them.<verse eid="JER 19:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 19:10"/>And you shall crush the jug in the sight of the men who go out with you<verse eid="JER 19:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 19:11"/>and shall say: This is what the Lord says: Thus will I crush this people and this city, as an earthen vessel is crushed, which can never be mended again.<verse eid="JER 19:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 19:12"/>Thus will I do, says the Lord, to this place and to the inhabitants in it, that this city be rendered as the one falling to ruin.<verse eid="JER 19:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 19:13"/>And the houses of Ierousalem and the houses of the kings of Iouda shall be like the ruinous place of unclean things in all the houses on whose roofs they have burned incense to the host of the sky and poured out libations to foreign gods.<verse eid="JER 19:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 19:14"/>And Ieremias came from the Fall, there where the Lord had sent him to prophesy, and he stood in the court of the Lord's house and said to all the people:<verse eid="JER 19:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 19:15"/>This is what the Lord says: Behold, I am bringing upon this city and upon its villages all the evil that I have spoken against it, because they have stiffened their neck so as not to listen to my commandments.<verse eid="JER 19:15"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 20">
<verse sid="JER 20:1"/>And the priest Paschor son of Emmer-- he was also appointed leader of the house of the Lord-- heard Ieremias prophesying these words.<verse eid="JER 20:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:2"/>And he struck him and put him into the sluice, which was by the gate of a house designated "the upper," which was in the house of the Lord.<verse eid="JER 20:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:3"/>And Paschor brought Ieremias out of the sluice, and Ieremias said to him, The Lord has called your name not Paschor, but Deportee,<verse eid="JER 20:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:4"/>for this is what the Lord says: Behold, I am assigning you to deportation with all your friends, and they shall fall by their enemies' dagger, and your eyes shall see it. And I will give you and all Iouda into the hands of the king of Babylon, and they shall deport them and shall cut them down with daggers.<verse eid="JER 20:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:5"/>And I will give all the strength of this city and all its toils and all the treasures of the king of Iouda into the hands of his enemies, and they shall bring them into Babylon.<verse eid="JER 20:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:6"/>And as for you and all who live in your house-- you shall go in captivity, and in Babylon you shall die, and there you shall be buried, you and all your friends, to them to whom you have prophesied lies.<verse eid="JER 20:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:7"/>O Lord, you have misled me, and I was misled; you got the upper hand and prevailed; I have become a laughingstock all day long; I continued to be mocked,<verse eid="JER 20:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:8"/>because I will laugh with my bitter speech; I will call upon faithlessness and wretchedness, because the Lord's word has become for me a reproach and a derision my whole day.<verse eid="JER 20:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:9"/>And I said, "I will not name the name of the Lord and will no longer speak in his name." And it became like a burning fire flaming in my bones, and I became limp everywhere, and I cannot bear up,<verse eid="JER 20:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:10"/>because I heard the blame of many gathered around, "Band together, and let us band together against him, all you men, his friends! Watch his intent, whether he can be misled, and we can prevail against him and take our revenge on him."<verse eid="JER 20:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:11"/>And the Lord is with me like a strong warrior; therefore they persecuted me and were not able to consider. They were greatly shamed, because they did not consider their dishonor, which will never be forgotten.<verse eid="JER 20:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:12"/>O Lord, one who tests what is right, one who understands kidneys<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">20:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'emotions'</char></note> and hearts, may I see your avenging among them, because to you I have revealed my defensive pleas.<verse eid="JER 20:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:13"/>Sing to the Lord; praise him, because he has delivered the soul of the needy from the hand of evildoers!<verse eid="JER 20:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:14"/>Cursed be the day on which I was born on it! The day on which my mother bore me-- let it not be longed for!<verse eid="JER 20:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:15"/>Cursed be the person who brought the good news to my father, saying, "A male child was born to you," being glad.<verse eid="JER 20:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:16"/>Let that person be like the cities that the Lord overthrew in anger and did not repent; let him hear a cry in the morning and a shouting at noon,<verse eid="JER 20:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:17"/>because he did not kill me in the womb, and my mother became my grave and the womb one of perpetual conception.<verse eid="JER 20:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 20:18"/>Why is it that I came forth from the womb to see toil and sorrow, and my days continued in shame?<verse eid="JER 20:18"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 21">
<verse sid="JER 21:1"/>The word that came from the Lord to Ieremias, when King Sedekias sent to him Paschor son of Melchias and the priest Sophonias son of Maasaios, saying,<verse eid="JER 21:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 21:2"/>Inquire of the Lord about us, because the king of Babylon has taken a stand against us, if the Lord will do according to all his wonderful deeds and he will withdraw from us.<verse eid="JER 21:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 21:3"/>And Ieremias said to them: Thus you shall say to Sedekias, king of Iouda:<verse eid="JER 21:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 21:4"/>This is what the Lord says: Behold, I am turning back the weapons of war with which you are fighting with them, against the Chaldeans who have enclosed you outside the wall, into the midst of this city.<verse eid="JER 21:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 21:5"/>And it is I who will fight you with outstretched hand and mighty arm, in anger and great wrath.<verse eid="JER 21:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 21:6"/>And I will strike all the inhabitants in this city, human beings and animals, with great death, and they shall die.<verse eid="JER 21:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 21:7"/>And afterwards, says the Lord, I will give Sedekias, king of Iouda, and his servants and the people left in this city from death and from famine and from the dagger into the hands of their enemies who are seeking their souls, and they shall cut them into pieces with a dagger's edge; I will not be sparing toward them, and I will not have compassion on them.<verse eid="JER 21:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 21:8"/>And to this people you shall say: This is what the Lord says: Behold, I have given before you the way of life and the way of death.<verse eid="JER 21:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 21:9"/>He who sits still in this city shall die by dagger and by famine, but he who goes out to side with the Chaldeans who have closed you in shall live and his soul shall be as booty, and he shall live,<verse eid="JER 21:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 21:10"/>for I have set my face against this city for evil and not for good. It shall be given over into the hands of the king of Babylon, and he shall burn it with fire.<verse eid="JER 21:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 21:11"/>As for the house of the king of Iouda-- hear a word of the Lord,<verse eid="JER 21:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 21:12"/>O house of Dauid! This is what the Lord says: Execute judgment in the morning, and guide from the hand of him that wrongs him anyone who has been seized in order that my wrath may not be kindled like fire and burn, and there will be no one to quench it.<verse eid="JER 21:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 21:13"/>Behold, I am against you, the inhabitant of the valley of Sor, the plain, against those who say, "Who shall terrify us, or who shall enter into our dwelling place?"<verse eid="JER 21:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 21:14"/>I will kindle a fire in its<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">21:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'valley'</char></note> forest, and it shall devour all that is round about it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">21:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'valley'</char></note>.<verse eid="JER 21:14"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 22">
<verse sid="JER 22:1"/>This is what the Lord says: Go, and descend to the house of the king of Iouda, and you shall speak there this word,<verse eid="JER 22:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:2"/>and you shall say: Hear a word of the Lord, O King of Iouda who sits on the throne of Dauid-- you and your house and your people and those who enter by these gates.<verse eid="JER 22:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:3"/>This is what the Lord says: Do justice and righteousness, and deliver one seized from the hand of one who does him wrong. And do not oppress, and do not act impiously against guest and orphan and widow, and do not shed innocent blood in this place,<verse eid="JER 22:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:4"/>for if in doing you do this word, by the gates of this house shall also enter kings who sit on the throne of Dauid, and mounted on chariots and horses, they and their servants and their people.<verse eid="JER 22:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:5"/>But if you will not do these words, by myself I have sworn, says the Lord, that this house shall become a desolation--<verse eid="JER 22:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:6"/>because this is what the Lord says against the house of the king of Iouda: You are Galaad to me, realm of Lebanon; if I do not make you a wilderness, cities not to be inhabited!<verse eid="JER 22:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:7"/>And I will bring destroyers against you, a man and his ax, and they shall cut down your choice cedars and cast them into the fire.<verse eid="JER 22:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:8"/>And nations will pass through this city, and they will say, each to his fellow, "Why did the Lord deal in this way with this great city?"<verse eid="JER 22:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:9"/>And they will say, "Because they abandoned the covenant of the Lord, their God, and did obeisance to foreign gods and were slaves to them."<verse eid="JER 22:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:10"/>Do not weep for him who is dead, nor bemoan him; with weeping weep for the one who goes away, because he shall return no more nor see his native land--<verse eid="JER 22:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:11"/>for this is what the Lord says regarding Sellem son of Iosias, who was reigning in place of his father Iosias, who went away from this place: He shall return there no more,<verse eid="JER 22:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:12"/>but in the place where I have deported him, there he shall die, and he shall never see this land again.<verse eid="JER 22:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:13"/>Ah, he who builds his house not with righteousness and his upper rooms not with judgment, he will work at his fellow's for nothing, and he will not pay him his wages.<verse eid="JER 22:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:14"/>You built for yourself a spacious house, ventilated upper rooms fitted with windows and paneled with cedar and painted with vermilion.<verse eid="JER 22:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:15"/>Surely, you will not be king, because you are irritated with Achaz your father? They will not eat, and they will not drink; it is better for you to execute judgment and righteousness.<verse eid="JER 22:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:16"/>They did not know; they did not judge the cause for the lowly nor the cause of the needy. Is not this so, because you do not know me? says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 22:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:17"/>Behold, are not your eyes and your heart on nothing but your greed and on innocent blood to shed it and on wrongdoing and on committing murder?<verse eid="JER 22:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:18"/>Therefore this is what the Lord says regarding King Ioakim son of Iosias of Iouda: Woe to this man! They shall not lament for him, "Ah, brother!" nor shall they weep for him, "Alas, lord!"<verse eid="JER 22:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:19"/>With the burial of a donkey he shall be buried-- swept up, he will be thrown out beyond the gate of Ierousalem.<verse eid="JER 22:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:20"/>Go up to Lebanon, and cry out, and give forth your voice in Basan, and shout to the other side of the sea, because all your lovers were crushed.<verse eid="JER 22:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:21"/>I spoke to you in your downfall, and you said, "I will not listen." This has been your way from your youth; you have not obeyed my voice.<verse eid="JER 22:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:22"/>A wind shall shepherd all your shepherds, and your lovers shall go out in captivity, because then you will be ashamed and disgraced because of all who would kiss you.<verse eid="JER 22:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:23"/>O inhabitant of Lebanon, nesting among the cedars, you will groan when pangs come upon you, pains as of one giving birth!<verse eid="JER 22:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:24"/>I live, says the Lord, if King Iechonias son of Ioakim of Iouda in being<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">22:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'in being':  Possibly 'when born'</char></note> was a signet on my right hand, from there I would tear you off<verse eid="JER 22:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:25"/>and give you into the hands of people seeking your soul, before whose face you are afraid, into the hands of the Chaldeans.<verse eid="JER 22:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:26"/>And I will hurl you and your mother who bore you into a land, there where you were not born, and there you shall die.<verse eid="JER 22:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:27"/>But to the land for which they long with their souls, they shall not return.<verse eid="JER 22:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:28"/>Iechonias was dishonored like a vessel which is without its use, which was hurled out, and he was cast out into a land that he did not know.<verse eid="JER 22:28"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:29"/>O land, land, hear a word of the Lord!<verse eid="JER 22:29"/>

<verse sid="JER 22:30"/>Record this man as a banished person, because none of his offspring shall grow up to sit on the throne of Dauid as ruler again in Iouda.<verse eid="JER 22:30"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 23">
<verse sid="JER 23:1"/>Ah, the shepherds who destroy and scatter the sheep of their pasture!<verse eid="JER 23:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:2"/>Therefore this is what the Lord says regarding those who shepherd my people: It is you who have scattered my sheep and have driven them away, and you have not visited them. Behold, I punish you for your evil doings.<verse eid="JER 23:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:3"/>And it is I who will receive those remaining of my people from every land, there where I have driven them, and I will restore them to their pasture, and they shall increase and multiply.<verse eid="JER 23:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:4"/>And I will raise up shepherds for them who will shepherd them, and they shall not fear any longer or be terrified, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 23:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:5"/>Behold, days are coming, says the Lord, and I will raise up for Dauid a righteous dawn, and a king shall reign and shall understand and shall execute judgment and righteousness in the land.<verse eid="JER 23:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:6"/>In his days Iouda<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">23:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = 'Ioudas'</char></note> will be saved, and Israel will encamp in confidence. And this is the name by which he [the Lord] will call him: "Iosedek (9) among the prophets."<verse eid="JER 23:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:7"/>Therefore, behold, days are coming, says the Lord, and they shall no longer say, "The Lord lives who brought the house of Israel up out of the land of Egypt,"<verse eid="JER 23:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:8"/>but "The Lord lives who gathered all the offspring of Israel from the land of the north and from all the countries, there where he had driven them, and restored them to their land."<verse eid="JER 23:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:9"/>My heart was crushed; within me all my bones shook; I became like a crushed man and like a person overcome by wine, due to the Lord and due to the dignity of his glory,<verse eid="JER 23:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:10"/>because due to these the land mourned, the pastures of the wilderness were dried up. And their course became evil, and their strength not so,<verse eid="JER 23:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:11"/>because priest and prophet were defiled, and in my house I have seen their wickedness.<verse eid="JER 23:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:12"/>Therefore let their way be to them like slipperiness in thick darkness, and they shall be tripped up and fall in it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">23:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'way'</char></note>; for I will bring evil upon them in the year of their visiting.<verse eid="JER 23:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:13"/>And in the prophets of Samaria I saw lawless deeds: they prophesied by the goddess Baal and led my people Israel astray.<verse eid="JER 23:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:14"/>And in the prophets of Ierousalem I have seen shocking things: people committing adultery and walking in lies and strengthening the hands of evildoers so that no one turns, each from his wicked way; all have become like Sodoma to me, and its inhabitants just like Gomorra.<verse eid="JER 23:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:15"/>Therefore this is what the Lord says: "Behold, I will feed them pain and will give them bitter water to drink, because from the prophets of Ierousalem defilement went out to the whole land."<verse eid="JER 23:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:16"/>Thus says the Lord Almighty: Do not hear the words of the prophets, because they are rendering a vision empty. They speak from their own heart and not from the mouth of the Lord.<verse eid="JER 23:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:17"/>They say to those who reject the word of the Lord, "There shall be peace for you," and to all who walk by their own will, [to every one who walks by the error of his own heart,] they said, "No evil shall come upon you"--<verse eid="JER 23:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:18"/>because who has stood in support of the Lord and seen his word? Who has given ear and obeyed?<verse eid="JER 23:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:19"/>Behold, an earthquake from the Lord, and wrath goes forth as a seismic upheaval<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">23:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'seismic upheaval':  Possibly 'earthquake and hurricane'</char></note>; when it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">23:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'wrath'</char></note> gathers, it will come against the impious.<verse eid="JER 23:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:20"/>And the anger of the Lord will no longer turn back until he has executed it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">23:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Antecedent unclear.</char></note> and until he accomplished it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">23:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Antecedent unclear.</char></note> due to the undertaking of his heart. In the last of days they will understand them<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">23:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Antecedent unclear.</char></note>.<verse eid="JER 23:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:21"/>I was not sending the prophets, and they themselves kept running; I did not speak to them, and they themselves kept prophesying.<verse eid="JER 23:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:22"/>And if they had stood in support of me and if they had heard my words, they would also have turned them, my people, from their evil doings.<verse eid="JER 23:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:23"/>I am a god nearby, says the Lord, and not a god far off.<verse eid="JER 23:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:24"/>If someone shall be hidden in secret places, is it not I that shall also see him? Do I not fill the sky and the earth? says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 23:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:25"/>I have heard what the prophets are saying who prophesy lies in my name, saying, "I have dreamed a dream!"<verse eid="JER 23:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:26"/>How long shall there be lies in the heart of the prophets who prophesy, when in fact they prophesy the will of their own heart,<verse eid="JER 23:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:27"/>those who plan to forget my name by their dreams which they tell, each to his fellow, just as their fathers forgot my name by the goddess Baal?<verse eid="JER 23:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:28"/>Let the prophet in whom there is the dream tell his dream, and let him in whom my word is to him tell my word in truth. What is the chaff to the grain?<verse eid="JER 23:28"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:29"/>Are not my words just like fire and like an ax that cuts a rock?<verse eid="JER 23:29"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:30"/>Therefore, behold, I am against the prophets, says the Lord God, who steal my words each from his fellow.<verse eid="JER 23:30"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:31"/>Behold, I am against the prophets who receive prophecies of tongue and slumber their slumber.<verse eid="JER 23:31"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:32"/>Behold, I am against the prophets who were prophesying lying dreams, and they kept telling them, and they led my people astray by their lies and by their errors, and it was not I that sent them, and I did not command them, and they will not profit this people with profit.<verse eid="JER 23:32"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:33"/>And if this people or a priest or a prophet asks you, "What is the issue of the Lord?" you shall then say to them, "You are the issue, and I will strike you, says the Lord."<verse eid="JER 23:33"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:34"/>And as for the prophet and the priest and the people who might say, "Issue of the Lord," I will also punish that person and his household.<verse eid="JER 23:34"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:35"/>Thus shall you say, each to his fellow and each to his brother, "What has the Lord answered?" and "What has the Lord spoken?"<verse eid="JER 23:35"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:36"/>And "Issue of the Lord," do not name it any more, because "the issue" will be the word belonging to the person.<verse eid="JER 23:36"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:37"/>And what has the Lord, our God, spoken?<verse eid="JER 23:37"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:38"/>Therefore, this is what the Lord God says: Because you have said this phrase, "Issue of the Lord," and I sent to you, saying, You shall not say, "Issue of the Lord,"<verse eid="JER 23:38"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:39"/>therefore, behold, I am taking you and striking you and the city that I gave to you and your fathers.<verse eid="JER 23:39"/>

<verse sid="JER 23:40"/>And I will render upon you everlasting disgrace and everlasting dishonor which shall not be forgotten.<verse eid="JER 23:40"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 24">
<verse sid="JER 24:1"/>The Lord showed me two baskets of figs placed before the shrine of the Lord, after King Nabouchodonosor of Babylon had taken into exile from Ierousalem King Iechonias son of Ioakim of Iouda and the rulers and the artisans and the prisoners and the wealthy and had brought them to Babylon.<verse eid="JER 24:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 24:2"/>The one basket had very good figs, like first-ripe figs, and the other basket had very bad figs, which could not be eaten because of their badness.<verse eid="JER 24:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 24:3"/>And the Lord said to me, "What do you see, Ieremias?" And I said, "Figs, the good ones very good and the bad ones very bad, which will not be eaten because of their badness."<verse eid="JER 24:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 24:4"/>And a word of the Lord came to me, saying:<verse eid="JER 24:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 24:5"/>This is what the Lord, the God of Israel, says: Like these good figs, so I will regard those exiled from Iouda, whom I have sent away from this place to the land of the Chaldeans, for good.<verse eid="JER 24:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 24:6"/>And I will fix my eyes upon them for good, and I will restore them to this land. And I will rebuild them and never tear down, and I will plant them and never pluck up.<verse eid="JER 24:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 24:7"/>And I will give them a heart that they may know me, that I am the Lord, and they shall become a people to me, and I will become a god to them, because they shall return to me with their whole heart.<verse eid="JER 24:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 24:8"/>And as the bad figs which will not be eaten because of their badness-- this is what the Lord says: So will I hand over King Sedekias of Iouda and his nobles and the remnant of Ierousalem, those left in this land and those who live in Egypt.<verse eid="JER 24:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 24:9"/>And I will give them as a scattering to all the kingdoms of the earth and as a disgrace and as an illustration and as a thing to be hated and as a curse in every place, there where I drove them.<verse eid="JER 24:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 24:10"/>And I will send to them the famine and the death and the dagger until they cease from the land that I gave to them.<verse eid="JER 24:10"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 25">
<verse sid="JER 25:1"/>The word that came to Ieremias regarding all the people of Iouda, in the fourth year of King Ioakim son of Iosias of Iouda,<verse eid="JER 25:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:2"/>which he spoke to all the people of Iouda and to the inhabitants of Ierousalem, saying:<verse eid="JER 25:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:3"/>In the thirteenth year of King Iosias son of Amos of Iouda, and until this day for twenty-three years, and I spoke to you, being early and speaking,<verse eid="JER 25:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:4"/>and I would send to you my slaves the prophets, sending them at dawn, but you have not listened and have not paid heed to your ears<verse eid="JER 25:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:5"/>when I was saying, "Do<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">25:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = Omit</char></note> turn, everyone from his evil way and from your evil doings, and dwell upon the land that I have given to you and your fathers from of old and forever;<verse eid="JER 25:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:6"/>do not go after foreign gods to be slaves to them and to do obeisance to them in order that you may not provoke me to anger with the works of your hands so as to do you harm."<verse eid="JER 25:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:7"/>And you did not hear me.<verse eid="JER 25:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:8"/>Therefore this is what the Lord says: Because you have not believed my words,<verse eid="JER 25:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:9"/>behold, I am sending for and I will take a paternal family from the north, and I will bring them against this land and against its inhabitants and against all nations around it, and I will utterly devastate them and render them into an annihilation and into a hissing and into an everlasting disgrace.<verse eid="JER 25:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:10"/>And I will banish from them a sound of mirth and a sound of gladness, a voice of bridegroom and a voice of bride, a fragrance of perfume and light of a lamp.<verse eid="JER 25:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:11"/>And the whole land shall become an annihilation, and they shall be slaves amongst the nations seventy years.<verse eid="JER 25:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:12"/>And when seventy years are completed, I will punish that nation, and I will make them an everlasting waste.<verse eid="JER 25:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:13"/>And I will bring upon that land all my words that I have spoken against it, everything written in this book.<verse eid="JER 25:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:14"/>(49.34) What Ieremias prophesied against the nations of Ailam.<verse eid="JER 25:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:15"/>(35) This is what the Lord says: Let the bow of Ailam be crushed, mainstay of their dominance.<verse eid="JER 25:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:16"/>(36) And I will bring upon Ailam four winds from the four quarters of the sky, and I will scatter them in all these winds, and there shall not be a nation to which it shall not come there-- those driven from Ailam.<verse eid="JER 25:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:17"/>(37) And I will terrify them before their enemies who seek their soul, and I will bring evil upon them, the wrath of my anger. And I will send my dagger after them until I have consumed them.<verse eid="JER 25:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:18"/>(38) And I will set my throne in Ailam and send out from there king and nobles.<verse eid="JER 25:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 25:19"/>(39) And it shall be in the last of days I will return the captivity of Ailam, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 25:19"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 26">
<verse sid="JER 26:1"/>(46.1) In the beginning when King Sedekias reigned, this word came concerning Ailam.<verse eid="JER 26:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:2"/>For Egypt, regarding the force of Pharao Nechao, king of Egypt, who was by the river Euphrates at Charchamis, whom King Nabouchodonosor of Babylon struck in the fourth year of King Ioakim of Iouda:<verse eid="JER 26:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:3"/>Take up weapons and shields, and advance for battle!<verse eid="JER 26:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:4"/>Saddle the horses; mount up, you horsemen! And take your stations with your helmets; throw your lances, and put on your breastplates!<verse eid="JER 26:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:5"/>Why is it that they are terrified and they fall back?-- for their strong shall be beaten down. They have fled in flight and did not turn back, being encircled all around! says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 26:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:6"/>Let not the swift flee away, and let not the strong one escape; to the north, the regions by the Euphrates were powerless; they have fallen.<verse eid="JER 26:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:7"/>Who is this that will rise up like a river, and like rivers surge with water?<verse eid="JER 26:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:8"/>Waters of Egypt will rise up like a river, and it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'waters' or 'river'</char></note> said, I will rise up and cover land and destroy inhabitants in it.<verse eid="JER 26:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:9"/>Mount on the horses; prepare the chariots! Go forth, O warriors of the Ethiopians and Libyans armed with weapons, and grasp, O Lydians; draw the bow.<verse eid="JER 26:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:10"/>And that day belongs to the Lord, our God, a day of vengeance, to take vengeance on his enemies. And a dagger of the Lord shall devour and be sated and be drunk with their blood, because there<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'it'</char></note> is a sacrifice for the Lord from the land of the north by the river Euphrates.<verse eid="JER 26:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:11"/>Go up, O Galaad, and take pine resin to the virgin daughter of Egypt! In vain you have multiplied your medicines; there is no help for you.<verse eid="JER 26:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:12"/>Nations have heard your voice, and the earth was filled with your cry, because warrior was weak against warrior; both have fallen together.<verse eid="JER 26:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:13"/>What the Lord spoke by the hand of Ieremias that the king of Babylon would come to smite the land of Egypt:<verse eid="JER 26:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:14"/>Declare in Magdolos, and proclaim in Memphis; Say, "Set up, and be ready, because a dagger devoured your yew<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'holm oak'</char></note>."<verse eid="JER 26:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:15"/>Why has Apis fled? Your [choice] bull calf did not remain, because the Lord paralyzed him.<verse eid="JER 26:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:16"/>And your multitude was weak and fell, and each kept saying to his fellow, "Let us rise up and return to our own people and to our fatherland, because of the Greek dagger."<verse eid="JER 26:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:17"/>Call the name of Pharao Nechao, king of Egypt, Saon-esbi-emoed<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'braggart who missed his chance'</char></note>.<verse eid="JER 26:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:18"/>I live, says the Lord God, because he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Nabouchodonosor'?</char></note> shall come like Itabyrion<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Mt. Tabor'</char></note> among the mountains and like Carmel by the sea.<verse eid="JER 26:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:19"/>Make for yourself implements for going into exile, resident daughter of Egypt, because Memphis shall become an annihilation, and it shall be burned, because there are no inhabitants in it.<verse eid="JER 26:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:20"/>A beautified heifer is Egypt-- a fragment from the north came upon her.<verse eid="JER 26:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:21"/>And her mercenaries in her are like grain-fed calves, for they too have turned and fled together; they did not stand, because a day of ruin has come upon them, and a time for their punishment.<verse eid="JER 26:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:22"/>A sound like of a hissing snake, because they will travel in sand, and they will come against her with axes, like people felling trees.<verse eid="JER 26:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:23"/>They shall cut down her forest, says the Lord, because there shall be nothing like it, because it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:23</char><char closed="false" style="ft">', because it':  I.e. 'forest'</char></note> is more numerous than grasshoppers, and they are without number.<verse eid="JER 26:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:24"/>The daughter of Egypt was put to shame; she was handed over into the hands of a people from the north.<verse eid="JER 26:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:25"/>Behold, I am avenging Amon, her son, on Pharao and on those who trust in him.<verse eid="JER 26:25"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 26:26"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:26</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 26:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:27"/>But as for you, have no fear, my slave Iakob, nor be terrified, O Israel; for behold, I am saving you from far away and your offspring from the land of their captivity. And Iakob shall return and have quiet and sleep, and there shall be no one to cause him difficulty.<verse eid="JER 26:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 26:28"/>Have no fear, my servant Iakob, says the Lord, because I am with you, because I will make an end among every nation, among people to whom I have banished you there, but I will not make you to fail! And I will discipline you in just measure, and when I deem innocent, I will not deem you innocent.<verse eid="JER 26:28"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 27">
<verse sid="JER 27:1"/>(50.1) A word of the Lord, which he spoke regarding Babylon.<verse eid="JER 27:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:2"/>Declare among the nations, and make heard, and do not conceal; say: Babylon has been taken; [Bel] the undaunted was put to shame; the gentle [Marodach was undone],<verse eid="JER 27:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:3"/>because from the north a nation has come up against her; he shall make her land an annihilation, and there shall be no one to live in it, from human being even to animal.<verse eid="JER 27:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:4"/>In those days and in that time the sons of Israel shall come, they and the sons of Iouda together; they shall come walking and weeping as they seek the Lord, their God.<verse eid="JER 27:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:5"/>They shall ask the way to Sion, for here they will set their face, and they shall come and flee for refuge to the Lord God, for an everlasting covenant will not be forgotten.<verse eid="JER 27:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:6"/>My people have become lost sheep; their shepherds expelled them; they have misled them to the mountains; from mountain to hill they went; they have forgotten their fold.<verse eid="JER 27:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:7"/>All who would find them would devour them; their enemies said, "Let us not release them, because they have sinned against the Lord. A pasture of righteousness they are<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">27:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'they are':  Lacking in Greek</char></note> for the one who gathered their fathers."<verse eid="JER 27:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:8"/>Become a stranger from the midst of Babylon and from the land of the Chaldeans, and go out, and become like dragons before sheep,<verse eid="JER 27:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:9"/>because behold, I am stirring up against Babylon gatherings of nations from the land of the north, and they shall array themselves against her; from there she shall be taken, as an arrow of a skilled warrior will not return empty.<verse eid="JER 27:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:10"/>Chaldea shall be for plunder; all who plunder her shall be sated--<verse eid="JER 27:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:11"/>because you were rejoicing and boasting while plundering my heritage; for you were frisking about like heifers in pasture, and you were butting horns like bulls;<verse eid="JER 27:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:12"/>your mother was utterly shamed, a mother for good, last<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">27:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'mother'</char></note> of nations, a wilderness.<verse eid="JER 27:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:13"/>Because of the wrath of the Lord she shall not be inhabited, and all of her shall become an annihilation, and everyone who passes through Babylon shall be sullen and whistle because of her every wound.<verse eid="JER 27:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:14"/>Take up your positions against Babylon round about, all you that bend a bow; shoot at her; do not be sparing with your arrows.<verse eid="JER 27:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:15"/>And applaud exceedingly over her: "Her hands were paralyzed; her bulwarks have fallen, and her wall was razed." Because vengeance is from God, take vengeance on her; do to her as she has done.<verse eid="JER 27:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:16"/>Utterly destroy seed from Babylon, and the wielder of the sickle in time of harvest; because of the Greek dagger, each of them shall return to his own people, and each of them shall flee to his own land.<verse eid="JER 27:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:17"/>Israel is a wandering sheep; lions drove him away. The first one, king of Assour, devoured him, and this later one, king of Babylon, his bones.<verse eid="JER 27:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:18"/>Therefore, this is what the Lord says: Behold, I am taking vengeance on the king of Babylon and on his land, as I took vengeance on the king of As-sour.<verse eid="JER 27:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:19"/>And I will restore Israel to his pasture, and he shall feed on Carmel and on Mount Ephraim and in Galaad, and his soul shall be satisfied.<verse eid="JER 27:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:20"/>In those days and at that time they will seek the injustice of Israel, and there shall be none, and the sins of Iouda, also they shall not be found, because I will be merciful to those that have remained in the land, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 27:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:21"/>Go up bitterly against her and against the inhabitants in her; take vengeance, O dagger, and annihilate, says the Lord, and act according to all that I am commanding you.<verse eid="JER 27:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:22"/>A noise of battle and great destruction is in the land of the Chaldeans!<verse eid="JER 27:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:23"/>How was the hammer of the whole earth broken and shattered! How has Babylon turned into an annihilation among nations!<verse eid="JER 27:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:24"/>They will attack you, and you will be taken, O Babylon, and you will not know it; you were discovered and seized, because you withstood the Lord.<verse eid="JER 27:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:25"/>The Lord has opened his store room and brought out the implements of his wrath, because there is a task for the Lord God in the land of the Chaldeans.<verse eid="JER 27:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:26"/>For her times have come. Open her storehouses; search her like a cave, and destroy her utterly; let there be no remnant of her.<verse eid="JER 27:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:27"/>Dry up all her fruit, and let them go down to slaughter. Woe to them, because their day has come and the time of their punishment!<verse eid="JER 27:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:28"/>A sound of people fleeing and escaping from the land of Babylon to declare in Sion the vengeance of the Lord, our God.<verse eid="JER 27:28"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:29"/>Summon many against Babylon, every one who bends a bow. Make a camp against her, all around; let there be no one to escape. Repay her according to her deeds; just as she has done, do to her-- because she withstood the Lord, holy God of Israel.<verse eid="JER 27:29"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:30"/>Therefore her young men shall fall in her squares, and all her fighting men shall be thrown down, said the Lord.<verse eid="JER 27:30"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:31"/>Behold, I am against you the arrogant one, says the Lord, because your day has come and the time of your punishment.<verse eid="JER 27:31"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:32"/>And your arrogance shall become weak and fall, and there shall not be one to raise it up, and I will kindle a fire in her<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">27:32</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Babylon'</char></note> forest, and it will devour everything around her<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">27:32</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Babylon'</char></note>.<verse eid="JER 27:32"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:33"/>This is what the Lord says: The sons of Israel have been oppressed, and so too the sons of Iouda; all their captors have oppressed them, because they were unwilling to send them off.<verse eid="JER 27:33"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:34"/>And he that redeems them is strong; the Lord Almighty is his name. He will judge with judgment against his adversaries, that he may destroy the earth, and for those that inhabit Babylon he will incite<verse eid="JER 27:34"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:35"/>a dagger against the Chaldeans and against the inhabitants of Babylon and against her nobles and against her sages,<verse eid="JER 27:35"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:36"/>a dagger against her warriors-- and they shall be paralyzed-- a dagger against their horses and against their chariots,<verse eid="JER 27:36"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:37"/>a dagger against their warriors and against the mixed populace in her midst-- and they shall become like women-- a dagger against her treasures-- and they shall be scattered<verse eid="JER 27:37"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:38"/>by her water, and they shall be disgraced, because it is a land of carved images, and in the islands they were boasting.<verse eid="JER 27:38"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:39"/>Therefore phantoms shall live in the islands, and daughters of Sirens shall inhabit her; she shall never again be inhabited forever.<verse eid="JER 27:39"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:40"/>As when God overturned Sodoma and Gomorra and those adjacent to them, said the Lord, no person shall live there, and no son of man shall sojourn there.<verse eid="JER 27:40"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:41"/>Behold, a people is coming from the north, and a great nation and many kings shall be stirred from the farthest part of the earth,<verse eid="JER 27:41"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:42"/>wielding bow and hand knife; it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">27:42</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'people'</char></note> is reckless and will show no mercy. The noise of them shall sound like the sea; they will ride upon horses, equipped, like a fire for battle against you, O daughter Babylon!<verse eid="JER 27:42"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:43"/>The king of Babylon heard news of them, and his hands became paralyzed; affliction tightly seized him, pains like those of one giving birth.<verse eid="JER 27:43"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:44"/>Behold, just like a lion it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">27:44</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'people' v. 41</char></note> will come up from the Jordan into Aithan-- because I will quickly pursue them away from her<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">27:44</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'Babylon'</char></note>, and I will set every young man against her. For who is like me? And who will withstand me? And who is this shepherd who will stand against me?<verse eid="JER 27:44"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:45"/>Therefore, hear the plan of the Lord, which he has planned against Babylon, and his purposes that he has formed against the inhabiting Chaldeans: If the lambs of the sheep be not killed, if their pasture be not annihilated from them ...--<verse eid="JER 27:45"/>

<verse sid="JER 27:46"/>because at the sound of the capture of Babylon the earth shall tremble, and her cry shall be heard among nations.<verse eid="JER 27:46"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 28">
<verse sid="JER 28:1"/>(51.1) This is what the Lord says: Behold, I am stirring up a destructive scorching wind against Babylon and against the inhabiting Chaldeans,<verse eid="JER 28:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:2"/>and I will send insolent men to Babylon, and they shall treat her with insolence and shall maltreat her land. Woe to Babylon on every side on the day of her trouble.<verse eid="JER 28:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:3"/>Let him that bends his bow bend it, and let him who has his armor put it on. Do not be sparing toward her young men, and annihilate her entire force.<verse eid="JER 28:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:4"/>And they shall fall down slain in the land of the Chaldeans and be pierced outside of her,<verse eid="JER 28:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:5"/>for Israel and Iouda<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = 'Ioudas'</char></note> did not become widowed from their God, from the Lord Almighty, because their land is full of injustice against the holy things of Israel!<verse eid="JER 28:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:6"/>Flee from the midst of Babylon, and save your souls, each of you! And do not be cast aside in her injustice, because it is a time of vengeance on her from the Lord; he is repaying repayment to her.<verse eid="JER 28:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:7"/>Babylon was a golden cup in the Lord's hand, making all the earth drunken; nations drank of her wine; therefore they were shaken.<verse eid="JER 28:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:8"/>And suddenly Babylon fell and was shattered; wail for her! Bring pine resin for her ruin, if perhaps she shall be healed.<verse eid="JER 28:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:9"/>We treated Babylon, but she was not healed. Let us forsake her, and let each of us go away to his own country, because her judgment has reached skyward; it rose up even to the stars.<verse eid="JER 28:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:10"/>The Lord has brought forth his judgment; come, and let us declare in Sion the works of the Lord, our God.<verse eid="JER 28:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:11"/>Equip the arrows! Fill the quivers! The Lord has stirred up the spirit of the king of the Medes, because his wrath is against Babylon to destroy it utterly, because it is vengeance from the Lord, vengeance for his shrine.<verse eid="JER 28:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:12"/>Raise a standard on the walls of Babylon; set up quivers; awaken the watch; prepare weapons; because he has taken in hand and the Lord will do what he spoke against the inhabitants of Babylon,<verse eid="JER 28:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:13"/>though she encamps by abundant waters and by the multitude of her treasures-- your end has truly come into your inwards,<verse eid="JER 28:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:14"/>because the Lord has sworn by his arm: For I will fill you with people like grasshoppers, and those that come down shall utter a sound against you.<verse eid="JER 28:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:15"/>When he was making the earth by his strength, when he was preparing the world by his wisdom, by his understanding he stretched out the sky;<verse eid="JER 28:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:16"/>he made the sound of water a voice in the sky, and he brought up clouds from the end of the earth. Lightnings he made into rain and brought out light from his store rooms.<verse eid="JER 28:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:17"/>Every person became vain, apart from<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'apart from':  I.e. 'without'</char></note> knowledge; every goldsmith was put to shame by his carved images; because they<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'goldsmiths'</char></note> cast lies, there is no breath in them.<verse eid="JER 28:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:18"/>Worthless they are, works to be ridiculed; at the time of their visiting they shall perish.<verse eid="JER 28:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:19"/>Such a portion is not Iakob's, because he who formed all things, he is his inheritance; the Lord is his name.<verse eid="JER 28:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:20"/>It is you who scatter for me implements of war, and in you I will scatter nations, and from<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'in consequence of'</char></note> you I will destroy kings,<verse eid="JER 28:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:21"/>and in you I will scatter a horse and its rider,<verse eid="JER 28:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:22"/>(21b) and in you I will scatter chariots and their charioteers, and in you I will scatter young man and girl, and in you I will scatter man and woman,<verse eid="JER 28:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:23"/>and in you I will scatter a shepherd and his flock, and in you I will scatter a farmer and his husbandry, and in you I will scatter leaders and generals.<verse eid="JER 28:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:24"/>And I will repay to Babylon and all the inhabiting Chaldeans all their wrongs that they have done against Sion before your very eyes, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 28:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:25"/>Behold, I am against you, the corrupted mountain that corrupts the whole earth, and I will stretch out my hand against you and roll you down from the rocks and render you like a burned-out mountain.<verse eid="JER 28:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:26"/>And they shall take no stone from you for a corner and no stone for a foundation, because you shall be an annihilation forever, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 28:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:27"/>Raise a standard on the land; trumpet with a trumpet among nations; consecrate nations against her, summon against her kingdoms of Araret, from me also the Aschanazeans; set up siege engines against her; mount up against her cavalry like a multitude of grasshoppers.<verse eid="JER 28:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:28"/>Consecrate nations against her, the king of the Medes and of the whole earth, his leading men and all his generals.<verse eid="JER 28:28"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:29"/>The land shook and toiled, for the Lord's purpose against Babylon stood, to make the land of Babylon an annihilation and that she would not be inhabited.<verse eid="JER 28:29"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:30"/>Babylon's warrior gave up fighting; they will sit there under siege; their dominance was broken; they became like women; her quarters were set on fire; her bars were crushed.<verse eid="JER 28:30"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:31"/>A pursuer will pursue to meet a pursuer, and a reporter to meet a reporter, to report to the king of Babylon that his city has been taken:<verse eid="JER 28:31"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:32"/>at the end of his fords they were seized, and their communities were burnt with fire, and his fighting men are coming out,<verse eid="JER 28:32"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:33"/>for this is what the Lord says: Houses of the king of Babylon will be threshed like a threshing floor in season; yet a little while and her harvest time will come.<verse eid="JER 28:33"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:34"/>"King Nabouchodonosor of Babylon has devoured me; he has apportioned me; he has seized me, a slim vessel; he has swallowed me like a dragon; he has filled his belly with my delicacies.<verse eid="JER 28:34"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:35"/>My hardships and my miseries drove me into Babylon," resident Sion shall say. "And my blood be<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:35</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> on the residing Chaldeans," Ierousalem shall say.<verse eid="JER 28:35"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:36"/>Therefore this is what the Lord says: Behold, I am judging your adversary and will take vengeance for you. And I will make desolate her sea and make her fountain dry,<verse eid="JER 28:36"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:37"/>and Babylon shall become an annihilation and shall not be inhabited.<verse eid="JER 28:37"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:38"/>As well, like lions they were aroused, and like lions' whelps.<verse eid="JER 28:38"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:39"/>When they are hot I will give them drink and make them drunk in order that they be stupefied and sleep a perpetual sleep and never wake, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 28:39"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:40"/>I will bring them down like lambs to slaughter and like rams with kids.<verse eid="JER 28:40"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:41"/>How she was taken, and the boast of the whole earth taken prey! How Babylon has become an annihilation among the nations!<verse eid="JER 28:41"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:42"/>The sea has come up to Babylon by the sound of its waves, and she has been covered up.<verse eid="JER 28:42"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:43"/>Her cities have become a waterless land and untrodden; no one will live in her, nor will a son of man lodge in her.<verse eid="JER 28:43"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:44"/>I will take vengeance on Babylon and bring out from her mouth what she has swallowed. And the nations shall no longer gather to her.<verse eid="JER 28:44"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 28:45"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:45</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 28:45"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 28:46"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:46</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 28:46"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 28:47"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:47</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 28:47"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 28:48"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:48</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 28:48"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:49"/>And in Babylon slain of all the earth will fall.<verse eid="JER 28:49"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:50"/>Since you are survivors of the land, go, and do not stop! You afar off, remember the Lord, and let Ierousalem come up into your heart:<verse eid="JER 28:50"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:51"/>We were put to shame, because we have heard our insult; dishonor has covered our face; aliens have entered into our holy places, into the Lord's house.<verse eid="JER 28:51"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:52"/>Therefore behold, days are coming, says the Lord, and I will take vengeance on her carved images, and in all her land wounded shall fall,<verse eid="JER 28:52"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:53"/>because, if Babylon should mount up like the sky, and because, if she should fortify the height of her strength, from me those who destroy utterly will come upon her, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 28:53"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:54"/>A sound of a cry in Babylon! And a great crashing in the land of the Chaldeans,<verse eid="JER 28:54"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:55"/>because the Lord utterly destroyed Babylon and ruined her great voice roaring like many waters; he gave her voice to destruction,<verse eid="JER 28:55"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:56"/>because distress has come against Babylon; her warriors were taken; their bow has been terrified, for a god is repaying them.<verse eid="JER 28:56"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:57"/>The Lord repays repayment to her, (57) and he will make drunk with drunkenness her leaders and her sages and her generals, says the King; Lord Almighty is his name.<verse eid="JER 28:57"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:58"/>This is what the Lord says: Babylon's wall was made broad; in being leveled it shall be leveled, and her high gates shall be set on fire. And peoples will not exhaust themselves for nothing, and nations shall fail in rule.<verse eid="JER 28:58"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:59"/>The word that the Lord commanded Ieremias the prophet to speak to Saraias son of Nerias son of Maasaias, when he was going with King Sedekias of Iouda to Babylon, in the fourth year of his reign. And Saraias was ruler of gifts.<verse eid="JER 28:59"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:60"/>And Ieremias wrote in one book all the evils that would come on Babylon, all these words that have been written regarding Babylon.<verse eid="JER 28:60"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:61"/>And Ieremias said to Saraias: "When you come to Babylon, also see and read all these words,<verse eid="JER 28:61"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:62"/>and you will say, 'O Lord, O Lord, it was you who spoke against this place to destroy it utterly and so that neither human nor animal inhabitants be in it, because it shall be an annihilation forever.'<verse eid="JER 28:62"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:63"/>And it shall be when you finish reading this book, you will then tie a stone to it and throw it into the middle of the Euphrates,<verse eid="JER 28:63"/>

<verse sid="JER 28:64"/>and you will say, 'Thus shall Babylon sink, and it shall rise up no more before the Chaldeans whom I am bringing on her.' "<verse eid="JER 28:64"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 29">
<verse sid="JER 29:1"/>(47.1) Regarding the allophyles. (2) This is what the Lord says:<verse eid="JER 29:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:2"/>Behold, waters are rising from the north and shall become a wadi overflowing and shall overflow a land and all that fills it, a city and those who live in it. And humans shall cry out, and all the inhabitants of the land shall shout.<verse eid="JER 29:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:3"/>At the noise of his onslaught, at the hoofs of his horses and at the commotion of his chariots, the noise of his wheels, fathers did not turn back for their sons, because of the feebleness of their hands,<verse eid="JER 29:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:4"/>in the day that is coming to destroy all the allophyles, and I will annihilate Tyre and Sidon and all those that remain for their help, because the Lord will utterly destroy those remaining in the islands.<verse eid="JER 29:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:5"/>Baldness has come upon Gaza; Ascalon was cast away, and the remaining Enakim.<verse eid="JER 29:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:6"/>How long will you cut, you dagger of the Lord? How long until you will be quiet? Restore yourself to your scabbard; rest, and be lifted up!<verse eid="JER 29:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:7"/>How shall it be quiet? And the Lord has ordered it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">29:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'dagger'</char></note> against Ascalon and against the seashores, against those remaining, that it be aroused.<verse eid="JER 29:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:8"/>(49.7) For Idumea. This is what the Lord says: There is no longer wisdom in Thaiman; counsel has perished from the prudent; their wisdom is vanishing;<verse eid="JER 29:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:9"/>(8) their face was misled. Sink deep into sitting, you that live in Dedan, because he did difficult things. I brought them<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">29:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> upon him at the time when I visited upon him,<verse eid="JER 29:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:10"/>(9) because grape gatherers came, who shall not leave for you things gleaned. As thieves by night they shall place their hand.<verse eid="JER 29:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:11"/>(10) Because I have ravaged Esau, I have uncovered their hiding places; they will not be able to hide; his brother's and his neighbor's rewards perished, and it is not possible<verse eid="JER 29:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:12"/>(11) for your orphan to be left in order to live, and widows trust in me--<verse eid="JER 29:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:13"/>(12) because this is what the Lord says: They who were not accustomed to drink the cup drank, and you, though being deemed innocent, shall not be declared innocent,<verse eid="JER 29:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:14"/>(13) because by myself I have sworn, says the Lord, that you shall become, in her<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">29:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Perhaps 'Idumea'?</char></note> midst, untrodden and an object of reproach and of cursing and all her towns shall be desolate forever.<verse eid="JER 29:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:15"/>(14) I have heard a tiding from the Lord, and he sent messengers to nations: "Gather yourselves together and come against her<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">29:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Idumea'</char></note>; rise up for battle!"<verse eid="JER 29:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:16"/>(15) I rendered you small among nations, despised among humankind.<verse eid="JER 29:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:17"/>(16) Your sporting laid hands on you; recklessness of your heart broke up holes in rocks; it seized strength of a high hill. Because like an eagle he set his nest high, from there I will bring you down.<verse eid="JER 29:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:18"/>(17) Idumea shall become untrodden; everyone who passes by will hiss at her.<verse eid="JER 29:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:19"/>(18) Just as Sodoma was overthrown, and Gomorra and her resident-alien towns, said the Lord Almighty, no person shall ever set down there, and no son of man shall dwell there.<verse eid="JER 29:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:20"/>(19) Behold, just like a lion it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">29:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Referent unclear</char></note> will come up from the midst of the Jordan to a place of Aithan-- because I will quickly pursue them away from her. Appoint over her<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">29:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'. Appoint over her':  Perhaps 'Idumea'?</char></note> the young men-- because who is like me? And who can withstand me? And who is this shepherd who will stand against me?<verse eid="JER 29:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:21"/>(20) Therefore, hear the Lord's plan, which he planned against Idumea, and his purpose, which he purposed against the inhabitants of Thaiman: If the least of the sheep be not swept away, if their lodging be not made untrodden to her!--<verse eid="JER 29:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:22"/>(21) because at the sound of their fall the earth feared, and a cry was heard at the sea of Souph.<verse eid="JER 29:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 29:23"/>(22) Behold, just like an eagle, he will see and extend the wings over her strongholds! And the heart of the strong of Idumea in that day shall be like the heart of a woman in labor.<verse eid="JER 29:23"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 30">
<verse sid="JER 30:1"/>(49.1) For the sons of Ammon. Thus did the Lord say: Surely, there are no sons in Israel, or have they none to succeed<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">30:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'by inheritance'</char></note>? Why did Melchol take Galaad, and shall their people settle in their towns?<verse eid="JER 30:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 30:2"/>Therefore behold, days are coming, quoth the Lord, I will make heard the tumult of battles against Rabbath; they shall become untrodden and a destruction, and her altars<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">30:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = bômos</char></note> shall be burned down with fire, and Israel shall succeed<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">30:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'by inheritance'</char></note> his rule.<verse eid="JER 30:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 30:3"/>Shout, O Hesebon, because Gai perished! Cry out, O daughters of Rabbath! Put on sackcloth, and lament, because Melchol shall go in exile, his priests and his rulers together.<verse eid="JER 30:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 30:4"/>Why will you rejoice in the plains, O daughter of disgrace who trusted in her treasures, who said, "Who will enter against me?"<verse eid="JER 30:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 30:5"/>Behold, I am bringing fear upon you, said the Lord, from all your surrounding area, and you will be scattered, each headlong, and there shall be no one to gather.<verse eid="JER 30:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 30:6"/>(28) For Kedar, the queen of the court, whom King Nabouchodonosor of Babylon struck. Thus did the Lord say: Rise up, and advance against Kedar, and strike the sons of Kedem!<verse eid="JER 30:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 30:7"/>(29) They shall take their tents and their sheep; their clothes and all their implements and their camels they shall take for themselves. And summon destruction against them all around!<verse eid="JER 30:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 30:8"/>(30) Flee very much; sink deep into sitting, you seated in the court, because the king of Babylon has planned a plan against you and formed a purpose against you.<verse eid="JER 30:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 30:9"/>(31) Rise up, and advance against a nation at ease, that sits in respite; they have no doors, no bolt pins; [no bars] they lodge alone.<verse eid="JER 30:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 30:10"/>(32) And their camels shall become plunder, and the multitude of their cattle, destruction. And with every wind I will winnow them, when they have been sheared before them. I will bring their rout from their every side, said the Lord.<verse eid="JER 30:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 30:11"/>(33) And the court shall become a haunt of sparrows and untrodden forever; no person shall ever sit down there, and no son of an earthborn shall settle there.<verse eid="JER 30:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 30:12"/>(23) For Damascus. Hemath and Arphad were put to shame, because they have heard bad tidings; they were astonished; they were angered; they will not be able to rest.<verse eid="JER 30:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 30:13"/>(24) Damascus has become undone; she turned to flight; trembling seized her.<verse eid="JER 30:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 30:14"/>(25) How did she not forsake a praiseworthy city, a village which I loved?<verse eid="JER 30:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 30:15"/>(26) Therefore young men shall fall in your squares, and all your warrior men shall fall, quoth the Lord.<verse eid="JER 30:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 30:16"/>(27) And I will burn a fire at Damascus' wall, and it shall devour the quarters of the son of Hader.<verse eid="JER 30:16"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 31">
<verse sid="JER 31:1"/>(48.1) For Moab. Thus did the Lord say: Woe for Nabau, because he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">31:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'it'</char></note> perished! Kariathaim was taken; Hamasagab was put to shame, and Hatath.<verse eid="JER 31:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:2"/>Healing of Moab is no more; in Hesebon they planned evil against her: "We cut her off from being a nation!" She shall stop with a stop; a dagger shall go after you,<verse eid="JER 31:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:3"/>because a voice of people that cry from Horonaim, "Desolation and a great fracture!"<verse eid="JER 31:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:4"/>"Moab was crushed!" announce to Zogora.<verse eid="JER 31:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:5"/>Because Halaoth was filled by weeping, he will go up weeping by way of Horonaim; a cry of fracture you have heard.<verse eid="JER 31:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:6"/>Flee, and save your souls, and you shall be like a wild ass in a wilderness!<verse eid="JER 31:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:7"/>Seeing that you trusted in your strongholds, you also shall be seized. And Chamos shall go out in exile, his priests and his rulers together.<verse eid="JER 31:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:8"/>And destruction shall come upon every city; it shall not be saved. And the valley shall perish, and the plain shall be destroyed utterly, as the Lord has said.<verse eid="JER 31:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:9"/>Give signs to Moab, because she will be kindled with kindling, and all her cities shall become untrodden; from where will she get an inhabitant?<verse eid="JER 31:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:10"/>Accursed is the one who is doing the work of the Lord carelessly by keeping back his dagger from bloodshed.<verse eid="JER 31:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:11"/>Moab was at rest from childhood and trusted in his glory; he did not pour from vessel to vessel, and he was not going into exile; therefore his flavor remained in him, and his aroma did not leave.<verse eid="JER 31:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:12"/>Therefore behold, days are coming, quoth the Lord, and I shall send to him people that deviate, and they will make him deviate, and they shall pulverize his vessels and break up his mixtures.<verse eid="JER 31:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:13"/>And Moab shall be ashamed of Chamos, as the house of Israel was ashamed of Baithel, when they had confidence in them.<verse eid="JER 31:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:14"/>How will you say, "We are strong and a strong person in warfare"?<verse eid="JER 31:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:15"/>Moab perished; his city and his choice young men went down to slaughter.<verse eid="JER 31:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:16"/>Moab's day is near to come, and his wickedness, very swiftly.<verse eid="JER 31:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:17"/>Stir for him, all you round about him and all who know his name; say, "How has a renowned staff broken to pieces, a rod of magnificence!"<verse eid="JER 31:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:18"/>Come down from glory, and sit on moist ground; seated she is being destroyed, because Moab has perished; he that ruins your stronghold came up against you.<verse eid="JER 31:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:19"/>Stand by the road, and watch, you<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">31:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = fem singular</char></note> that sit in Aroer! And ask him that flees and escapes, and say, "What has happened?"<verse eid="JER 31:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:20"/>Moab was put to shame, because he was broken to pieces; wail, and cry! Tell it in Arnon that Moab has perished.<verse eid="JER 31:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:21"/>And judgment is coming to the land of Misor, upon Chelon and upon Rephas and upon Mophaath<verse eid="JER 31:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:22"/>and upon Daibon and upon Nabau and upon the house of Deblathaim<verse eid="JER 31:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:23"/>and upon Kariathaim and upon the house of Gamol and upon the house of Maon<verse eid="JER 31:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:24"/>and upon Karioth and upon Bosor and upon all the cities of Moab, those far and those near.<verse eid="JER 31:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:25"/>Moab's horn was cut off, and his effort was crushed.<verse eid="JER 31:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:26"/>Make him drunk, because he was magnified against the Lord, and Moab shall clap with his hand, and he too shall become a laughingstock.<verse eid="JER 31:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:27"/>And if not, was Israel a jest for you? If he was found among your thefts, is it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">31:27</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'is it':  Lacking in Greek</char></note> because you kept fighting him?<verse eid="JER 31:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:28"/>The inhabitants of Moab left the cities and lived among rocks; they became like doves that nest among rocks at the mouth of a gorge.<verse eid="JER 31:28"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:29"/>I heard of Moab's insolence; he was very insolent in his insolence and his arrogance. And his heart was lifted up.<verse eid="JER 31:29"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:30"/>But I knew his works. It was not enough for him; he did not do thus.<verse eid="JER 31:30"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:31"/>Therefore wail for Moab on all sides; shout to the men of Kir Hadas, of drought.<verse eid="JER 31:31"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:32"/>As with the weeping for Iazer I will weep for you, O vine of Sebema! Your branches crossed over the sea; cities reached Iazer; upon your summer fruit, upon your grape gatherers destruction has fallen.<verse eid="JER 31:32"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:33"/>Joy and gladness were swept away from the land of Moabitis, and wine was in your vats; they did not tread in the early morning; "aided"<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">31:33</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'shouting'</char></note> "aided"<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">31:33</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'shouting'</char></note>, [they did] not "aided"<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">31:33</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'shouting'</char></note><verse eid="JER 31:33"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:34"/>From a cry of Hesebon as far as Eleale, their cities gave forth their voice, from Zogor as far as Horonaim and Agela Salasia, because even the water of Nebrim shall become something burnt.<verse eid="JER 31:34"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:35"/>And I will destroy Moab, quoth the Lord, since he ascends upon an altar<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">31:35</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = bômos</char></note> and offers incense to his gods.<verse eid="JER 31:35"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:36"/>Therefore my heart will <note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">31:36</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = fem singular</char></note>rumble<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">31:36</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> for Moab<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">31:36</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek uncertain</char></note> as pipes will rumble; my heart will rumble like a pipe for the people of Kir Hadas. Therefore, what one gained perished [from a person].<verse eid="JER 31:36"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:37"/>They will have every head in every place shaved, and every beard shall be shaved, and all hands shall beat, and sackcloth on every loin,<verse eid="JER 31:37"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:38"/>even on all the housetops of Moab and in her squares, because I have crushed her, quoth the Lord, like a container for which no one has any use.<verse eid="JER 31:38"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:39"/>How Hatat shouted! How Moab turned her back! Moab was ashamed and became a laughingstock and an object of indignation to all those about her--<verse eid="JER 31:39"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:40"/>because thus did the Lord say:<verse eid="JER 31:40"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:41"/>Hakkarioth was seized, and the strongholds were also seized.<verse eid="JER 31:41"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:42"/>And Moab shall be destroyed from being a crowd, because he was magnified against the Lord.<verse eid="JER 31:42"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:43"/>Trap and fear and pit are upon you, you seated one of Moab!<verse eid="JER 31:43"/>

<verse sid="JER 31:44"/>He who flees from before fear shall fall into the pit, and he who climbs out of the pit shall be caught in the trap, because I will bring these things upon Moab in the year of their visiting.<verse eid="JER 31:44"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 32">
<verse sid="JER 32:1"/>(25.15) Thus did the Lord, the God of Israel, say: Take from my hand the cup of this unmixed wine, and you shall make all the nations, to them to whom I send you, drink,<verse eid="JER 32:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:2"/>(16) and they are vomiting and will go out of their minds before the dagger that I am sending among them.<verse eid="JER 32:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:3"/>(17) And I took the cup from the Lord's hand and made the nations, to whom the Lord sent me to them, drink:<verse eid="JER 32:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:4"/>(18) Ierousalem and the cities of Iouda and its kings and its rulers, to make them a desolation and something untrodden and a hissing<verse eid="JER 32:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:5"/>(19) and Pharao king of Egypt and his servants and his nobles<verse eid="JER 32:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:6"/>(20) and all his people and all the mixed peoples and all the kings of the allophyles, Ascalon and Gaza and Akkaron and the remnant of Azotus<verse eid="JER 32:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:7"/>(21) and Idumea and Moabitis and the sons of Ammon<verse eid="JER 32:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:8"/>(22) and the kings of Tyre and the kings of Sidon and the kings who are across the sea<verse eid="JER 32:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:9"/>(23) and Dedan and Thaiman and Ros and every one shaven on his face<verse eid="JER 32:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:10"/>(24) and all the mixed peoples that lodge in the wilderness<verse eid="JER 32:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:11"/>(25) and all the kings of Ailam and all the kings of the Persians<verse eid="JER 32:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:12"/>(26) and all the kings from the east wind, those far and those near, each with his brother, and all the kingdoms that are on the surface of the earth.<verse eid="JER 32:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:13"/>(27) And you shall say to them, Thus did the Lord Almighty say: Drink, and get drunk, and vomit, and you will fall and rise no more from before the dagger that I am sending among you.<verse eid="JER 32:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:14"/>(28) And it will be if they refuse to accept the cup from your hand so as to drink, and you shall say: Thus did the Lord say: In drinking you shall drink,<verse eid="JER 32:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:15"/>(29) because I am beginning to bring evil on a city that my name is called on it, and you will not be cleansed with cleansing, because I am summoning a dagger against those settled on the earth.<verse eid="JER 32:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:16"/>(30) And you shall prophesy against them these words, and you will say: The Lord will give an oracle from on high; from his holy place give forth his voice; he will give a word as an oracle over his place, and they will answer, "aided"<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">32:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'shouting'</char></note>, like those that reap, and destruction has come on the inhabitants of the earth,<verse eid="JER 32:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:17"/>(31) on a part of the earth, because the Lord has an indictment against the nations; he is entering into judgment with all flesh, and the impious will be given over to a dagger, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 32:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:18"/>(32) Thus did the Lord say: Behold, evil is coming from nation to nation, and a great tempest is issuing from the farthest part of the earth!<verse eid="JER 32:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:19"/>(33) And there shall be slain by the Lord on the day of the Lord from one part of the earth even to another part of the earth. They shall not be interred; they shall become dung on the surface of the ground.<verse eid="JER 32:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:20"/>(34) Shout, you shepherds, and cry out, and beat yourselves, you rams of the sheep, because your days for slaughter have been fulfilled, and you shall fall like the choice rams.<verse eid="JER 32:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:21"/>(35) And flight shall perish from the shepherds, and deliverance from the rams of the sheep.<verse eid="JER 32:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:22"/>(36) A sound of a cry of the shepherds and a shouting of the rams of the sheep, because the Lord despoiled their fatted animals!<verse eid="JER 32:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:23"/>(37) And the lodgings of peace will cease from before the wrath of my anger.<verse eid="JER 32:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 32:24"/>(38) Like a lion he has left his lodging, because their land became untrodden from before the great dagger.<verse eid="JER 32:24"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 33">
<verse sid="JER 33:1"/>(26.1) At the beginning of King Ioakim son of Iosias, this word came from the Lord:<verse eid="JER 33:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:2"/>Thus did the Lord say: Stand in the court of the Lord's house, and you will give an oracle to all the Judeans that come to do obeisance in the house of the Lord all the words, which I instructed you to give them as an oracle; do not hold back a thing.<verse eid="JER 33:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:3"/>Perhaps they will hear and will turn each from his evil way, and I will cease from the evils that I am planning to do to them on account of their evil doings.<verse eid="JER 33:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:4"/>And you shall say: Thus did the Lord say: If you do not hear me, to walk in my precepts that I have given before you,<verse eid="JER 33:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:5"/>to heed the words of my servants the prophets whom I send to you early in the morning, and I sent and you did not heed me,<verse eid="JER 33:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:6"/>I will also give over this house like Selo, and I will give over the city as a curse, to all the nations of the entire earth.<verse eid="JER 33:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:7"/>And the priests and the pseudo-prophets and all the people heard Ieremias speaking these words in the house of the Lord.<verse eid="JER 33:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:8"/>And it happened when Ieremias had stopped speaking all that the Lord had instructed him to speak to all the people, then the priests and the pseudo-prophets and all the people laid hold of him, saying, "You shall die by death!<verse eid="JER 33:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:9"/>Whatever did you prophesy in the name of the Lord, saying, 'This house shall be like Selo, and this city shall be made desolate of inhabitants'?" And all the people assembled against Ieremias in the house of the Lord.<verse eid="JER 33:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:10"/>And Iouda's rulers heard this matter, and they came up from the king's house to the house of the Lord and took their seat in the entry of the new gate of the house of the Lord.<verse eid="JER 33:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:11"/>And the priests and the pseudo-prophets said to the rulers and to all the people, "A sentence of death on this person, because he has prophesied against this city, as you have heard with your own ears."<verse eid="JER 33:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:12"/>And Ieremias spoke to the rulers and to all the people, saying, "The Lord sent me to prophesy against this house and this city all the words you have heard.<verse eid="JER 33:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:13"/>And now make your ways and your deeds better, and obey the voice of the Lord, and the Lord will cease from the evils that he has spoken against you.<verse eid="JER 33:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:14"/>And behold, I am in your hands. Do with me as seems advantageous and as is better to you.<verse eid="JER 33:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:15"/>Only, in knowing you will know that, if you kill me, you are bringing innocent blood upon yourselves and upon this city and upon its inhabitants in it, because in truth the Lord has sent me to you to speak all these words in your ears."<verse eid="JER 33:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:16"/>And the rulers and all the people said to the priests and to the pseudo-prophets, "There is no sentence of death on this person, because he has spoken to us in the name of the Lord, our God."<verse eid="JER 33:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:17"/>And men of the elders of the land arose and said to the entire gathering of the people,<verse eid="JER 33:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:18"/>"There was Michaias the Morasthite in the days of King Hezekias of Iouda, and he said to all the people of Iouda: 'Thus did the Lord say, Sion shall be plowed like a field; and Ierousalem shall become untrodden, and the mountain of the house a forest grove.'<verse eid="JER 33:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:19"/>Surely, when killing, Hezekias and all Iouda did not kill him? Was it not that they feared the Lord and that they entreated the face of the Lord, and the Lord ceased from the evils that he had spoken against them? And we did great evils against our souls!"<verse eid="JER 33:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:20"/>There was a person prophesying in the name of the Lord, Ourias son of Samaias from Kariathiarim, and he prophesied concerning this land according to all the words of Ieremias.<verse eid="JER 33:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:21"/>And King Ioakim and all the rulers heard all his words, and they were seeking to kill him, and Ourias heard of it and entered into Egypt.<verse eid="JER 33:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:22"/>And the king sent men to Egypt,<verse eid="JER 33:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:23"/>and they brought him from there and led him to the king, and he struck him with a dagger and threw him into the burial place of the sons of his people.<verse eid="JER 33:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 33:24"/>In any case, the hand of Achikam son of Saphan was with Ieremias so as not to hand him over into the hands of the people to kill him.<verse eid="JER 33:24"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 34">
<verse sid="JER 34:1"/>(27.2) Thus did the Lord say: Make bonds and collars, and put them around your neck.<verse eid="JER 34:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:2"/>(3) And you will send them to the king of Idumea and to the king of Moab and to the king of the sons of Ammon and to the king of Tyre and to the king of Sidon by the hands of their envoys who are coming to meet them in Ierousalem, to King Sedekias of Iouda.<verse eid="JER 34:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:3"/>(4) And you will instruct them to say to their masters: Thus did the Lord, the God of Israel say: Thus you shall say to your masters:<verse eid="JER 34:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:4"/>(5) Because it is I who by my great strength and my lofty effort have made the earth, I will also give it to whom it may seem good in my eyes,<verse eid="JER 34:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:5"/>(6) I have given the earth to King Nabouchodonosor of Babylon to be subject to him, and the wild animals of the field to work for him.<verse eid="JER 34:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:6"/>(8) And the nation and the kingdom, as many as do not put their neck under the yoke of the king of Babylon, I will visit them with dagger and with famine, said the Lord, until they fail in his hand.<verse eid="JER 34:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:7"/>(9) And you, do not keep heeding your pseudo-prophets and your diviners and your dreamers and your soothsayers and your sorcerers, when they say, "You shall not work for the king of Babylon,"<verse eid="JER 34:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:8"/>(10) because they are prophesying lies to you so as to distance you far from your land.<verse eid="JER 34:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:9"/>(11) And the nation that brings its neck under the yoke of the king of Babylon and works for him, I will also leave him on his own land, and it will work for him and will live in it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">34:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'his own land'</char></note>.<verse eid="JER 34:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:10"/>(12) And I spoke to King Sedekias of Iouda according to all these words, saying: Bring your neck, and work for the king of Babylon,<verse eid="JER 34:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:11"/>(14) because they are prophesying wrong things to you,<verse eid="JER 34:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:12"/>(15) because I did not send them, quoth the Lord, and they are prophesying wrongly in my name so as to destroy you, and you will perish, you and your prophets who are [wrongly] prophesying lies to you.<verse eid="JER 34:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:13"/>(16) I spoke to you and all this people and the priests, saying, Thus did the Lord say: Do not listen to the words of the prophets who are prophesying to you, saying, "Behold, the vessels of the Lord's house are returning from Babylon," <note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">34:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'Because they are prophesying wrong things to you, I did not send them'</char></note>because they are prophesying wrong things to you;<verse eid="JER 34:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:14"/>(17) I did not send them<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">34:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'Because they are prophesying wrong things to you, I did not send them'</char></note>.<verse eid="JER 34:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:15"/>(18) If they are prophets and if there is a word of the Lord in them, let them counter me,<verse eid="JER 34:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:16"/>(19) because thus did the Lord say: Even some of the remaining vessels,<verse eid="JER 34:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:17"/>(20) which the king of Babylon did not take when he exiled Iechonias from Ierousalem,<verse eid="JER 34:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 34:18"/>(22) shall enter into Babylon, says the Lord.<verse eid="JER 34:18"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 35">
<verse sid="JER 35:1"/>(28.1) And it happened in the fourth year of King Sedekias of Iouda, in the fifth month that the pseudo-prophet Hananias son of Azor, from Gabaon, said to me in the house of the Lord, in the sight of the priests and all the people, saying,<verse eid="JER 35:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 35:2"/>"Thus did the Lord say: I have crushed the yoke of the king of Babylon.<verse eid="JER 35:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 35:3"/>Yet two years of days and I will bring back to this place the vessels of the Lord's house<verse eid="JER 35:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 35:4"/>and Iechonias and the exile of Iouda, because I will crush the yoke of the king of Babylon."<verse eid="JER 35:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 35:5"/>And Ieremias said to Hananias in the sight of all the people and in the sight of the priests who stood in the house of the Lord,<verse eid="JER 35:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 35:6"/>and Ieremias said, "Truly, thus may the Lord do; may the Lord establish the word which you prophesy, to bring back to this place from Babylon the vessels of the house of the Lord and all the exile.<verse eid="JER 35:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 35:7"/>In any case, hear a word of the Lord that I speak in your ears and in the ears of all the people.<verse eid="JER 35:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 35:8"/>The prophets who preceded me and preceded you<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">35:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = plural</char></note> from ancient times also prophesied with reference to much land and great kingdoms for war.<verse eid="JER 35:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 35:9"/>As for the prophet who prophesied for peace-- when the matter came to pass, they would know the prophet, him whom the Lord had sent in faithfulness."<verse eid="JER 35:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 35:10"/>And Hananias in the sight of all the people took the collars from the neck of Ieremias and crushed them.<verse eid="JER 35:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 35:11"/>And Hananias said in the sight of the people, saying, "Thus did the Lord say: Thus I will crush the yoke of the king of Babylon from the necks of all the nations." And Ieremias went on his way.<verse eid="JER 35:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 35:12"/>And a word of the Lord came to Ieremias after Hananias had crushed the collars from his neck:<verse eid="JER 35:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 35:13"/>Go, and say to Hananias, saying, Thus did the Lord say: Wooden collars you have crushed, and I will make iron collars in place of them!--<verse eid="JER 35:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 35:14"/>because thus did the Lord say: I have put an iron yoke on the neck of all the nations so that they might work for the king of Babylon.<verse eid="JER 35:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 35:15"/>And Ieremias said to Hananias, "The Lord has not sent you, and you have made this people trust wrongly.<verse eid="JER 35:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 35:16"/>Therefore thus did the Lord say: Behold, I am sending you from off the earth. In this year you will die."<verse eid="JER 35:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 35:17"/>And he died in the seventh month.<verse eid="JER 35:17"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 36">
<verse sid="JER 36:1"/>(29.1) And these are the words of the book, which Ieremias sent from Ierousalem to the elders of the exile and to the priests and to the pseudo-prophets, as a letter to the exile in Babylon and to all the people,<verse eid="JER 36:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:2"/>later than when King Iechonias and the queen and the eunuchs and every free person and prisoner and artisan had departed from Ierousalem,<verse eid="JER 36:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:3"/>by the hand of Eleasa son of Saphan and Gamarias son of Chelkias, whom King Sedekias of Iouda sent to the king of Babylon in Babylon, saying:<verse eid="JER 36:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:4"/>Thus did the Lord God of Israel say to the exile which I exiled from Ierousalem:<verse eid="JER 36:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:5"/>Build houses, and settle down, and plant orchards, and eat their fruit,<verse eid="JER 36:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:6"/>and take wives, and produce sons and daughters, and take wives for your sons, and give your daughters to husbands, and multiply, and do not decrease,<verse eid="JER 36:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:7"/>and seek for peace of the land into which I have exiled you there, and pray to the Lord on their behalf, because in their peace there will be peace for you--<verse eid="JER 36:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:8"/>because thus did the Lord say: Do not let the pseudo-prophets who are among you persuade you, and do not let your diviners persuade you, and do not listen for your dreams that you dream,<verse eid="JER 36:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:9"/>because it is wrong what they are prophesying to you in my name, and I did not send them--<verse eid="JER 36:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:10"/>because thus did the Lord say: When Babylon's seventy years are about to be completed, I will visit you, and I will establish my words upon you to bring your people back to this place.<verse eid="JER 36:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:11"/>And I will plan a plan of peace for you, and not to give you these evils.<verse eid="JER 36:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:12"/>And pray to me, and I will listen to you.<verse eid="JER 36:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:13"/>And seek me out, and you will find me, because you will seek me with your whole heart,<verse eid="JER 36:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:14"/>and I will appear to you.<verse eid="JER 36:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:15"/>Because you have said, "The Lord appointed prophets for us in Babylon,"<verse eid="JER 36:15"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 36:16"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">36:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 36:16"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 36:17"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">36:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 36:17"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 36:18"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">36:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 36:18"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 36:19"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">36:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 36:19"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 36:20"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">36:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 36:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:21"/>thus did the Lord say with reference to Achiab and with reference to Sedekias: Behold, I am delivering them into the hands of the king of Babylon, and he shall strike them before your eyes.<verse eid="JER 36:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:22"/>And from them they shall receive a curse in the whole exile of Iouda in Babylon, saying: "May the Lord make you as he made Sedekias and as Achiab, whom the king of Babylon roasted in the fire,"<verse eid="JER 36:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:23"/>on account of the lawlessness they perpetrated in Israel, and they would commit adultery with the wives of their citizens and gave as oracle in my name a word that I did not instruct them, and it is I that am witness, quoth the Lord.<verse eid="JER 36:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:24"/>And to Samaias the Nelamite you shall say:<verse eid="JER 36:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:25"/>I did not send you in my name and to say to the priest Sophonias son of Maasaias:<verse eid="JER 36:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:26"/>The Lord has given you as priest instead of the priest Iodae to be an officer in the house of the Lord over every person prophesying and every person in a frenzy, and you will give him over to the lockup and to the sluice.<verse eid="JER 36:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:27"/>And now why have you not reviled Ieremias of Anathoth who prophesied to you?<verse eid="JER 36:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:28"/>Has he not for this reason sent to us in Babylon, saying, "It is far off; build houses, and settle down, and plant gardens, and eat their fruit"?<verse eid="JER 36:28"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:29"/>And Sophonias read the document in the ears of Ieremias.<verse eid="JER 36:29"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:30"/>And a word of the Lord came to Ieremias, saying:<verse eid="JER 36:30"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:31"/>Send to the exile, saying, Thus did the Lord say with reference to Samaias the Nelamite: Whereas Samaias has prophesied to you, and I did not send him, and he has made you trust wrongly,<verse eid="JER 36:31"/>

<verse sid="JER 36:32"/>therefore thus did the Lord say: Behold, I am going to visit upon Samaias and upon his family, and he shall not have a person in your midst to see the good that I am going to do for you.<verse eid="JER 36:32"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 37">
<verse sid="JER 37:1"/>(30.1) The word that came to Ieremias from the Lord to say:<verse eid="JER 37:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:2"/>Thus did the Lord, the God of Israel, say, saying: Write in a book all the words that I gave you as oracles,<verse eid="JER 37:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:3"/>because, behold, days are coming, quoth the Lord, and I will bring back the exile of my people, Israel and Iouda, said the Lord, and I will bring them back to the land that I gave to their fathers, and they shall have dominion over it.<verse eid="JER 37:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:4"/>And these are the words that the Lord spoke with reference to Israel and Iouda.<verse eid="JER 37:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:5"/>Thus did the Lord say: A sound of fear you will hear. Fear there is, and no peace.<verse eid="JER 37:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:6"/>Ask, and see if a male gave birth, and about fear, with which they will hold on to loin and safety.[Why have I seen every person, and his hands are on his loins?] Faces turned, they became jaundiced,<verse eid="JER 37:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:7"/>because that day is great and there is none like it; it is a limited time for Iakob,<verse eid="JER 37:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:8"/>and from this he shall be saved.(8) On that day, said the Lord, I will shatter a yoke from off their neck, and I will burst their bonds, and they shall no more work for foreigners.<verse eid="JER 37:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:9"/>And they shall work for the Lord, their God, and I will raise up Dauid as their king for them.<verse eid="JER 37:9"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 37:10"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">37:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 37:10"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 37:11"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">37:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 37:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:12"/>Thus did the Lord say: I raised up a fracture; your wound was grievous.<verse eid="JER 37:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:13"/>There is no one to judge your cause; you were doctored into pain; there is no benefit for you.<verse eid="JER 37:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:14"/>All your friends have forgotten you; they will never inquire; because I struck you a blow of an enemy, firm discipline, your sins multiplied relative to all your injustice.<verse eid="JER 37:14"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 37:15"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">37:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 37:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:16"/>Therefore all who eat you shall be consumed, and all your enemies shall eat all their own flesh, and those who plunder you shall become plunder, and all those who ravage you I will give over to ravaging,<verse eid="JER 37:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:17"/>because I will bring up your healing and I will cure you from a painful blow, quoth the Lord, because you were called dispersed: "She is our prey, because there is no one seeking for her!"<verse eid="JER 37:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:18"/>Thus did the Lord say: Behold, I am bringing back the exile of Iakob and will have mercy on his captivity, and a city shall be built upon its<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">37:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'city's'</char></note> mound, and the shrine will sit on its rightful site.<verse eid="JER 37:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:19"/>And out of them shall come singers and the sound of merrymakers. And I will make them many, and they shall not be made few.<verse eid="JER 37:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:20"/>And their sons shall go in as formerly, and their testimonies shall be rectified before me, and I will visit those who oppress them.<verse eid="JER 37:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:21"/>And his stronger ones shall be over them, and his ruler shall come out from his midst, and I will gather them, and they shall return to me, because who is this that gave his heart to return to me? quoth the Lord,<verse eid="JER 37:21"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 37:22"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">37:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 37:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:23"/>because a fierce wrath of the Lord has gone forth; a revolving wrath has gone forth; it will come upon the impious.<verse eid="JER 37:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 37:24"/>Wrath of the Lord's anger shall not turn back until he has executed and until he has accomplished the undertaking of his heart. In the latter days you will understand them.<verse eid="JER 37:24"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 38">
<verse sid="JER 38:1"/>(31.1) At that time, said the Lord, I will become a god to the race of Israel, and they shall become a people to me.<verse eid="JER 38:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:2"/>Thus did the Lord say: I found him warm in a wilderness with people that perished by dagger. Go, and do not destroy Israel!<verse eid="JER 38:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:3"/>The Lord appeared to him from far away. I have loved you with an everlasting love; therefore I have drawn you into compassion.<verse eid="JER 38:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:4"/>Again I will build you, and you shall be built, O virgin Israel! Again you shall take your tambourine and go forth with a gathering of jesters.<verse eid="JER 38:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:5"/>Again you shall plant vineyards on the mountains of Samaria. Plant, and praise,<verse eid="JER 38:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:6"/>because it is a day of calling of people who argue in the mountains of Ephraim: "Rise up, and go up to Sion, to the Lord our God,"<verse eid="JER 38:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:7"/>because thus did the Lord say to Iakob: Be glad, and neigh for the head of nations; make heard, and give praise; say, "The Lord saved his people, the remnant of Israel."<verse eid="JER 38:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:8"/>Behold, I am bringing them from the north, and I will gather them from the farthest part of the earth at the feast of phasek<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'passover'</char></note>, and you will breed a large crowd, and they shall return here.<verse eid="JER 38:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:9"/>With weeping they went out, and with consolation I will bring them up, making them lodge by channels of waters in a straight road, and they shall not wander in it, because I became a father to Israel, and Ephraim is my firstborn.<verse eid="JER 38:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:10"/>Hear a word of the Lord, O nations, and declare it in the islands far off; say, "He who winnowed Israel will gather him and will keep him, as he who feeds his flock."<verse eid="JER 38:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:11"/>Because the Lord has redeemed Iakob, he has delivered him from the hand of people stronger than he.<verse eid="JER 38:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:12"/>And they shall come and be glad on the mountain of Sion, and they shall come to the good things of the Lord, to a land of grain and wine and fruit and cattle and sheep, and their soul shall become like a fruitful tree, and they shall hunger no more.<verse eid="JER 38:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:13"/>Then shall girls rejoice in a gathering of young men, and the old shall rejoice, and I will turn their mourning into joy, and I will make them glad.<verse eid="JER 38:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:14"/>I will magnify and intoxicate the soul of the priests, sons of Leui, and my people shall be satisfied with my good things.<verse eid="JER 38:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:15"/>Thus did the Lord say: A voice of lamentation and weeping and mourning was heard in Rama; Rachel did not want to stop weeping for her sons, because they are not.<verse eid="JER 38:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:16"/>Thus did the Lord say: Let your voice cease from weeping, and your eyes from tears, because there is a wage for your works, and they shall come back from a land of enemies;<verse eid="JER 38:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:17"/>there will be permanence for your children.<verse eid="JER 38:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:18"/>In hearing I heard Ephraim mourning: "You instructed me, and I was instructed; I was not trained like a calf. Bring me back, and I shall come back, because you are the Lord my God.<verse eid="JER 38:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:19"/>Because later than<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'later than':  I.e. 'induced by'</char></note> my captivity I repented, and later than that I became<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'later than that I became':  I.e. 'induced by my becoming'</char></note> aware, I sighed for days of shame, and I yielded to you, because I bore the disgrace of my youth."<verse eid="JER 38:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:20"/>Ephraim is my beloved son, a child to delight in; because, since my words are in him, I will remember him with remembrance. Therefore I hurried for him; in having mercy I will have mercy on him, quoth the Lord.<verse eid="JER 38:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:21"/>Set up for yourself sionim<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'road marks'</char></note>; make timrorim<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'guideposts'</char></note>; give your heart to the shoulders. Return by the road which you went, O virgin Israel. Return to your cities in mourning.<verse eid="JER 38:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:22"/>How long will you turn away, O dishonored daughter?-- because the Lord has created salvation for a new planting in which people will go about in safety.<verse eid="JER 38:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:23"/>Thus did the Lord say: Once more they shall speak this word in the land of Iouda and in his cities when I bring back his captivity: "Blessed be the Lord on his righteous, holy mountain!"<verse eid="JER 38:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:24"/>And there shall be people dwelling in the cities of Iouda, and in all his land, together with the farmer, and he shall be raised up<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'raised up':  Perhaps 'gotten under way'</char></note> with a flock,<verse eid="JER 38:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:25"/>because I intoxicated every thirsty soul and every hungry soul I replenished.<verse eid="JER 38:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:26"/>For this reason I awoke and saw, and my sleep was pleasant to me.<verse eid="JER 38:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:27"/>Therefore behold, days are coming, quoth the Lord, and I will sow Israel and Iouda with the seed of a human and the seed of an animal.<verse eid="JER 38:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:28"/>And it shall be just as I used to watch over them to pull down and bring evil, so I will watch over them to build and to plant, quoth the Lord.<verse eid="JER 38:28"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:29"/>In those days they shall not say: "The fathers have eaten unripe grapes, and the children's teeth were set on edge."<verse eid="JER 38:29"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:30"/>But each shall die for his own sins, and the teeth of him who eats unripe grapes shall be set on edge.<verse eid="JER 38:30"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:31"/>Behold, days are coming, quoth the Lord, and I will make a new covenant with the house of Israel and the house of Iouda.<verse eid="JER 38:31"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:32"/>It will not be like the covenant that I made with their fathers in the day when I took them by their hand to bring them out of the land of Egypt, because they did not abide in my covenant, and I was unconcerned for them, quoth the Lord,<verse eid="JER 38:32"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:33"/>because this is the covenant that I will make with the house of Israel after those days, quoth the Lord. Giving I will give my laws in their mind, and I will write them on their hearts, and I will become a god to them, and they shall become a people to me.<verse eid="JER 38:33"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:34"/>And they shall not teach, each his fellow citizen and each his brother, saying, "Know the Lord," because they shall all know me, from their small even to their great, because I will be gracious regarding their injustices, and remember their sins no more.<verse eid="JER 38:34"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:35"/>(37) If the sky be elevated to midair, quoth the Lord, and if the floor of the earth below be brought low, even then I will not reject the race of Israel, quoth the Lord, because of all they have done.<verse eid="JER 38:35"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:36"/>(35) Thus did the Lord say, who gives the sun as light by day, moon and stars as light by night, and a scream in the sea and its waves made a booming noise-- the Lord Almighty is his name:<verse eid="JER 38:36"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:37"/>(36) If these laws cease from before me, quoth the Lord, also the race of Israel will cease to be a nation before me, all the days.<verse eid="JER 38:37"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:38"/>Behold, days are coming, quoth the Lord, and a city shall be built for the Lord from the tower of Hananeel to the gate of the corner.<verse eid="JER 38:38"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:39"/>And its measuring shall go out before them to the hills of Gareb, and it shall be encompassed all round with a circle of choice stones.<verse eid="JER 38:39"/>

<verse sid="JER 38:40"/>And all hasaremoth<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:40</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'the fields'?</char></note> as far as Nachal Kedron, to the corner of the gate of horses in the east, a holy precinct to the Lord, and it shall never again fail and shall never ever be destroyed.<verse eid="JER 38:40"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 39">
<verse sid="JER 39:1"/>(32.1) The word that came from the Lord to Ieremias in the tenth year of King Sedekias; this was the eighteenth year for King Nabouchodonosor of Babylon.<verse eid="JER 39:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:2"/>And the force of the king of Babylon raised a barricade against Ierousalem, and Ieremias was being confined in the court of the guard that was in the house of the king<verse eid="JER 39:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:3"/>in which King Sedekias had shut him up, saying, "Why do you prophesy, saying: Thus did the Lord say: Behold, I am giving this city in the hands of the king of Babylon, and he shall take it,<verse eid="JER 39:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:4"/>and Sedekias shall not be saved out of the hand of the Chaldeans, because in handing over he shall be handed over into the hands of the king of Babylon, and his mouth shall speak to his mouth and his eyes shall see his eyes,<verse eid="JER 39:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:5"/>and Sedekias shall enter into Babylon and be seated there."<verse eid="JER 39:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:6"/>And a word of the Lord came to Ieremias, saying:<verse eid="JER 39:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:7"/>Behold, Hanameel son of Salom your father's brother is coming to you, saying, "Acquire for yourself the field that is at Anathoth, because the right of acquisition is yours to take."<verse eid="JER 39:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:8"/>And Hanameel son of Salom my father's brother came to me in the court of the guard and said to me, "Acquire my field that is in the land of Beniamin at Anathoth, because the right to acquire is yours, and you are the elder. And I knew that it was a word of the Lord.<verse eid="JER 39:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:9"/>And I acquired the field from Hanameel son of my father's brother and weighed out to him seventeen shekels of silver.<verse eid="JER 39:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:10"/>And I wrote in a document and sealed it and got witnesses to witness and weighed the silver on a scale.<verse eid="JER 39:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:11"/>And I took the document of purchase, the sealed one and the open one,<verse eid="JER 39:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:12"/>and I gave it to Barouch son of Nerias son of Maasaias, in the sight of Hanameel son of my father's brother and in the sight of those who were present and signed the document of purchase, and in the sight of the Judeans who were in the court of the guard.<verse eid="JER 39:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:13"/>And in their sight I instructed Barouch, saying,<verse eid="JER 39:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:14"/>Thus did the Lord Almighty say: Take this document of purchase and the open document, and you shall put it in an earthenware jar in order that it may last for rather many days,<verse eid="JER 39:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:15"/>because thus did the Lord say: Fields and houses and vineyards shall again be bought in this land.<verse eid="JER 39:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:16"/>And after I had given the document of purchase to Barouch son of Nerias, I prayed to the Lord, saying:<verse eid="JER 39:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:17"/>"You That Are, Lord! It is you who made the sky and the earth by your great strength and by your high arm! Nothing shall be hidden from you<verse eid="JER 39:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:18"/>when you do mercy for thousands and repay the sins of fathers into the laps of their children after them, you the great, the strong God,<verse eid="JER 39:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:19"/>Lord of great counsel and powerful in deeds, the great God Almighty, Lord of great name. Your eyes are on the ways of the sons of men, to give each according to his way,<verse eid="JER 39:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:20"/>you who performed signs and wonders in the land of Egypt to this day both in Israel and among the earthborn, and you have made yourself a name, as this day.<verse eid="JER 39:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:21"/>And you brought your people Israel out of the land of Egypt with signs and with wonders and with a strong hand and with a high arm<verse eid="JER 39:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:22"/>and with great spectacles, and you gave them this land, which you swore to their fathers, a land flowing with milk and honey,<verse eid="JER 39:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:23"/>and they entered and took it and did not obey your voice and did not walk by your ordinances; all you commanded them they did not do. And you have made all these evils to happen to them.<verse eid="JER 39:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:24"/>Behold, a crowd has come against<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">39:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'into'</char></note> the city to take it, and the city has been given into the hands of the Chaldeans who are fighting it from before the dagger and the famine. As you spoke, so it happened.<verse eid="JER 39:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:25"/>And you are saying to me, "Acquire for yourself the field for money." And I wrote a document and sealed it and had witnesses witness it, and the city was given into the hands of the Chaldeans.<verse eid="JER 39:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:26"/>And a word of the Lord came to me, saying:<verse eid="JER 39:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:27"/>I am the Lord, the God of all flesh; surely nothing will be hidden from me?<verse eid="JER 39:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:28"/>Therefore, thus did the Lord say: When this city is surrendered it will be given over into the hands of the king of Babylon, and he shall seize it.<verse eid="JER 39:28"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:29"/>And the Chaldeans who are fighting against this city shall come and shall burn this city with fire, and they shall burn down the houses in which, on their roofs, they burnt incense to the goddess Baal and they would pour libations to other gods so as to embitter me,<verse eid="JER 39:29"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:30"/>because the sons of Israel and the sons of Iouda were alone in doing evil in my sight from their youth,<verse eid="JER 39:30"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:31"/>because this city existed for my wrath and for my anger, from the day they built it even until this day, to remove it from before me,<verse eid="JER 39:31"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:32"/>because of all the evils of the sons of Israel and Iouda that they did to embitter me, they and their kings and their rulers and their priests and their prophets, men of Iouda and those that inhabit Ierousalem.<verse eid="JER 39:32"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:33"/>And they have turned their back to me and not their face, and I have taught them in the early morning, and I have taught, and they did not hear to accept instruction.<verse eid="JER 39:33"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:34"/>And they set up their defilements in the house, where my name is called on it, in their impurities.<verse eid="JER 39:34"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:35"/>And they built the altars<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">39:35</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = bômos</char></note> to the goddess Baal, which are in the valley of Hennom's son, to offer up their sons and their daughters to the king<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">39:35</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'the king':  Hebrew = 'Molech'</char></note>, things which I did not instruct them to do, and it did not arise in my heart that they do this abomination so as to cause Iouda to sin.<verse eid="JER 39:35"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:36"/>And now thus did the Lord, the God of Israel, say with reference to the city of which you say, "It will be given over into the hands of the king of Babylon by dagger and by famine and by dispatch":<verse eid="JER 39:36"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:37"/>Behold, I am gathering them from every land, there where I dispersed them in my wrath and in my anger and in great irritation, and I will bring them back to this place, and I will settle them in confidence.<verse eid="JER 39:37"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:38"/>And they shall become a people to me, and I will become a god to them.<verse eid="JER 39:38"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:39"/>And I will give them another way and another heart, to fear me all the days, both for their own good and for that of their children after them.<verse eid="JER 39:39"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:40"/>And I will make an everlasting covenant with them, which I will not turn away from behind them, and I will assign my fear to their heart so that they may not turn away from me.<verse eid="JER 39:40"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:41"/>And I will visit them to do good to them, and I will plant them in this land in faithfulness, both with all my heart and with all my soul,<verse eid="JER 39:41"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:42"/>because thus did the Lord say: Just as I have brought all these great evils upon this people, so I will bring upon them all the good that I told them.<verse eid="JER 39:42"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:43"/>And fields shall be acquired again in the land of which you are saying, It is untrodden by human being or animal, and they were given over into the hands of the Chaldeans.<verse eid="JER 39:43"/>

<verse sid="JER 39:44"/>And they shall acquire fields with money, and you shall write in a document and seal it and have witnesses witness it in the land of Beniamin and around Ierousalem and in the cities of Iouda and in the cities of the mountain and in the cities of the Sephela and in the cities of the Nageb, because I will bring back their exiles.<verse eid="JER 39:44"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 40">
<verse sid="JER 40:1"/>(33.1) And a word of the Lord came to Ieremias a second time, and he was still confined in the court of the guard, saying:<verse eid="JER 40:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 40:2"/>Thus did the Lord say, when he was making earth and forming it to establish it-- the Lord is his name:<verse eid="JER 40:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 40:3"/>Cry to me, and I will answer you and will tell you great and mighty things, them that you have not known,<verse eid="JER 40:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 40:4"/>because thus did the Lord say concerning the houses of this city and concerning the houses of the king of Iouda that have been torn down for stakes and breastworks<verse eid="JER 40:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 40:5"/>to do battle against the Chaldeans and to fill it with corpses of people whom I struck in my wrath and in my anger, and I turned away my face from them for all their acts of wickedness.<verse eid="JER 40:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 40:6"/>Behold, I am bringing it soundness and healing, and I will make clear to them and heal it and make for them peace and trust.<verse eid="JER 40:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 40:7"/>I will return the exile of Iouda and the exile of Israel and build them as they were before.<verse eid="JER 40:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 40:8"/>And I will cleanse them from all their injustices which they sinned against me, and I will not remember their sins which they sinned against me and they withdrew from me.<verse eid="JER 40:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 40:9"/>And it shall be for gladness and for praise and for greatness for all the people of the earth, whoever shall hear of all the good that I shall perform, and they shall fear and be embittered concerning all the good and concerning all the peace which I shall make for them.<verse eid="JER 40:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 40:10"/>Thus did the Lord say: There shall yet be heard in this place of which you say, "It is a wilderness apart from<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">40:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'apart from':  I.e. 'without'</char></note> human beings and animals," in the cities of Iouda and outside of Ierousalem, that are desolate, to the point that there are no human being or animal,<verse eid="JER 40:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 40:11"/>a voice of gladness and a voice of joy, a voice of bridegroom and a voice of bride, a voice of people saying, "Acknowledge the Lord Almighty, because the Lord is kind, because his mercy is forever!" And they will bring gifts into the house of the Lord, because I will return the exile of that land as before, said the Lord.<verse eid="JER 40:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 40:12"/>Thus did the Lord say: There shall again be in this place that is waste and in all its cities, lodgings of shepherds resting sheep.<verse eid="JER 40:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 40:13"/>In the cities of the hill country and in the cities of the Sephela and in the cities of the Nageb and in the land of Beniamin and in those around Ierousalem and in the cities of Iouda sheep shall again pass under the hand of one who counts them, said the Lord.<verse eid="JER 40:13"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 41">
<verse sid="JER 41:1"/>(34.1) The word that came to Ieremias from the Lord, and King Nabouchodonosor of Babylon and all his army and all the land under his dominion were fighting against Ierousalem and against all the cities of Iouda, saying:<verse eid="JER 41:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:2"/>Thus did the Lord say: Go to King Sedekias of Iouda, and you shall say to him: Thus did the Lord say: In surrender this city shall be surrendered into the hands of the king of Babylon, and he shall seize it and burn it with fire.<verse eid="JER 41:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:3"/>Even you shall not be saved from his hand, and with a seizing you shall be seized and given over into his hands, and your eyes shall see his eyes, and you shall enter into Babylon.<verse eid="JER 41:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:4"/>But hear a word of the Lord, O King Sedekias of Iouda! Thus says the Lord,<verse eid="JER 41:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:5"/>You shall die in peace. And as they wept for your fathers, those who reigned before you, they shall also weep for you and lament for you: "Alas, Adon<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">41:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'lord'</char></note>," because I have spoken a word, said the Lord.<verse eid="JER 41:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:6"/>And Ieremias spoke all these words to King Sedekias in Ierousalem,<verse eid="JER 41:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:7"/>and the force of the king of Babylon was fighting against Ierousalem and against the cities of Iouda, against Lachis and against Azeka, because these were left among the cities of Iouda as strong cities.<verse eid="JER 41:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:8"/>The word that came to Ieremias from the Lord, after King Sedekias had concluded a covenant with the people to call for a release,<verse eid="JER 41:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:9"/>to send off free each his Hebrew male servant and each his Hebrew female servant so as not to have a man from Iouda in slavery.<verse eid="JER 41:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:10"/>And all the nobles and all the people, who had entered into the covenant to dismiss each his male servant and each his female servant, reneged and let them<verse eid="JER 41:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:11"/>be their male and female servants.<verse eid="JER 41:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:12"/>And a word of the Lord came to Ieremias, saying:<verse eid="JER 41:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:13"/>Thus did the Lord say: It was I that made a covenant with your fathers in the day I delivered them from the land of Egypt, from a house of slavery, saying,<verse eid="JER 41:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:14"/>"When six years are complete, you shall dismiss your Hebrew brother, who will be sold to you. And he shall work for you for six years, and you shall send him off free." And they did not hear me and did not incline their ear.<verse eid="JER 41:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:15"/>And today they have turned to do what is right before my eyes, to call for a release, each of his fellow, and they concluded a covenant before me in the house where my name is called on it.<verse eid="JER 41:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:16"/>And you turned and profaned my name when each of you turned back his male servant and each his female servant, whom you had sent off free, for their own self, as male and female servants for you.<verse eid="JER 41:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:17"/>Therefore, thus did the Lord say: You have not obeyed me by calling for a release, each pertaining to his fellow. Behold, I am calling for a release for you to the dagger and to death and to the famine, and I will give you as a dispersion to all the kingdoms of the earth.<verse eid="JER 41:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:18"/>And as for the men who have transgressed my covenant, those that did not stand by my covenant that they made before me, I will render them as the bull calf which they made, to work for it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">41:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'calf'</char></note>:<verse eid="JER 41:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:19"/>the rulers of Iouda and those with power and the priests and the people.<verse eid="JER 41:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:20"/>And I will hand them over to their enemies. And their carcasses shall become food for the birds of the air and the wild animals of the earth.<verse eid="JER 41:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:21"/>And as for King Sedekias of Judea and their rulers, I will hand them over into the hands of their enemies-- and the force of the king of Babylon is for those that are running away from them.<verse eid="JER 41:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 41:22"/>Behold, I am giving instructions, quoth the Lord, and will bring them back to this land, and they will fight against it and take it and burn it down with fire, and the cities of Iouda, and I will render them desolate apart from<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">41:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'apart from':  I.e. 'without'</char></note> inhabitants.<verse eid="JER 41:22"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 42">
<verse sid="JER 42:1"/>(35.1) The word that came to Ieremias from the Lord in the days of King Ioakim of Iouda, saying:<verse eid="JER 42:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:2"/>Go to the house of Archabin<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">42:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'the Rechabites'</char></note>, and you shall bring them into the house of the Lord, into one of the courts, and you shall offer them wine to drink.<verse eid="JER 42:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:3"/>And I brought out Iezonias son of Ieremin son of Chabasin and his brothers and his sons and the whole house of Archabin<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">42:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'the Rechabites'</char></note>.<verse eid="JER 42:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:4"/>And I brought them into the house of the Lord into the priestly chamber of the sons of Hananias son of Godolias, man of God, which was near the house of the rulers who were over the house of Maasaias son of Selom, the keeper of the court.<verse eid="JER 42:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:5"/>And I gave before them a jug of wine and cups, and I said, "Drink wine."<verse eid="JER 42:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:6"/>And they said, "We will not drink wine, because our father Ionadab son of Rechab commanded us, saying, 'You shall not drink wine, you and your sons forever,<verse eid="JER 42:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:7"/>and you shall not build a house, and you shall not sow seed, and you shall not have a vineyard, because you shall live in tents all your days, that you may live many days in the land in which you spent time in it.'<verse eid="JER 42:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:8"/>And we have obeyed the voice of our father Ionadab so as not to drink wine all our days, we and our wives and our sons and our daughters,<verse eid="JER 42:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:9"/>and so as not to build houses to live there. And we did not have vineyard and field and seed,<verse eid="JER 42:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:10"/>and we have lived in tents and obeyed and acted in accordance with all that our father Ionadab commanded us.<verse eid="JER 42:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:11"/>And it happened, when King Nabouchodonosor of Babylon came up against the land, we also said, 'Come, and let us enter into Ierou-salem from before the force of the Chaldeans and from before the force of the Assyrians,' and we are living there."<verse eid="JER 42:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:12"/>And a word of the Lord came to me, saying:<verse eid="JER 42:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:13"/>Thus says the Lord: Go, and say to a person of Iouda and the inhabitants of Ierousalem, Will you not receive instruction to obey my words?<verse eid="JER 42:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:14"/>The sons of Ionadab son of Rechab upheld the dictum which he commanded his children so as not to drink wine, and they did not drink. And I spoke to you early, and I spoke, and you did not obey.<verse eid="JER 42:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:15"/>And I have sent to you my servants the prophets, saying, "Turn, everyone from his evil way, and make your doings better, and do not go after other gods to be slaves to them, and live in the land that I gave to you and your fathers." And you did not incline your ears and did not obey.<verse eid="JER 42:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:16"/>And the sons of Ionadab son of Rechab have upheld the command of their father, but this people have not obeyed me.<verse eid="JER 42:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:17"/>Therefore, thus did the Lord say: Behold, I am bringing on Iouda and on the inhabitants of Ierousalem all the evils that I have spoken against them.<verse eid="JER 42:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:18"/>Therefore, thus did the Lord say: Whereas the sons of Ionadab son of Rechab have obeyed the command of their father, to do just as their father commanded them,<verse eid="JER 42:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 42:19"/>Ionadab son of Rechab shall not lack a man to stand before me for all the days of the earth.<verse eid="JER 42:19"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 43">
<verse sid="JER 43:1"/>(36.1) In the fourth year of Ioakim son of Iosias, king of Iouda, a word of the Lord came to me saying:<verse eid="JER 43:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:2"/>Take for yourself a small roll of a book, and write on it all the words that I gave you as oracles against Ierousalem and against Iouda and against all the nations, from the day of my speaking to you, from the days of King Iosias of Iouda even until this day.<verse eid="JER 43:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:3"/>Perhaps the house of Iouda will hear of all the evil that I intend to do to them in order that they turn from their evil way, and I shall be gracious regarding their injustices and their sins.<verse eid="JER 43:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:4"/>And Ieremias called Barouch son of Nerias, and Barouch<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">43:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = 'he'</char></note> wrote on a small roll of a book from the mouth of Ieremias all the words of the Lord that he had given as oracles to him.<verse eid="JER 43:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:5"/>And Ieremias commanded Barouch, saying, "I am under guard. I shall not be able to enter into the house of the Lord,<verse eid="JER 43:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:6"/>and on a day of fasting you shall read from this small roll into the ears of the people in the Lord's house and in the ears of every one of Iouda, those that come out from their city-- you shall read to them.<verse eid="JER 43:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:7"/>Perhaps mercy for them<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">43:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'those from outside Ierousalem'</char></note> will come about before the Lord, and they<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">43:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'those from outside Ierousalem'</char></note> will turn them out of their evil way, because great is the anger and wrath of the Lord that the Lord<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">43:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'the Lord':  Ziegler = 'he'</char></note> spoke against this people."<verse eid="JER 43:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:8"/>And Barouch did according to all that Ieremias commanded him, to read in the book the Lord's words in the Lord's house.<verse eid="JER 43:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:9"/>And it happened in the eighth year of King Ioakim, in the ninth month, all the people in Ierousalem and the house of Iouda proclaimed in assembly a fast before the Lord.<verse eid="JER 43:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:10"/>And in the ears of the people, Barouch would read words of Ieremias from the book, in the house of the Lord, in the house of Gamarias son of Saphan the secretary, in the upper court, at the entry of the new gate of the Lord's house.<verse eid="JER 43:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:11"/>And Michaias son of Gamarias son of Saphan heard all the words of the Lord from the book.<verse eid="JER 43:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:12"/>And he went down to the king's house, into the secretary's house, and behold, all the rulers were sitting there: Elisama the secretary and Dalaias son of Selemias and Ionathan son of Akchobor and Gamarias son of Saphan and Sedekias son of Hananias and all the rulers.<verse eid="JER 43:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:13"/>And Michaias told them all the words that he had heard Barouch read in the ears of the people.<verse eid="JER 43:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:14"/>And all the rulers sent Ioudin son of Nathanias son of Selemias son of Chousi to Barouch son of Nerias, saying, "The small roll in which you were reading in it, in the ears of the people, take it into your hand, and come." And Barouch son of Nerias<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">43:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'son of Nerias':  Ziegler = Omit</char></note> took the small roll and went down to them.<verse eid="JER 43:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:15"/>And they said to him, "Again read it into our ears." And Barouch read.<verse eid="JER 43:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:16"/>And it happened, when they heard all the words, they took counsel, each with his fellow, and they said, "In reporting let us report all these words to the king."<verse eid="JER 43:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:17"/>And they questioned Barouch, saying, "From where did you write all these words?"<verse eid="JER 43:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:18"/>And Barouch said, "From his mouth Ieremias proclaimed to me all these words, and I would write them in a book."<verse eid="JER 43:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:19"/>And they said to Barouch, "Go, hide, you and Ieremias, and let no person know where you are."<verse eid="JER 43:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:20"/>And they entered to the king in the court, and the small roll they gave to be watched in the house of Elisama, and they reported all the words to the king.<verse eid="JER 43:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:21"/>And the king sent Ioudin to take the small roll, and he took it from the house of Elisama, and Ioudin read it into the ears of the king and into the ears of all the rulers who stood around the king.<verse eid="JER 43:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:22"/>And the king was sitting in his winter house, and there was a hearth of fire in front of him.<verse eid="JER 43:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:23"/>And it happened when Ioudin would read three or four columns, he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">43:23</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the king'</char></note> would cut them off with the secretary's penknife and would throw them into the fire that was in the hearth, until the entire roll had vanished into the fire that was in the hearth.<verse eid="JER 43:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:24"/>And the king and his servants, who were hearing all these words, were not alarmed, and they did not tear their garments.<verse eid="JER 43:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:25"/>And Elnathan and Dalaias<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">43:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = 'Godolias'</char></note> and Gamarias suggested to the king not to burn the small roll.<verse eid="JER 43:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:26"/>And the king commanded Ieremeel the king's son and Saraias son of Esriel to arrest Barouch and Ieremias. And they were hidden.<verse eid="JER 43:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:27"/>And after the king had burned the small roll, all the words that Barouch wrote from the mouth of Ieremias, a word of the Lord came to Ieremias, saying:<verse eid="JER 43:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:28"/>Again, take another small roll, and write all the words that were in the small roll, which words King Ioakim has burned.<verse eid="JER 43:28"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:29"/>And you shall say: Thus did the Lord say, You burned this small roll, saying, Why have you written on it, saying, In coming the king of Babylon will come and destroy utterly this land, and human and animals will fail from it?<verse eid="JER 43:29"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:30"/>Therefore thus did the Lord say with reference to King Ioakim of Iouda: He shall have no one to sit upon the throne of Dauid, and his carcass shall lie cast out in the heat of the day and in the frost of the night.<verse eid="JER 43:30"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:31"/>And I will visit upon him and upon his family and upon his servants, and I will bring upon them and upon the inhabitants of Ierousalem and upon the land of Iouda all the evils, which I have spoken to them-- and they did not listen.<verse eid="JER 43:31"/>

<verse sid="JER 43:32"/>And Barouch took another small roll and wrote on it from the mouth of Ieremias all the words of the book, which words Ioakim had burned, and more words like these were yet added to them.<verse eid="JER 43:32"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 44">
<verse sid="JER 44:1"/>(37.1) And Sedekias son of Iosias became king in place of Ioakim, whom King Nabouchodonosor of Babylon made king to be king over Iouda.<verse eid="JER 44:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:2"/>And he and his servants and the people of the land did not obey the words of the Lord that he spoke by the hand of Ieremias.<verse eid="JER 44:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:3"/>And King Sedekias sent Ioachal son of Selemias and the priest Sophonias son of Maasaias to Ieremias, saying, "Pray for us to the Lord."<verse eid="JER 44:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:4"/>And Ieremias went and passed through the midst of the city, and they had not consigned him to the house of the guard.<verse eid="JER 44:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:5"/>And a force of Pharao had come out of Egypt, and the Chaldeans heard news of them, and they withdrew from Ierousalem.<verse eid="JER 44:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:6"/>And a word of the Lord came to Ieremias, saying:<verse eid="JER 44:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:7"/>Thus did the Lord say: Thus you shall say to the king of Iouda, who sent to you to inquire of me, Behold, Pharao's force, which came out for assistance, will return to the land of Egypt.<verse eid="JER 44:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:8"/>And the Chaldeans themselves shall return and fight against this city, and they shall seize it and burn it with fire,<verse eid="JER 44:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:9"/>because thus did the Lord say: Do not suppose in your souls, saying, "In departing the Chaldeans will go away from us," for they will not go away.<verse eid="JER 44:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:10"/>Even if you struck the whole force of the Chaldeans, those who are fighting you, and there remained of them some pierced, each in his place, these would rise up and burn this city with fire.<verse eid="JER 44:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:11"/>And it happened, when the force of the Chaldeans had withdrawn from Ierousalem from before Pharao's force,<verse eid="JER 44:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:12"/>Ieremias set out from Ierousalem to go to the land of Beniamin to buy property there among the people.<verse eid="JER 44:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:13"/>And he was at the gate of Beniamin, and there was a person with whom he used to lodge, Sarouia son of Selemias son of Hananias, and he arrested Ieremias, saying, "You are fleeing to the Chaldeans."<verse eid="JER 44:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:14"/>And he said, "That is a lie; I am not fleeing to the Chaldeans." And he did not listen to him, and Sarouia arrested Ieremias and brought him to the rulers.<verse eid="JER 44:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:15"/>And the rulers were embittered against Ieremias, and they struck him and sent him to the house of the secretary Ionathan, because they had made this into a house of the guard.<verse eid="JER 44:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:16"/>And Ieremias went into the house of the cistern and into the chereth<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">44:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = ?</char></note> and sat there many days.<verse eid="JER 44:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:17"/>And King Sedekias sent word and called him. And the king questioned him secretly to say if there was a word from the Lord. And he said, "There is! You shall be handed over into the hands of the king of Babylon."<verse eid="JER 44:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:18"/>And Ieremias said to the king, "What wrong have I done you and your servants and this people that you are giving me over into the house of the guard?<verse eid="JER 44:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:19"/>And where are your prophets who prophesied to you, saying, 'The king of Babylon will not come against this land'?<verse eid="JER 44:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:20"/>And now, my lord king, let mercy for me come about before you, and why do you return me to the house of the secretary Ionathan? And shall I not die there?"<verse eid="JER 44:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 44:21"/>And the king gave instructions, and they committed him to the court of the guard and would give him one loaf of bread a day from outside where they bake until the bread of the city was gone. And Ieremias sat in the court of the guard.<verse eid="JER 44:21"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 45">
<verse sid="JER 45:1"/>(38.1) And Saphatias son of Matthan and Godolias son of Paschor and Ioachal son of Selemias heard the words that Ieremias was speaking to the crowd, saying,<verse eid="JER 45:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:2"/>Thus did the Lord say, He who lives in this city shall die by sword and by famine, and he who goes out to the Chaldeans shall live, and his soul shall be his windfall, and he shall live,<verse eid="JER 45:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:3"/>because thus did the Lord say, In being handed over this city shall be handed over into the hands of the force of the king of Babylon, and he shall seize it.<verse eid="JER 45:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:4"/>And they said to the king, "Let that person be put to death, because he is relaxing the hands of the people that fight, who are left in the city, and the hands of all the people, by speaking such words to them. For this person does not utter an oracle of peace to this people but only hardship."<verse eid="JER 45:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:5"/>And the king said, "Behold, he is in your hands," because the king was powerless against them.<verse eid="JER 45:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:6"/>And they threw him into a cistern of Melchias, the king's son, which was in the court of the guard, and they let him down into the cistern. And there was no water in the cistern, but only mire, and he was in the mire.<verse eid="JER 45:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:7"/>And Abdemelech the Ethiopian-- and he was in the king's house-- heard that they had consigned Ieremias to the cistern. And the king was at the gate of Beniamin.<verse eid="JER 45:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:8"/>And he went out to him, and he spoke to the king and said,<verse eid="JER 45:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:9"/>"You acted wickedly in what you did to kill this person from before the famine, because there is no longer any bread in the city."<verse eid="JER 45:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:10"/>And the king commanded Abdemelech, saying, "Take in hand thirty persons from here, and bring him up out of the cistern so that he may not die."<verse eid="JER 45:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:11"/>And Abdemelech took the persons and entered into the house of the king-- the underground chamber-- and took from there old rags and old ropes and threw them into the cistern to Ieremias.<verse eid="JER 45:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:12"/>And he said, "Put these under the ropes." And Ieremias did so.<verse eid="JER 45:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:13"/>And they drew him up by the ropes and brought him up out of the cistern. And Ieremias sat in the court of the guard.<verse eid="JER 45:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:14"/>And the king sent word and called him to himself at the house of Aselisel<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">45:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'the third'</char></note>, which is in the house of the Lord. And the king said to him, "I will ask you a matter, and do not hide any dictum from me."<verse eid="JER 45:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:15"/>And Ieremias said to the king, "If I tell you, will you not put me to death with death? And if I give you advice, you will not hear me."<verse eid="JER 45:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:16"/>And the king swore to him, saying, "The Lord lives, who made for us this life, if I shall kill you and if I shall give you into the hands of these people!"<verse eid="JER 45:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:17"/>And Ieremias said to him, "Thus did the Lord say, If in going out you go out to the leaders of the king of Babylon, your soul shall live, and this city shall not be burned with fire, and you shall live and your house.<verse eid="JER 45:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:18"/>And if you do not go out, this city shall be handed over into the hands of the Chaldeans, and they shall burn it with fire, and you shall not be saved."<verse eid="JER 45:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:19"/>And the king said to Ieremias, "I have a concern regarding the Judeans who have fled to the Chaldeans, lest they give me into their hands and they shall mock me."<verse eid="JER 45:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:20"/>And Ieremias said, "They will not deliver you up. Obey a word of the Lord, which I say to you, and it shall be better for you, and your soul shall live.<verse eid="JER 45:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:21"/>And if you are not willing to go out, this is the word the Lord has shown me:<verse eid="JER 45:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:22"/>And behold, all the women that are left in the house of the king of Iouda were being led out to the rulers of the king of Babylon, and they kept saying, 'Your men of peace have misled you and will overpower you, and they will sink your feet in slipperiness; they turned away from you.'<verse eid="JER 45:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:23"/>And your wives and your children they shall lead out to the Chaldeans, and you shall not be saved, because you shall be seized by the hand of the king of Babylon, and this city shall be burned down."<verse eid="JER 45:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:24"/>And the king said to him, "Let no person know any of these words, and you will not die.<verse eid="JER 45:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:25"/>And if the rulers hear that I have spoken with you, and they come to you and say to you, Tell us what the king said to you; do not conceal it from us, and we will not kill you. And what did the king say to you?'<verse eid="JER 45:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:26"/>And you shall say to them, 'I am casting pity for me in the sight of the king so as not to return me to the house of Ionathan to die there.' "<verse eid="JER 45:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:27"/>And all the rulers came to Ieremias and questioned him, and he told them according to all these words which the king had commanded him. And they maintained silence, because a word of the Lord was not heard.<verse eid="JER 45:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 45:28"/>And Ieremias sat in the court of the guard until the time when Ierousalem was seized.<verse eid="JER 45:28"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 46">
<verse sid="JER 46:1"/>(39.1) And it happened in the ninth year of King Sedekias of Iouda, in the tenth month, King Nabouchodonosor of Babylon and all his force came against Ierousalem, and they were laying siege to it,<verse eid="JER 46:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 46:2"/>and in the eleventh year of Sedekias, in the fourth month, on the ninth of the month, the city was breached.<verse eid="JER 46:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 46:3"/>And all the leaders of the king of Babylon entered and sat in the middle gate: Nargalsarasar, Samagoth, Nabousarsachar, Nabousaris, Nargalsaraser, Rabamag and the rest of the leaders of the king of Babylon.<verse eid="JER 46:3"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 46:4"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">46:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 46:4"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 46:5"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">46:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 46:5"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 46:6"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">46:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 46:6"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 46:7"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">46:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 46:7"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 46:8"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">46:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 46:8"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 46:9"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">46:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 46:9"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 46:10"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">46:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 46:10"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 46:11"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">46:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 46:11"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 46:12"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">46:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 46:12"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 46:13"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">46:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 46:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 46:14"/>And they sent and took Ieremias from the court of the guard and gave him to Godolias son of Achikam son of Saphan, and they brought him out, and he sat in the midst of the people.<verse eid="JER 46:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 46:15"/>And a word of the Lord came to Ieremias in the court of the guard, saying:<verse eid="JER 46:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 46:16"/>Go, and say to Abdemelech the Ethiopian: Thus did the Lord, the God of Israel, say: Behold, I am bringing my words against this city for evil and not for good.<verse eid="JER 46:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 46:17"/>And I will save you on that day, and I shall not hand you over into the hands of the people, before them whom you fear,<verse eid="JER 46:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 46:18"/>because in saving I will save you, and you shall not fall by sword, and your soul shall be your windfall, because you have trusted in me, quoth the Lord.<verse eid="JER 46:18"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 47">
<verse sid="JER 47:1"/>(40.1) The word that came from the Lord to Ieremias after Nabouzardan the chief cook from Dama sent him off, when he took him in handcuffs in the midst of the exile of Iouda, those led away to Babylon.<verse eid="JER 47:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 47:2"/>And the chief cook took him and said to him, "The Lord, your God, has given in oracles these evils against this place,<verse eid="JER 47:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 47:3"/>and the Lord acted, because you sinned against him and did not obey his voice.<verse eid="JER 47:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 47:4"/>Behold, I have released you from the handcuffs on your hands. If it is good before you to come with me to Babylon, come, and I will set my eyes on you.<verse eid="JER 47:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 47:5"/>But if not, depart, and return to Godolias son of Achikam son of Saphan, whom the king of Babylon has appointed in the land of Iouda, and live with him among the people in the land of Iouda. Go to all that is good in your eyes to go to." And the chief cook gave him presents and sent him off.<verse eid="JER 47:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 47:6"/>And he went to Godolias at Massepha and settled among the people who were left in the land.<verse eid="JER 47:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 47:7"/>And all the leaders of the force in the open country, they and their men, heard that the king of Babylon had appointed Godolias in the land and that he had committed to him men and their women, whom he had not exiled to Babylon.<verse eid="JER 47:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 47:8"/>And there came to Godolias at Massepha Ismael son of Nathanias and Ioanan son of Karee and Saraia son of Thanaemeth and sons of Ophei the Netophati and Iezonias son of the Moochati, they and their men.<verse eid="JER 47:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 47:9"/>And Godolias swore to them and their men, saying, "Do not be afraid before the servants of the Chaldeans. Settle in the land. and work for the king of Babylon, and it shall be better for you.<verse eid="JER 47:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 47:10"/>And behold, I am stationed before you at Massepha, to stand before the Chaldeans who may come to us, and as for you, gather wine and summer fruit and oil, and put them in your vessels, and live in the cities that you have taken over."<verse eid="JER 47:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 47:11"/>And all the Judeans, those in Moab and those among the sons of Ammon and those in Idumea and those in any other land, heard that the king of Babylon had given a remnant to Iouda and that he had appointed over them Godolias son of Achikam.<verse eid="JER 47:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 47:12"/>And they came to Godolias to the land of Iouda at Massepha, and they gathered wine and summer fruit in great abundance.<verse eid="JER 47:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 47:13"/>And Ioanan son of Karee and all the leaders of the force, those in the open fields, came to Godolias at Massepha<verse eid="JER 47:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 47:14"/>and said to him, "Do you know by knowledge that Beelias, king of the sons of Ammon, has sent to you Ismael to strike your soul?" And Godolias did not believe them.<verse eid="JER 47:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 47:15"/>And Ioanan said to Godolias secretly at Massepha, "I will indeed go and strike Ismael, and let no one else know, lest he slay your soul, and all Iouda, those gathered to you, be scattered, and those remaining of Iouda shall perish."<verse eid="JER 47:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 47:16"/>And Godolias said to Ioanan, "Do not do this thing, because you are telling lies about Ismael."<verse eid="JER 47:16"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 48">
<verse sid="JER 48:1"/>(41.1) And it happened in the seventh month, Ismael son of Nathanias son of Eleasa of the family of the king came and ten men with him to Godolias at Massepha. And they ate bread together there.<verse eid="JER 48:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:2"/>And Ismael got up, and the ten men who were with him, and they struck Godolias, whom the king of Babylon had appointed over the land,<verse eid="JER 48:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:3"/>and all the Judeans who were with him at Massepha and all the Chaldeans who were found there.<verse eid="JER 48:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:4"/>And it happened on the second day after he had struck Godolias, and no person knew,<verse eid="JER 48:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:5"/>men also arrived from Sychem and from Salem and from Samaria, eighty men with their beards shaved and their clothes torn and beating themselves, and manaa<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">48:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'grain offering'</char></note> and frankincense in their hands to bring to the house of the Lord.<verse eid="JER 48:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:6"/>And Ismael came out to meet them. They were going and weeping, and he said, "Enter to Godolias."<verse eid="JER 48:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:7"/>And it happened, when they came into the middle of the city, he slaughtered them into the well.<verse eid="JER 48:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:8"/>And ten men were found there, and they said to Ismael, "Do not kill us, because we have stores of wheat and barley, honey and oil in a field." And he passed them over and did not kill them in the midst of their brothers.<verse eid="JER 48:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:9"/>And the well into which Ismael had thrown all whom he had struck-- this is a large well that King Asa had made from before King Baasa of Israel-- Ismael filled this with the slain.<verse eid="JER 48:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:10"/>And Ismael turned away all the people who were left in Massepha, and the king's daughters, whom the chief cook had committed to Godolias son of Achikam. And he went away beyond the sons of Ammon.<verse eid="JER 48:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:11"/>And Ioanan son of Karee and all the leaders of the force, those with him, heard of all the evil that Ismael had done,<verse eid="JER 48:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:12"/>and they brought their whole army and went out to fight him. And they found him at a great water in Gabaon.<verse eid="JER 48:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:13"/>And it happened when all the people who were with Ismael saw Ioanan and the leaders of the force that was with him,<verse eid="JER 48:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:14"/>they then went back to Ioanan.<verse eid="JER 48:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:15"/>And Ismael was saved with eight people and went to the sons of Ammon.<verse eid="JER 48:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:16"/>And Ioanan and all the leaders of the force, those with him, took all the rest of the people whom he had turned away from Ismael-- mighty men in war and the women and the rest and the eunuchs, whom he brought back from Gabaon.<verse eid="JER 48:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:17"/>And they went out and settled at Gaberoth Chamaam, which is near Bethleem, to go to Egypt<verse eid="JER 48:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 48:18"/>from before the Chaldeans, because they feared before them, because Ismael had struck Godolias, whom the king of Babylon had appointed in the land.<verse eid="JER 48:18"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 49">
<verse sid="JER 49:1"/>(42.1) And all the leaders of the force and Ioanan and Azarias son of Maasaias and all the people from small even to great approached<verse eid="JER 49:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:2"/>the prophet Ieremias and said to him, "Let mercy for us come about before you, and pray to the Lord, your God, for these that remain, because there are a few of us left out of many, as your eyes see.<verse eid="JER 49:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:3"/>And let the Lord your God tell us the way we should go in it and the word we should do."<verse eid="JER 49:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:4"/>And Ieremias said to them, "I have heard; behold, I shall pray to the Lord, your God, according to your words, and it shall be, the word whichever the Lord will answer, I will tell you; I will not hide from you what is said."<verse eid="JER 49:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:5"/>And they in their turn said to Ieremias, "Let the Lord be among us as a just and faithful witness, if-- according to every word with which the Lord sends you to us-- we shall not act thus.<verse eid="JER 49:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:6"/>Both if it is good and if it is bad, we will obey the voice of the Lord, our God, to him to whom we are sending you, in order that it may go better with us, because we will obey the voice of the Lord our God."<verse eid="JER 49:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:7"/>And it happened after ten days a word of the Lord came to Ieremias.<verse eid="JER 49:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:8"/>And he summoned Ioanan and the leaders of the force and all the people from small even to great<verse eid="JER 49:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:9"/>and said to them, "Thus did the Lord say:<verse eid="JER 49:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:10"/>If in settling you settle in this land, I will build you up and not pull down, and I will plant you and not pluck up, because I am at rest regarding the evils that I have done to you.<verse eid="JER 49:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:11"/>Do not be afraid before the king of Babylon, whom you fear before him. Do not be afraid, quoth the Lord, because I am with you, to rescue you and to save you from his hand.<verse eid="JER 49:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:12"/>And I will grant you mercy, and I will have mercy on you and return you to your land.<verse eid="JER 49:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:13"/>And if you keep saying, 'We will not settle in this land,' so as not to obey the voice of the Lord,<verse eid="JER 49:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:14"/>'because we will go into the land of Egypt, and we shall not see war, and we shall not hear a trumpet sound, and we shall not be hungry because of bread, and there we will live,'<verse eid="JER 49:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:15"/>therefore hear a word of the Lord. Thus did the Lord say: If you incline your face towards Egypt and enter to live there,<verse eid="JER 49:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:16"/>it shall also be that the sword, which you fear before it, shall find you in Egypt, and the famine, regarding which you have a concern before it, shall seize you in Egypt, and there you shall die.<verse eid="JER 49:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:17"/>And there shall be: all the people and all the aliens who have set their faces towards the land of Egypt to live there, they shall expire by sword and by famine, and there shall not be any of them that escapes from the evils that I am bringing upon them,<verse eid="JER 49:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:18"/>because thus did the Lord say: Just as my anger dripped on the inhabitants of Ierousalem, so my anger will drip on you, when you go into Egypt. And you shall become untrodden and be in subjection and become a curse and a reproach, and you shall see this place no more.<verse eid="JER 49:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:19"/>This is what the Lord has spoken to you who remain of Iouda: Do not enter into Egypt. And now in knowing you shall know<verse eid="JER 49:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:20"/>that you have acted wickedly in your souls in having sent to me, saying, 'Pray for us to the Lord, and according to everything, whatever the Lord speaks to you, we will do.'<verse eid="JER 49:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:21"/>And you have not obeyed the voice of the Lord by which he sent me to you.<verse eid="JER 49:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 49:22"/>And now you shall expire by sword and by famine in the place where you desire to go to settle there."<verse eid="JER 49:22"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 50">
<verse sid="JER 50:1"/>(43.1) And it happened, when Ieremias stopped saying to the people all the words of the Lord, with which the Lord had sent him to them-- all these words--<verse eid="JER 50:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 50:2"/>then Azarias son of Maasaias said, and Ioanan son of Karee and all the men who had spoken to Ieremias, saying, "Lies! The Lord did not send you to us to say, 'Do not enter into Egypt to live there,'<verse eid="JER 50:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 50:3"/>but Barouch son of Nerias is inciting you against us in order that you hand us over into the hands of the Chaldeans that they put us to death and that we be exiled to Babylon."<verse eid="JER 50:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 50:4"/>And Ioanan and all the leaders of the force and all the people did not obey the voice of the Lord, to settle down in the land of Iouda.<verse eid="JER 50:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 50:5"/>And Ioanan and all the leaders of the force took all those remaining of Iouda who had returned to settle down in the land--<verse eid="JER 50:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 50:6"/>the mighty men and the women and the rest and the daughters of the king and the souls whom Nabouzardan had left with Godolias son of Achikam and the prophet Ieremias and Barouch son of Nerias.<verse eid="JER 50:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 50:7"/>And they entered into Egypt, because they did not obey the voice of the Lord. And they entered into Taphnas.<verse eid="JER 50:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 50:8"/>And a word of the Lord came to Ieremias in Taphnas, saying:<verse eid="JER 50:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 50:9"/>Take some large stones for yourself, and hide them in the entrance to Pharao's house in Taphnas in the sight of the men of Iouda.<verse eid="JER 50:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 50:10"/>And you will say, Thus did the Lord say: Behold, I am sending for and will bring King Nabouchodonosor of Babylon, and he will set his throne over these stones that you have hidden, and he will raise his weapons against them<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">50:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Egyptians'</char></note>,<verse eid="JER 50:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 50:11"/>and he shall enter and strike the land of Egypt, giving those who are destined for death, to death, and those who are destined for going into exile, to going into exile, and those who are destined for the sword, to the sword.<verse eid="JER 50:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 50:12"/>And he shall burn a fire in the houses of their gods, and he shall set them<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">50:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'houses'</char></note> on fire and exile them<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">50:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Egyptians'</char></note>, and he shall delouse the land of Egypt, as a shepherd delouses his cloak, and he shall depart in peace.<verse eid="JER 50:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 50:13"/>And he shall crush the pillars of Heliopolis, those in On, and their<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">50:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'people's' or 'gods''</char></note> houses he shall burn down with fire.<verse eid="JER 50:13"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 51">
<verse sid="JER 51:1"/>(44.1) The word that came to Ieremias for all the Judeans living in Egypt, even those settled in Magdolos and in Taphnas and in the land of Pathoures, saying,<verse eid="JER 51:1"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:2"/>Thus did the Lord, the God of Israel, say: You have seen all the evils that I have brought on Ierousalem and on the cities of Iouda. And behold, they are desolate of inhabitants<verse eid="JER 51:2"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:3"/>because of their wickedness that they committed, to embitter me, by having gone to burn incense to other gods that they did not know.<verse eid="JER 51:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:4"/>And I sent to you my servants the prophets early in the morning, and I sent, saying, "Do not do the thing of this defilement that I hated!"<verse eid="JER 51:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:5"/>And they did not listen and did not incline their ear, to turn from their evils so as not to offer incense to other gods.<verse eid="JER 51:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:6"/>And my wrath and my anger dripped, and it burned in the cities of Iouda and outside of Ierousalem, and they became a desolation and something untrodden, as this day.<verse eid="JER 51:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:7"/>And now thus did the Lord Almighty say: Why are you doing great harm to your souls, to cut off your man and woman, infant and suckling, from the midst of Iouda so as not to have any one left,<verse eid="JER 51:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:8"/>to embitter me with the works of your hands, to offer incense to other gods in the land of Egypt, there where you have come to live, that you be cut off and that you become a curse and reproach among the nations of the earth?<verse eid="JER 51:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:9"/>Surely, you have not forgotten the evils of your fathers and the evils of the kings of Iouda and the evils of your rulers and the evils of your wives, which they committed in the land of Iouda and outside of Ierousalem?<verse eid="JER 51:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:10"/>And they have not stopped to this day, and they have not clung to my ordinances that I gave before their fathers.<verse eid="JER 51:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:11"/>Therefore thus did the Lord say: Behold, I am setting my face<verse eid="JER 51:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:12"/>to destroy all those remaining who are in Egypt, and they shall fall; by sword and by famine they shall fail from small even to great, and they shall become a reproach and destruction and a curse.<verse eid="JER 51:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:13"/>And I will visit upon those who are settled in Egypt, as I have visited upon Ierousalem, with sword and with famine,<verse eid="JER 51:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:14"/>and none of those remaining of Iouda who sojourn in the land of Egypt shall be saved to return to the land of Iouda, there to which they hope in their souls to return; they shall not go back, except as escapees.<verse eid="JER 51:14"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:15"/>And all the men, who were aware that their wives were offering incense to other gods, and all the women, a great gathering, and all the people who settled in Pathoures in the land of Egypt answered Ieremias, saying:<verse eid="JER 51:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:16"/>"As for the word that you have spoken to us in the name of the Lord, we are not going to hear you,<verse eid="JER 51:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:17"/>because in doing we will do every word that shall come out of our mouth, to offer incense to the queen of the sky and to pour out libations to her, just as we and our fathers and our kings and our rulers did in the cities of Iouda and outside of Ierousalem. And we were filled with bread, and we were well-off and saw no evil.<verse eid="JER 51:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:18"/>But when we left off offering incense to the queen of the sky, we all were diminished and have failed by sword and by famine.<verse eid="JER 51:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:19"/>And because we were offering incense to the queen of the sky and poured out libations to her-- surely, we did not make cakes for her and poured out libations to her without our husbands?"<verse eid="JER 51:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:20"/>And Ieremias said to all the people, the mighty men and the women and all the people who answered him words, saying:<verse eid="JER 51:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:21"/>"As for the incense offering that you offered in the cities of Iouda and outside of Ierousalem, you and your fathers and your kings and your rulers and the people of the land, did not the Lord remember it, and did it not come up in his heart?<verse eid="JER 51:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:22"/>And the Lord could no longer bear up before the evil of your deeds, before the abominations that you committed, and your land became a desolation and something untrodden and a curse, as this day.<verse eid="JER 51:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:23"/>Because you were burning incense and because you sinned against the Lord and did not obey the voice of the Lord and did not walk by his ordinances and by his law and by his testimonies, these evils have also taken hold of you."<verse eid="JER 51:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:24"/>And Ieremias said to the people and the women, "Hear a word of the Lord,<verse eid="JER 51:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:25"/>Thus did the Lord, the God of Israel, say: You wives have spoken with your mouth and have accomplished with your hands, saying, 'In enacting we will enact our agreements to which we have agreed, to burn incense to the queen of the sky and to pour out libations to her.' In respecting you respected your agreements, and in enacting you enacted!<verse eid="JER 51:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:26"/>Therefore hear a word of the Lord, all Iouda who settled in the land of Egypt: Behold, I swore by my great name, said the Lord, if my name shall ever be in the mouth of all Iouda in all the land of Egypt to say, 'The Lord lives!'--<verse eid="JER 51:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:27"/>because, behold, I am watchful over them to harm them and not to do good, and all Iouda, those who live in the land of Egypt, shall fail by sword and by famine until they expire.<verse eid="JER 51:27"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:28"/>And those who have escaped from the sword shall return to the land of Iouda, few in number, and those remaining of Iouda, who are established in the land of Egypt to sojourn there, shall know whose word will endure!<verse eid="JER 51:28"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:29"/>And this shall be the sign that I am going to visit upon you for evil:<verse eid="JER 51:29"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:30"/>Thus did the Lord say, Behold, I am giving Ouaphre, king of Egypt, into the hands of his enemy and into the hands of people that seek his soul, just as I gave King Sedekias of Iouda into the hands of King Nabouchodonosor of Babylon, his enemy and one who sought his soul."<verse eid="JER 51:30"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:31"/>(45.1) The word that the prophet Ieremias spoke to Barouch son of Nerias, when he would write these words in a book from the mouth of Ieremias, in the fourth year of Ioakim son of King Iosias of Iouda:<verse eid="JER 51:31"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:32"/>(2) Thus did the Lord say with reference to you, O Barouch:<verse eid="JER 51:32"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:33"/>(3) Because you said, "Woe is me! Woe is me! because the Lord has added sorrow to my pain, I slept in groaning, and I found no rest."<verse eid="JER 51:33"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:34"/>(4) Say to him, "Thus did the Lord say: Behold, I bring down whom I have built up and pluck up whom I planted.<verse eid="JER 51:34"/>

<verse sid="JER 51:35"/>(5) And you will seek great things for yourself. Do not seek them because, behold, I am bringing evil upon all flesh, says the Lord, but I will give your soul as a windfall in every place, there where you may go."<verse eid="JER 51:35"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="JER 52">
<verse sid="JER 52:1"/>It being Sedekias' twenty-first year when he began to reign-- and he reigned eleven years in Ierousalem, and his mother's name was Hamital daughter of Ieremias from Lobena.<verse eid="JER 52:1"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 52:2"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">52:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 52:2"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 52:3"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">52:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 52:3"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:4"/>And it happened in the ninth year of his reign, in the tenth month, on the tenth of the month, King Nabouchodonosor of Babylon came with all his force against Ierousalem, and they blockaded it and walled it in on four sides, all around.<verse eid="JER 52:4"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:5"/>And the city came under siege until the eleventh year of King Sedekias.<verse eid="JER 52:5"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:6"/>On the ninth of the month also the famine took a firm hold in the city, and there were no loaves for the people of the land.<verse eid="JER 52:6"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:7"/>And the city was breached, and all the men of war went out by night by the way of the gate between the wall and the outer wall, which was by the king's garden, and the Chaldeans were at the city, all around. And they went in the direction of Araba.<verse eid="JER 52:7"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:8"/>And the force of the Chaldeans pursued after the king and overtook him across from Iericho, and all his servants were scattered from him.<verse eid="JER 52:8"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:9"/>And they captured the king and brought him to the king of Babylon at Deblatha, and he spoke to him in judgment.<verse eid="JER 52:9"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:10"/>And the king of Babylon slew the sons of Sedekias before his eyes, and he slew all the rulers of Iouda at Deblatha.<verse eid="JER 52:10"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:11"/>And he blinded the eyes of Sedekias and bound him in fetters, and the king of Babylon brought him to Babylon and delivered him to the mill house until the day he died.<verse eid="JER 52:11"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:12"/>And in the fifth month, on the tenth of the month, Nabouzardan the chief cook, who stood before the king of Babylon, came to Ierousalem.<verse eid="JER 52:12"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:13"/>And he set on fire the house of the Lord and the house of the king and all the houses of the city, and every great house he set on fire with fire.<verse eid="JER 52:13"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:14"/>And the force of the Chaldeans, which was with the chief cook, pulled down every wall around Ierousalem.<verse eid="JER 52:14"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 52:15"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">52:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 52:15"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:16"/>And the chief cook left a residue of the people to be vinedressers and tillers of the soil.<verse eid="JER 52:16"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:17"/>And the pillars of bronze that were in the house of the Lord and the bases and the bronze sea that was in the house of the Lord, the Chaldeans broke in pieces and took their bronze and carried it off to Babylon.<verse eid="JER 52:17"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:18"/>And the rim and the saucers and the meat hooks and all the bronze vessels with them with which they were ministering.<verse eid="JER 52:18"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:19"/>And the chief cook took away the saphphoth<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">52:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'basins'</char></note> and the masmaroth<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">52:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = ?</char></note> and the pitchers and the lampstands and the censers and the ladles, which were gold gold<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">52:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'gold gold':  Possibly 'all gold'</char></note> and which were silver silver<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">52:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'silver silver':  Possibly 'all silver'</char></note>.<verse eid="JER 52:19"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:20"/>And as for the two pillars and the one sea and the twelve bronze bull calves under the sea, which things King Salomon had made for the house of the Lord, there was no weighing of their bronze.<verse eid="JER 52:20"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:21"/>And as for the pillars, the height of the one pillar was thirty-five cubits, and a cord of twelve cubits encompassed it, and its thickness was four fingers all round.<verse eid="JER 52:21"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:22"/>And upon them was a bronze cornice, and the excess of the one cornice was five cubits in length, and lattice-work and pomegranates were on the cornice all round; all was of bronze. And the second pillar had the same, with eight pomegranates to a cubit for the twelve cubits.<verse eid="JER 52:22"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:23"/>And there were ninety-six pomegranates on the one side, and all the pomegranates on the latticework were one hundred, all around.<verse eid="JER 52:23"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:24"/>And the chief cook took the first priest and the priest ranked second and the three that were guarding the threshold<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">52:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = 'way'</char></note><verse eid="JER 52:24"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:25"/>and one eunuch, who was overseer of the men of war, and seven men of name in the presence of the king, who were found in the city, and the recorder of the forces, who was recording for the people of the land, and sixty persons of the people of the land, who were found in the midst of the city.<verse eid="JER 52:25"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:26"/>And Nabouzardan the chief cook took them and brought them to the king of Babylon at Deblatha.<verse eid="JER 52:26"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:27"/>And the king of Babylon struck them at Deblatha in the land of Hemath.<verse eid="JER 52:27"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 52:28"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">52:28</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 52:28"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 52:29"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">52:29</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 52:29"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="JER 52:30"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">52:30</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="JER 52:30"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:31"/>And it happened in the thirty-seventh year after King Ioakim of Iouda had been exiled, in the twelfth month, on the twenty-fourth of the month, King Oulaimaradach of Babylon, in the year in which he became king, received the head of King Ioakim of Iouda and brought him out the house where he was being guarded,<verse eid="JER 52:31"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:32"/>and he spoke kindly to him and gave him a seat above the seats of the other kings who were with him in Babylon.<verse eid="JER 52:32"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:33"/>And he exchanged his prison robe, and he would always eat bread in his presence all the days he lived.<verse eid="JER 52:33"/>

<verse sid="JER 52:34"/>For the allowance was given him always by the king of Babylon, from day to day, until the day he died.<verse eid="JER 52:34"/>
</_X_chapter></_X_book></_X_usx>