<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<_X_usx version="2.0">
<para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
<_X_book code="LEV">





<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 1">
<verse sid="LEV 1:1"/>And the Lord summoned Moyses and spoke to him from the tent of witness, saying:<verse eid="LEV 1:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 1:2"/>Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: When a person of you brings gifts of livestock to the Lord, you shall bring your gifts from the cattle and from the sheep.<verse eid="LEV 1:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 1:3"/>If his gift is a whole burnt offering from the cattle, he shall present a male without blemish; he shall bring it to the door of the tent of witness, acceptable before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 1:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 1:4"/>And he shall lay his hand on the head of the offering, a thing acceptable to him to atone for him.<verse eid="LEV 1:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 1:5"/>And they shall slaughter the bull calf before the Lord, and the sons of Aaron the priests shall offer the blood, and they shall pour out the blood against all sides of the altar that is at the entrance of the tent of witness.<verse eid="LEV 1:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 1:6"/>And when they flay the whole burnt offering, they shall cut it up limb by limb.<verse eid="LEV 1:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 1:7"/>And the sons of Aaron the priests shall put fire on the altar and pile wood onto the fire.<verse eid="LEV 1:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 1:8"/>And the sons of Aaron the priests shall pile the divided parts and the head and the suet onto the wood that is on the fire on the altar,<verse eid="LEV 1:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 1:9"/>but the entrails and the legs they shall wash with water, and the priests shall lay everything on the altar. It is an offering, a sacrifice, an odor of fragrance to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 1:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 1:10"/>But if his gift for a whole burnt offering to the Lord is from the small cattle, both from the lambs and the kids, he shall present a male without blemish, and he shall lay his hand on its head.<verse eid="LEV 1:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 1:11"/>And they shall slaughter it on the north side of the altar before the Lord, and the sons of Aaron the priests shall pour out its blood against all sides of the altar.<verse eid="LEV 1:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 1:12"/>And they shall divide it up limb by limb with its head and its suet, and the priests shall pile them on the wood that is on the fire on the altar,<verse eid="LEV 1:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 1:13"/>and its entrails and its legs they shall wash with water. And the priest shall present everything and lay it on the altar. It is an offering, a sacrifice, an odor of fragrance to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 1:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 1:14"/>But if the gift he brings to the Lord is an offering from the birds, then he shall bring his gift from the turtledoves or from the doves.<verse eid="LEV 1:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 1:15"/>And the priest shall do the presenting at the altar and snip off the head. And the priest shall do the placing on the altar and squeeze out the blood against the base of the altar.<verse eid="LEV 1:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 1:16"/>And he shall remove the crop with the feathers and throw it at the east side of the altar, in the place for ashes.<verse eid="LEV 1:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 1:17"/>And he shall break it open by the wings and not divide it. And the priest shall lay it on the altar on the wood that is on the fire. It is an offering, a sacrifice, an odor of fragrance to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 1:17"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 2">
<verse sid="LEV 2:1"/>Now if a soul presents a gift, a sacrifice to the Lord, his gift shall be fine flour, and he shall pour oil on it and put frankincense on it-- it is a sacrifice--<verse eid="LEV 2:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 2:2"/>and he shall bring it to the sons of Aaron the priests. And after gripping from it a handful of the fine flour with the oil and all its frankincense, the priest shall lay its memorial portion on the altar; it is a sacrifice, an odor of fragrance to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 2:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 2:3"/>And what remains from the sacrifice is for Aaron and his sons, a holy of holies from the Lord's sacrifices.<verse eid="LEV 2:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 2:4"/>But if he presents a gift, a sacrifice baked in the oven, it shall be of fine flour: unleavened cakes mixed with oil and unleavened wafers spread with oil.<verse eid="LEV 2:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 2:5"/>But if your gift is a sacrifice from a frying-pan, it shall be fine flour mixed with oil, unleavened,<verse eid="LEV 2:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 2:6"/>and you shall break them in pieces and pour oil onto them; it is a sacrifice to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 2:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 2:7"/>But if your gift is a sacrifice from a brazier, fine flour shall be prepared in oil.<verse eid="LEV 2:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 2:8"/>And he shall present to the Lord the sacrifice that he may prepare from these, and he shall do the presenting to the priest. And having approached the altar,<verse eid="LEV 2:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 2:9"/>the priest shall remove from the sacrifice its memorial portion, and the priest shall lay it on the altar; it is an offering, an odor of fragrance to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 2:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 2:10"/>But what is left of the sacrifice is for Aaron and his sons: a holy of holies from the Lord's offerings.<verse eid="LEV 2:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 2:11"/>You shall not prepare any sacrifice that you may bring to the Lord with leaven, for you shall not present any leaven and any honey to offer of it to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 2:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 2:12"/>You shall present them to the Lord as a gift of first fruit, but they shall not be brought onto the altar for an odor of fragrance to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 2:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 2:13"/>And every gift of your sacrifice shall be salted with salt. You shall not omit from your sacrifices the salt of the Lord's covenant; on each gift of yours you shall offer salt to the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 2:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 2:14"/>But if you present a sacrifice of first products to the Lord, new, roasted, pounded, wheatengroats, to the Lord, then you shall bring the sacrifice of first products,<verse eid="LEV 2:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 2:15"/>and you shall pour oil onto it and lay frankincense on it; it is a sacrifice.<verse eid="LEV 2:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 2:16"/>And the priest shall offer up its memorial portion-- some of the roasted wheatengroats with the oil and all its frankincense. It is an offering to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 2:16"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 3">
<verse sid="LEV 3:1"/>Now if his gift to the Lord is a sacrifice of deliverance, if he brings it from the cattle, whether male or female, he shall bring it without blemish before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 3:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 3:2"/>And he shall lay his hands on the head of the gift, and he shall slaughter it at the entrance to the tent of witness, and the sons of Aaron the priests shall pour out the blood against all sides of the altar of whole burnt offerings.<verse eid="LEV 3:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 3:3"/>And they shall bring from the sacrifice of deliverance an offering to the Lord: the fat that covers the entrails and all the fat that is on the entrails<verse eid="LEV 3:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 3:4"/>and the two kidneys and the fat that is on them at the thighs, and he shall remove the appendage that is on the liver with the kidneys.<verse eid="LEV 3:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 3:5"/>And the sons of Aaron the priests shall offer them up on the altar, on the whole burnt offerings on the wood that is on the fire; it is an offering, an odor of fragrance to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 3:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 3:6"/>But if his gift, a sacrifice of deliverance to the Lord, is from the sheep, male or female, he shall present it without blemish.<verse eid="LEV 3:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 3:7"/>If he brings a lamb as his gift, he shall bring it before the Lord,<verse eid="LEV 3:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 3:8"/>and he shall lay his hands on the head of his gift, and he shall slaughter it at the entrance of the tent of witness. And the sons of Aaron the priests shall pour out the blood against all sides of the altar.<verse eid="LEV 3:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 3:9"/>And he shall present some of the sacrifice of deliverance as an offering to God: the fat and the lower back without blemish (he shall remove it with the loin muscles) and the fat that covers the entrails and the fat that is on the entrails<verse eid="LEV 3:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 3:10"/>and both the kidneys and the fat that is on them at the thighs, having also removed the appendage which is on the liver with the kidneys,<verse eid="LEV 3:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 3:11"/>the priest shall make an offering on the altar, an odor of fragrance, an offering to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 3:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 3:12"/>But if his gift is from the goats, he shall both do the presenting before the Lord,<verse eid="LEV 3:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 3:13"/>and he shall lay his hands on its head, and they shall slaughter it before the Lord at the entrance of the tent of witness, and the sons of Aaron the priests shall pour out the blood against all sides of the altar.<verse eid="LEV 3:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 3:14"/>And he shall offer up of it as an offering to the Lord: the fat that covers the entrails and all the fat that is on the entrails<verse eid="LEV 3:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 3:15"/>and both the kidneys and all the fat that is on them at the thighs, and he shall remove the appendage of the liver with the kidneys.<verse eid="LEV 3:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 3:16"/>And the priest shall offer on the altar an offering, an odor of fragrance to the Lord. All the fat is the Lord's.<verse eid="LEV 3:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 3:17"/>It shall be a precept forever throughout your generations, in all your settlement; you shall not eat any fat and any blood.<verse eid="LEV 3:17"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 4">
<verse sid="LEV 4:1"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 4:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:2"/>Speak to the sons of Israel, saying: If a soul sins unintentionally before the Lord regarding the Lord's ordinances, which one must not do, and does any one of them:<verse eid="LEV 4:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:3"/>If it is the anointed high priest who sins, so that the people sin, then he shall bring for his sin that he has committed a calf from the cattle without blemish to the Lord for his sin.<verse eid="LEV 4:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:4"/>And he shall bring the bull calf to the door of the tent of witness before the Lord and lay his hand on the head of the bull calf before the Lord, and he shall slaughter the bull calf in front of the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 4:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:5"/>And the anointed priest, who has had his hands validated, after taking some of the blood of the bull calf, shall then bring it into the tent of witness.<verse eid="LEV 4:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:6"/>And the priest shall dip his finger in the blood and sprinkle some of the blood seven times with his finger before the Lord in front of the holy veil.<verse eid="LEV 4:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:7"/>And the priest shall put some of the blood of the bull calf on the horns of the altar of the incense of the combination that is before the Lord, which is in the tent of witness, and all the blood of the bull calf he shall pour out at the base of the altar of whole burnt offerings, which is at the entrance of the tent of witness.<verse eid="LEV 4:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:8"/>And all the fat of the bull calf for sin he shall remove from it: the fat that covers the innards and all the fat that is on the innards<verse eid="LEV 4:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:9"/>and the two kidneys and the fat that is on them, which is on the thighs, and the appendage which is on the liver-- he shall remove it with the kidneys,<verse eid="LEV 4:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:10"/>just as he removes it from the bull calf of the sacrifice of deliverance. And the priest shall offer on the altar of offering.<verse eid="LEV 4:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:11"/>And the skin of the bull calf and all its flesh, as well as its head and its appendages and its entrails and its dung--<verse eid="LEV 4:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:12"/>even the whole bull calf they shall carry out to a clean place outside the camp where they shall pour out the ash, and they shall burn it completely on wood by fire; at the outpouring of the ash it shall be burned.<verse eid="LEV 4:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:13"/>But if the whole congregation of Israel acts in ignorance and the matter escapes the notice of the eyes of the congregation and they do one of any of the commandments of the Lord, which shall not be done, and they shall be in error<verse eid="LEV 4:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:14"/>and the sin wherein they were sinning should become known to them, then the congregation shall bring a calf of the cattle without blemish for the sin and bring it to the entrance of the tent of witness.<verse eid="LEV 4:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:15"/>And the elders of the congregation shall lay their hands on the head of the bull calf before the Lord, and they shall slaughter the bull calf before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 4:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:16"/>And the anointed priest shall bring some of the blood of the bull calf into the tent of witness,<verse eid="LEV 4:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:17"/>and the priest shall dip his finger into some of the blood of the bull calf and sprinkle it seven times before the Lord in front of the holy veil.<verse eid="LEV 4:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:18"/>And the priest shall put some of the blood onto the horns of the altar of the incense of the combination that is before the Lord, which is in the tent of witness, and he shall pour out all the blood at the base of the altar of offerings that is near the door of the tent of witness.<verse eid="LEV 4:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:19"/>And he shall remove all the fat from it and offer it up on the altar.<verse eid="LEV 4:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:20"/>And he shall do with the bull calf just as he did with the bull calf for sin; thus it shall be done. And the priest shall make atonement for them, and the sin shall be forgiven them.<verse eid="LEV 4:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:21"/>And they shall carry the whole bull calf outside the camp and burn up the bull calf as they completely burned the first bull calf. It is for<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Wevers Ed. = Omit</char></note> a sin of the congregation.<verse eid="LEV 4:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:22"/>But if the ruler sins and does unintentionally one of any of the commandments of the Lord their God, which shall not be done, and sins and is in error<verse eid="LEV 4:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:23"/>and the sin wherein he has sinned becomes known to him, then he shall bring his gift: a young billy goat, a male without blemish.<verse eid="LEV 4:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:24"/>And he shall lay his hand on the head of the young goat, and they shall slaughter it at the spot where they slaughter the whole burnt offerings before the Lord. It is for<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Wevers Ed. = Omit</char></note> sin.<verse eid="LEV 4:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:25"/>And the priest shall put some of the blood of the one for sin with his finger on the horns of the altar of whole burnt offerings, and he shall pour out all its blood at the base of the altar of whole burnt offerings.<verse eid="LEV 4:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:26"/>And all its fat he shall offer up on the altar, like the fat of the sacrifice of deliverance. And the priest shall make atonement for him because of his sin, and it shall be forgiven him.<verse eid="LEV 4:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:27"/>But if any one soul of the people of the land sins unintentionally in doing one of any of the Lord's commandments that shall not be done and he is in error<verse eid="LEV 4:27"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:28"/>and the sin wherein he sins becomes known to him, then he shall bring a young nanny goat; he shall bring a female without blemish for the sin that he has committed,<verse eid="LEV 4:28"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:29"/>and he shall lay his hand on the head of his mistake, and they shall slaughter the nanny goat for sin at the place where they slaughter the whole burnt offerings.<verse eid="LEV 4:29"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:30"/>And the priest shall take some of its blood with his finger and put it onto the horns of the altar of whole burnt offerings, and he shall pour out all its blood at the base of the altar.<verse eid="LEV 4:30"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:31"/>And he shall remove all the fat in the same way that he removes from the sacrifice of deliverance, and the priest shall offer it up on the altar for an odor of fragrance to the Lord. And the priest shall make atonement for him, and it shall be forgiven him.<verse eid="LEV 4:31"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:32"/>But if he brings as his gift a sheep for sin, he shall bring it: a female without blemish.<verse eid="LEV 4:32"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:33"/>And he shall lay his hand on the head of the one for sin, and they shall slaughter it at the spot where they slaughter the whole burnt offerings.<verse eid="LEV 4:33"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:34"/>And after taking some of the blood of the one for sin with his finger, the priest shall put it on the horns of the altar of whole burnt offering, and he shall pour out all its blood at the base of the altar of whole burnt offering.<verse eid="LEV 4:34"/>

<verse sid="LEV 4:35"/>And he shall remove all its fat, as the fat of a sheep is removed from the sacrifice of deliverance, and the priest shall lay it on the altar, on the whole burnt offering of the Lord. And the priest shall make atonement for him for the sin that he has committed, and it shall be forgiven him.<verse eid="LEV 4:35"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 5">
<verse sid="LEV 5:1"/>Now if a soul sins and hears a sound of oath-taking and he is a witness or has seen it or knows of it, if he does not report the matter, he will assume the guilt.<verse eid="LEV 5:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:2"/>Or a soul who touches any unclean thing, whether a carcass or the kill of an unclean animal or unclean carcasses of abominations or the unclean carcasses of cattle<verse eid="LEV 5:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:3"/>or touches some uncleanness of a person, any of his uncleanness in which he be defiled by touching, and it escaped his notice, but later on comes to know it, and should be in error,<verse eid="LEV 5:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:4"/>or a soul who swears, determining with his lips to do evil or to do good, in any way that the person may speak forcefully by an oath, and if it escapes the notice of his eyes and if he comes to know it and should sin in any one of these,<verse eid="LEV 5:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:5"/>then he shall declare his sin concerning the things in which he has sinned.<verse eid="LEV 5:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:6"/>And he shall bring to the Lord for whatever he has done amiss, for the sin that he has committed, a female from the sheep-- a lamb, or a young nanny goat for sin. And the priest shall make atonement for him, for his sin that he has committed, and the sin will be forgiven him.<verse eid="LEV 5:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:7"/>But if his hand does not have the capability for what is sufficient for a sheep, he shall bring for his sin which he has committed two turtledoves or two young doves to the Lord, one for sin and one for a whole burnt offering.<verse eid="LEV 5:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:8"/>And he shall bring them to the priest, and the priest shall bring the one for sin first. And the priest shall snip off its head at the neck, and he shall not divide it.<verse eid="LEV 5:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:9"/>And he shall sprinkle some blood of the one for sin against the wall of the altar, but what remains of the blood he shall squeeze out against the base of the altar, for it is for<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Wevers Ed. = Omit</char></note> sin.<verse eid="LEV 5:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:10"/>And the second he shall prepare as a whole burnt offering, as is customary. And the priest shall make atonement for him for his sin that he has committed, and it shall be forgiven him.<verse eid="LEV 5:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:11"/>But if his hand does not find a brace of turtledoves or two young doves, then he shall bring his gift for that in which he sinned: one-tenth of an oiphi<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew 1 ephah = 22 liters</char></note> of fine flour for sin. He shall not pour oil on it; neither shall he place frankincense on it, because it is for sin.<verse eid="LEV 5:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:12"/>And he shall bring it to the priest, and after gripping from it a handful, the priest shall lay its memorial portion on the altar on the<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Wevers Ed. = Omit</char></note> whole burnt offerings to the Lord. It is for<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Wevers Ed. = Omit</char></note> sin.<verse eid="LEV 5:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:13"/>And the priest shall make atonement for him, for his sin that he has committed in respect of one of these things, and it will be forgiven him. But what is left shall be for the priest like the offering of fine flour.<verse eid="LEV 5:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:14"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 5:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:15"/>If a soul forgets obliviously and sins unintentionally regarding any of the holy things of the Lord, he shall then bring to the Lord for his error a ram without blemish from the sheep, of the value of silver shekels, according to the shekel of holy things for what he has done amiss.<verse eid="LEV 5:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:16"/>And he shall make restitution for some of the holy things in which he was remiss and add a fifth to it and give it to the priest. And the priest shall make atonement for him with the ram for error, and it will be forgiven him.<verse eid="LEV 5:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:17"/>And a soul that sins and does one of any of the Lord's commandments, which he ought not to do, and does not know and is in error and assumes the sin<verse eid="LEV 5:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:18"/>shall then bring a ram, without blemish from the sheep of the value of silver, for error to the priest. And the priest shall make atonement for him concerning his ignorance of which he was ignorant and did not know himself, and it shall be forgiven him,<verse eid="LEV 5:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 5:19"/>because he has committed an error before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 5:19"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 6">
<verse sid="LEV 6:1"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 6:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:2"/>If a soul sins and by overlooking disregards the commandments of the Lord and falsifies matters pertaining to his neighbor-- in a deposit or regarding joint ownership or regarding plunder or did his neighbor some wrong<verse eid="LEV 6:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:3"/>or has found a loss and lied about it-- and he swears falsely about one of all which a man may do in order to sin by these,<verse eid="LEV 6:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:4"/>then it shall be whenever he sins and is in error and restores the booty which he seized or the injustice he committed or the deposit which was deposited with him or the loss which he found<verse eid="LEV 6:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:5"/>because of every matter about that which he swore about unjustly, he shall also repay the capital itself, and he shall add to it one fifth. Whosesoever it is, he shall restore to him on the day he should be convicted.<verse eid="LEV 6:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:6"/>And for his error he shall bring to the Lord: a ram from the sheep without blemish, of the value for that which he offended.<verse eid="LEV 6:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:7"/>And the priest shall make atonement for him before the Lord, and he shall be forgiven for one of all that he did and offended by it.<verse eid="LEV 6:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:8"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 6:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:9"/>Command Aaron and his sons, saying: This is the law of the whole burnt offering. The whole burnt offering itself in its burning shall be on the altar all night until the morning, and the fire of the altar shall burn on it; it shall not be put out.<verse eid="LEV 6:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:10"/>And the priest shall put on a linen tunic, and he shall put on linen undergarments around his body, and he shall remove from the altar the sacrificial remains to which the fire has reduced the whole burnt offering, and he shall deposit it nearby the altar.<verse eid="LEV 6:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:11"/>And he shall take off his vestment and put on another vestment and carry the sacrificial remains out to a clean place outside the camp.<verse eid="LEV 6:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:12"/>And fire on the altar shall burn on it and shall not be put out. And the priest shall burn wood on it morning by morning and pile on it the whole burnt offering and place on it the fat of the deliverance.<verse eid="LEV 6:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:13"/>And a fire shall burn perpetually on the altar. It shall not be put out.<verse eid="LEV 6:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:14"/>This is the law of the sacrifice, that which the sons of Aaron shall offer before the Lord in front of the altar.<verse eid="LEV 6:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:15"/>And he shall remove from it with a handful some of the fine flour of the sacrifice with its oil and with its frankincense that are on the sacrifice, and he shall offer its memorial portion on the altar: an offering, an odor of fragrance to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 6:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:16"/>But what remains of it Aaron and his sons shall eat. It shall be consumed unleavened in a holy place. In the court of the tent of witness they shall eat it.<verse eid="LEV 6:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:17"/>It shall not be baked as leavened. I have given it as a portion to them from the offerings of the Lord. They are holy of holies like the one for sin and like the one for error.<verse eid="LEV 6:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:18"/>Everything male of the priests shall eat it. It is a perpetual precept for your generations from the Lord's offerings; any one who touches them shall become holy.<verse eid="LEV 6:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:19"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 6:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:20"/>This is the gift of Aaron and his sons, which they shall present to the Lord on the day you shall anoint him: one tenth of an oiphi<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew 1 ephah = 22 liters</char></note> of fine flour as a perpetual sacrifice, half of it in the morning and half of it in the evening.<verse eid="LEV 6:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:21"/>It shall be prepared in a frying-pan with oil; he shall bring it kneaded, rolled, a sacrifice of pieces, a sacrifice as an odor of fragrance to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 6:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:22"/>The priest who is anointed after him from his sons shall prepare it; it is a perpetual law; all of it shall be completely consumed.<verse eid="LEV 6:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:23"/>And every sacrifice of a priest shall be wholly burned and shall not be eaten.<verse eid="LEV 6:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:24"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 6:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:25"/>Speak to Aaron and his sons, saying: This is the law for the sin. They shall slaughter the one for sin before the Lord at the spot where they slaughter the whole burnt offering. They are holy of holies.<verse eid="LEV 6:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:26"/>The priest who offers it up shall eat it. It shall be eaten in a holy place, in the court of the tent of witness.<verse eid="LEV 6:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:27"/>Whoever touches any of its flesh shall become holy. And for whomever some of its blood is sprinkled on a garment, that on which it is sprinkled shall be washed in a holy place.<verse eid="LEV 6:27"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:28"/>And an earthen vessel wherein it was boiled shall be smashed. But if it is boiled in a bronze vessel, he shall scour it and wash it out with water.<verse eid="LEV 6:28"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:29"/>Every male among the priests shall eat them. They are holy of holies to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 6:29"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:30"/>And none of the ones for sin, some of whose blood is brought into the tent of witness to make atonement in the holy place, shall be eaten. It shall be burned up by fire.<verse eid="LEV 6:30"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:31"/>(7.1) And this is the law of the ram for error. They are holy of holies.<verse eid="LEV 6:31"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:32"/>(2) At a spot where they slaughter the whole burnt offering they shall slaughter the ram for error before the Lord, and he shall pour out the blood against all sides of the base of the altar.<verse eid="LEV 6:32"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:33"/>(3) And he shall present from it all its fat from it and the lower back and all the fat that covers the innards and all the fat that is on the innards<verse eid="LEV 6:33"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:34"/>(4) and the two kidneys and the fat that is on them at the thighs and the appendage that is on the liver-- he shall remove them with the kidneys.<verse eid="LEV 6:34"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:35"/>(5) And the priest shall offer them up on the altar as an offering to the Lord; it is for error.<verse eid="LEV 6:35"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:36"/>(6) Every male among the priests shall eat them; in a holy place they shall eat them; they are holy of holies.<verse eid="LEV 6:36"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:37"/>(7) As is the one for sin, so is the one for error. For them there is one law. The priest who makes atonement with it shall have it.<verse eid="LEV 6:37"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:38"/>(8) And the priest who offers a person's whole burnt offering: the skin of the whole burnt offering that he offers shall be his.<verse eid="LEV 6:38"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:39"/>(9) And every sacrifice that is prepared in the oven and everything that is prepared on a hearth or in a pan is for the priest who offers it; it shall be his.<verse eid="LEV 6:39"/>

<verse sid="LEV 6:40"/>(10) And every sacrifice made up with oil or not made up shall belong to all the sons of Aaron, to each the same.<verse eid="LEV 6:40"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 7">
<verse sid="LEV 7:1"/>(7.11) This is the law of the sacrifice of deliverance that they shall offer to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 7:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:2"/>(12) If he brings it for praise, then he shall bring for the sacrifice of praise cakes of fine flour made up with oil and unleavened wafers spread with oil and fine flour mixed with oil.<verse eid="LEV 7:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:3"/>(13) In addition to leavened cakes he shall bring his gifts for a sacrifice of praise for deliverance.<verse eid="LEV 7:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:4"/>(14) And he shall present one out of all his gifts as an advance deduction for the Lord. It shall belong to the priest who pours out the blood of the deliverance. It shall be his.<verse eid="LEV 7:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:5"/>(15) And the flesh of the sacrifice of praise for deliverance shall belong to him, and on the day it is given it shall be eaten. They shall not leave any of it until the morning.<verse eid="LEV 7:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:6"/>(16) And if it is a vow or if he sacrifices his gift voluntarily, it shall be eaten on the same day that he brought his sacrifice and on the next day.<verse eid="LEV 7:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:7"/>(17) And what is left of the flesh of the sacrifice until the third day shall be burned up by fire.<verse eid="LEV 7:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:8"/>(18) But if when eating, he should eat some of the meat on the third day, it will not be accepted for him who offers it, nor shall it be credited to him. It is a defilement, and the soul who eats any of it shall assume the guilt.<verse eid="LEV 7:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:9"/>(19) And meat that touches any unclean thing shall not be eaten; it shall be burned up by fire. Anyone clean shall eat meat.<verse eid="LEV 7:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:10"/>(20) But the soul who should eat any of the meat of the sacrifice of deliverance, which belongs to the Lord, and his uncleanness is on him-- that soul shall be utterly destroyed from his people.<verse eid="LEV 7:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:11"/>(21) And a soul who touches any unclean thing whether of human uncleanness or of unclean quadrupeds or any unclean abomination and eats of the meat of the sacrifice of deliverance, which is the Lord's, that soul shall be utterly destroyed from his people.<verse eid="LEV 7:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:12"/>(22) And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 7:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:13"/>(23) Speak to the sons of Israel, saying: You shall eat no fat of cows and of sheep and of goats.<verse eid="LEV 7:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:14"/>(24) And the fat of carcasses and of things caught by wild animals may be put to any use but shall not be eaten for food.<verse eid="LEV 7:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:15"/>(25) Anyone who eats the fat of animals, of which he may bring some of them as an offering to the Lord-- that soul shall be utterly destroyed from his people.<verse eid="LEV 7:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:16"/>(26) You shall not eat any blood, either of birds or of animals, in any of your settlements.<verse eid="LEV 7:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:17"/>(27) Any soul who eats blood-- that soul shall be utterly destroyed from his people.<verse eid="LEV 7:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:18"/>(28) And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 7:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:19"/>(29) And you shall speak to the sons of Israel, saying: He who brings to the Lord a sacrifice of deliverance shall bring his gift to the Lord from the sacrifice of deliverance.<verse eid="LEV 7:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:20"/>(30) His hands shall bring the offerings to the Lord. The fat that is on the breast and the appendage of the liver-- he shall offer them to add to a gift before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 7:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:21"/>(31) And the priest shall offer up the fat on the altar, and the breast shall belong to Aaron and his sons.<verse eid="LEV 7:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:22"/>(32) And the right shoulder from your sacrifices of deliverance you shall give as an advance deduction for the priest.<verse eid="LEV 7:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:23"/>(33) The one among the sons of Aaron who brings the blood and the fat of the deliverance shall have the right shoulder as a share.<verse eid="LEV 7:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:24"/>(34) For I have taken the breast of the addition and the shoulder of the advance deduction from the sons of Israel, from your sacrifices of deliverance, and I have given them to Aaron the priest and to his sons as a perpetual precept from the sons of Israel.<verse eid="LEV 7:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:25"/>(35) This is the anointing of Aaron and the anointing of his sons from the offerings of the Lord on the day he procured them to serve the Lord as priests,<verse eid="LEV 7:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:26"/>(36) just as the Lord commanded to give to them on the day he anointed them out of the sons of Israel. It is a perpetual precept throughout their generations.<verse eid="LEV 7:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:27"/>(37) This is the law of the whole burnt offerings and of sacrifice and for sin and for error and for validation, and of the sacrifice of deliverance,<verse eid="LEV 7:27"/>

<verse sid="LEV 7:28"/>(38) as the Lord commanded Moyses on the mountain of Sina on the day he commanded the sons of Israel to bring their gifts before the Lord in the wilderness of Sina.<verse eid="LEV 7:28"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 8">
<verse sid="LEV 8:1"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 8:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:2"/>Take Aaron and his sons and his vestments and the anointing oil and the bull calf for sin and the two rams and the basket of unleavened bread,<verse eid="LEV 8:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:3"/>and assemble the whole congregation at the door of the tent of witness.<verse eid="LEV 8:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:4"/>And Moyses did as the Lord instructed him, and he assembled the congregation at the door of the tent of witness.<verse eid="LEV 8:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:5"/>And Moyses said to the congregation: This is the thing that the Lord commanded to do.<verse eid="LEV 8:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:6"/>And Moyses brought Aaron and his sons forward and washed them with water.<verse eid="LEV 8:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:7"/>And he put the tunic on him and fastened the girdle about him and put the undergarment on him, and he placed on him the shoulder-strap and girded him about according to the procedure of the shoulder-strap, and he bound him fast with it.<verse eid="LEV 8:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:8"/>And he put on him the oracle, and he put on the oracle the explanation and the truth.<verse eid="LEV 8:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:9"/>And he put the headband on his head, and on the headband, in front, he put the golden leaf, the devoted holy object, as the Lord instructed Moyses.<verse eid="LEV 8:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:10"/>And Moyses took some of the anointing oil<verse eid="LEV 8:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:11"/>and sprinkled some of it on the altar seven times and anointed the altar and consecrated it and all its utensils and the washbasin and its base and consecrated them. And he anointed the tent and all the things in it and consecrated it.<verse eid="LEV 8:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:12"/>And Moyses poured out some of the anointing oil on Aaron's head and anointed him and consecrated him.<verse eid="LEV 8:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:13"/>And Moyses brought forward the sons of Aaron and clothed them with tunics and fastened belts around them and tied turbans on them just as the Lord instructed Moyses.<verse eid="LEV 8:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:14"/>And Moyses led forward the bull calf for sin, and Aaron and his sons laid their hands on the head of the bull calf for sin.<verse eid="LEV 8:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:15"/>And he slaughtered it, and Moyses took some of the blood and with his finger put it on the horns of the altar round about, and he purified the altar. And he poured out the blood at the base of the altar, and he consecrated it to make atonement on it.<verse eid="LEV 8:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:16"/>And Moyses took all the fat that was on the innards and the appendage on the liver and both kidneys and the fat on them, and Moyses performed the offering on the altar.<verse eid="LEV 8:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:17"/>And the bull calf and its hide and its flesh and its dung-- he burned them with fire outside the camp as the Lord instructed Moyses.<verse eid="LEV 8:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:18"/>And Moyses brought forward the ram that was for the whole burnt offering, and Aaron and his sons laid their hands on the head of the ram.<verse eid="LEV 8:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:19"/>And Moyses slaughtered the ram, and Moyses poured out the blood against all sides of the altar.<verse eid="LEV 8:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:20"/>And he divided up the ram limb by limb, and Moyses offered up the head and the limbs and the fat.<verse eid="LEV 8:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:21"/>And the entrails and the legs he washed with water, and Moyses offered up the whole ram on the altar. It is a whole burnt offering, for an odor of fragrance; it is an offering to the Lord, as the Lord commanded Moyses.<verse eid="LEV 8:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:22"/>And Moyses brought forward the second ram, the ram of validation. And Aaron and his sons laid their hands on the head of the ram.<verse eid="LEV 8:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:23"/>And he slaughtered it, and Moyses took some of its blood and put it on the lobe of Aaron's right ear and on the tip of his right hand and on the tip of his right foot.<verse eid="LEV 8:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:24"/>And Moyses brought forward the sons of Aaron, and Moyses put some of the blood on the lobes of their right ears and on the tips of their right hands and on the tips of their right feet. And Moyses poured out the blood against all sides of the altar.<verse eid="LEV 8:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:25"/>And he took the fat and the lower back and the fat that was on the entrails and the appendage of the liver and the two kidneys and the fat on them and the right shoulder.<verse eid="LEV 8:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:26"/>And out of the basket of validation that is before the Lord he took one unleavened cake and one oil bread and one wafer and placed them on the fat and the right shoulder.<verse eid="LEV 8:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:27"/>He placed all these onto the hands of Aaron and on the hands of his sons, and he offered them up as an advance deduction before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 8:27"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:28"/>Then Moyses took them from their hands, and Moyses offered them up on the altar on the whole burnt offering of validation, which is an odor of fragrance; it is an offering to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 8:28"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:29"/>And after Moyses took the breast, he separated it as an addition before the Lord, from the ram of validation, and it was Moyses' portion as the Lord commanded Moyses.<verse eid="LEV 8:29"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:30"/>And Moyses took some of the anointing oil and some of the blood that was on the altar and sprinkled them onto Aaron and his vestments and onto his sons and the vestments of his sons with him, and he consecrated Aaron and his vestments and his sons and vestments of his sons with him.<verse eid="LEV 8:30"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:31"/>And Moyses said to Aaron and his sons, "Boil the meat in the court of the tent of witness in a holy place, and there eat it and the cakes that are in the basket of validation as I was instructed, saying, 'Aaron and his sons shall eat them.'<verse eid="LEV 8:31"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:32"/>And what remains of the flesh and the cakes shall be burned up by fire.<verse eid="LEV 8:32"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:33"/>And you shall not go outside the door of the tent of witness seven days until the day of your validation is completed. For for seven days he will validate your hands.<verse eid="LEV 8:33"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:34"/>As he did on this day, the Lord commanded to be done in order that atonement be made for you.<verse eid="LEV 8:34"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:35"/>And you shall sit at the door of the tent of witness for seven days, day and night. And you shall keep the Lord's charges so that you do not die, for so the Lord God commanded me."<verse eid="LEV 8:35"/>

<verse sid="LEV 8:36"/>And Aaron and his sons did all the things that the Lord instructed Moyses.<verse eid="LEV 8:36"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 9">
<verse sid="LEV 9:1"/>And it happened on the eighth day that Moyses called Aaron and his sons and the council of elders of Israel.<verse eid="LEV 9:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:2"/>And Moyses said to Aaron, "Take for yourself a calf from the cows for sin and a ram for a whole burnt offering, without blemish, and offer them before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 9:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:3"/>And speak to the council of elders of Israel, saying, 'Take one billy goat from the goats for sin, a calf and a yearling lamb without blemish for a whole offering<verse eid="LEV 9:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:4"/>and a calf and a ram for a sacrifice of deliverance before the Lord and fine flour mixed with oil. For today the Lord will be seen among you.'"<verse eid="LEV 9:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:5"/>And they took them, as Moyses commanded, to the front of the tent of witness, and the whole congregation drew near, and they stood before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 9:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:6"/>And Moyses said, "This is the thing that the Lord said, 'Do, and the glory of the Lord will be seen among you.'"<verse eid="LEV 9:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:7"/>And Moyses said to Aaron, "Draw near to the altar, and perform the one for your sin and your whole burnt offering, and make atonement for yourself and your house. And deal with the gifts of the people, and make atonement for them, as the Lord has commanded Moyses."<verse eid="LEV 9:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:8"/>And Aaron drew near to the altar and slaughtered the calf for sin.<verse eid="LEV 9:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:9"/>And the sons of Aaron presented the blood to him, and he dipped his finger in the blood, and he put it on the horns of the altar, and he poured out the blood onto the base of the altar.<verse eid="LEV 9:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:10"/>But the fat and the kidneys and the appendage of the liver of the one for sin he offered on the altar as the Lord commanded Moyses.<verse eid="LEV 9:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:11"/>And the flesh and the hide-- he burned them with fire outside the camp.<verse eid="LEV 9:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:12"/>And he slaughtered the whole burnt offering. And the sons of Aaron brought him the blood, and he poured it out against all sides of the altar.<verse eid="LEV 9:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:13"/>And they brought him the whole burnt offering limb by limb, them and the head, and he placed them on the altar.<verse eid="LEV 9:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:14"/>And he washed the entrails and the legs with water, and he placed them on the whole burnt offering on the altar.<verse eid="LEV 9:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:15"/>And he presented the people's gift. And he took the goat for the sin of the people, and he slaughtered it and purified it like the first time.<verse eid="LEV 9:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:16"/>And he presented the whole burnt offering and performed it as was proper.<verse eid="LEV 9:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:17"/>And he presented the sacrifice, and he filled his hands with some of it and placed it on the altar apart from the morning whole burnt offering.<verse eid="LEV 9:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:18"/>And he slaughtered the bull calf and the ram of the sacrifice of deliverance that was of the people. And the sons of Aaron brought the blood to him-- and he poured it out against all sides of the altar--<verse eid="LEV 9:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:19"/>and the fat of the bull calf and of the ram, the lower back and the fat that covers over the entrails and the two kidneys and the fat on them and the appendage on the liver.<verse eid="LEV 9:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:20"/>And he placed the fat pieces on the breasts, and he offered up the fat pieces on the altar,<verse eid="LEV 9:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:21"/>and the breast and the right shoulder Aaron removed as an advance deduction before the Lord, as the Lord had instructed Moyses.<verse eid="LEV 9:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:22"/>And after Aaron raised his hands towards the people, he blessed them. And he came down after performing the one for sin and the whole burnt offerings and those pertaining to deliverance.<verse eid="LEV 9:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:23"/>Moyses and Aaron entered the tent of witness, and when they came out, they blessed all the people, and the glory of the Lord became visible to all the people.<verse eid="LEV 9:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 9:24"/>And fire came out from the Lord and consumed what was on the altar, both the whole burnt offerings and the fat pieces, and all the people saw it and were amazed and fell face down.<verse eid="LEV 9:24"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 10">
<verse sid="LEV 10:1"/>And when the two sons of Aaron, Nadab and Abioud, each took his fire-pan, they placed fire on it and threw incense on it and offered before the Lord strange fire such as the Lord had not ordered them.<verse eid="LEV 10:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:2"/>And fire came out from the Lord and consumed them, and they died before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 10:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:3"/>And Moyses said to Aaron, "This is what the Lord spoke, saying, 'Among those who are near me I will be shown holy, and in the whole congregation I will be glorified.'" And Aaron was shocked.<verse eid="LEV 10:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:4"/>And Moyses summoned Misael and Elisaphan sons of Oziel, sons of the brother of Aaron's father, and said to them, "Come forward, and carry your brothers away from the holy things, outside the camp."<verse eid="LEV 10:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:5"/>And they came forward and carried them by their tunics outside the camp as Moyses had said.<verse eid="LEV 10:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:6"/>And Moyses said to Aaron and Eleazar and Ithamar, his sons who remained, "You shall not unbind your head, and you shall not tear your vestments so that you do not die, and wrath will come over the whole congregation, but your kindred, the whole house of Israel, shall bewail the burning with which they were set on fire by the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 10:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:7"/>And you shall not go out of the door of the tent of witness so that you do not die, for the anointing oil from the Lord is on you." And they did according to the word of Moyses.<verse eid="LEV 10:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:8"/>And the Lord spoke to Aaron, saying:<verse eid="LEV 10:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:9"/>You shall not drink wine nor sikera<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Aramaic = 'strong drink'</char></note>, neither you nor your sons with you, whenever you enter into the tent of witness or when you approach the altar, and you will not die; it is a perpetual precept throughout your generations<verse eid="LEV 10:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:10"/>to distinguish between the holy and the profane and between the unclean and the clean,<verse eid="LEV 10:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:11"/>and you shall teach the sons of Israel all the precepts that the Lord has spoken to them by the hand of Moyses.<verse eid="LEV 10:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:12"/>And Moyses said to Aaron and<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">+ Wevers Ed. = 'to'</char></note> Eleazar and Ithamar the sons of Aaron who remained: Take the sacrifice that is left from the Lord's offerings, and you shall eat it unleavened beside the altar. They are holy of holies.<verse eid="LEV 10:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:13"/>And you shall eat it in a holy place. For this is a precept for you and a precept for your sons from the offerings to the Lord, for so I am commanded.<verse eid="LEV 10:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:14"/>And the breast of what has been set apart and the shoulder of the advance deduction you shall eat in a holy place, you and your sons and your house with you, for it was given as a precept to you and as a precept to your sons, from the sacrifices of deliverance of the sons of Israel.<verse eid="LEV 10:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:15"/>The shoulder of the advance deduction and the breast of what was set apart you shall offer besides the sacrifices of the fat pieces, to set apart what was set apart before the Lord. And it shall belong to you and to your sons and to your daughters with you as a perpetual precept, as the Lord instructed Moyses.<verse eid="LEV 10:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:16"/>And when Moyses inquired and sought the goat for sin-- this had already been burned up! And Moyses was angry with Eleazar and Ithamar, Aaron's remaining sons, saying,<verse eid="LEV 10:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:17"/>"Why did you not eat the one for sin in a sacred place? For, because they are holy of holies, he gave this to you to eat so that you may remove the guilt of the congregation and make atonement for them before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 10:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:18"/>For nothing of its blood was brought into the sanctuary. You shall eat it in a holy place facing inside, as the Lord instructed me."<verse eid="LEV 10:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:19"/>And Aaron spoke to Moyses, saying, "If today they have brought their items for sin and their whole burnt offerings before the Lord, and these things have befallen me, and if I shall eat the items for sin today, will it not be pleasing to the Lord?"<verse eid="LEV 10:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 10:20"/>And Moyses heard this, and it pleased him.<verse eid="LEV 10:20"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 11">
<verse sid="LEV 11:1"/>And he Lord spoke to Moyses and Aaron, saying:<verse eid="LEV 11:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:2"/>Speak to the sons of Israel, saying: From all the land animals, these are the animals that you shall eat.<verse eid="LEV 11:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:3"/>Any animal that divides the hoof and splits the hooves into two parts and brings up the cud among the animals-- these you shall eat.<verse eid="LEV 11:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:4"/>But among those that bring up the cud and divide the hoof and split the hoof, you shall not eat any of them: the camel, because it brings up the cud but does not split the hoof-- this one is unclean for you.<verse eid="LEV 11:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:5"/>And the hare, because this animal brings up the cud but does not split the hoof-- this one is unclean for you.<verse eid="LEV 11:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:6"/>And the coney, because this animal brings up the cud but does not split the hoof-- this one is unclean for you.<verse eid="LEV 11:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:7"/>And the pig, because this animal divides the hoof and cleaves the claws of the hoof, but this animal does not bring up the cud-- this one is unclean for you.<verse eid="LEV 11:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:8"/>Of their flesh you shall not eat, and their carcasses you shall not touch; these things are unclean for you.<verse eid="LEV 11:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:9"/>And these you shall eat of all that are in the waters. All those that have fins and scales in the waters and in the seas and in the wadis-- these you shall eat.<verse eid="LEV 11:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:10"/>And all those in the waters or in the seas and in the wadis that do not have fins or scales, of all those things that the waters disgorge and of every living being which is in the water are an abomination.<verse eid="LEV 11:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:11"/>And they shall be abominations to you. Of their flesh you shall not eat, and you shall feel loathing for their carcasses.<verse eid="LEV 11:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:12"/>And all things without fins and scales, of those in the water-- this is an abomination to you.<verse eid="LEV 11:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:13"/>And these you shall regard with loathing among the birds. And they shall not be eaten; they are an abomination: the eagle and the bearded vulture and the osprey<verse eid="LEV 11:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:14"/>and the vulture and the kite and those like it<verse eid="LEV 11:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:15"/>and a raven and those like it<verse eid="LEV 11:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:16"/>and ostrich and little owl and sea gull and those like it and a hawk and those similar to it<verse eid="LEV 11:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:17"/>and long-eared owl and diving petrel and ibis<verse eid="LEV 11:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:18"/>and water hen and pelican and swan<verse eid="LEV 11:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:19"/>and heron and water plover and those like it and hoopoe and bat.<verse eid="LEV 11:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:20"/>And all creeping things that can fly, that walk upon on all fours, shall be abominations to you.<verse eid="LEV 11:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:21"/>But among the winged creeping things that walk on all fours, these you shall eat: they that have upper legs above their feet with which to leap on the ground.<verse eid="LEV 11:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:22"/>And of them, these you shall eat: the locust larva and those similar to it and the bald locust and those similar to it and the grasshopper and those similar to it and the snake-fighting grasshopper and those similar to it.<verse eid="LEV 11:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:23"/>All winged creeping things that have four feet are an abomination to you.<verse eid="LEV 11:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:24"/>And by these you shall incur defilement; anyone who touches any of their carcasses shall be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 11:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:25"/>And anyone who carries any of their carcasses shall wash his clothes and shall be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 11:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:26"/>And among all the animals the one that is a divider of the hoof and has a cloven hoof but does not chew the cud-- they shall be unclean to you. Everyone who touches any of their carcasses shall be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 11:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:27"/>And every one that walks on paws among any animals that walk on all fours shall be unclean to you. Anyone who touches any of their carcasses shall be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 11:27"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:28"/>And the one who carries any of their carcasses shall wash his clothes and shall be unclean until the evening. These things shall be unclean for you.<verse eid="LEV 11:28"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:29"/>And these are unclean for you among the creeping things that creep on the earth: the weasel and the mouse and the dry-land crocodile,<verse eid="LEV 11:29"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:30"/>field mouse and chameleon and gecko and lizard and blind rat.<verse eid="LEV 11:30"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:31"/>These are unclean to you among all the creeping things that are on the earth. Anyone that touches them when they are dead shall be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 11:31"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:32"/>And anything onto which any of them falls upon, when they are dead, shall be unclean, whether any article of wood or cloth or skin or sacking, any article, when work is done with it; it shall be dipped into water, and it shall be unclean until the evening, and then it shall be clean.<verse eid="LEV 11:32"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:33"/>And any earthen vessel into which some of them fall inside, whatever is in it shall be unclean, and it shall be smashed.<verse eid="LEV 11:33"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:34"/>And any food that could be eaten, which water comes onto, shall be unclean. And any liquid that could be drunk shall be unclean in any such vessel.<verse eid="LEV 11:34"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:35"/>Anything that any of their carcasses falls onto shall be unclean. Bread-ovens and pot-stands shall be demolished. These are unclean, and these shall remain unclean for you,<verse eid="LEV 11:35"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:36"/>with the exception of springs of water and a cistern and a gathering of water-- it shall be clean, but whoever touches carcasses in them shall be unclean.<verse eid="LEV 11:36"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:37"/>But if any of their carcasses fall on any sowing seed that could be sown, it shall be clean.<verse eid="LEV 11:37"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:38"/>But if water is poured onto any seed and any of their carcasses fall onto it, it shall be unclean for you.<verse eid="LEV 11:38"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:39"/>Now if an animal dies, that which it is permitted for you to eat-- anyone who touches their carcasses shall be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 11:39"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:40"/>And he who eats of any of these carcasses shall wash his clothing and shall be unclean until the evening. And he who carries any of their carcasses shall wash his clothing and shall be bathed in water and shall be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 11:40"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:41"/>And every creeping thing that creeps on the earth: this shall be an abomination to you; it shall not be eaten.<verse eid="LEV 11:41"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:42"/>And whatever moves on its belly and whatever moves on four legs at all times, whatever has many feet among all the creeping things that creep upon the earth, you shall not eat it, for it is an abomination to you.<verse eid="LEV 11:42"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:43"/>And you shall not make your souls detestable with any that creep, those that creep on the earth, and you shall not defile yourselves with them, and you shall not become unclean by them.<verse eid="LEV 11:43"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:44"/>For it is I who am the Lord your God, and you shall be sanctified, and you shall be holy, for I am holy, I the Lord your God. And you shall not defile your souls with any of the creeping things that stir on the earth.<verse eid="LEV 11:44"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:45"/>For it is I who am the Lord who brought you up from the land of Egypt to be your God; you shall be holy, for I am holy, I, the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 11:45"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:46"/>This is the law pertaining to land animals and birds and every being that moves through the water and every being that crawls upon the earth,<verse eid="LEV 11:46"/>

<verse sid="LEV 11:47"/>to make a distinction between the unclean and between the clean and between breeding things that may be eaten and between breeding things that may not be eaten.<verse eid="LEV 11:47"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 12">
<verse sid="LEV 12:1"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 12:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 12:2"/>Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: Any woman, if she is fertilized and bears a male child, shall also be unclean seven days; as at the days of the separation of her period, she shall be unclean.<verse eid="LEV 12:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 12:3"/>And on the eighth day she shall circumcise the flesh of his foreskin.<verse eid="LEV 12:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 12:4"/>And thirty-three days shall she remain in her unclean blood; she shall not touch anything holy or come into the holy place until the days of her purification are completed.<verse eid="LEV 12:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 12:5"/>But if she bears a female child, she shall be unclean twice seven days, as in her sitting apart, and sixty-six days shall she remain in her unclean blood.<verse eid="LEV 12:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 12:6"/>And when the days of her purification are completed, for a son or for a daughter, she shall bring to the priest at the door of the tent of witness a lamb in its first year without blemish, for a whole burnt offering, and a young of the doves or a turtledove for sin.<verse eid="LEV 12:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 12:7"/>And he shall offer it before the Lord, and the priest shall make atonement for her, and he shall purify her from the source of her blood. This is the law for her who bears a male or female child.<verse eid="LEV 12:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 12:8"/>But if her hand does not find what is enough for a lamb, then she shall take two turtledoves or two young of doves, one for a whole burnt offering and one for sin, and the priest shall make atonement for her, and she shall be clean.<verse eid="LEV 12:8"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 13">
<verse sid="LEV 13:1"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses and Aaron, saying:<verse eid="LEV 13:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:2"/>When any person has on the skin of his body a conspicuous lesion indicating disease, and if there is an attack of leprous disease on the skin of his body, then he shall be brought to Aaron the priest or to one of his sons the priests.<verse eid="LEV 13:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:3"/>And the priest shall look at the attack on the skin of his body, and if the hair in the attacked area has turned white and the appearance of the attack is low in the skin of the body, it is an attack of a leprous disease, and the priest shall look and declare him defiled.<verse eid="LEV 13:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:4"/>But if the conspicuous spot is white in the skin of his body and its appearance is not low in the skin and its hair has not changed to white hair but it is hardly visible, the priest shall isolate the attack for seven days.<verse eid="LEV 13:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:5"/>And the priest shall look at the attack on the seventh day, and look, the attack remains before him, the attack has not undergone change in the skin, then the priest shall isolate him seven days for the second time.<verse eid="LEV 13:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:6"/>And the priest shall look at him a second time on the seventh day, and look, the attack is not apparent, the attack has not changed in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him clean, for it is a mark, and after he has washed his clothes he shall be clean.<verse eid="LEV 13:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:7"/>But if the mark in the skin by altering changes after the priest has looked at him for his cleansing, then he shall appear a second time before the priest.<verse eid="LEV 13:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:8"/>And the priest shall look at him, and look, the mark has changed on his skin, then the priest shall declare him defiled; it is a leprous disease.<verse eid="LEV 13:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:9"/>And as for an attack of a leprous disease-- if it happens to a person, then he shall come to the priest.<verse eid="LEV 13:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:10"/>And the priest shall see, and look, there is a white lesion in the skin, and it has turned the hair white, and some of the healthy part of the living flesh is in the lesion;<verse eid="LEV 13:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:11"/>it is a leprous disease of long standing; it is in the skin of the body. And the priest shall pronounce him defiled and isolate him, for he is unclean.<verse eid="LEV 13:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:12"/>But if in breaking out, the leprous disease breaks out in the skin, and the leprous disease covers all the skin of the attacked area, from head to foot, so far as the priest can see,<verse eid="LEV 13:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:13"/>then the priest shall see, and look, the leprous disease has covered all the skin of the body. And the priest shall declare him clean of the attack; since it has all turned white, he is clean.<verse eid="LEV 13:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:14"/>And on the day when living tissue appears in it, he shall be declared defiled,<verse eid="LEV 13:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:15"/>and the priest shall look at the healthy tissue, and the healthy tissue will render him defiled because it is unclean. It is a leprous disease.<verse eid="LEV 13:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:16"/>But if the healthy tissue restores itself and changes to white, then he shall come to the priest,<verse eid="LEV 13:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:17"/>and the priest shall see, and look, the attack has changed to white, and the priest shall pronounce the attacked area clean. It is clean.<verse eid="LEV 13:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:18"/>And if the flesh in its skin becomes a festering sore and if it heals<verse eid="LEV 13:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:19"/>and in the place of the festering sore there is a white lesion or a shiny one that turns white or reddens, then he shall appear before the priest.<verse eid="LEV 13:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:20"/>And the priest shall see, and look, its appearance is deeper than the skin, and its hair has turned white, and the priest shall pronounce him unclean; it is a leprous disease; it broke out in the festering sore.<verse eid="LEV 13:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:21"/>But if the priest sees, and look, the hair on it is not white, and it is not low in the skin of the flesh but is hardly visible, then the priest shall isolate him seven days.<verse eid="LEV 13:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:22"/>And if in spreading out it spreads in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean; it is an attack of leprous disease. It has broken out in the festering sore.<verse eid="LEV 13:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:23"/>But if the bright spot remains in one place and does not spread, it is the scar of the festering sore, and the priest shall pronounce him clean.<verse eid="LEV 13:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:24"/>And if the flesh on his skin has a burn by fire and the healthy part of the burn on his skin becomes bright, shiny reddish-white or white,<verse eid="LEV 13:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:25"/>then the priest shall see, and look, the hair in the bright spot has turned white, and its appearance is low in the skin, it is a leprous disease; it has broken out in the burn, and the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is an attack of leprous disease.<verse eid="LEV 13:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:26"/>But if the priest sees, and look, the hair in the bright spot is not white, and it is not low in the skin but is inconspicuous, then the priest shall isolate him seven days.<verse eid="LEV 13:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:27"/>And the priest shall examine him on the seventh day, and if in spreading out it spreads in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is an attack of leprous disease. It has broken out in the festering sore.<verse eid="LEV 13:27"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:28"/>But if the bright spot remains in one place and does not spread in the skin but is inconspicuous, it is a lesion from the burn, and the priest shall pronounce him clean, for it is the style of the burn.<verse eid="LEV 13:28"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:29"/>And as for man or woman-- if there is on them an attack of leprous disease on the head or in the beard,<verse eid="LEV 13:29"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:30"/>then the priest shall examine the attack. And look, its appearance is more hollow than the skin and the hair in turning yellow is thin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean; it is a rupture, a leprous disease of the head or a leprous disease of the beard.<verse eid="LEV 13:30"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:31"/>And if the priest examines the attack of the rupture, and look, its appearance is no more hollow than the skin and there is no yellow hair in it, then the priest shall isolate the attack of the rupture for seven days.<verse eid="LEV 13:31"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:32"/>And on the seventh day the priest shall examine the attack, and look, the rupture has not spread and there is no yellow hair in it and the appearance of the rupture is not hollow in the skin,<verse eid="LEV 13:32"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:33"/>then the skin shall be shaven, but the rupture shall not be shaven. And the priest shall isolate the rupture for a second seven days.<verse eid="LEV 13:33"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:34"/>And on the seventh day the priest shall examine the rupture, and look, the rupture has not spread in the skin after he has been shaven and the appearance of the rupture is not hollow in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him clean. And he shall wash his clothes and be clean.<verse eid="LEV 13:34"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:35"/>But if in spreading, the rupture spreads in the skin after he was pronounced clean,<verse eid="LEV 13:35"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:36"/>then the priest shall look. And look, the rupture has spread in the skin; the priest shall not inspect for yellow hair because he is unclean.<verse eid="LEV 13:36"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:37"/>But if the rupture remains in place, visibly, and black hair has grown in it, the rupture has healed; he is clean, and the priest shall pronounce him clean.<verse eid="LEV 13:37"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:38"/>And as for man or woman-- if there are bright spots on the skin of their flesh, appearing white,<verse eid="LEV 13:38"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:39"/>then the priest shall make an examination, and look, the bright spots on the skin of his flesh appear white, it is a scaly condition; he is clean. It broke out in the skin of his flesh; he is clean.<verse eid="LEV 13:39"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:40"/>Now if anyone's head becomes bald, he is bald-headed; he is clean.<verse eid="LEV 13:40"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:41"/>But if his head becomes bald from the front, he has baldness of the forehead; he is clean.<verse eid="LEV 13:41"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:42"/>But if there is on his baldness or on the baldness of his forehead a white attack that reddens, it is a leprous disease breaking out on his bald head or his bald forehead.<verse eid="LEV 13:42"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:43"/>And the priest shall examine him, and look, the appearance of the attack is white, becoming red on his baldness or on the baldness of his forehead, like the appearance of a leprous disease in the skin of his flesh,<verse eid="LEV 13:43"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:44"/>he is a leprous person. With defilement the priest shall pronounce him defiled; his attack is on his head.<verse eid="LEV 13:44"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:45"/>And the leprous person on whom is the attack-- let his clothes be loosened and his head be uncovered, and let him put on something around his mouth, and he will have been called unclean.<verse eid="LEV 13:45"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:46"/>He is unclean and shall remain unclean all the days the attack is on him. He shall reside apart; he shall spend his life outside the camp.<verse eid="LEV 13:46"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:47"/>As for clothing: if an attack of leprous disease appears in it, in woolen cloth or cloth made of tow,<verse eid="LEV 13:47"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:48"/>whether in the warp or in the woof, or in linen clothes or in woolen clothes or in a skin or in any article made of skin,<verse eid="LEV 13:48"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:49"/>and the attack becomes greenish or reddish in the skin or in the garment, whether in warp or woof, or in any article made of skin, it is an attack of leprous disease, and one shall show it to the priest.<verse eid="LEV 13:49"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:50"/>And the priest shall examine the attack, and the priest shall isolate the attack for seven days.<verse eid="LEV 13:50"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:51"/>And the priest shall examine the attack on the seventh day. And if the attack has spread in the cloth, whether in the warp or in the woof, or in the skin, in the case of anything whereby skin is made into a product, the attack is a lasting leprous disease; it is unclean.<verse eid="LEV 13:51"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:52"/>He shall burn the clothing, whether the warp or the woof, in woolen things or in linen things, or any article of skin which the attack is in, for it is a lasting leprous disease; it shall be burned with fire.<verse eid="LEV 13:52"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:53"/>Now if the priest looks, and the attack has not spread in the clothing, whether in the warp or in the woof or in any article of skin,<verse eid="LEV 13:53"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:54"/>then the priest shall give orders, and he shall wash the article which the disease appears in, and the priest shall isolate the attack for a second seven days.<verse eid="LEV 13:54"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:55"/>And the priest shall examine the attack after it has been washed, and this attack has not changed its appearance, and the attack is not spreading: it is something unclean; it shall be burnt with fire, it has been firmly set in the garment, whether in the warp or in the woof.<verse eid="LEV 13:55"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:56"/>And if the priest looks and the attack has become inconspicuous after it is washed, he shall tear it out of the cloth, whether out of the warp<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:56</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'out of the warp': Wevers Ed. = transposed</char></note> or out of the woof or out of the skin<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:56</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'out of the skin': Wevers Ed. = transposed</char></note>.<verse eid="LEV 13:56"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:57"/>But if it still appears in the garment, whether in the warp or in the woof or in any article of skin, it is leprous disease that has broken out; that in which the attack occurs shall be burned with fire.<verse eid="LEV 13:57"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:58"/>But the cloth, whether warp or woof, or any article of skin that shall be washed and the attack shall leave it, shall then be washed a second time, and it shall be clean.<verse eid="LEV 13:58"/>

<verse sid="LEV 13:59"/>This is the law for an attack of leprous disease in a cloth of wool or tow, either in warp or woof, or in any article of skin, to declare it clean or defiled.<verse eid="LEV 13:59"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 14">
<verse sid="LEV 14:1"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 14:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:2"/>This is the law for the leprous person on the day that he is to be cleansed: And he shall be brought to the priest,<verse eid="LEV 14:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:3"/>and the priest shall go out, outside of the camp, and the priest shall see, and look, the attack of leprous disease is healed from the leprous person,<verse eid="LEV 14:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:4"/>and the priest shall give orders, and they shall take for the one who has been cleansed two living clean fowl and cedar wood and scarlet spun thread and hyssop.<verse eid="LEV 14:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:5"/>And the priest shall give orders, and they shall slaughter the one fowl over living water in an earthen vessel.<verse eid="LEV 14:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:6"/>And as for the living fowl: he shall take it and the cedar wood and the scarlet spun thread and the hyssop and dip them and the living fowl in the blood of the fowl that was slaughtered over living water.<verse eid="LEV 14:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:7"/>And he shall sprinkle it about, seven times upon the one who was cleansed of the leprous disease, and he shall be clean, and he shall send forth the living bird into the plain.<verse eid="LEV 14:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:8"/>And the one who was cleansed shall wash his clothes and have all his hair shaven and bathe in water, and he shall be clean. And after that he shall come into the camp and shall spend time outside his dwelling seven days.<verse eid="LEV 14:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:9"/>And it shall be on the seventh day that he shall have all his hair shaven: his head and his beard and his eyebrows, and he shall have all his hair shaven. And he shall wash his clothes and bathe his body in water, and he shall be clean.<verse eid="LEV 14:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:10"/>And on the eighth day he shall take two lambs of a year old without blemish and one sheep in its first year without blemish and three-tenths of choice flour as an offering mixed with oil and one cup of oil.<verse eid="LEV 14:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:11"/>And the priest who cleanses shall set the person who is being cleansed, along with these things, before the Lord, at the door of the tent of witness.<verse eid="LEV 14:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:12"/>And the priest shall take the one lamb and offer it for error, along with the cup of oil, and set it apart as something set apart before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 14:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:13"/>And they shall slaughter the lamb in the place where they slaughter the whole burnt offerings and the ones for sin, in a holy place, for the one for sin, like the one for error, belongs to the priest; they are holy of holies.<verse eid="LEV 14:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:14"/>And the priest shall take some of the blood of the one for error, and the priest shall put it onto the lobe of the right ear of the one who is being cleansed and on the tip of his right hand and on the tip of his right foot.<verse eid="LEV 14:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:15"/>And the priest, after taking some of the cup of oil, shall pour it into the left hand of the priest<verse eid="LEV 14:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:16"/>and wet his right finger with the oil that is in his left hand and sprinkle seven times with his finger before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 14:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:17"/>But the remaining oil that is in his hand the priest shall put on the lobe of the right ear of the one being cleansed and on the tip of his right hand and on the tip of his right foot, on the place of the blood of the one for error.<verse eid="LEV 14:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:18"/>Now the oil that is left in the priest's hand the priest shall put on the head of the one who was cleansed. And the priest shall make atonement for him before the Lord;<verse eid="LEV 14:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:19"/>the priest shall perform the one for sin, and the priest shall make atonement for the one being cleansed from his sin. And afterward the priest shall slaughter the whole burnt offering,<verse eid="LEV 14:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:20"/>and the priest shall offer the whole burnt offering and the sacrifice on the altar before the Lord. And the priest shall make atonement for him, and he shall be clean.<verse eid="LEV 14:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:21"/>But if he is poor and his hand does not find, he shall take one lamb for what he has done in error as an advance deduction, to make atonement for him, and one-tenth of fine flour mixed with oil for a sacrifice and one cup of oil,<verse eid="LEV 14:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:22"/>also two turtledoves or two young doves, such as his hand finds, and one shall be for sin and one for a whole burnt offering.<verse eid="LEV 14:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:23"/>And on the eighth day he shall bring them to render him clean, to the priest, to the door of the tent of witness, before the Lord,<verse eid="LEV 14:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:24"/>and the priest shall take the lamb for error and the cup of oil and shall place them as an addition before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 14:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:25"/>And he shall slaughter the lamb for error and the priest shall take some of the blood of the one for error and put it on the lobe of the right ear of the one being cleansed and on the tip of his right hand and on the tip of his right foot.<verse eid="LEV 14:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:26"/>And the priest shall pour out some of the oil into the left hand of the priest,<verse eid="LEV 14:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:27"/>and the priest shall sprinkle with the right finger some of the oil that is in his left hand seven times before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 14:27"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:28"/>And the priest shall put some of the oil that is in his hand onto the lobe of the right ear of the one being cleansed and on the tip of his right hand and the tip of his right foot, on the place of the blood of the one for error.<verse eid="LEV 14:28"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:29"/>Now the oil that is remaining in the priest's hand he shall put onto the head of the one who was cleansed, and the priest shall make atonement for him before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 14:29"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:30"/>And he shall do one of the turtledoves or of the young doves, as his hand found,<verse eid="LEV 14:30"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:31"/>one for sin and one for a whole burnt offering, along with the sacrifice, and the priest shall make atonement before the Lord for the one being cleansed.<verse eid="LEV 14:31"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:32"/>This is the law in which is the attack of leprous disease and of the one who cannot find with his hand for his cleansing.<verse eid="LEV 14:32"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:33"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses and Aaron, saying:<verse eid="LEV 14:33"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:34"/>When you come into the land of the Chananites, which I give you in possession, and I shall give a leprous disease in the houses in the land acquired by you,<verse eid="LEV 14:34"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:35"/>then he whose house it is shall come and report to the priest, saying, "Something like an attack has been seen in my house"<verse eid="LEV 14:35"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:36"/>And the priest shall give orders to strip the house before the priest goes in to look at the attack, and whatever is in the house will not become unclean, and afterward the priest shall go in to examine the house.<verse eid="LEV 14:36"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:37"/>And he shall look at the attack in the walls of the house, hollow, greenish or reddish, and their appearance is lower than the walls,<verse eid="LEV 14:37"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:38"/>and the priest, after going out of the house at the door of the house, the priest shall then isolate the house seven days.<verse eid="LEV 14:38"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:39"/>And the priest shall return on the seventh day and look at the house, and look, the attack has spread in the walls of the house.<verse eid="LEV 14:39"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:40"/>And the priest shall give orders, and they shall take out the stones in which is the attack and throw them into an unclean place outside the city.<verse eid="LEV 14:40"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:41"/>And they shall scrape off the inside of the house round about and pour out the soil in an unclean place outside the city.<verse eid="LEV 14:41"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:42"/>And they shall take other scraped stones and place them in return, instead of the stones, and take other soil and re-plaster the house.<verse eid="LEV 14:42"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:43"/>But if the attack returns again and arises in the house, after he has taken out the stones and after the house has been scraped out and after it has been plastered over,<verse eid="LEV 14:43"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:44"/>then the priest shall go in and look; if the attack has spread in the house, it is a lasting leprous disease in the house; it is unclean.<verse eid="LEV 14:44"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:45"/>And they shall demolish the house, both its timber and its stones, and all the soil they shall take outside the city to an unclean place.<verse eid="LEV 14:45"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:46"/>And he who enters the house all the days that it is isolated shall be unclean until the evening,<verse eid="LEV 14:46"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:47"/>and he who sleeps in the house shall wash his garments and shall be unclean until the evening, and he who eats in the house shall wash his garments and be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 14:47"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:48"/>But if the priest after coming near, enters and sees, and look, the attack, by spreading, has not spread in the house after the house was plastered over, then the priest shall declare the house clean, because the attack is healed.<verse eid="LEV 14:48"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:49"/>And to purify the house he shall take two living, clean fowl and cedar wood and scarlet spun yarn and hyssop<verse eid="LEV 14:49"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:50"/>and shall slaughter the one fowl over living water in an earthen vessel<verse eid="LEV 14:50"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:51"/>and shall take the cedar wood and the scarlet spun yarn and the hyssop and the living fowl and dip them in the blood of the slaughtered fowl over living water and sprinkle with them on the house seven times.<verse eid="LEV 14:51"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:52"/>And he shall purify the house with the blood of the fowl and with the living water and with the living fowl and with the cedar wood and with the hyssop and with the scarlet spun yarn,<verse eid="LEV 14:52"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:53"/>and he shall send forth the living fowl away from the city into the plain, and he shall make atonement for the house, and it shall be clean.<verse eid="LEV 14:53"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:54"/>This is the law concerning every attack of a leprous disease and of a rupture<verse eid="LEV 14:54"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:55"/>and of leprous disease of clothing and of a house<verse eid="LEV 14:55"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:56"/>and of a scar and of a mark and of a bright spot<verse eid="LEV 14:56"/>

<verse sid="LEV 14:57"/>and to determine on which day something is unclean and on which day it will be declared clean. This is the law for leprous disease.<verse eid="LEV 14:57"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 15">
<verse sid="LEV 15:1"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses and Aaron, saying:<verse eid="LEV 15:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:2"/>Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: Man by man, whoever has a flow out of his body, his flow is unclean.<verse eid="LEV 15:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:3"/>And this is the law of his uncleanness: when he flows seed out of his body from the flow or if his body has become compacted through the flow, this is his uncleanness because of it. All the days of the flow of his body or if his body has become compacted through the flow, this is his uncleanness.<verse eid="LEV 15:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:4"/>Every bed that the one suffering from spermatorrhoea lies on shall be unclean, and every thing that the one suffering from spermatorrhoea sits on shall be unclean.<verse eid="LEV 15:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:5"/>And a person who touches his bed shall wash his clothes and bathe in water and be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:6"/>And he who sits on the object that the one suffering from spermatorrhoea has sat on shall wash his clothes and bathe in water and be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:7"/>And he who touches the flesh of the one suffering from spermatorrhoea shall wash his clothes and bathe in water and be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:8"/>But if the one suffering from spermatorrhoea spits on one who is clean, he shall wash his clothes and bathe in water and be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:9"/>And any packsaddle of a donkey that the one suffering from spermatorrhoea mounts on shall be unclean until evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:10"/>And everyone who touches anything that was under him shall be unclean until the evening, and he who carries these things shall wash his clothes and bathe in water and be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:11"/>And as many as the one suffering from spermatorrhoea touches without his having rinsed his hands shall wash his clothes and bathe his body in water and be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:12"/>And as for an earthen vessel that the one suffering from spermatorrhoea touches-- it shall be shattered, and a vessel of wood shall be rinsed in water and shall be clean.<verse eid="LEV 15:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:13"/>But if the one suffering from spermatorrhoea is cleansed of his flow, then there shall be counted off for him seven days for his cleansing, and he shall wash his clothes and bathe his body in water, and he shall be clean.<verse eid="LEV 15:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:14"/>And on the eighth day he shall take for himself two turtledoves or two young doves and shall bring them before the Lord to the entrance of the tent of witness and give them to the priest.<verse eid="LEV 15:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:15"/>And the priest shall prepare them, one for sin and one for a whole burnt offering, and the priest shall make atonement for him before the Lord for his flow.<verse eid="LEV 15:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:16"/>And as for a person whose bed of semen issues forth from him, he shall then bathe his whole body in water and shall be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:17"/>And all clothing and all skin which a bed of semen comes upon shall then be washed with water and be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:18"/>In the case of a woman, if a man lies with her in a bed of semen, then they shall bathe in water and be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:19"/>And a woman who is flowing with blood, her flow shall be in her body; she shall be in her period for seven days. Any one who touches her shall be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:20"/>And everything which she sleeps on during her period shall be unclean; everything also which she sits down on shall be unclean.<verse eid="LEV 15:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:21"/>And anyone who touches her bed shall wash his clothes and bathe his body in water and be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:22"/>And anyone who touches any object that she sits on shall wash his clothes and bathe in water and be unclean until the evening,<verse eid="LEV 15:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:23"/>but if while she is in her bed or on the object where she sits on-- when he touches her he shall be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:24"/>But if anyone sleeps with her in bed and her impurity be on him, then he shall be unclean seven days, and every bed that he lies on shall be unclean.<verse eid="LEV 15:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:25"/>And a woman, if she flows with a flow of blood for rather many days, not at the time of her period, even if she flows after her period, all the days of the flow of her impurity are like the days of her period; she shall be unclean.<verse eid="LEV 15:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:26"/>And every bed that she lies on during all the days of the flow shall be for her as in the case of the bed of her period, and every object which she sits on shall be unclean, as in the uncleanness of her period.<verse eid="LEV 15:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:27"/>Anyone who touches her shall be unclean and shall wash his clothes and bathe his body in water and be unclean until the evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:27"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:28"/>But if she is cleansed of the flow, there shall then be counted off for her seven days, and after that she shall be cleansed.<verse eid="LEV 15:28"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:29"/>And on the eighth day she shall take for herself two turtledoves or two young doves and bring them to the priest to the door of the tent of witness.<verse eid="LEV 15:29"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:30"/>And the priest shall perform one for sin and one for a whole burnt offering, and the priest shall make atonement for her before the Lord because of the flow of her uncleanness.<verse eid="LEV 15:30"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:31"/>And you shall make the sons of Israel cautious about their uncleanness, and they shall not die on account of their uncleanness when they defile my tent that is among them.<verse eid="LEV 15:31"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:32"/>This is the law of the one suffering from spermatorrhoea, and if for someone a bed of semen issues forth from him so that he becomes unclean thereby,<verse eid="LEV 15:32"/>

<verse sid="LEV 15:33"/>and for her who flows with blood in her period: the one suffering from spermatorrhoea in his flow, whether for a male or for a female-- and for the man who lies with one who sits apart.<verse eid="LEV 15:33"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 16">
<verse sid="LEV 16:1"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses after the two sons of Aaron died, when they brought near strange fire before the Lord, and they died.<verse eid="LEV 16:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:2"/>And the Lord said to Moyses: Speak to Aaron your brother, and let him not enter at any time into the sanctuary inside the veil facing the propitiatory that is on the ark of witness, and he will not die, for I will be seen in the cloud upon the propitiatory.<verse eid="LEV 16:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:3"/>Thus shall Aaron come into the holy place: with a calf from the cattle for sin and a ram for a whole burnt offering.<verse eid="LEV 16:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:4"/>And he shall put on the consecrated linen tunic, and linen pants shall be on his flesh, and he shall gird himself with a linen girdle and wrap around a linen turban; they are holy vestments. And he shall bathe his entire body in water and then put them on.<verse eid="LEV 16:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:5"/>And he shall take from the congregation of the sons of Israel two billy goats for sin and one ram for a whole burnt offering.<verse eid="LEV 16:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:6"/>And Aaron shall offer the bull calf for sin, which is his own, and shall make atonement for himself<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">16:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Wevers Ed. = 'him'</char></note> and for his house.<verse eid="LEV 16:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:7"/>And he shall take the two goats and set them before the Lord at the door of the tent of witness,<verse eid="LEV 16:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:8"/>and Aaron shall place lots on the two goats, one lot for the Lord and one lot for the one to be sent off.<verse eid="LEV 16:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:9"/>And Aaron shall present the goat which the lot fell on for the Lord and offer for sin,<verse eid="LEV 16:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:10"/>and the goat which the lot fell on of the one to be sent off he shall set it alive before the Lord to make atonement over it, to send it away into the place for sending away-- he shall let it go into the wilderness.<verse eid="LEV 16:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:11"/>And Aaron shall offer the bull calf for sin, which is his, and shall make atonement for himself<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">16:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Wevers Ed. = 'him'</char></note> and for his house, and he shall slaughter the bull calf for sin, which is his own.<verse eid="LEV 16:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:12"/>And he shall take the fire-pan full of coals of fire from the altar that is before the Lord and shall fill his hands with a fine incense-compound, and he shall bring it inside the veil<verse eid="LEV 16:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:13"/>and put the incense on the fire before the Lord, and the vapor of the incense shall cover the propitiatory that is upon the witnesses, and he will not die.<verse eid="LEV 16:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:14"/>And he shall take some of the blood of the bull calf and sprinkle with his finger onto the propitiatory towards the east. In front of the propitiatory he shall sprinkle some of the blood with his finger seven times.<verse eid="LEV 16:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:15"/>And he shall slaughter the goat for sin that is for the people before the Lord and bring in its blood inside the veil and do with its blood as he did with the blood of the bull calf, and he shall sprinkle its blood on the propitiatory in front of the propitiatory.<verse eid="LEV 16:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:16"/>And he shall make the holy place ritually acceptable because of the unclean things of the sons of Israel and because of their wrongs-- concerning all their sins, and so he shall do for the tent of witness, which has been established among them in the midst of their uncleanness.<verse eid="LEV 16:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:17"/>And no person shall be in the tent of witness, when he enters to make atonement in the holy place, until he comes out. And he shall make atonement for himself<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">16:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Wevers Ed. = 'him'</char></note> and for his house and for all the congregation of the sons of Israel.<verse eid="LEV 16:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:18"/>And he shall go out to the altar which is before the Lord and make atonement on it and shall take some of the blood of the bull calf and some of the blood of the goat and put it on the horns of the altar, round about.<verse eid="LEV 16:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:19"/>And he shall sprinkle some of the blood on it with his finger seven times and pronounce it clean and hallow it from the uncleanness of the sons of Israel.<verse eid="LEV 16:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:20"/>And he shall finish making the holy place and the tent of witness and the altar ritually acceptable, and he shall pronounce clean the things that pertain to the priests. And he shall bring near the live goat.<verse eid="LEV 16:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:21"/>And Aaron shall lay his hands on the head of the live goat and confess over it all the lawless acts of the sons of Israel and all their offences and all their sins and shall put them on the head of the live goat and shall send it away into the desert by the hand of a ready person.<verse eid="LEV 16:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:22"/>And the goat shall bear on itself their offences to an untrodden region, and he shall send off the goat into the wilderness.<verse eid="LEV 16:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:23"/>And Aaron shall enter the tent of witness and shall take off the linen garment that he put on when he went into the holy place and shall deposit it there.<verse eid="LEV 16:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:24"/>And he shall bathe his body in water in a holy place and put on his garment; then he shall come out and perform his sacrifice and the sacrifice of the people and shall make atonement for himself<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">16:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Wevers Ed. = 'him'</char></note> and his house and for the people as for the priests.<verse eid="LEV 16:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:25"/>And the fat for sins he shall offer up on the altar.<verse eid="LEV 16:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:26"/>And the one who sends off the goat set apart for release shall wash his clothes and bathe his body in water and afterward shall come into the camp.<verse eid="LEV 16:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:27"/>And the bull calf for sin and the goat for sin, of whom their<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">16:27</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Wevers Ed. = Omit</char></note> blood was brought in to make atonement in the holy place-- they shall take them outside the camp and burn them up with fire, and their skins and their flesh and their dung.<verse eid="LEV 16:27"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:28"/>Now the one who burns them shall wash his clothes and bathe his body in water and afterward shall come into the camp.<verse eid="LEV 16:28"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:29"/>And this shall be a perpetual precept to you: In the seventh month, on the tenth of the month, you shall humble your souls and shall do no work, neither the native nor the guest among you who adheres.<verse eid="LEV 16:29"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:30"/>For on this day he shall make atonement for you, to cleanse you from all your sins before the Lord, and you shall be clean.<verse eid="LEV 16:30"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:31"/>This rest shall be Sabbata of sabbaths to you, and you shall humble your souls; it is a perpetual precept.<verse eid="LEV 16:31"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:32"/>The priest, he whom they anoint and he whose hands they shall validate to serve as priest in his father's place, shall make atonement and shall put on the linen garment, the holy vestment.<verse eid="LEV 16:32"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:33"/>And he shall make the holy of the holy ritually acceptable, and he shall make ritually acceptable the tent of meeting and the altar, and he shall make atonement for the priests and for the entire congregation.<verse eid="LEV 16:33"/>

<verse sid="LEV 16:34"/>And this shall be a perpetual precept for you, to make atonement for the sons of Israel for all their sins. It shall be done once a year as the Lord instructed Moyses.<verse eid="LEV 16:34"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 17">
<verse sid="LEV 17:1"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 17:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 17:2"/>Speak to Aaron and his sons and to all the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: This is the word that the Lord has commanded, saying:<verse eid="LEV 17:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 17:3"/>Person by person of the sons of Israel, whoever slaughters a calf or a sheep or a goat in the camp, or who slaughters it outside the camp<verse eid="LEV 17:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 17:4"/>and does not bring it to the door of the tent of witness, to perform it as a whole burnt offering or as a deliverance to the Lord, acceptable for an odor of fragrance, and who slaughters outside and does not bring it to the door of the tent of witness in order to bring a gift to the Lord before the tent of the Lord, then bloodshed shall be reckoned to that person. He has shed blood; that soul shall be exterminated from its people<verse eid="LEV 17:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 17:5"/>in order that the sons of Israel may bring their sacrifices, whatever they shall slaughter in the plains, and they shall bring them to the Lord, to the priest at the entrance of the tent of witness, and they shall offer them as a sacrifice of deliverance to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 17:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 17:6"/>And the priest shall dash the blood against all sides of the altar, before the Lord at the entrance of the tent of witness and offer up the fat as an odor of fragrance to the Lord,<verse eid="LEV 17:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 17:7"/>and they shall no longer offer their sacrifices to useless things, to whom they go out to commit fornication after them. It shall be a perpetual precept to you throughout your generations.<verse eid="LEV 17:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 17:8"/>And you shall say to them: Person by person of the sons of Israel and from the sons of the guests among you who adhere, whoever performs a whole burnt offering or sacrifice<verse eid="LEV 17:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 17:9"/>and does not bring it to the door of the tent of witness, to perform it to the Lord, that person shall be exterminated from his people.<verse eid="LEV 17:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 17:10"/>Person by person of the sons of Israel or of the guests among you who adhere, whoever eats any blood-- and I will set my face against the soul who eats blood and will utterly destroy it from its people.<verse eid="LEV 17:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 17:11"/>For the life of all flesh is its blood, and I have given it to you for making atonement for your souls on the altar, for it is its blood that makes atonement for the soul.<verse eid="LEV 17:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 17:12"/>Therefore I have said to the sons of Israel: No soul among you shall eat blood, and no guest among you who adheres shall eat blood.<verse eid="LEV 17:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 17:13"/>And person by person of the sons of Israel and of the guests among you who adhere, whoever hunts as prey a wild animal or bird that may be eaten, shall pour out the blood and cover it with earth.<verse eid="LEV 17:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 17:14"/>For the life of all flesh is its blood, and I have said to the sons of Israel: You shall not eat the blood of any flesh. For the life of all flesh is its blood; anyone who eats it shall be exterminated.<verse eid="LEV 17:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 17:15"/>And any soul, among the natives or among the guests who eats a carcass or what has been torn by wild animals shall wash his clothes and bathe in water and be unclean until the evening; then he shall be clean.<verse eid="LEV 17:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 17:16"/>But if he does not wash his clothes and bathe his body in water, he shall assume his transgression of the law.<verse eid="LEV 17:16"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 18">
<verse sid="LEV 18:1"/>And the Lord said to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 18:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:2"/>Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: I am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 18:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:3"/>You shall not act according to the practices of the land of Egypt, wherein you lived, and you shall not act according to the practices of the land of Chanaan, there where I am bringing you, and you shall not live by their precepts.<verse eid="LEV 18:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:4"/>My judgments you shall perform, and my ordinances you shall keep, to walk by them; I am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 18:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:5"/>And you shall keep all my ordinances and all my judgments, and you shall do them; as for the things a person does, he shall live by them; I am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 18:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:6"/>Person by person shall not approach any of the household of his flesh to uncover shame; I am the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 18:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:7"/>You shall not uncover the shame of your father and the shame of your mother, for she is your mother; you<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">18:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">preceded by Wevers Ed. = 'and'</char></note> shall not uncover her shame.<verse eid="LEV 18:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:8"/>You shall not uncover the shame of your father's wife; it is the shame of your father.<verse eid="LEV 18:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:9"/>You shall not uncover her shame-- the shame of your sister, from your father or from your mother, whether born at home or born abroad.<verse eid="LEV 18:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:10"/>You shall not uncover their shame-- the shame of your son's daughter or of your daughter's daughter, for it is your own shame.<verse eid="LEV 18:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:11"/>You shall not uncover the shame of your father's wife's daughter; she is your sister by the same father. You shall not uncover her shame.<verse eid="LEV 18:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:12"/>You shall not uncover the shame of your father's sister, for she is of your father's own household.<verse eid="LEV 18:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:13"/>You shall not uncover the shame of your mother's sister, for she is of your mother's own household.<verse eid="LEV 18:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:14"/>You shall not uncover the shame of your father's brother, and you shall not approach his wife, for she is your relative.<verse eid="LEV 18:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:15"/>You shall not uncover the shame of your daughter-in-law, for she is your son's wife; you shall not uncover her shame.<verse eid="LEV 18:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:16"/>You shall not uncover the shame of your brother's wife; it is your brother's shame.<verse eid="LEV 18:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:17"/>You shall not uncover the shame of a woman and her daughter. You shall not take her son's daughter and her daughter's daughter to uncover their shame, for they are of your own household; it is a profane act.<verse eid="LEV 18:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:18"/>You shall not take a woman as a rival in addition to her sister, to uncover her shame in addition to her while she is still alive.<verse eid="LEV 18:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:19"/>And you shall not approach a woman to uncover her shame in the separation of her uncleanness.<verse eid="LEV 18:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:20"/>And you shall not give your bed of semen to the wife of your neighbor, to bring defilement onto her.<verse eid="LEV 18:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:21"/>And you shall not give any of your offspring to serve a ruler. And you shall not profane the holy name. I am the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 18:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:22"/>And you shall not sleep with a male as in a bed of a woman, for it is an abomination.<verse eid="LEV 18:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:23"/>And you shall not give your bed to any quadruped for sowing to bring defilement on it, nor shall any woman stand before any quadruped so as to be mounted, for it is loathsome.<verse eid="LEV 18:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:24"/>Do not defile yourselves in any of these ways. For by all these things the nations I am sending out before your face were defiled.<verse eid="LEV 18:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:25"/>And the land became defiled, and I repaid their evil because of it, and the land was angry with its inhabitants.<verse eid="LEV 18:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:26"/>And you shall keep all my precepts and all my ordinances and not commit any of all these abominations, the inhabitant and the guest among you who has come<verse eid="LEV 18:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:27"/>(for the men of the land, who were before you, committed all of these abominations, and the land became defiled);<verse eid="LEV 18:27"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:28"/>otherwise the land will become angry with you when you defile it, as it became angry with the nations that were before you.<verse eid="LEV 18:28"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:29"/>For anyone who commits any of all these abominations-- the souls that do so shall be exterminated from their people.<verse eid="LEV 18:29"/>

<verse sid="LEV 18:30"/>And keep my ordinances: not to commit any of all these abominable precepts that were done before you, and you shall not be defiled by them, for I am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 18:30"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 19">
<verse sid="LEV 19:1"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 19:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:2"/>Speak to the congregation of the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: You shall be holy, for I am holy, the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:3"/>Let each fear his father and his mother, and you shall keep my sabbaths; I am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:4"/>You shall not follow after idols, and you shall not make gods of cast metal for yourselves; I am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:5"/>And if you offer a sacrifice of deliverance to the Lord, offer it acceptable on your behalf.<verse eid="LEV 19:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:6"/>It shall be eaten on the day you offer it and on the next day, and if it is left over until the third day, it shall be burned up by fire.<verse eid="LEV 19:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:7"/>But if in eating it is eaten on the third day, it is not fit to be offered; it will not be accepted.<verse eid="LEV 19:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:8"/>And he who eats it shall assume guilt because he has profaned what is holy to the Lord, and the souls who eat it shall be exterminated from their people.<verse eid="LEV 19:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:9"/>And when you reap the harvest of your land, you shall not make a thorough job of your harvest, to harvest your field altogether, and you shall not gather what falls down of your harvest.<verse eid="LEV 19:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:10"/>And you shall not harvest your vineyard over again or gather the grapes of your vineyard; you shall leave them for the poor and the guest; it is I who am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:11"/>You shall not steal; you shall not deal falsely; each of you shall not falsely accuse his neighbor.<verse eid="LEV 19:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:12"/>And you shall not swear by my name in an unjust matter, and you shall not profane the name of your God; it is I who am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:13"/>You shall not act unjustly towards your neighbor, and you shall not plunder, and the wages of a day laborer shall not rest overnight with you until morning.<verse eid="LEV 19:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:14"/>You shall not speak badly of the deaf and put an obstacle before the blind, and you shall fear the Lord your God; it is I who am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:15"/>You shall not do something unjust in judgment; you shall not accept the person of the poor or admire the person of a high official; with justice you shall judge your neighbor.<verse eid="LEV 19:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:16"/>You shall not go around in deceit among your nation; you shall not conspire against the blood of your neighbor; it is I who am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:17"/>You shall not hate in your mind your kin; in reproof you shall reprove your neighbor, and you shall not assume guilt because of him.<verse eid="LEV 19:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:18"/>And your own hand shall not take vengeance, and you shall not be angry against the sons of your people, and you shall love your neighbor as yourself; it is I who am the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 19:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:19"/>You shall keep my law. You shall not breed your animals to those of a different kind, and you shall not sow your vineyard with something different, and you shall not put on yourself an adulterated garment woven with two materials.<verse eid="LEV 19:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:20"/>And if one lies with a woman in a bed of semen and she is a domestic carefully guarded for a man but she by means of release had not been ransomed neither had freedom been given her, they shall get an inquiry. They shall not die, since she had not been freed,<verse eid="LEV 19:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:21"/>and he shall bring for his error to the Lord, at the door of the tent of meeting, a ram for error.<verse eid="LEV 19:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:22"/>And the priest shall make atonement for him with the ram for error before the Lord for the sin that he committed, and the sin he committed shall be forgiven him.<verse eid="LEV 19:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:23"/>Now when you enter into the land that the Lord your God is giving you and plant any kind of tree for food, then you shall thoroughly purify its uncleanness; three years its fruit shall be impure to you; it shall not be eaten.<verse eid="LEV 19:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:24"/>And in the fourth year all its fruit shall be holy, laudable to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 19:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:25"/>But in the fifth year you shall eat the fruit, its yield is an increase for you; it is I who am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:26"/>Do not eat on the mountains. And you shall not practice ornithomancy or divination by means of birds.<verse eid="LEV 19:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:27"/>You shall not make a hair roll out of the hair on your head or spoil the appearance of your beard.<verse eid="LEV 19:27"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:28"/>And you shall not make any incisions in your body for a soul<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">19:28</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'departed soul' tantamount to 'corpse'</char></note> and make any tattooed characters upon you; it is I who am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:28"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:29"/>Do not profane your daughter by making her commit fornication, and the land will not fornicate, and the land shall be full of lawlessness.<verse eid="LEV 19:29"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:30"/>You shall keep my sabbaths and be respectful of my sanctuaries; it is I who am the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 19:30"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:31"/>You shall not follow after ventriloquists, and you shall not attach yourselves to enchanters, to be thoroughly polluted by them; it is I who am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:31"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:32"/>You shall rise before a grey-haired person and honor the person of the old, and you shall fear your God; it is I who am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:32"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:33"/>Now if some guest approaches you in your land, you shall not oppress him.<verse eid="LEV 19:33"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:34"/>The guest who comes over to you shall be to you as the native among you, and you shall love him as yourself, for you were guests in the land of Egypt; it is I who am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:34"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:35"/>You shall not do what is unjust in judgment in measures and in standard weights and in balances.<verse eid="LEV 19:35"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:36"/>You shall have just balances and just standard weights and an honest half-peck; it is I who am the Lord your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt.<verse eid="LEV 19:36"/>

<verse sid="LEV 19:37"/>And you shall keep my entire law and all my ordinances, and you shall do them; it is I who am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:37"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 20">
<verse sid="LEV 20:1"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 20:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:2"/>You shall also speak to the sons of Israel: If any of the sons of Israel or of the guests who have come in Israel-- whoever gives any of his offspring to a ruler, by death let him be put to death; the nation in the land shall stone them with stones.<verse eid="LEV 20:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:3"/>And it is I who will set my face against that person and will utterly destroy him from his people, because he has given of his offspring to a ruler, to defile my holy things and to profane the name of those consecrated to me.<verse eid="LEV 20:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:4"/>But if the natives of the land should by an oversight overlook with their eyes away from that person when he gives of his offspring to a ruler in order not to kill him,<verse eid="LEV 20:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:5"/>then I will set my face against that person and his family and will utterly destroy him from among his people, him and all who are like-minded in going out to commit fornication with the rulers.<verse eid="LEV 20:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:6"/>And a soul that follows after ventriloquists or enchanters so as to commit fornication after them, I will set my face against that soul and will utterly destroy him from his people.<verse eid="LEV 20:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:7"/>And you shall be holy, for I, the Lord your God, am holy.<verse eid="LEV 20:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:8"/>And you shall keep my ordinances and observe them; I am the Lord that sanctifies you.<verse eid="LEV 20:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:9"/>A person, a person who speaks severely with his father or his mother-- with death let him be put to death; he has spoken severely with his father or his mother-- he shall be liable.<verse eid="LEV 20:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:10"/>A person who commits adultery with the wife of a man or who commits adultery with the wife of his neighbor-- let both the adulterer and the adulteress by death be put to death.<verse eid="LEV 20:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:11"/>And if anyone lies with his father's wife, he has uncovered his father's shame; let both of them by death be put to death; they are liable.<verse eid="LEV 20:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:12"/>And if anyone lies with his daughter-in-law, let both of them by death be put to death, for they have behaved impiously; they are liable.<verse eid="LEV 20:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:13"/>And he who lies with a male in a bed for a woman, both have committed an abomination; by death let them be put to death; they are liable.<verse eid="LEV 20:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:14"/>He who takes a wife and her mother-- it is transgression of the law; they shall burn both him and them with fire, and there shall be no lawlessness among you.<verse eid="LEV 20:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:15"/>And he who gives his sleeping-with to a quadruped, by death let him be put to death, and you shall kill the quadruped.<verse eid="LEV 20:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:16"/>And a woman who shall approach any animal for her to be mounted by it-- you shall kill the woman and the animal; by death they shall be put to death; they are liable.<verse eid="LEV 20:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:17"/>He who takes his sister, from his father or from his mother, and sees her shame, and she sees his shame; it is a disgrace; they shall be exterminated before the sons of their race; he has uncovered his sister's shame; he shall bear guilt.<verse eid="LEV 20:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:18"/>And a man who lies with a woman who sits apart and uncovers her shame-- he has laid bare her spring, and she has laid bare her flow of blood; both of them shall be exterminated from their race.<verse eid="LEV 20:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:19"/>And you shall not uncover the shame of your father's sister or of your mother's sister, for one has laid bare one's own blood family; they shall carry guilt.<verse eid="LEV 20:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:20"/>He who lies with one who is his relative-- he has uncovered the shame of his kinship; they shall die childless.<verse eid="LEV 20:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:21"/>He who takes the wife of his brother-- it is impurity; he has uncovered his brother's shame; they shall die childless.<verse eid="LEV 20:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:22"/>And you shall keep all my ordinances and all my judgments and do them, and the land to which I bring you there to settle in it will never be angry with you.<verse eid="LEV 20:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:23"/>And you shall not walk by the precepts of the nations that I am sending out away from you. Because they did all these things, I also abhorred them.<verse eid="LEV 20:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:24"/>And I have said to you: You shall inherit their land, and it is I who will give it to you in possession, a land that is flowing with milk and honey. I am the Lord your God who has separated you from all the nations.<verse eid="LEV 20:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:25"/>And you shall separate them: between the clean animals and between the unclean animals and between the clean birds and between the unclean; you shall not cause your souls to be loathsome by the animals and by the birds and by any of the creeping things of the earth, which I have set apart for you by uncleanness.<verse eid="LEV 20:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:26"/>And you shall be holy to me, for I the Lord your God am holy, who has separated you from all the nations to be mine.<verse eid="LEV 20:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 20:27"/>And a man or a woman-- whoever among them becomes a ventriloquist or an enchanter, let both by death be put to death; with stones you shall stone them; they are liable.<verse eid="LEV 20:27"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 21">
<verse sid="LEV 21:1"/>And the Lord said to Moyses<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">21:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">+ Wevers Ed. = 'saying'</char></note>: Address the priests, the sons of Aaron, and you shall say to them: They shall not be defiled by souls<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">21:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'departed soul' tantamount to 'corpse'</char></note> among their nation<verse eid="LEV 21:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:2"/>except by their nearest kin: for father and mother and sons and daughters, for a brother<verse eid="LEV 21:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:3"/>and for a virgin sister, who approaches him, who had not been given in marriage to a husband-- he shall be defiled for these.<verse eid="LEV 21:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:4"/>He shall not be defiled suddenly among his people to his own desecration.<verse eid="LEV 21:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:5"/>And you shall not have a bald spot shaven upon your head for the dead, nor shall they shave the appearance of their beard, and they shall not cut incisions into their flesh.<verse eid="LEV 21:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:6"/>They shall be holy to their God and not profane the name of their God. For it is they that offer the sacrifices of the Lord as gifts of their God, and they shall be holy.<verse eid="LEV 21:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:7"/>They shall not marry a woman who is a prostitute and one who has been profaned and a woman rejected by her husband. For he is holy to the Lord his God,<verse eid="LEV 21:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:8"/>and he will sanctify him-- it is he that offers the gifts of the Lord your God; he shall be holy, for I the Lord, who sanctifies them, am holy.<verse eid="LEV 21:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:9"/>And if the daughter of a person who is a priest profanes herself through going out to commit fornication, she profanes the name of her father; she shall be burned on fire.<verse eid="LEV 21:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:10"/>And the priest who is great among his brothers, when the anointing oil has been poured on his head and when he has been validated to wear the vestments, shall not unbind his head and shall not tear his vestments.<verse eid="LEV 21:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:11"/>And he shall not enter for any dead soul; he shall not be defiled for his father or even for his mother.<verse eid="LEV 21:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:12"/>And he shall not depart from the holy things, and he shall not profane what is consecrated, belonging to his God, for God's holy oil of anointing is upon him; I am the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 21:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:13"/>He shall marry a wife who is a virgin of his own kin.<verse eid="LEV 21:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:14"/>A widow and one rejected and profaned and a prostitute-- these he shall not marry. Rather, he shall marry a wife who is a virgin of his own kin,<verse eid="LEV 21:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:15"/>and he shall not profane his offspring among his kin; I am the Lord that sanctifies him.<verse eid="LEV 21:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:16"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 21:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:17"/>Say to Aaron: A person from your kin among your families-- if any such person has a blemish on him, he shall not approach to offer the gifts of his God.<verse eid="LEV 21:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:18"/>Any person who has a blemish on him shall not draw near-- a person who is lame or blind or having a mutilated nose or who has a cut ear<verse eid="LEV 21:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:19"/>or a person who has a crushed hand or a crushed foot<verse eid="LEV 21:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:20"/>or a hunchback or one with white spots on the eye or one that has inflammation in his eyes or a person who has on him a severe itch or lichen-like growth or one with a single testicle.<verse eid="LEV 21:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:21"/>Anyone of the offspring of Aaron the priest who has on him a blemish shall not come near to offer sacrifices to your God; since he has a blemish, he shall not come near to offer the gifts of God.<verse eid="LEV 21:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:22"/>He shall eat the gifts of God, the holy of holies, and of the holy things.<verse eid="LEV 21:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:23"/>Only he shall not draw near to the veil and not come near the altar, because he has a blemish, and he shall not profane the sanctuary of his God, for it is I who am the Lord who sanctify them.<verse eid="LEV 21:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 21:24"/>And Moyses spoke to Aaron and his sons and to all the sons of Israel.<verse eid="LEV 21:24"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 22">
<verse sid="LEV 22:1"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 22:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:2"/>Speak to Aaron and his sons, and let them give heed because of the sacred things of the sons of Israel, which they dedicate to me, and they shall not profane my holy name; I am the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 22:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:3"/>Say to them: Any person from all your offspring throughout your generations who comes near the sacred things, which the sons of Israel dedicate to the Lord, and his uncleanness is upon him-- that soul shall be exterminated from my presence; I am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 22:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:4"/>And a man of the offspring of Aaron the priest-- and he is a sufferer from a leprous disease or spermatorrhoea-- shall not eat of the sacred things until he has been cleansed. And he who touches anything of the uncleanness of a soul<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">22:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'departed soul' tantamount to 'corpse'</char></note> or a person whose bed of semen issues forth from him<verse eid="LEV 22:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:5"/>or whoever touches any unclean creeping thing that defiles him or by any human being by whom he defiles him, according to all his uncleanness--<verse eid="LEV 22:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:6"/>a soul who touches them shall be unclean until evening. He shall not eat of the sacred things unless he has washed his body in water.<verse eid="LEV 22:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:7"/>And should the sun set, he shall then be clean, and then he shall eat of the sacred things, for it is his bread.<verse eid="LEV 22:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:8"/>A carcass and what was torn by wild animals he shall not eat, to be defiled by them; I am the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 22:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:9"/>And they shall keep my charges so that they may not through them assume guilt and die because of them, if they profane them; I am the Lord, the God who sanctifies them.<verse eid="LEV 22:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:10"/>And no alien shall eat sacred things. No resident alien of a priest or a hireling shall eat sacred things,<verse eid="LEV 22:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:11"/>but if a priest procures a soul by acquisition of money, he shall eat of his bread, and those that are homebred, they too shall eat of his bread.<verse eid="LEV 22:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:12"/>If a daughter of a person who is a priest belongs to a foreign husband, she shall not eat of the first fruits of the sacred things,<verse eid="LEV 22:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:13"/>and if a priest's daughter becomes a widow or is rejected, though without having offspring, she shall return to her paternal home, as in her youth; she shall eat of her father's food. And no alien shall eat of them.<verse eid="LEV 22:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:14"/>If a person eats sacred things out of ignorance, he shall then add one-fifth to it and give the sacred thing to the priest.<verse eid="LEV 22:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:15"/>And they shall not profane the sacred things of the sons of Israel, which they separate for the Lord,<verse eid="LEV 22:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:16"/>and bring upon themselves lawless conduct of error, by eating their sacred things, for I am the Lord who sanctify them.<verse eid="LEV 22:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:17"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 22:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:18"/>Speak to Aaron and his sons and the whole congregation of Israel, and you shall say to them: Person by person of the sons of Israel or of the guests who adhere to them in Israel, whoever presents his gifts according to any agreement of theirs or according to any choice of theirs, whatever they may bring to the Lord<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">22:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'the Lord':  Wevers Ed. = 'God'</char></note> as a whole burnt offering,<verse eid="LEV 22:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:19"/>these shall be<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">22:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'these shall be':  Lacking in Greek</char></note> acceptable to you-- a male without blemish of the cattle-herds and of the sheep and of the goats.<verse eid="LEV 22:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:20"/>They shall not offer to the Lord anything that has on it a blemish, for it shall not be acceptable to you.<verse eid="LEV 22:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:21"/>And a person who offers a sacrifice of deliverance to the Lord, expressly uttering a vow according to a choice, or at your feasts, from the cattle-herds or from the sheep, to be acceptable it shall be without blemish; there shall be no blemish in it.<verse eid="LEV 22:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:22"/>Anything blind or broken-limbed or with its tongue cut or having warts or acute itching or having lichen-like growth-- these you shall not offer to the Lord<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">22:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'the Lord':  Wevers Ed. = 'God'</char></note> and you shall not give of them as an offering on the altar to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 22:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:23"/>And a calf or a sheep that has a cut on its ear or one with a stunted tail, you shall make a slaughtering of them for yourself, but it will not be accepted for your vow.<verse eid="LEV 22:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:24"/>A gelding and one bruised and one castrated and one whose testicles were torn off-- you shall not offer these to the Lord, and you shall not do them in your land.<verse eid="LEV 22:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:25"/>And from an alien's hand you shall not offer any of these as gifts to your God, since there are corruptions in them; there is a blemish in them; they shall not be acceptable to you.<verse eid="LEV 22:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:26"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 22:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:27"/>When a calf or a sheep or a goat is born, then it shall remain seven days under its mother, but on the eighth day and beyond it shall be accepted as a gift, an offering to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 22:27"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:28"/>And as for a calf or a sheep-- you shall not slaughter her and her young on one day.<verse eid="LEV 22:28"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:29"/>But if you sacrifice a sacrifice, a vow of joyfulness, to the Lord, you shall sacrifice it as something acceptable to you.<verse eid="LEV 22:29"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:30"/>It shall be eaten on the same day; you shall not leave any of the meat until morning; I am the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 22:30"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:31"/>And you shall keep my commandments and do them.<verse eid="LEV 22:31"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:32"/>And you shall not profane the name of the holy one, and I shall be sanctified among the sons of Israel; I am the Lord who sanctifies you,<verse eid="LEV 22:32"/>

<verse sid="LEV 22:33"/>who brought you out of the land of Egypt to be your God; I am the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 22:33"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 23">
<verse sid="LEV 23:1"/>And the Lord said to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 23:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:2"/>Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: The feasts of the Lord, those that you shall call designated, holy-- these are my feasts.<verse eid="LEV 23:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:3"/>Six days you shall do acts of work, and on the seventh day there is Sabbata, a rest, designated, holy to the Lord; you shall do no work; it is Sabbata to the Lord in your every settlement.<verse eid="LEV 23:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:4"/>These are the feasts for the Lord, and they are designated, holy, those that you shall call out at their appointed time.<verse eid="LEV 23:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:5"/>In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month, in the middle of the time approaching evening, is a pascha to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 23:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:6"/>And on the fifteenth day of the same month is the feast of unleavened bread to the Lord; seven days you shall eat unleavened things.<verse eid="LEV 23:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:7"/>And the first day shall be a designated, holy one to you; you shall not do any work of service.<verse eid="LEV 23:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:8"/>And for seven days you shall present whole burnt offerings to the Lord, and the seventh day shall be a designated holy one to you; you shall not do any work of service.<verse eid="LEV 23:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:9"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 23:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:10"/>Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: When you enter into the land that I give you and you reap its harvest, you shall also bring a sheaf as the first fruit of your harvest to the priest.<verse eid="LEV 23:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:11"/>And he shall raise up the sheaf before the Lord, acceptable for you; on the day after the first the priest shall raise it up.<verse eid="LEV 23:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:12"/>And on the day when you bring the sheaf, you shall do a sheep a year old, without blemish, as a whole burnt offering to the Lord,<verse eid="LEV 23:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:13"/>and its sacrifice-- two-tenths of choice flour prepared with oil; a sacrifice to the Lord it is, an odor of fragrance to the Lord, and its libation, one-fourth of a hin<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">23:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew 1 hin = 4 liters</char></note> of wine.<verse eid="LEV 23:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:14"/>And you shall eat no bread or parched fresh kernels until this very day, until you yourselves offer the gifts to your God; it is a perpetual precept throughout your generations in your every settlement.<verse eid="LEV 23:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:15"/>And from the day after the sabbaths, from the day on which you bring the sheaf of the addition, you shall count off seven whole weeks.<verse eid="LEV 23:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:16"/>You shall count until the day after the last week, fifty days, and you shall present a new sacrifice to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 23:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:17"/>You shall offer bread as an addition from your settlement: two loaves of bread. They shall consist of two-tenths of fine flour, baked with leaven, of first products to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 23:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:18"/>And you shall offer with the bread seven lambs, a year old without blemish, and one calf from the cattle-herd and two rams without blemish; they shall be a whole burnt offering to the Lord, along with their sacrifices and their libations: a sacrifice, an odor of fragrance to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 23:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:19"/>You shall also prepare one young billy goat from the goats for sin and two lambs a year old as a sacrifice of deliverance with the bread of the first products.<verse eid="LEV 23:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:20"/>And the priest shall place them with the bread of the first products-- an addition before the Lord, together with the two lambs; they shall be holy to the Lord for the priest who offers them; they shall be his.<verse eid="LEV 23:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:21"/>And this day you shall call designated; it shall be holy to you; you shall not do any work of service on it-- a perpetual precept throughout your generations in your every settlement.<verse eid="LEV 23:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:22"/>And when you reap the harvest of your land, you shall not in your harvesting thereafter make a thorough job of the harvest of your field, and you shall not gather the gleanings of your harvest; you shall leave them remaining for the poor and for the guest; I am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 23:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:23"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 23:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:24"/>Speak to the sons of Israel, saying: In the seventh month, on the first of the month, you shall have a rest, a memorial with trumpets; it shall be designated, holy to you.<verse eid="LEV 23:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:25"/>You shall do no work of service, and you shall present a whole burnt offering to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 23:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:26"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 23:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:27"/>Also on the tenth of this seventh month there is a day of atonement; it shall be designated, holy to you, and you shall humble your souls and present a whole burnt offering to the Lord;<verse eid="LEV 23:27"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:28"/>you shall do no work on this particular day; for this is a day of atonement for you, to make atonement for you before the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 23:28"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:29"/>Any soul who does not humble himself on that particular day shall be exterminated from his people.<verse eid="LEV 23:29"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:30"/>And any soul that shall do work on that particular day-- that soul shall be utterly destroyed from his people.<verse eid="LEV 23:30"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:31"/>You shall do no work; it is a perpetual precept throughout your generations in all your settlements.<verse eid="LEV 23:31"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:32"/>It shall be to you Sabbata of sabbaths, and you shall humble your souls; from the ninth of the month, from evening to evening you shall sabbatize on your sabbaths.<verse eid="LEV 23:32"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:33"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 23:33"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:34"/>Speak to the sons of Israel, saying: On the fifteenth day of this seventh month and lasting seven days is the feast of tents to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 23:34"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:35"/>And the first day is designated, holy; you shall not do any work of service.<verse eid="LEV 23:35"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:36"/>Seven days you shall present whole burnt offerings to the Lord, and the eighth day shall be designated, holy to you, and you shall present a whole burnt offering to the Lord; it is a finale; you shall not do any work of service.<verse eid="LEV 23:36"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:37"/>These are the feasts to the Lord, which you shall call designated, holy, for presenting to the Lord offerings-- whole burnt offerings and their sacrifices and their libations, each on its proper day--<verse eid="LEV 23:37"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:38"/>apart from the sabbaths of the Lord and apart from your gifts and apart from all your vows and apart from your voluntary gifts, which you give to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 23:38"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:39"/>Also on the fifteenth day of this seventh month, when you finish the produce of the land, you shall keep a feast to the Lord for seven days, a rest on the first day and a rest on the eighth day.<verse eid="LEV 23:39"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:40"/>And on the first day you shall take ripe fruit of a tree, both brushes of palm trees and bushy branches of a tree and branches of willow and of chaste-tree from a wadi, to rejoice before the Lord your God for seven days in the year.<verse eid="LEV 23:40"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:41"/>It is a perpetual precept throughout your generations. You shall keep it as a feast in the seventh month.<verse eid="LEV 23:41"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:42"/>You shall live in tents for seven days; everyone who is a native in Israel shall live in tents,<verse eid="LEV 23:42"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:43"/>so that your generations may know that I made the sons of Israel settle in tents when I brought them out of the land of Egypt; I am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 23:43"/>

<verse sid="LEV 23:44"/>And Moyses declared to the sons of Israel the feasts of the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 23:44"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 24">
<verse sid="LEV 24:1"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 24:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:2"/>Command the sons of Israel, and let them take for you oil, pure olive, beaten, for light, to burn a lamp continually<verse eid="LEV 24:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:3"/>outside the veil in the tent of witness. And Aaron and his sons shall burn it from evening to morning before the Lord perpetually; it is a perpetual precept throughout your generations.<verse eid="LEV 24:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:4"/>You shall burn the lamps on the pure lampstand before the Lord until morning.<verse eid="LEV 24:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:5"/>And you shall take fine flour and make it twelve loaves; two-tenths shall be the one loaf.<verse eid="LEV 24:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:6"/>And you shall lay them in two piles, six loaves per one pile, on the pure table before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 24:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:7"/>You shall put on the pile pure frankincense and salt, and they shall be as loaves for remembrance, set before the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 24:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:8"/>On the day of the sabbaths he shall set them out before the Lord continually as an everlasting covenant from the sons of Israel.<verse eid="LEV 24:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:9"/>And they shall be for Aaron and his sons, and they shall eat them in a holy place, for they are holy of holies; this is for him from the things sacrificed to the Lord, a perpetual precept.<verse eid="LEV 24:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:10"/>And a son of an Israelite woman (and he was the son of an Egyptian) came out among the sons of Israel, and the Israelite woman's son and the Israelite person began fighting in the camp.<verse eid="LEV 24:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:11"/>And the Israelite woman's son called down a curse while naming the Name. And they brought him to Moyses-- now his mother's name was Salomith daughter of Dabri of the tribe of Dan--<verse eid="LEV 24:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:12"/>and they put him away in custody, to decide about him by the ordinance of the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 24:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:13"/>And the Lord said to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 24:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:14"/>Take the one who called down the curse outside the camp, and all who heard shall lay their hands on his head, and the whole congregation shall stone him.<verse eid="LEV 24:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:15"/>And speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: If a person, a person should curse God, he shall assume guilt.<verse eid="LEV 24:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:16"/>Whoever names the name of the Lord-- by death let him be put to death; let the whole congregation of Israel stone him with stones. Whether a guest or a native, when he names the name, let him die.<verse eid="LEV 24:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:17"/>And a person who strikes a person's soul and he dies, by death let him be put to death.<verse eid="LEV 24:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:18"/>And whoever strikes an animal and it dies-- let him repay soul for soul.<verse eid="LEV 24:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:19"/>And if anyone should give a blemish to his neighbor-- as he did to him, so also shall it be done to him in return:<verse eid="LEV 24:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:20"/>fracture for fracture, eye for eye, tooth for tooth; as one gives a blemish to a person, so shall it be given to him.<verse eid="LEV 24:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:21"/>Whoever strikes a person, and he dies, by death let him be put to death.<verse eid="LEV 24:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:22"/>There shall be one judgment for the guest and for the inhabitant of the country; for it is I who am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 24:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 24:23"/>And Moyses spoke to the sons of Israel, and they brought the one who had called down the curse outside the camp and stoned him with stones. And the sons of Israel did as the Lord had instructed Moyses.<verse eid="LEV 24:23"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 25">
<verse sid="LEV 25:1"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses on the mountain Sina, saying:<verse eid="LEV 25:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:2"/>Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: If you enter the land that I give you, the land which I give you, shall also rest-- Sabbata to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 25:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:3"/>Six years you shall sow your field, and six years you shall prune your vine and gather in its fruit,<verse eid="LEV 25:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:4"/>but in the seventh year there shall be Sabbata-- a rest for the land, Sabbata for the Lord; you shall not sow your field, and you shall not prune your vine.<verse eid="LEV 25:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:5"/>You shall not reap completely that which sprouts by itself of your field or gather in the grapes of what is something made holy for you; it shall be a year of rest for the land.<verse eid="LEV 25:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:6"/>And the sabbaths of the land shall be food for you and for your male slave and your female slave and your hired laborer and for the resident alien who adheres to you,<verse eid="LEV 25:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:7"/>for your livestock also and for the wild animals which are in your land all its yield shall be for food.<verse eid="LEV 25:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:8"/>And you shall count off for yourself seven rests of years, seven times seven years, and they shall be for you seven weeks of years-- forty-nine years.<verse eid="LEV 25:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:9"/>And you shall proclaim with the sound of the trumpet throughout all your land, in the seventh month, on the tenth of the month. On the day of atonement you shall proclaim with the trumpet throughout all your land.<verse eid="LEV 25:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:10"/>And you shall hallow the year, the fiftieth year, and you shall proclaim release on the land to all its inhabitants. It shall be a year of release; a signal this shall be for you, and each one shall depart to his possession, and each shall depart to his clan.<verse eid="LEV 25:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:11"/>This is a signal of release: the fiftieth year. It shall be a year for you; you shall not sow or gather its<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">25:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the land's'</char></note> spontaneous sprouts, and you shall not harvest its<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">25:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the land's'</char></note> consecrated things.<verse eid="LEV 25:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:12"/>For it is a signal of release; it shall be a holy thing to you; from the plains you shall eat its<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">25:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the land's'</char></note> produce.<verse eid="LEV 25:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:13"/>In the year of release, by its signal, each one shall return to his possession.<verse eid="LEV 25:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:14"/>But if you make a sale to your neighbor, even if you make an acquisition from your neighbor, let a person not oppress his neighbor.<verse eid="LEV 25:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:15"/>You shall acquire from your neighbor according to the number of years since the signal; he shall sell to you according to the number of years of produce.<verse eid="LEV 25:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:16"/>Insofar as there be an increase in years, you shall increase his tenure, and insofar as there be a decrease in years, you shall decrease his tenure, for he shall sell to you a number of yields.<verse eid="LEV 25:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:17"/>Let not a person oppress his neighbor, and you shall fear the Lord your God; it is I who am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 25:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:18"/>And you shall observe all my statutes and all my judgments, and you shall guard yourselves and do them, and you shall dwell on the land feeling confident.<verse eid="LEV 25:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:19"/>And the land will yield its produce, and you will eat to satiety and dwell on it feeling confident.<verse eid="LEV 25:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:20"/>But if you say, What shall we eat in this seventh year, if we do not sow or gather in our crop?<verse eid="LEV 25:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:21"/>I will also send my blessing to you in the sixth year, and it will yield its crop for three years.<verse eid="LEV 25:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:22"/>And you shall sow in the eighth year, and you will be eating from the old crop until the ninth year. When its produce comes in, you shall eat old of old things.<verse eid="LEV 25:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:23"/>And the land shall not be sold irrevocably, for the land is mine, because before me you are guests and resident aliens.<verse eid="LEV 25:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:24"/>And on the basis of all the land of your holding, you shall provide ransom for the land.<verse eid="LEV 25:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:25"/>But if your brother who is with you should become poor and should sell some of what he holds and the next of kin who is nearest should come, then he shall redeem the sale of his brother.<verse eid="LEV 25:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:26"/>But if someone does not have one who is next of kin and has plenty in hand and finds for himself what is sufficient for his ransom,<verse eid="LEV 25:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:27"/>then he shall compute the years of his sale and give back what he has over to the person who sold it to him, and he shall depart to his holding.<verse eid="LEV 25:27"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:28"/>But if his hand does not find what is sufficient to give it back to him, then the sale shall belong to the one who acquired them until the year of release, and at the release it shall expire, and he shall depart to his holding.<verse eid="LEV 25:28"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:29"/>But if anyone sells a dwelling house in a walled city, then its redemption shall stand; until a year of days has elapsed, its redemption shall stand.<verse eid="LEV 25:29"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:30"/>But if it is not redeemed until a full year has elapsed, the house that is in a city that has a wall shall be confirmed irrevocably to belong to its purchaser, throughout his generations, and it shall not expire in the release.<verse eid="LEV 25:30"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:31"/>But houses in farmsteads, those that have no wall around them, let them be classed as the field of the earth; these shall always be redeemed, and they shall expire in the release.<verse eid="LEV 25:31"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:32"/>And as for the cities of the Leuites, the houses of the cities of their holding shall always be redeemed for the Leuites.<verse eid="LEV 25:32"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:33"/>And he who redeems from the Leuites, then the sale of their houses of a city of their holding shall expire in the release, because the dwellings in the cities of the Leuites are their holding among the sons of Israel.<verse eid="LEV 25:33"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:34"/>And the fields bordering on their cities shall not be sold; for this is their holding for all time.<verse eid="LEV 25:34"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:35"/>Now if your brother is needy and with you becomes weak in his hands, you shall help him as a guest and a resident alien, and your brother shall live with you.<verse eid="LEV 25:35"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:36"/>You shall not take interest from him, not even in any amount, and you shall fear your God; I am the Lord. And your brother shall live with you.<verse eid="LEV 25:36"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:37"/>You shall not give him your money at interest; neither shall you give him your food in excess.<verse eid="LEV 25:37"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:38"/>I am the Lord your God, the one who brought you out from the land of Egypt, to give you the land Chanaan in order to be your God.<verse eid="LEV 25:38"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:39"/>Now if your brother with you is humbled and is sold to you, he shall not be subject to you with the subjection of a domestic.<verse eid="LEV 25:39"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:40"/>He shall be to you as a hired laborer or a resident alien. He shall work with you until the year of the release.<verse eid="LEV 25:40"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:41"/>And he and his children with him shall go forth at the release, and he shall go away to his kin; he shall depart to his ancestral holding.<verse eid="LEV 25:41"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:42"/>For they are my domestics, whom I brought out of the land of Egypt; he shall not be sold in a sale of a domestic.<verse eid="LEV 25:42"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:43"/>You shall not abuse him with toil, and you shall fear the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 25:43"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:44"/>And as for a male and female servant whom you may have from the nations that are around you-- from them you shall acquire a male and female slave.<verse eid="LEV 25:44"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:45"/>Also from the sons of the resident aliens residing among you-- from these and from their families who have been born in your land you shall acquire; let them be to you as a possession.<verse eid="LEV 25:45"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:46"/>And you shall distribute them to your children after you, and they shall be held in possession by you forever. But of your brothers the sons of Israel, each shall not abuse his brother with toil.<verse eid="LEV 25:46"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:47"/>If the hand of the guest or the resident alien with you finds, and if your brother, having fallen in difficulty, is sold to the guest or to the resident alien with you or to a guest by descent,<verse eid="LEV 25:47"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:48"/>after he has been sold to him he shall have redemption; one of his brothers shall redeem him;<verse eid="LEV 25:48"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:49"/>a brother of his father or a son of his father's brother shall redeem him, or some of his relatives who are of his own flesh, of his own tribe, shall redeem him, but if he prospers with his hands he shall redeem himself.<verse eid="LEV 25:49"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:50"/>He shall compute with his purchaser from the year when he sold himself to him until the year of the release, and the amount of the sale shall be as for a hired laborer. Year by year he shall be with him.<verse eid="LEV 25:50"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:51"/>But if more years remain to someone, for these he shall pay his ransom from the money of his sale,<verse eid="LEV 25:51"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:52"/>but if few years remain until the year of the release, then he shall compute for him according to his years, and he shall pay his ransom.<verse eid="LEV 25:52"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:53"/>As a hired laborer he shall be with him year by year. You shall not abuse him with toil in your sight.<verse eid="LEV 25:53"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:54"/>But if he has not been redeemed in any of these ways, he and his young children with him shall go forth in the year of release.<verse eid="LEV 25:54"/>

<verse sid="LEV 25:55"/>For to me the sons of Israel are domestics; these are my servants whom I brought out from the land of Egypt.<verse eid="LEV 25:55"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 26">
<verse sid="LEV 26:1"/>I am the Lord your God. You shall make for yourselves nothing made by hand nor carved, neither erect a stele of your own, nor shall you place a stone as a look-out in your land, to do obeisance to it; it is I who am the Lord your God.<verse eid="LEV 26:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:2"/>You shall keep my sabbaths and be respectful of my sanctuaries; I am the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 26:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:3"/>If you walk by my ordinances and observe my commandments and do them,<verse eid="LEV 26:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:4"/>I will then give you the rain in its season, and the land shall yield its produce, and the trees of the plains shall yield their fruit.<verse eid="LEV 26:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:5"/>And for you the harvest shall overtake the vintage, and the vintage shall overtake the sowing, and you shall eat your bread to satiety and dwell in safety on your land, and war shall not go through your land.<verse eid="LEV 26:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:6"/>And I will grant peace in your land, and you shall fall asleep, and there shall be no one making you afraid, and I will destroy bad animals from your land.<verse eid="LEV 26:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:7"/>And you shall give chase to your enemies, and they shall fall before you by slaughter.<verse eid="LEV 26:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:8"/>And five of you shall give chase to a hundred, and a hundred of you shall give chase to tens of thousands, and your enemies shall fall before you by dagger.<verse eid="LEV 26:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:9"/>And I will look attentively upon you and increase you and multiply you, and I will establish my covenant with you.<verse eid="LEV 26:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:10"/>And you shall eat the old and the old things of the old, and you shall bring out the old out of the new.<verse eid="LEV 26:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:11"/>And I will place my tent among you, and my soul shall not abhor you.<verse eid="LEV 26:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:12"/>And I will walk about among you and will be your God, and you shall be for me a nation<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'for me a nation':  Wevers Ed. = 'my people'</char></note>.<verse eid="LEV 26:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:13"/>It is I who am the Lord your God who brought you out of the land of Egypt since you were slaves, and I have shattered the bond of your yoke and led you with boldness.<verse eid="LEV 26:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:14"/>But if you do not obey me, neither do these ordinances of mine,<verse eid="LEV 26:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:15"/>but refuse to comply with them, and your soul be angered by my judgments so that you do not carry out all my commandments so that you scatter my covenant to the wind,<verse eid="LEV 26:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:16"/>then I in turn will do thus to you, and I will gather difficulty upon you, both itch and jaundice, and your eyes as being purulent and your life as pining away. And you shall sow your seed in vain, and your adversaries shall eat it.<verse eid="LEV 26:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:17"/>And I will set my face against you, and you shall fall down before your enemies, and those who hate you shall pursue you, and you shall flee though no one pursues you.<verse eid="LEV 26:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:18"/>And if up to this point you do not obey me, then I will do more to discipline you sevenfold for your sins.<verse eid="LEV 26:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:19"/>And I will smash the insolence of your arrogance, and I will make your sky iron and your earth like copper.<verse eid="LEV 26:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:20"/>And your strength shall be to no purpose, and your land shall not yield its seed time, and the tree of your field shall not yield its fruit.<verse eid="LEV 26:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:21"/>If after this you walk sideways and are not willing to obey me, I will add to you seven blows in accordance with your sins.<verse eid="LEV 26:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:22"/>And I will send the wild animals of the land against you, and they shall devour you and utterly destroy your livestock, and they shall make you very few in number, and your roads shall be deserted.<verse eid="LEV 26:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:23"/>And if by these things you are not disciplined but walk sideways with me,<verse eid="LEV 26:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:24"/>then I too will walk with you in skewed anger, and I myself will strike you sevenfold for your sins.<verse eid="LEV 26:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:25"/>And I will bring against you a dagger avenging the cause of the covenant, and you will flee for refuge to your cities. And I will send death among you, and you shall be delivered into enemy hands.<verse eid="LEV 26:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:26"/>When you are hard pressed for want of bread, then ten women shall bake your bread in a single oven, and they shall dole out your bread by weight, and you shall eat and never be satisfied.<verse eid="LEV 26:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:27"/>Now if by these things you do not obey me but walk sideways with me,<verse eid="LEV 26:27"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:28"/>I myself too will walk with you in skewed anger, and it is I who will discipline you sevenfold in accordance with your sins.<verse eid="LEV 26:28"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:29"/>And you shall eat the flesh of your sons, and you shall eat the flesh of your daughters.<verse eid="LEV 26:29"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:30"/>And I will strip bare your steles and utterly destroy your wooden handcrafted objects, and I will place your limbs on the limbs of your idols. And my soul will be very angry with you.<verse eid="LEV 26:30"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:31"/>And I will lay your cities waste, will make your sanctuaries quite desolate, and I will not smell the odor of your sacrifices anymore.<verse eid="LEV 26:31"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:32"/>And I will devastate your land, and your enemies who inhabit it shall be astonished at it.<verse eid="LEV 26:32"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:33"/>And you I will scatter into the nations, and the dagger, coming by surprise, will utterly destroy you, and your land shall be desolate, and your cities shall be desolate.<verse eid="LEV 26:33"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:34"/>Then the land shall enjoy its sabbaths all the days of its desolation. And you shall be in the land of your enemies; then the land shall sabbatize and enjoy its sabbaths.<verse eid="LEV 26:34"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:35"/>All the days of its desolation, it shall sabbatize what it did not sabbatize on your sabbaths when you were living on it.<verse eid="LEV 26:35"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:36"/>And onto those of you who are left, I will send faintness into their heart in the land of their enemies, and the sound of a driven leaf shall put them to flight, and they shall flee as those who flee from battle, and they shall fall though no one pursues.<verse eid="LEV 26:36"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:37"/>And brother shall disdain brother as in a war, though no one is running away, and you shall not be able to withstand your enemies.<verse eid="LEV 26:37"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:38"/>And you shall perish among the nations, and the land of your enemies shall devour you.<verse eid="LEV 26:38"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:39"/>And those of you who are left shall be corrupted because of their sins. In the land of their enemies they shall melt away.<verse eid="LEV 26:39"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:40"/>And they shall confess their sins and the sins of their fathers, because they transgressed and disdained me and because they walked sideways before me,<verse eid="LEV 26:40"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:41"/>and I, in turn, walked in skewed anger with them, and I shall destroy them in the land of their enemies. Then their uncircumcised heart will feel ashamed, and then they will be content with their iniquities.<verse eid="LEV 26:41"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:42"/>And I will remember the covenant of Iakob, and I will remember the covenant of Isaak and the covenant of Abraam, and I will remember the land.<verse eid="LEV 26:42"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:43"/>And the land shall be abandoned by them. Then the land shall accept its sabbaths while it was made desolate by them, and they themselves shall accept their lawlessness on account of which they disdained my judgments and were vexed in their soul by my ordinances.<verse eid="LEV 26:43"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:44"/>And not even when they were in the land of their enemies did I ever disdain them or was angered by them so as to destroy them utterly, to scatter to the wind my covenant with them; for it is I who am the Lord their God,<verse eid="LEV 26:44"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:45"/>and I will remember their former covenant when I brought them out of the land of Egypt, out of a house of slavery in the sight of the nations, to be their God; I am the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 26:45"/>

<verse sid="LEV 26:46"/>These are the judgments and the ordinances and the law that the Lord established between him and between the sons of Israel on the mountain Sina by the hand of Moyses.<verse eid="LEV 26:46"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="LEV 27">
<verse sid="LEV 27:1"/>And the Lord spoke to Moyses, saying:<verse eid="LEV 27:1"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:2"/>Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: A person who vows a vow to the Lord, for instance the value of his life,<verse eid="LEV 27:2"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:3"/>the value for a male shall be: from twenty to sixty years of age the value shall be fifty didrachmas<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">27:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">A didrachma is the rough equivalent of two days' wages</char></note> of silver by the sanctuary standard.<verse eid="LEV 27:3"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:4"/>But for a female the valuation shall be thirty didrachmas.<verse eid="LEV 27:4"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:5"/>Now if it is from five to twenty years of age, the value of a male shall be twenty didrachmas and of a female, ten didrachmas.<verse eid="LEV 27:5"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:6"/>And from one month to five years, the value of a male shall be five didrachmas of silver, but of a female, three didrachmas.<verse eid="LEV 27:6"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:7"/>But if from sixty years and over, if the person is a male-- the value shall be fifteen didrachmas of silver, but in the case of a female ten didrachmas.<verse eid="LEV 27:7"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:8"/>And if he is base with regard to the value, he shall stand before the priest, and the priest shall assess him; in accordance with the strength of the hand of the one making the vow, the priest shall assess him.<verse eid="LEV 27:8"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:9"/>But if a gift to the Lord be from the animals, from those that are being offered, if he gives from these to the Lord, it shall be holy.<verse eid="LEV 27:9"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:10"/>He shall not exchange it, either good for bad or bad for good. But if by exchanging he exchanges it, animal for animal, both that one and its substitute shall be holy.<verse eid="LEV 27:10"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:11"/>But if a gift to the Lord is any unclean animal, from those that are not brought, he shall set the animal before the priest.<verse eid="LEV 27:11"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:12"/>And the priest shall assess it; between good and between bad, as the priest sets the value, so it shall stand.<verse eid="LEV 27:12"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:13"/>But if by redeeming, he redeems it, he shall add one-fifth to its value.<verse eid="LEV 27:13"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:14"/>If a person consecrates his house holy to the Lord, then the priest shall assess it: whether between good and between bad; as the priest values it, so it shall be fixed.<verse eid="LEV 27:14"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:15"/>But if the one who consecrates it redeems his house, he shall add to it one-fifth of the money of its value, and it shall be his.<verse eid="LEV 27:15"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:16"/>Now if a person consecrates to the Lord some of the field of his holding, then its value shall be in accordance with its seed: fifty didrachmas of silver to a kor<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">27:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew 1 kor = 220 liters</char></note> of barley seed.<verse eid="LEV 27:16"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:17"/>But if he consecrates his field from the year of release, according to its assessment it shall stand,<verse eid="LEV 27:17"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:18"/>but if he consecrates his field later, after the release, the priest shall compute the price for it according to the years that remain until the year of release, and there shall be a deduction made from its assessment.<verse eid="LEV 27:18"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:19"/>Now if the one who consecrates it redeems the field, then he shall add one-fifth of the money to its value, and it shall be his,<verse eid="LEV 27:19"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:20"/>but should he not redeem the field and should sell the field to another person, he shall no longer redeem it.<verse eid="LEV 27:20"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:21"/>But when the release has expired, the field shall be holy to the Lord as the land that has been set aside; it shall be the priest's holding.<verse eid="LEV 27:21"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:22"/>Now if someone consecrates to the Lord part of the field that he has purchased, which is not a part of the field of his holding,<verse eid="LEV 27:22"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:23"/>the priest shall assign to it the full amount of the value from the year of release, and he shall pay the value on that day, something sacred to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 27:23"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:24"/>And in the year of release the field shall be given back to the person from whom he bought it, whose land-holding it had been.<verse eid="LEV 27:24"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:25"/>And every assessment shall be by holy weights: twenty obols shall make a didrachma.<verse eid="LEV 27:25"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:26"/>And every firstling that may be born among your animals shall belong to the Lord, and no one shall consecrate it; whether calf or sheep, it is the Lord's.<verse eid="LEV 27:26"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:27"/>But if it is of unclean quadrupeds, he shall make an alteration according to its assessment and add one-fifth to it. And it shall be his. But if he does not redeem, it shall be sold at its assessed value.<verse eid="LEV 27:27"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:28"/>But nothing dedicated that a person may dedicate to the Lord, which he owns, from human to animal and from his field of holding, shall be sold or redeemed; every devoted thing shall be holy of holies to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 27:28"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:29"/>And nothing that has been dedicated of human beings shall be redeemed, but by death it shall be put to death.<verse eid="LEV 27:29"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:30"/>Every tithe of the land from the seed of the ground and of tree-fruit is the Lord's; it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">27:30</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the tithe'</char></note> is holy to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 27:30"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:31"/>But if a person should by redeeming redeem his tithe, he shall add one-fifth to it, and it shall be his.<verse eid="LEV 27:31"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:32"/>And every tithe of cows and sheep, and everything that may come into the count under the rod-- the tithe shall be holy to the Lord.<verse eid="LEV 27:32"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:33"/>You shall not exchange good for bad. But if by exchanging you exchange it, then its substitute shall be holy; it shall not be redeemed.<verse eid="LEV 27:33"/>

<verse sid="LEV 27:34"/>These are the commandments that the Lord commanded Moyses for the sons of Israel on the mountain Sina.<verse eid="LEV 27:34"/>
</_X_chapter></_X_book></_X_usx>