<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<_X_usx version="2.0">
<para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
<_X_book code="NEH">





<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="NEH 1">
<verse sid="NEH 1:1"/>(2Esdras 11.1) Words of Neemias son of Hachalia. And it happened in the month of Chaseleu, in the twentieth year, and I was in Sousan Habira<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'the citadel'</char></note>,<verse eid="NEH 1:1"/>

<verse sid="NEH 1:2"/>and one of my brothers, Hanani, he and men of Iouda came, and I asked them about those that survived, those who had been left over from the captivity, and about Ierousalem.<verse eid="NEH 1:2"/>

<verse sid="NEH 1:3"/>And they said to me, "Those who are left over from the captivity there in the country are in great trouble and in shame, and the walls of Ierousalem are broken down, and its gates were burned with fire."<verse eid="NEH 1:3"/>

<verse sid="NEH 1:4"/>And it happened, when I heard these words, I sat down and wept and mourned for days, and I was fasting and praying before the God of heaven,<verse eid="NEH 1:4"/>

<verse sid="NEH 1:5"/>And I said, "Nay indeed, O Lord, you the strong and the great and the awesome God of heaven, one who keeps covenant and mercy with those who love him and keep his commandments,<verse eid="NEH 1:5"/>

<verse sid="NEH 1:6"/>let now your ear be attentive and your eyes opened to hear the prayer of your slave that I am praying before you today, day and night, for Israel's sons, your slaves, and I am declaring with regard to the sins of Israel's sons, which we have sinned against you. Both I and my father's house have sinned.<verse eid="NEH 1:6"/>

<verse sid="NEH 1:7"/>In breaking up we broke up with you and did not keep the commandments and the ordinances and the judgments that you commanded your servant Moyses.<verse eid="NEH 1:7"/>

<verse sid="NEH 1:8"/>Remember now the word that you commanded your servant Moyses, saying, 'You, if you are faithless, I will scatter you among the peoples,<verse eid="NEH 1:8"/>

<verse sid="NEH 1:9"/>and if you return to me and keep my commandments and do them, if your dispersion is to the farthest skies, from there I will gather them and lead them to the place where I have chosen my name to encamp there.'<verse eid="NEH 1:9"/>

<verse sid="NEH 1:10"/>And they are your servants and your people, whom you redeemed by your great power and by your strong hand.<verse eid="NEH 1:10"/>

<verse sid="NEH 1:11"/>Nay indeed; rather, let your ear be attentive to the prayer of your slave and to the prayer of your servants who want to revere your name, and give now success to your servant today, and give him over to feelings of<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'give him over to feelings of':  I.e. 'grant that he may be shown'</char></note> compassion before this man!" And I was cupbearer to the king.<verse eid="NEH 1:11"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="NEH 2">
<verse sid="NEH 2:1"/>(2Esdras 12.1) And it happened in the month of Nisan, in the twentieth year of Arthasastha the king. And wine was before me, and I took the wine and gave it to the king, and there was no one else before him.<verse eid="NEH 2:1"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:2"/>And the king said to me, "Why is your face sad," and, "You are not unwell, are you? This is nothing except sadness of the heart." And I was very much afraid.<verse eid="NEH 2:2"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:3"/>And I said to the king, "Let the king live forever! Why should my face not be sad, since the city, the home of my fathers' graves, was laid waste, and its gates have been consumed with fire?"<verse eid="NEH 2:3"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:4"/>And the king said to me, "For what are you looking in this matter?" And I prayed to the God of heaven<verse eid="NEH 2:4"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:5"/>and said to the king, "If it is good to the king and if your servant shall find favor before you so that you send him to Iouda, to the city of my fathers' graves, I will also rebuild it."<verse eid="NEH 2:5"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:6"/>And the king and his concubine who was sitting beside him said, "How long will your journey be, and when will you return?" And it found favor before the king, and he sent me, and I gave him a limit.<verse eid="NEH 2:6"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:7"/>And I said to the king, "If it is good to the king, let him give me letters to the governors beyond the river<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'beyond the river':  Perhaps 'of Beyond the River'</char></note> so that I may go on my way until I arrive in Iouda;<verse eid="NEH 2:7"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:8"/>and a letter to Asaph, the keeper of the park that belongs to the king, so that he will give me timber to cover the gates and for the wall of the city and for the house into which I shall enter it." And the king gave them to me, because the hand of God was good.<verse eid="NEH 2:8"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:9"/>And I came to the governors beyond the river<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'beyond the river':  Perhaps 'of Beyond the River'</char></note> and gave them the king's letters, and the king had sent leaders of the force and horsemen with me.<verse eid="NEH 2:9"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:10"/>And Sanaballat the Haroni and Tobia the slave, the Ammoni, heard it, and it displeased them that a person had come to seek good for the sons of Israel.<verse eid="NEH 2:10"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:11"/>And I came to Ierousalem and was there for three days.<verse eid="NEH 2:11"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:12"/>And I got up during the night, I and a few men with me, and I told no one what God was putting into my heart to do along with Israel, and there is no animal with me except the animal which I ride upon it.<verse eid="NEH 2:12"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:13"/>And I went out by the gate of Golela<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'by night + Valley'</char></note> and to the mouth of the fountain of the figs and to the gate of the dung. And I was crushing in the wall of Ierousalem, which they<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Referent unclear</char></note> are pulling down. And its gates were consumed by fire.<verse eid="NEH 2:13"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:14"/>And I went on to the gate of Ain and in the king's swimming pool, and there was no place for the animal under me to continue.<verse eid="NEH 2:14"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:15"/>And I kept going up in the wall of<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'at'</char></note> the wadi by night and kept crushing in the wall. And I was in the gate of the ravine and returned.<verse eid="NEH 2:15"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:16"/>And those who were guarding did not know why I went and what I was doing, and until then I had not told the Judeans and the priests and the distinguished and the generals and the rest that were doing the work.<verse eid="NEH 2:16"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:17"/>And I said to them, "You see the trouble in which we are in it, how Ierousalem is in ruins, and its gates were given to fire. Come, and let us wall off Ierousalem's wall, and we will no longer suffer disgrace."<verse eid="NEH 2:17"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:18"/>And I reported to them the hand of God that was good upon me and the words that the king had spoken to me, and I said, "Let us arise and build!" And their hands were strengthened for the good.<verse eid="NEH 2:18"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:19"/>And Sanaballat the Haroni and Tobia the slave, the Ammoni, and Gesam the Arabi heard, and they mocked us and came against us and said, "What is this matter that you are doing? Are you rebelling against the king?"<verse eid="NEH 2:19"/>

<verse sid="NEH 2:20"/>And I returned word to them and said to them, "The God of heaven, he will give us success, and we are his pure slaves, and we will build it, and you have no share and righteousness and record in Ierousalem."<verse eid="NEH 2:20"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="NEH 3">
<verse sid="NEH 3:1"/>(2Esdras 13.1) And the great priest Elisoub and his brothers the priests set out and built the sheep gate. They consecrated it and set up its doors, and they consecrated it as far as the tower of the hundred, as far as the tower of Hanameel,<verse eid="NEH 3:1"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:2"/>and at the hand of the sons of the men of Iericho and at the hand of the sons of Zakchour son of Amari.<verse eid="NEH 3:2"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:3"/>And Hasana's sons built the fish gate; they covered it and set up its doors and its bars and its bolts.<verse eid="NEH 3:3"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:4"/>And at their hand, one of Ramoth son of Ouria son of Hakkos took control. And at their hand Mesoulam son of Barachiou son of Masezebel took charge. And at their hand Sadouk son of Baana took charge.<verse eid="NEH 3:4"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:5"/>And at their hand the Thekoim took charge, and the Adoreem did not contribute their neck to their service.<verse eid="NEH 3:5"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:6"/>And Ioida son of Phasek and Mesoulam son of Basodia-- they took control of the gate of Iasana; they covered it and set up its doors and its bars and its bolts.<verse eid="NEH 3:6"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:7"/>And at their hand Maltias the Gabaonite and Euaron the Meronothite, men of Gabaon and of Maspha, took control as far as the throne of the ruler beyond the river<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'beyond the river':  Perhaps 'of Beyond the River'</char></note>.<verse eid="NEH 3:7"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:8"/>And beside them Oziel son of Harachias, one of the smiths, secured things. And at their hand Hananias son of Rokeim took control, and they left Ierousalem alone as far as the broad wall.<verse eid="NEH 3:8"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:9"/>And at their hand Raphaia son of Hour, ruler of half the area around Ierousalem, took control.<verse eid="NEH 3:9"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:10"/>And at their hand and opposite his home Iedaia son of Heromaph took control. And at his hand Hattous son of Hasbania took control.<verse eid="NEH 3:10"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:11"/>And a second Melchias son of Heram and Hasoub son of Phaathmoab took control as far as the tower of the Thannourim.<verse eid="NEH 3:11"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:12"/>And at his hand Salloum son of Halloes, ruler of half the area around Ierousalem, took control, he and his daughters.<verse eid="NEH 3:12"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:13"/>Hanoun and the inhabitants of Zano took control of the gate of the ravine; they built it and set up its doors and its bars and its bolts and a thousand cubits on the wall, as far as the gate of dung.<verse eid="NEH 3:13"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:14"/>And Melchia son of Rechab, ruler of the area around Bethachcharam, took control of the gate of dung, he and his sons, and covered it and set up its doors and its bars and its bolts.<verse eid="NEH 3:14"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:15"/>Then Salomon son of Coleze, ruler of the district of Maspha, fortified the gate of the fountain; he himself built it up and covered it and set up its doors and its bolts, and he built the wall of the pool of the fleeces at the shearing of the king, and as far as the stairs that go down from the city of Dauid.<verse eid="NEH 3:15"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:16"/>Behind him Neemias son of Azbouch, ruler of half the area around Bethsour, took control as far as the garden of the grave of Dauid and as far as the artificial pool and as far as Bethaggabarim.<verse eid="NEH 3:16"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:17"/>Behind him the Leuites took control: Raoum son of Bani, and at his hand Hasabia, ruler of half the area around Keila, took control for his surrounding area.<verse eid="NEH 3:17"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:18"/>After him their brothers took control: Benei son of Hanadad, ruler of half the area around Keila.<verse eid="NEH 3:18"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:19"/>And at his hand Azour son of Iesous, ruler of Masphe, controlled a second section of the tower of ascent, which joins the corner.<verse eid="NEH 3:19"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:20"/>And after him Barouch son of Zabou took control of the next section from the corner to the door of Bethelisoub the great priest.<verse eid="NEH 3:20"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:21"/>And after him Meramoth son of Ouria son of Hakkos controlled a second section from the door of Bethelisoub to where Bethelisoub leaves off.<verse eid="NEH 3:21"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:22"/>And after him the priests, the men of Hachchechar, took control.<verse eid="NEH 3:22"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:23"/>And after him Beniamin and Hasoub took control opposite their house. And after him Azaria son of Maasias son of Anania took control beside his house.<verse eid="NEH 3:23"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:24"/>After him Bani son of Henadad controlled a second section, from Bethazaria to the corner and as far as the bend<verse eid="NEH 3:24"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:25"/>of Phalal son of Euzai from opposite the corner-- and it is<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'it is':  Lacking in Greek</char></note> the upper tower that projects from the house of the king at the court of the guard-- and after him Padaia son of Phoros.<verse eid="NEH 3:25"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:26"/>(And the nathinim<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:26</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'temple servants'</char></note> were dwelling in Ophal as far as the garden of the gate of water to the east. And the tower is<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:26</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> the one projecting.)<verse eid="NEH 3:26"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:27"/>After him the Thekoim took control of a second section from opposite the great projecting tower and as far as the wall of Ophla.<verse eid="NEH 3:27"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:28"/>Above the gate of the horses the priests took control, a man opposite his house.<verse eid="NEH 3:28"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:29"/>After him Saddouk son of Emmer took control opposite his house. And after him Samaia son of Sechenia, the keeper of the gate of the east, took control.<verse eid="NEH 3:29"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:30"/>After him Hanania son of Selemia and Hanom sixth son of Seleph took control of a second section. After him Mesoulam son of Barchia took control opposite his treasure chamber.<verse eid="NEH 3:30"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:31"/>After him Melchia son of Sarephi took control as far as Bethannathinim and the hucksters opposite the gate of Maphekad and as far as the ascent at the bend.<verse eid="NEH 3:31"/>

<verse sid="NEH 3:32"/>And in the midst of the sheep gate the smiths<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:32</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'bronze smiths'</char></note> and the huck-sters took control.<verse eid="NEH 3:32"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="NEH 4">
<verse sid="NEH 4:1"/>(2Esdras 14.1) And it happened, when Sanaballat heard that we were building the wall, and he was upset and greatly enraged, and he mocked at the Judeans.<verse eid="NEH 4:1"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:2"/>And he said in the presence of his brothers, "Is this the power of Somoron, that these Judeans are building the city for themselves? Are they, then, sacrificing? Will they, then, be strong, and will they today repair the scorched stones after they had become the rubbish heap of the land?"<verse eid="NEH 4:2"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:3"/>And Tobias the Ammanite came beside him, and they said to themselves, "They will not sacrifice or eat in their place, will they? Will a fox not go up and break down their stone wall?"<verse eid="NEH 4:3"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:4"/>Hear, O our God, for we have become despised;<verse eid="NEH 4:4"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:5"/>and return their taunt to their heads, and give them over to sneering in a land of captivity;<verse eid="NEH 4:5"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:6"/>and do not cover over lawlessness.<verse eid="NEH 4:6"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:7"/>And it happened, when Sanaballat and Tobia and the Arabs and the Ammanites heard that the stature of the walls of Ierousalem was rising because the gaps were beginning to be closed, and it looked very bad to them.<verse eid="NEH 4:7"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:8"/>And they all gathered together to come and get ready to fight in Ierousalem.<verse eid="NEH 4:8"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:9"/>And we prayed to our God and set up an advance guard against them day and night because of their presence.<verse eid="NEH 4:9"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:10"/>And Ioudas said, "The strength of the enemies was crushed. And there is much rubbish, and we will not be able to build on the wall."<verse eid="NEH 4:10"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:11"/>And those who were afflicting us said, "They will not know and will not see until we come into their midst and kill them and stop the work."<verse eid="NEH 4:11"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:12"/>And it happened, when the Judeans who lived next to them came, and they said to us, "They are coming up against us from all the places."<verse eid="NEH 4:12"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:13"/>And I stationed some into the lowest parts of the space behind the wall, in covered places, and I stationed the people according to divisions, their spears and their bows, with their swords.<verse eid="NEH 4:13"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:14"/>And I looked and stood up and said to the distinguished and to the generals and to the rest of the people, "Do not be afraid from before them. Remember our great and awesome God, and get ready to fight for your brothers, your sons and your daughters and your wives and your homes."<verse eid="NEH 4:14"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:15"/>And it happened, when our enemies heard that it was known to us and that God had scattered their council, and we all returned to the wall, a man to his work.<verse eid="NEH 4:15"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:16"/>And it happened from that day on, half of the outcasts were doing the work and half were standing in defense, and there were spears and oblong shields and the bows and body-armor and the rulers behind every house of Iouda<verse eid="NEH 4:16"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:17"/>belonging to those who were building on the wall. And as for those who were lifting with lifters with weapons-- with one hand he was doing his work and with one he was grasping the javelin.<verse eid="NEH 4:17"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:18"/>And as for the builders-- a man with his sword strapped on his lower back-- and they kept building, and the one who trumpeted with the horn was beside him.<verse eid="NEH 4:18"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:19"/>And I said to the distinguished and to the rulers and to the remainders of the people, "The work is wide-spread and great, and we are far scattered, a man from his brother, on the wall.<verse eid="NEH 4:19"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:20"/>In whatever place you hear the sound of the horn there, you shall gather to us, and our God will fight for us."<verse eid="NEH 4:20"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:21"/>And we were doing the work, and half of them were holding the spears from the rising of the dawn until the coming out of the stars.<verse eid="NEH 4:21"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:22"/>And I said to the people at that time, "Each of you with his young man, pass the night inside Ierousalem, and let the night be an advance guard for you and the day work."<verse eid="NEH 4:22"/>

<verse sid="NEH 4:23"/>And I and the men of the advanced guard behind me were there, and there was not a man of us taking off his clothes.<verse eid="NEH 4:23"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="NEH 5">
<verse sid="NEH 5:1"/>(2Esdras 15.1) And there was a great outcry of the people and their wives against their Judean brothers.<verse eid="NEH 5:1"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:2"/>And there were some, saying, "With our sons and our daughters, we are many, and we will get grain and eat and stay alive."<verse eid="NEH 5:2"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:3"/>And there are some, saying, "As for our fields and our vineyards and our homes-- we are mortgaging them, and we will get grain and eat."<verse eid="NEH 5:3"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:4"/>There are some, saying, "As for our fields and our vineyards and our homes-- we borrowed money for the king's tributes.<verse eid="NEH 5:4"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:5"/>And now our flesh is like the flesh of our brothers; our sons like their sons, and behold we are oppressing our sons and daughters, making them slaves, and some of our daughters are being oppressed, and there is no power in our hands, and our fields and our vineyards belong to the distinguished."<verse eid="NEH 5:5"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:6"/>And I was very distressed as I heard their outcry and these words.<verse eid="NEH 5:6"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:7"/>And my heart deliberated with me, and I quarreled with the distinguished and the rulers and said to them, "Will a man demand back of his brother? You are demanding back." And I held a great assembly for them.<verse eid="NEH 5:7"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:8"/>And I said to them, "We, of our own free-will, have acquired our Judean brothers who were being sold to the nations. And you, are you selling your own brothers, and they shall be handed over to us?" And they were silent and could not find a word.<verse eid="NEH 5:8"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:9"/>And I said, "The matter that you are doing is not good. Not thus! You shall depart in the fear of our God, from the reproach of the nations our enemies.<verse eid="NEH 5:9"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:10"/>And my brothers and my acquaintances and I put up our own money and grain. We certainly abandoned this demanding back.<verse eid="NEH 5:10"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:11"/>Return now to them, this very day, their fields and their vineyards and their olive orchards and their homes. And bring out for yourselves the grain and wine and olive-oil from<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'by means of'</char></note> the money."<verse eid="NEH 5:11"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:12"/>And they said, "We will give these back and not seek these from them. We will do just as you say." And I called the priests and made them swear to do like this word.<verse eid="NEH 5:12"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:13"/>And I shook out the fold of my garment and said, "So may God shake out every man from his house and from his property who does not establish this word, and thus they will be shaken out and emptied." And all the assembly said, "Amen," and praised the Lord, and the people did this word.<verse eid="NEH 5:13"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:14"/>From the day that he commanded me to be their ruler in the land of Iouda, from the twentieth year even to the thirty-second year of Arthasastha, twelve years, I and my brothers did not eat an exaction from them.<verse eid="NEH 5:14"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:15"/>And as for the first exactions, with which they burdened them before me, they also took the last money from them for food and wine, forty didrachmas. And their outcasts exercise authority over the people, and I did not do so, from before fear of God.<verse eid="NEH 5:15"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:16"/>And I did not take control over them by the work on the wall, and I did not acquire a field, and all who were gathered were there for the work.<verse eid="NEH 5:16"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:17"/>And the Judeans, one hundred fifty men, and those who came to us from the nations around us, were at my table.<verse eid="NEH 5:17"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:18"/>And what was prepared for one day was one bull calf, and they were preparing six choice sheep and a goat for me and among ten days wine in abundance with everything, and I did not seek the food of exaction with them, because the service was heavy on this people.<verse eid="NEH 5:18"/>

<verse sid="NEH 5:19"/>Remember me, O God, for good, all that I have done for this people.<verse eid="NEH 5:19"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="NEH 6">
<verse sid="NEH 6:1"/>(2Esdras 16.1) And it happened, when it was heard to Sanaballat and Tobias and to Gesam the Arabi and to the rest of our enemies that I had built the wall, and there was no breath left in them. Up to that time I had not set up the doors in the gates.<verse eid="NEH 6:1"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:2"/>And Sanaballat and Gesam sent to me, saying, "Come, and let us meet together in the villages in the plain of Ono." And they were intending to do me harm.<verse eid="NEH 6:2"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:3"/>And I sent messengers to them, saying, "I am doing a great work, and I will not be able to come down, lest the work stop. Whenever I finish it, I will come down to you."<verse eid="NEH 6:3"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:4"/>And they sent to me like this word, and I sent to them in the same manner.<verse eid="NEH 6:4"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:5"/>And Sanaballat sent his servant to me and an open letter in his hand.<verse eid="NEH 6:5"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:6"/>And in it was written, "It was heard among the nations that you and the Judeans intend to rebel, which is why you are building the wall, and you are becoming their king.<verse eid="NEH 6:6"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:7"/>And besides these, you have set up prophets for yourself so that you might sit in Ierousalem as king in Iouda. And now these words will be reported to the king. And now come, let us confer together."<verse eid="NEH 6:7"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:8"/>And I sent to him, saying, "It did not happen like these words that you say, because you are inventing them out of your own heart."<verse eid="NEH 6:8"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:9"/>Because they all were trying to frighten us, saying, "Their hands will slacken from this work, and it will not be done." But now I strengthened my hands.<verse eid="NEH 6:9"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:10"/>And I went into the house of Semei son of Dalaia son of Metabeel, and he was confined. And he said, "Let us gather together at the house of God, in the midst of it, and let us close its doors, because they are coming by night to kill you."<verse eid="NEH 6:10"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:11"/>And I said, "Should a man like me run away? Or, what kind of man would enter the house and live?"<verse eid="NEH 6:11"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:12"/>And I perceived, and behold, God had not sent him, because the prophecy was a message against me, and Tobias and Sanaballat had hired<verse eid="NEH 6:12"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:13"/>a crowd against me, so I might become afraid and do so and sin and become a bad name for them so they could taunt me.<verse eid="NEH 6:13"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:14"/>Remember, O God, against Tobias and against Sanaballat as these acts of his and against the prophet Noadia and against the rest of the prophets who were trying to make me afraid.<verse eid="NEH 6:14"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:15"/>And the wall was finished on the twenty-fifth of the month Eloul, in fifty-two days.<verse eid="NEH 6:15"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:16"/>And it happened, when all our enemies heard, and all the nations around us were afraid, and fear fell severely on their eyes, and they knew that this work came to be completed with the help of our God.<verse eid="NEH 6:16"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:17"/>And in those days letters were going from many of Iouda's distinguished to Tobias, and those of Tobias were coming to them,<verse eid="NEH 6:17"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:18"/>because many in Iouda were bound by oath to him, because he was the son-in-law of Sechenia son of Erae, and his son Ionathan had taken the daughter of Mesoulam son of Barachia as wife.<verse eid="NEH 6:18"/>

<verse sid="NEH 6:19"/>And they were telling me his words and were conveying my words to him, and Tobias sent letters to intimidate me.<verse eid="NEH 6:19"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="NEH 7">
<verse sid="NEH 7:1"/>(2Esdras 17.1) And it happened, when the wall was built, and I set up the doors, and the gatekeepers and the singers and the Leuites were reviewed.<verse eid="NEH 7:1"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:2"/>And I commanded my brother Hanania and Hanania, ruler of the bira<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'citadel'</char></note> in Ierousalem, because he was like a truthful man and feared God more than many;<verse eid="NEH 7:2"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:3"/>and I said to them, "The gates of Ierousalem will not be opened until at the same as the sun<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'at the same as the sun':  I.e. 'the hottest time of the day'</char></note>, and while they are still keeping watch, let the doors be shut and barred. And appoint advance guards from those living in Ierousalem, a man at his watch and a man opposite his home."<verse eid="NEH 7:3"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:4"/>And the city was wide and large, and the people in it were few, and no homes had been built.<verse eid="NEH 7:4"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:5"/>And God gave it into my heart, and I assembled the distinguished and the rulers and the people into a company. And I found the book of the company-- those who came up at first, and I found written in it:<verse eid="NEH 7:5"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:6"/>And these are sons of the country who went up from the captivity of the exile which Nabouchodonosor, king of Babylon, had exiled, and they returned to Ierousalem and to Iouda, a man to his city;<verse eid="NEH 7:6"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:7"/>with Zorobabel and Iesous, and Neemias, Azaria, Reelma, Naemani, Mardochaios, Balsan, Maaspharath, Esdras, Bagouiai, Naoum, Baana, Masphar, men of the people of Israel:<verse eid="NEH 7:7"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:8"/>Sons of Phoros, two thousand one hundred seventy-two.<verse eid="NEH 7:8"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:9"/>Sons of Saphatia, three hundred seventy-two.<verse eid="NEH 7:9"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:10"/>Sons of Era, six hundred fifty-two.<verse eid="NEH 7:10"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:11"/>Sons of Phaathmoab, in reference to the sons of Iesous and Ioab, two thousand eight hundred eighteen.<verse eid="NEH 7:11"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:12"/>Sons of Ailam, one thousand two hundred fifty-four.<verse eid="NEH 7:12"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:13"/>Sons of Zaththouia, eight hundred forty-five.<verse eid="NEH 7:13"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:14"/>Sons of Zakchou, seven hundred sixty.<verse eid="NEH 7:14"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:15"/>Sons of Banoui, six hundred forty-eight.<verse eid="NEH 7:15"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:16"/>Sons of Bebei, six hundred twenty-eight.<verse eid="NEH 7:16"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:17"/>Sons of Azgad, two thousand three hundred twenty-two.<verse eid="NEH 7:17"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:18"/>Sons of Adonikam, six hundred sixty-seven.<verse eid="NEH 7:18"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:19"/>Sons of Bagoui, two thousand sixty-seven.<verse eid="NEH 7:19"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:20"/>Sons of Edin, six hundred fifty-four.<verse eid="NEH 7:20"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:21"/>Sons of Ater, in reference to Hezekias, ninety-eight.<verse eid="NEH 7:21"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:22"/>Sons of Hesami, three hundred twenty-eight.<verse eid="NEH 7:22"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:23"/>Sons of Basi, three hundred twenty-four.<verse eid="NEH 7:23"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:24"/>Sons of Hariph, one hundred twelve. Sons of Hasen, two hundred twenty-three.<verse eid="NEH 7:24"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:25"/>Sons of Gabaon, ninety-five.<verse eid="NEH 7:25"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:26"/>Sons of Baithleem, one hundred twenty three. Sons of Netopha, fifty six.<verse eid="NEH 7:26"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:27"/>Sons of Anathoth, one hundred twenty-eight.<verse eid="NEH 7:27"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:28"/>Men of Beth, forty-two.<verse eid="NEH 7:28"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:29"/>Men of Kariathiarim, Chaphira and Beroth, seven hundred forty-three.<verse eid="NEH 7:29"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:30"/>Men of Harama and Gabaa, six hundred twenty-one.<verse eid="NEH 7:30"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:31"/>Men of Machmas, one hundred twenty-two.<verse eid="NEH 7:31"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:32"/>Men of Baithel and Ai, one hundred twenty-three.<verse eid="NEH 7:32"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:33"/>Men of Nabiar, fifty-two. Sons of Magebos, one hundred fifty-six.<verse eid="NEH 7:33"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:34"/>Men of Elamaar, one thousand two hundred fifty-four.<verse eid="NEH 7:34"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:35"/>Sons of Heram, three hundred twenty.<verse eid="NEH 7:35"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:36"/>Sons of Iericho, three hundred forty-five.<verse eid="NEH 7:36"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:37"/>Sons of Lod, Hadid and Ono, seven hundred twenty-one.<verse eid="NEH 7:37"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:38"/>Sons of Sanana, three thousand nine hundred thirty.<verse eid="NEH 7:38"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:39"/>The priests: sons of Iodae, for the house of Iesous, nine hundred seventy-three.<verse eid="NEH 7:39"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:40"/>Sons of Emmer, one thousand fifty-two.<verse eid="NEH 7:40"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:41"/>Sons of Phaseour, one thousand two hundred forty-seven.<verse eid="NEH 7:41"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:42"/>Sons of Heram, one thousand seventeen.<verse eid="NEH 7:42"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:43"/>The Leuites: sons of Iesous, in reference to Kadmiel, in reference to the sons of Houdouia, seventy-four.<verse eid="NEH 7:43"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:44"/>The singers: sons of Asaph, one hundred forty-eight.<verse eid="NEH 7:44"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:45"/>The gatekeepers: sons of Selloum, sons of Ater, sons of Tolmon, sons of Akoub, sons of Hatita, sons of Sabi, one hundred thirty-eight.<verse eid="NEH 7:45"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:46"/>The nathinim<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:46</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'temple servants'</char></note>: sons of Siaa, sons of Hasipha, sons of Tabbaoth;<verse eid="NEH 7:46"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:47"/>sons of Kiras, sons of Siaia, sons of Phadon;<verse eid="NEH 7:47"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:48"/>sons of Labana, sons of Hangaba, sons of Akoud, sons of Outa, sons of Ketar, sons of Hagab, sons of Selmei;<verse eid="NEH 7:48"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:49"/>sons of Hanan, sons of Sadel, sons of Gaar;<verse eid="NEH 7:49"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:50"/>sons of Raaia, sons of Rason, sons of Nekoda;<verse eid="NEH 7:50"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:51"/>sons of Gezam, sons of Ozi, sons of Phese;<verse eid="NEH 7:51"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:52"/>sons of Besi, sons of Meinom, sons of Nephosasim;<verse eid="NEH 7:52"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:53"/>sons of Bakbouk, sons of Hachipha, sons of Harour;<verse eid="NEH 7:53"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:54"/>sons of Basaloth, sons of Meida, sons of Hadasan;<verse eid="NEH 7:54"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:55"/>sons of Barkous, sons of Sisarath, sons of Thema;<verse eid="NEH 7:55"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:56"/>sons of Nisia, sons of Hatipha.<verse eid="NEH 7:56"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:57"/>Sons of Salomon's slaves: sons of Soutei, sons of Sapharath, sons of Pherida;<verse eid="NEH 7:57"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:58"/>sons of Ieale, sons of Dorkon, sons of Gaddel;<verse eid="NEH 7:58"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:59"/>sons of Saphatia, sons of Hettel, sons of Phacharath, sons of Sabaim, sons of Emim.<verse eid="NEH 7:59"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:60"/>All the nathinim<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:60</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'temple servants'</char></note> and sons of Salomon's slaves, three hundred ninety-two.<verse eid="NEH 7:60"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:61"/>And these went up from Thermelech, Thelaresa, Cheroub, Eron, Iemmer, and they could not declare their paternal houses and their seed, whether they were from Israel:<verse eid="NEH 7:61"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:62"/>sons of Dalaia, sons of Boua, sons of Tobia, sons of Nekoda, six hundred forty-two.<verse eid="NEH 7:62"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:63"/>And from the priests: sons of Hebia, sons of Hakkos, sons of Berzellai (because they had taken of the daughters of Berzellai the Galaadite as wives and were called by their name).<verse eid="NEH 7:63"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:64"/>These sought their registration of the company, and it was not found, and they were made near kin from the priesthood;<verse eid="NEH 7:64"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:65"/>and Hathersatha spoke so that they would not eat from the holy of holies until the priest should arise to enlighten.<verse eid="NEH 7:65"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:66"/>And all the assembly was as one, forty-two thousand three hundred sixty;<verse eid="NEH 7:66"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:67"/>apart from their male and female slaves-- these were seven thousand three hundred thirty-seven and two hundred forty-five male singers and female singers--<verse eid="NEH 7:67"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:68"/>seven hundred thirty-six horses, two hundred forty-five mules;<verse eid="NEH 7:68"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:69"/>four hundred thirty-five camels, six thousand seven hundred twenty donkeys.<verse eid="NEH 7:69"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:70"/>And some of a portion of the leaders of paternal families contributed to the work of Hathersatha, they contributed to the treasury one thousand gold coins, fifty saucers and thirty chothonoth<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:70</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'robes'</char></note> of the priests.<verse eid="NEH 7:70"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:71"/>And some of the leaders of paternal families gave to the building fund twenty thousand gold coins and two thousand two hundred minas of silver;<verse eid="NEH 7:71"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:72"/>and the rest of the people gave twenty thousand gold coins, two thousand two hundred minas<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:72</char><char closed="false" style="ft">one mina = 100 drachmas</char></note> of silver and sixty-seven chothonoth<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:72</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'robes'</char></note> of the priests.<verse eid="NEH 7:72"/>

<verse sid="NEH 7:73"/>And the priests and the Leuites and the gatekeepers and the singers and those from the people and the nathinim<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:73</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'temple servants'</char></note> and all Israel settled in their cities.<verse eid="NEH 7:73"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="NEH 8">
<verse sid="NEH 8:1"/>(2Esdras 18.1) And the seventh month came, and the sons of Israel were in their cities, and all the people gathered together as one man into the square that is before the gate of the water, and they told Esdras the scribe to bring the book of the law of Moyses, which the Lord had commanded Israel.<verse eid="NEH 8:1"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:2"/>And Esdras the priest brought the law before the assembly, from man to woman and every person who understands, to listen on the first day of the seventh month;<verse eid="NEH 8:2"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:3"/>and he read in it from the hour the sun dawned until half the day, opposite the men and the women, and they were understanding, and the ears of all the people were unto the book of the law.<verse eid="NEH 8:3"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:4"/>And Esdras the scribe stood on a wooden platform, and beside him stood Mattathias and Samaias and Hananias and Ouria and Helkia and Maasia on his right hand, and Phadaias and Misael and Melchias and Hosam and Hasabdama and Zacharias and Mesoulam on the left hand.<verse eid="NEH 8:4"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:5"/>And Esdras opened the book before all the people, because he was above the people, and it happened, when he opened it, all the people stood.<verse eid="NEH 8:5"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:6"/>And Esdras blessed the Lord, the great God, and all the people answered and said, "Amen," lifting up their hands, and they bowed and did obeisance to the Lord with their face to the ground.<verse eid="NEH 8:6"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:7"/>And Iesous and Banaias and Sarabia were instructing; Akoub, Sabbathaios, Kallitas, Azarias, Iozabad, Hanani, Phalaias and the Leuites tutored the people in the law, and the people kept their stance.<verse eid="NEH 8:7"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:8"/>And they read from the book of the law of God, and Esdras was teaching and expanding on the knowledge of the Lord, and the people understood during the reading.<verse eid="NEH 8:8"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:9"/>And Neemias said, and Esdras the priest and scribe and the Leuites and those who were instructing the people, and they said to all the people, "A holy day it is to the Lord our God; do not mourn, and do not weep." Because all the people were weeping when they heard the words of the law.<verse eid="NEH 8:9"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:10"/>And he said to them, "Go, eat fat, and drink sweet wine, and send portions to those who do not have, because the day is holy to our Lord, and do not err, because he is our strength."<verse eid="NEH 8:10"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:11"/>And the Leuites tried to still all the people, saying, "Be quiet, because the day is holy, and do not be downcast."<verse eid="NEH 8:11"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:12"/>And all the people went away to eat and to drink and to send portions and to make great rejoicing, because they had understood by the words that were made known to them.<verse eid="NEH 8:12"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:13"/>And on the second day the chiefs of paternal families of all the people, the priests and the Leuites, gathered together to Esdras the scribe, to give their attention to all the words of the law.<verse eid="NEH 8:13"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:14"/>And they found it written in the law, which the Lord had commanded Moyses, that sons of Israel should live in tents during a feast of the seventh month<verse eid="NEH 8:14"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:15"/>and that they should sound with trumpets in all their cities and in Ierousalem. And Esdras said, "Go out to the mountain and bring foliage of olive trees and foliage of cypress wood and foliage of myrtle and foliage of palm and foliage of the leafy tree to make tents, in accord with what is written."<verse eid="NEH 8:15"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:16"/>And the people went out and brought them and made tents for themselves, a man on his housetop, and in their courts and in the courts of the house of God and in the squares of the city and as far as the house of Ephraim.<verse eid="NEH 8:16"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:17"/>And all the assembly, those who had returned from the captivity, made tents and lived in tents, because from the days of Iesous son of Naue to that day sons of Israel had not done so. And there was very great rejoicing.<verse eid="NEH 8:17"/>

<verse sid="NEH 8:18"/>And day by day, from the first day to the last day, he read from the book of the law of God, and they kept the feast seven days, and on the eighth day there was a finale, according to the judgment.<verse eid="NEH 8:18"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="NEH 9">
<verse sid="NEH 9:1"/>(2Esdras 19.1) And on the twenty-fourth of this month the sons of Israel gathered with fasting and in sackcloth and with ashes on their head.<verse eid="NEH 9:1"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:2"/>And the sons of Israel were separated from every foreign son, and they stood and declared their sins and the acts of lawlessness of their fathers.<verse eid="NEH 9:2"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:3"/>And they kept their stance and read in the book of the law of the Lord, their God, and they were declaring to the Lord and doing obeisance to the Lord, their God.<verse eid="NEH 9:3"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:4"/>And Iesous and the sons of Kadmiel, Sechenia the son of Sarabia, sons of Chanani, stood at the ascent of the Leuites and cried out with a loud voice to the Lord their God.<verse eid="NEH 9:4"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:5"/>And the Leuites, Iesous and Kadmiel, said, "Stand up. Bless the Lord, our God, from everlasting and to everlasting, and they will bless your glorious name and exalt it with every blessing and praise."<verse eid="NEH 9:5"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:6"/>And Esdras said: "You yourself are the Lord alone; you made heaven and the heaven of heaven and all their position, the earth and all that is on it, the seas and all that is in them, and you give everything life, and the armies of the heavens do obeisance to you.<verse eid="NEH 9:6"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:7"/>You are the Lord God. You made a choice in Abram and brought him out of the country of the Chaldeans and made for him a name, Abraam;<verse eid="NEH 9:7"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:8"/>and you found his heart faithful before you and made a covenant with him to give him and his seed the land of the Chananites and Chettites and Amorrites and Pherezites and Iebousites and Gergesites, and you have established your word, because you are righteous.<verse eid="NEH 9:8"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:9"/>"And you saw the humiliation of our ancestors in Egypt and heard their cry at the Red Sea.<verse eid="NEH 9:9"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:10"/>And you gave signs in Egypt against Pharao and against all his servants and against all the people of his land, because you knew that they acted insolently against them, and you made a name for yourself, as this day.<verse eid="NEH 9:10"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:11"/>And you broke asunder the sea before them, and they passed through in the midst of the sea on dry land, and those who pursued them closely you threw into the depths, like a stone in violent water.<verse eid="NEH 9:11"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:12"/>And by day you led them with a pillar of cloud, and during the night with a pillar of fire, to give them light on the way in which they should go in it.<verse eid="NEH 9:12"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:13"/>And you came down upon Mount Sina and spoke to them from heaven and gave them straightforward judgments and laws of truth and ordinances and good commandments.<verse eid="NEH 9:13"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:14"/>And you made known your holy sabbath to them; you commanded them commandments and ordinances and law by the hand of your slave Moyses.<verse eid="NEH 9:14"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:15"/>And you gave them bread from heaven in their famine, and you brought water for them out of the rock for their thirst. And you told them to go in to possess the land to which you stretched out your hand to give them.<verse eid="NEH 9:15"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:16"/>"And they and our fathers behaved arrogantly and stiffened their neck and did not listen to your commandments;<verse eid="NEH 9:16"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:17"/>and they refused to obey and were not mindful of your wonders that you performed with them, and they stiffened their neck, and they gave<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'made'</char></note> a beginning to return to their slavery in Egypt. And you are the God who forgives sins, is gracious and merciful, slow to anger and very gracious, and you did not forsake them.<verse eid="NEH 9:17"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:18"/>Furthermore, they made a cast-metal bull calf for themselves and said, 'These are the gods who brought us up out of Egypt' and committed great provocations.<verse eid="NEH 9:18"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:19"/>And you in your great mercies did not forsake them in the wilderness; you did not turn away from them the pillar of cloud for leading them on the way by day and the pillar of fire to lighten for them the way in which they should go in it during the night.<verse eid="NEH 9:19"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:20"/>And you gave your good spirit to instruct them and did not withhold your manna from their mouth and gave them water in their thirst.<verse eid="NEH 9:20"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:21"/>And forty years you sustained them in the wilderness; there was no lack of anything for them; their clothes did not grow old, and their sandals did not tear.<verse eid="NEH 9:21"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:22"/>And you gave them kingdoms and allotted them peoples, and they took possession of the land of Seon, king of Hesebon, and the land of Og, king of Basan.<verse eid="NEH 9:22"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:23"/>And you multiplied their sons like the stars of heaven and brought them into the land about which you told their fathers, and they possessed it.<verse eid="NEH 9:23"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:24"/>And you wiped out before them the inhabitants of the land of the Chananites and gave them and their kings and the peoples of the land into their hands, to do with them as was pleasing before them.<verse eid="NEH 9:24"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:25"/>And they captured lofty cities and took possession of homes filled with all sorts of goods, hewn cisterns, vineyards and olive orchards and every sort of fruit tree in abundance, and they ate and were filled and became fat and were nourished on your great goodness.<verse eid="NEH 9:25"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:26"/>"And they changed and departed from you and cast your law behind their body and killed your prophets, who had warned them to turn them back to you, and they committed great provocations.<verse eid="NEH 9:26"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:27"/>And you gave them into the hand of their oppressors, and they oppressed them. And they cried out to you in their time of oppression, and you heard from your heaven, and through your great mercies you gave them deliverers and delivered them from the hand of their oppressors.<verse eid="NEH 9:27"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:28"/>And after they rested, they returned to doing what is evil before you, and you abandoned them to the hands of their enemies, and they ruled among them. And again they cried to you, and you listened from heaven and rescued them by your many mercies.<verse eid="NEH 9:28"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:29"/>And you repeatedly warned them in order to turn them to your law, and they did not listen but sinned against your commandments and judgments by the doing of which a person shall live by them. And they presented a disobedient back and stiffened their neck and did not listen.<verse eid="NEH 9:29"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:30"/>And many years you lasted with them and repeatedly warned them by your spirit by the hand of your prophets, and they did not give ear, and you gave them into the hand of the peoples of the land.<verse eid="NEH 9:30"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:31"/>And in your many mercies you did not make an end of them and forsake them, because you are strong and merciful and compassionate.<verse eid="NEH 9:31"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:32"/>"And now, our strong, great, mighty and awesome God, in keeping the covenant and your mercy, let all the hardship not be treated lightly before you, which found us and our kings and our rulers and our priests and our prophets and our fathers and among all your people from the days of the kings of Assour even until this day.<verse eid="NEH 9:32"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:33"/>And you are just in all that has come upon us, for you have dealt truthfully, and we did wrong.<verse eid="NEH 9:33"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:34"/>And our kings and our rulers and our priests and our fathers did not practice your law and did not heed your commandments or your testimonies about which you repeatedly warned them.<verse eid="NEH 9:34"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:35"/>And even they-- in your rule and in your great goodness that you bestowed on them and in the broad and rich land that you set before them-- were not subject to you and did not turn from their wicked habits.<verse eid="NEH 9:35"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:36"/>Behold, we are slaves today, and the land that you gave to our fathers to eat its fruit<verse eid="NEH 9:36"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:37"/>belongs to the kings whom you gave over us because of our sins, and they have power over our bodies and over our animals as seems best to them, and we are in great affliction."<verse eid="NEH 9:37"/>

<verse sid="NEH 9:38"/>And by all these things we are setting forth a pledge of faith and are writing it down, and all our rulers, our Leuites, our priests are sealing it.<verse eid="NEH 9:38"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="NEH 10">
<verse sid="NEH 10:1"/>(2Esdras 20.1) And over those affixing seals were Neemias son of Hachalia and Sedekias<verse eid="NEH 10:1"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:2"/>son of Saraia and Azaria and Ieremia;<verse eid="NEH 10:2"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:3"/>Phasour, Amaria, Melchia;<verse eid="NEH 10:3"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:4"/>Hattous, Sebani, Malouch,<verse eid="NEH 10:4"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:5"/>Hiram, Meramoth, Abdia;<verse eid="NEH 10:5"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:6"/>Daniel, Gaannathon, Barouch;<verse eid="NEH 10:6"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:7"/>Mesoulam, Abia, Miamin;<verse eid="NEH 10:7"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:8"/>Maazia, Belgai, Samaia-- these are priests.<verse eid="NEH 10:8"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:9"/>And the Leuites were Iesous son of Azania, Banaiou of Banaiou's sons of Henadad's sons, Kadmiel<verse eid="NEH 10:9"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:10"/>and his brothers, Sabania, Hodouia, Kalitan, Pheleia, Hanan,<verse eid="NEH 10:10"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:11"/>Micha, Roob, Hesebias;<verse eid="NEH 10:11"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:12"/>Zakchor, Sarabia, Sebania;<verse eid="NEH 10:12"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:13"/>Hodoua, sons of Banounai.<verse eid="NEH 10:13"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:14"/>The rulers of the people were Phoros, Phaathmoab, Elam, Zaththouia. The sons of Bani were<verse eid="NEH 10:14"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:15"/>Azgad, Bebai,<verse eid="NEH 10:15"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:16"/>Adania, Bagoi, Edin,<verse eid="NEH 10:16"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:17"/>Ater, Hezekia, Azour,<verse eid="NEH 10:17"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:18"/>Hodouia, Hesam, Besi;<verse eid="NEH 10:18"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:19"/>Hariph, Anathoth, Nobai;<verse eid="NEH 10:19"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:20"/>Magaphes, Mesoulam, Hezir;<verse eid="NEH 10:20"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:21"/>Mesozebel, Sadouk, Ieddoua;<verse eid="NEH 10:21"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:22"/>Phaltia, Hanan, Anaia;<verse eid="NEH 10:22"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:23"/>Hosee, Hanania, Hasoub;<verse eid="NEH 10:23"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:24"/>Haloes, Phalai, Sobek,<verse eid="NEH 10:24"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:25"/>Raoum, Hesabana, Maasaia<verse eid="NEH 10:25"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:26"/>and Aia, Hainan, Enan;<verse eid="NEH 10:26"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:27"/>Malouch, Reoum and Baana.<verse eid="NEH 10:27"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:28"/>And the rest of the people, the priests, the Leuites, the gatekeepers, the singers, the nathinim<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:28</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'temple servants'</char></note> and every one who adheres to the law of God from the people of the land, their wives, their sons, their daughters, every one who knows and understands,<verse eid="NEH 10:28"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:29"/>were prevailing against their brothers, and they cursed them and entered into a curse and an oath to go in God's law, which was given by the hand of Moyses the slave of God, to observe and to do all the commandments of the Lord and his judgments;<verse eid="NEH 10:29"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:30"/>and in order not to give our daughters to the peoples of the land. And we will not take their daughters for our sons.<verse eid="NEH 10:30"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:31"/>And the peoples of the land who bring in merchandise and any sale on the sabbath day to sell, we will not buy from them on the sabbath and on a holy day. And we will release the seventh year and a claim of every hand.<verse eid="NEH 10:31"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:32"/>And we will lay on ourselves the commandments to charge ourselves yearly one-third of a didrachma<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:32</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'two-drachma coin'</char></note> for the service of the house of our God<verse eid="NEH 10:32"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:33"/>for the loaves of the presence and the sacrifice of perpetuity and for the whole burnt offering of perpetuity of the sabbaths, of the new moons, for the feasts and for the sacred things and the items for sin to make atonement for Israel and for the projects of the house of our God.<verse eid="NEH 10:33"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:34"/>And we, the priests and the Leuites and the people, have cast lots for the assignment of carrying wood, to bring it for the house of our God, for the houses of our paternal families, for seasons of the times, year by year, to burn on the altar of the Lord our God, as it is written in the law;<verse eid="NEH 10:34"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:35"/>and to bring the first products of our land and the first products of the fruit of every tree, year by year, to the house of the Lord,<verse eid="NEH 10:35"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:36"/>and to the house of our God for the priests who minister in the house of our God, the firstborn of our sons and of our livestock, as it is written in the law, and the firstborn of our cattle and of our flocks.<verse eid="NEH 10:36"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:37"/>We will bring the first fruit of our grain and the fruit of every tree, wine and oil, for the priests, to the treasure chamber of the house of God, and the tithes of our soil for the Leuites. And the Leuites themselves are collecting the tithes in all the cities of our service;<verse eid="NEH 10:37"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:38"/>and the priest, the son of Aaron, shall be with the Leuite in the tithe of the Leuite, and the Leuites shall bring up the tithe of the tithe to the house of our God, to the treasure chambers at the house of God.<verse eid="NEH 10:38"/>

<verse sid="NEH 10:39"/>Because the sons of Israel and the sons of Leui shall bring into the storerooms the first fruits of the grain and wine and the oil, and the holy vessels and the priests that minister and the gatekeepers and the singers are there. And we will not neglect the house of our God.<verse eid="NEH 10:39"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="NEH 11">
<verse sid="NEH 11:1"/>(2Esdras 21.1) And the rulers of the people lived in Ierousalem, and the rest of the people cast lots to bring one out of ten to live in Ierousalem, the holy city, and nine-tenths remained in the other cities.<verse eid="NEH 11:1"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:2"/>And the people blessed all the men who willingly offered to live in Ierousalem.<verse eid="NEH 11:2"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:3"/>And these are the rulers of the province who lived in Ierousalem and in the cities of Iouda: they lived, a man on his holding, in their cities: Israel, the priests and the Leuites and the nathineans<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'temple servants'</char></note> and sons of Salomon's slaves.<verse eid="NEH 11:3"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:4"/>And in Ierousalem lived some of the sons of Iouda and some of the sons of Beniamin. Of Iouda's sons: Athaia son of Ozia-- he being a son of Zacharia-- he being a son of Amaria-- he being a son of Saphatia-- he being a son of Maleleel, and some sons of Phares.<verse eid="NEH 11:4"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:5"/>And Maasia son of Barouch-- he being son of Chalaza-- he being son of Ozia-- he being son of Adaias-- he being son of Ioiarib-- he being son of Zacharias-- he being a son of the Seloni.<verse eid="NEH 11:5"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:6"/>All the sons of Phares, who lived in Ierousalem, were four hundred sixty-eight men of power.<verse eid="NEH 11:6"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:7"/>And these are sons of Beniamin: Selo son of Mesoulam-- he being a son of Ioad-- he being a son of Phadaia-- he being a son of Koleia-- he being a son of Maasias-- he being a son of Aithiel-- he being a son of Iessia.<verse eid="NEH 11:7"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:8"/>And after him Gebi, Seli, nine hundred twenty-eight.<verse eid="NEH 11:8"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:9"/>And Joel son of Zechri was overseer over them, and Ioudas son of Hasana from the city was second.<verse eid="NEH 11:9"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:10"/>From the priests: also Iadia son of Ioarim, Iachin;<verse eid="NEH 11:10"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:11"/>Saraia son of Helkia-- he being a son of Mesoulam-- he being a son of Saddouk-- he being a son of Marioth-- he being a son of Aitob, opposite the house of God.<verse eid="NEH 11:11"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:12"/>And their brothers who did the work of the house: Amasi son of Zacharia-- he being a son of Phaseour-- he being a son of Melchia;<verse eid="NEH 11:12"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:13"/>and his brothers, chiefs of paternal families, two hundred forty-two. And Amessai son of Esdriel<verse eid="NEH 11:13"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:14"/>and his brothers, powerful in battle, one hundred twenty-eight, and the overseer over them was Zechriel son of the great men.<verse eid="NEH 11:14"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:15"/>And from the Leuites: Samaia son of Hasoub-- he being a son of Ezri<verse eid="NEH 11:15"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="NEH 11:16"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="NEH 11:16"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:17"/>and Maththanias son of Micha and Iobeb son of Samoui;<verse eid="NEH 11:17"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:18"/>two hundred eighty-four.<verse eid="NEH 11:18"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:19"/>And the gatekeepers, Akoub, Telamin and their brothers were one hundred seventy-two.<verse eid="NEH 11:19"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="NEH 11:20"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="NEH 11:20"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="NEH 11:21"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="NEH 11:21"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:22"/>And the overseer of the Leuites was son of Bani, Ozi son of Hasabia-- he being son of Micha, from the sons of Asaph, who sing opposite the work of the house of God;<verse eid="NEH 11:22"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:23"/>because there was a command of the king for them.<verse eid="NEH 11:23"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:24"/>And Phathaia son of Baseza was at <note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'the service of the king for every word concerning the people'</char></note>the king's hand for every word for<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'word for':  Or 'pronouncement to'</char></note> the peopleb<verse eid="NEH 11:24"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:25"/>and went to the country villages, in their field. And some of the sons of Iouda lived in Kariatharbok<verse eid="NEH 11:25"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:26"/>and in Iesou<verse eid="NEH 11:26"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:27"/>and in Bersabee,<verse eid="NEH 11:27"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="NEH 11:28"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:28</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="NEH 11:28"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="NEH 11:29"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:29</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="NEH 11:29"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:30"/>and their country villages were Lacheis and its fields, and they camped in Bersabee.<verse eid="NEH 11:30"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:31"/>And sons of Beniamin were from Gabaa, Machmas.<verse eid="NEH 11:31"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="NEH 11:32"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:32</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="NEH 11:32"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="NEH 11:33"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:33</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="NEH 11:33"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="NEH 11:34"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:34</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="NEH 11:34"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="NEH 11:35"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:35</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="NEH 11:35"/>

<verse sid="NEH 11:36"/>And from the Leuites were divisions of Iouda for Beniamin.<verse eid="NEH 11:36"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="NEH 12">
<verse sid="NEH 12:1"/>(2Esdras 22.1) And these are the priests and the Leuites who went up with Zorobabel son of Salathiel and Iesous: Saraia, Iermia, Esdra;<verse eid="NEH 12:1"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:2"/>Amaria, Malouch;<verse eid="NEH 12:2"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:3"/>Sechenia.<verse eid="NEH 12:3"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="NEH 12:4"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="NEH 12:4"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="NEH 12:5"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="NEH 12:5"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="NEH 12:6"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="NEH 12:6"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:7"/>These were the rulers of the priests and their brothers in the days of Iesous.<verse eid="NEH 12:7"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:8"/>And the Leuites: Iesou, Banoui, Kadmiel, Sarabia, Iodae, Maththania. He was over<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'in charge of'</char></note> the hands, and their brothers were in the daily divisions.<verse eid="NEH 12:8"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="NEH 12:9"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="NEH 12:9"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:10"/>And Iesous begat Ioakim, and Ioakim begat Eliasib, and Eliasib, Iodae;<verse eid="NEH 12:10"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:11"/>and Iodae begat Ionathan and Ionathan begat Iadou.<verse eid="NEH 12:11"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:12"/>And in the days of Ioakim, his brothers, the priests and chiefs of paternal families were: for Saraia, Amaria; for Iermia, Hanania;<verse eid="NEH 12:12"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:13"/>for Esdra, Mesoulam; for Amaria, Ioanan;<verse eid="NEH 12:13"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:14"/>for Amalouch, Ionathan; for Sechenia, Ioseph;<verse eid="NEH 12:14"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:15"/>for Harem, Hannas; for Marioth, Helkai;<verse eid="NEH 12:15"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:16"/>for Addai, Zacharias; for Ganathoth, Mesoulam;<verse eid="NEH 12:16"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:17"/>for Abia, Zechri; for Beniamin, in the times of Peleti;<verse eid="NEH 12:17"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:18"/>for Balga, Samoue; for Semeias, Ionathan;<verse eid="NEH 12:18"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:19"/>for Iarim, Maththania; for Idia, Ozi;<verse eid="NEH 12:19"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:20"/>for Salai, Kallai; for Amek, Abed;<verse eid="NEH 12:20"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:21"/>for Helkia, Hasabias; for Iedeiou, Nathanael.<verse eid="NEH 12:21"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:22"/>The Leuites, in the days of Eliasib, Ioada and Ioa and Ioanan and Idoua, were recorded as the chiefs of paternal families and priests in the reign of Darius the Persian:<verse eid="NEH 12:22"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:23"/>sons of Leui were chiefs of paternal families, having been recorded in the book of the words of the days, even until the days of Ionan son of Elisoue.<verse eid="NEH 12:23"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:24"/>And the rulers of the Leuites, Hasabia and Sarabia and Iesou and sons of Kadmiel, and their brothers were over against them, to sing hymns and to praise, by the commandment of Dauid the man of God, class with class;<verse eid="NEH 12:24"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:25"/>when I gathered the gatekeepers<verse eid="NEH 12:25"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:26"/>in the days of Ioakim son of Iesous son of Iosedek and in the days of Neemias. And Esdras was the priest and the scribe.<verse eid="NEH 12:26"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:27"/>And at the rededications of the wall of Ierousalem they sought the Leuites in their places, to bring them to Ierousalem, to celebrate the rededications and the merriment with thodatha<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:27</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'thanksgivings'</char></note> and with odes, while playing the cymbal and harps and cinyras<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:27</char><char closed="false" style="ft">= Hebrew 'kinnor' = 'lyre'</char></note>.<verse eid="NEH 12:27"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:28"/>And the sons of the singers and some from the region that circles around Ierousalem and some from villages<verse eid="NEH 12:28"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:29"/>and some from the fields gathered, because the singers in Ierousalem built the villages for themselves.<verse eid="NEH 12:29"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:30"/>And the priests and the Leuites were purified, and they purified the people, the gatekeepers and the wall.<verse eid="NEH 12:30"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:31"/>And they brought the rulers of Iouda up onto the wall and appointed two great ones<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:31</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'companies'; Greek = masc.</char></note> concerning praise and went through to the right on the wall of dung;<verse eid="NEH 12:31"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:32"/>and after them went Hosaia and half the rulers of Iouda<verse eid="NEH 12:32"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:33"/>and Azarias, Esdra and Mesoulam;<verse eid="NEH 12:33"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:34"/>Iouda and Beniamin and Samaias and Ieremia<verse eid="NEH 12:34"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:35"/>and some of the sons of priests with trumpets: Zacharias son of Ionathan-- being a son of Samaia-- being a son of Maththania-- being a son of Michaia-- being a son of Zakchour-- being a son of Asaph;<verse eid="NEH 12:35"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:36"/>and his brothers were Samaia and Oziel, Gelolia, Maaia, Nathanael and Ioudas, Hanani, so that they might sing with the songs of Dauid the man of God, and Esdras the scribe was in front of them<verse eid="NEH 12:36"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:37"/>at the gate of Ain, opposite them, and they went up to the stairs of the city of Dauid, in the ascent of the wall above the house of Dauid and as far as the gate of water in the east.<verse eid="NEH 12:37"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:38"/>And concerning praise, the second one<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:38</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'company'; Greek = fem</char></note> meeting them went out, and I followed it, and half of the people were on the wall above the tower of the Thennorim even as far as the broad wall<verse eid="NEH 12:38"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:39"/>and above the gate of Ephraim and to the Eisiana gate and to the fish gate and at the tower of Hanameel and from the tower of Mea, even as far as the sheep gate, and they stood in the gate of the guard.<verse eid="NEH 12:39"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:40"/>And the two<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:40</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'companies'; Greek = fem</char></note> of praise stood in the house of God, and I and half of the generals with me<verse eid="NEH 12:40"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:41"/>and the priests Eliakim, Maasias, Beniamin, Michaias, Elionai, Zacharias, Hananias<verse eid="NEH 12:41"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:42"/>and Semeias and Eleazar and Ozias and Ioanna and Melchias and Ailam and Ezour and the singers were heard and reviewed.<verse eid="NEH 12:42"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:43"/>And they offered great sacrifices on that day and rejoiced, because God made them rejoice greatly, and their wives and their children rejoiced, and the joy in Ierousalem was heard from far away.<verse eid="NEH 12:43"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:44"/>And on that day they appointed men over the treasure chambers for stores, for the first fruits and for the tithes and for the things collected in them for the rulers of the cities, portions for the priests and for the Leuites, because there was joy in Iouda both over the priests and over the Leuites that stood<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:44</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'were appointed'</char></note>.<verse eid="NEH 12:44"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:45"/>And they guarded the guard stations of the house of their God and the guard stations for purification and the singers and the gatekeepers, according to the commandments of Dauid and his son Salomon.<verse eid="NEH 12:45"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:46"/>Because in the days of Dauid, Asaph from the beginning was the first of those that sing both hymn and praise to God;<verse eid="NEH 12:46"/>

<verse sid="NEH 12:47"/>and in the days of Zorobabel all Israel was giving portions for the singers and the gatekeepers, the rule of a day for its day, and were sanctifying for the Leuites, and the Leuites were sanctifying for sons of Aaron.<verse eid="NEH 12:47"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="NEH 13">
<verse sid="NEH 13:1"/>(2Esdras 23.1) On that day there was read from the book of Moyses in the hearing of the people, and there was found written in it that Ammanites and Moabites should not enter in the assembly of God forever;<verse eid="NEH 13:1"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:2"/>because they did not meet the sons of Israel with bread and with water and hired Balaam against him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Israel'</char></note> to curse himd, and our God turned the curse into a blessing.<verse eid="NEH 13:2"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:3"/>And it happened, when the people heard the law, and every person of mixed race in Israel was separated.<verse eid="NEH 13:3"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:4"/>And before this, Eliasib the priest, while living in the treasure chamber of the house of our God, being next of kin to Tobias;<verse eid="NEH 13:4"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:5"/>also prepared for him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Tobias'</char></note> a large treasure chamber, and there they had previously put the manaa<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'grain offering'</char></note> and the frankincense and the vessels and the tithe of grain and of the wine and of the oil (a commandment of the Leuites and of the singers and of the gatekeepers) and the first fruits of the priests.<verse eid="NEH 13:5"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:6"/>And in all this I was not in Ierousalem, because in the thirty-second year of Arthasastha, king of Babylon, I went to the king. And after the end of the days, I made a request from the king<verse eid="NEH 13:6"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:7"/>and went to Ierousalem. And I gained understanding in the wrong that Eliasib had done for Tobias, to prepare a treasure chamber for him in the court of the house of God.<verse eid="NEH 13:7"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:8"/>And it seemed very bad to me, and I threw all the vessels of the house of Tobias out from the treasure chamber.<verse eid="NEH 13:8"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:9"/>And I spoke, and they cleansed the treasure chambers, and I brought back there the vessels of the house of God, the manaa<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'grain offering'</char></note> and the frankincense.<verse eid="NEH 13:9"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:10"/>And I knew that the portions of the Leuites had not been given, and the Leuites and the singers, who were doing their task, had fled, a man to his field.<verse eid="NEH 13:10"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:11"/>And I remonstrated with the generals and said, "Why was the house of God forsaken?" And I gathered them together and set them in their station.<verse eid="NEH 13:11"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:12"/>And all Iouda brought the tithe of the wheat and the wine and the oil into the storehouses<verse eid="NEH 13:12"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:13"/>upon the hand of Selemia the priest and Sadok the scribe and Phadaia from the Leuites, and upon their hand was Hanan son of Zakchour-- he being son of Maththaniou, because they were considered faithful to them to distribute to their brothers.<verse eid="NEH 13:13"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:14"/>Remember me, O God, in this<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Antecedent unclear</char></note>, and let not the mercy I did in the house of the Lord God be wiped out.<verse eid="NEH 13:14"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:15"/>In those days I saw in Iouda people treading wine presses on the sabbath and bringing in sheaves of grain and loading them on donkeys and also bringing into Ierousalem on the sabbath day wine and grapes and figs and all kinds of burdens, and I warned them on their day of sale.<verse eid="NEH 13:15"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:16"/>And they settled in it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Ierousalem'</char></note>, bringing fish and selling all kinds of merchandise on the sabbath to the sons of Iouda, and in Ierousalem.<verse eid="NEH 13:16"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:17"/>And I remonstrated with the free sons of Iouda and said to them, "What is this evil matter that you are doing and profaning the sabbath day?<verse eid="NEH 13:17"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:18"/>Did not our fathers act in this way? And our God brought all these terrible things upon them and upon us and upon this city. And you are adding wrath to Israel to profane the sabbath."<verse eid="NEH 13:18"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:19"/>And it happened, when the gates in Ierousalem settled down before the sabbath, and I spoke, and they shut the gates, and I spoke so that they would not be opened until after the sabbath. And I set some of my servants over the gates so that people would not carry burdens on the sabbath day.<verse eid="NEH 13:19"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:20"/>And they all spent the night and made sales outside Ierousalem once and twice.<verse eid="NEH 13:20"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:21"/>And I warned them and said to them, "Why do you spend the night in front of the wall? If you do so again, I will extend my hand against you." From that time on they did not come on the sabbath.<verse eid="NEH 13:21"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:22"/>And I told the Leuites who were purifying themselves and were coming, guarding the gates, to keep the sabbath day holy. Remember me for these things, O God, and spare me according to the fullness of your mercy.<verse eid="NEH 13:22"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:23"/>And in those days I saw Judeans who had set up<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:23</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'set up':  I.e. 'married'</char></note> women of Azotia, Ammanites, Moabites<verse eid="NEH 13:23"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:24"/>(and half of their sons speak Azotian and do not know how to speak Judean);<verse eid="NEH 13:24"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:25"/>and I contended with them and cursed them and beat the men among them and pulled out their hair, and I made them take an oath by God: "If you give your daughters to their sons and if you take some of their daughters for your sons!"<verse eid="NEH 13:25"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:26"/>Did not Salomon, king of Israel, sin in this way? And among many nations there was no king like him. And he was beloved to God, and God gave him as king over all Israel. And foreign women ruined this man.<verse eid="NEH 13:26"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:27"/>And shall we listen to you to do all this evil to be faithless with our God to set up<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:27</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'set up':  I.e. 'married'</char></note> foreign women?"<verse eid="NEH 13:27"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:28"/>And one of the sons of Ioada the son of Elisoub, the great priest-- he was the son-in-law of Sanaballat the Horanite-- and I chased him away from me.<verse eid="NEH 13:28"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:29"/>Remember them, O God, because of their close kinship to the priesthood and the covenant of the priesthood and the Leuites.<verse eid="NEH 13:29"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:30"/>And I cleansed them from everything foreign, and I established classes for the priests and Leuites, a man according to his task;<verse eid="NEH 13:30"/>

<verse sid="NEH 13:31"/>and the gift of the wood carriers, in seasons of the times and in the bakchouria<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:31</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = 'firstlings'</char></note>. Remember me, O our God, for goodness.<verse eid="NEH 13:31"/>
</_X_chapter></_X_book></_X_usx>