<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<_X_usx version="2.0">
<para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
<_X_book code="PRO">





<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 1">
<verse sid="PRO 1:1"/>Proverbs of Salomon son of Dauid, who reigned in Israel:<verse eid="PRO 1:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:2"/>To learn wisdom and discipline and to understand words of prudence<verse eid="PRO 1:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:3"/>and to grasp subtlety of words and to understand true righteousness and to direct judgment<verse eid="PRO 1:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:4"/>in order that he might give shrewdness to the innocent and both perception and insight to the young child,<verse eid="PRO 1:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:5"/>for by hearing these things the wise will become wiser and the discerning will acquire direction,<verse eid="PRO 1:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:6"/>and he will understand an illustration<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'analogy'</char></note> and an obscure word, both the sayings and the riddles of the wise.<verse eid="PRO 1:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:7"/>Beginning of wisdom is fear of God, and understanding is good for all those who practice it, and piety unto God is the beginning of perception; the impious, however, will despise wisdom and discipline.<verse eid="PRO 1:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:8"/>Hear, my son, your father's discipline, and do not reject your mother's precepts,<verse eid="PRO 1:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:9"/>for you will receive a crown of graces for your head and a golden collar around your neck.<verse eid="PRO 1:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:10"/>My son, let not impious men lead you astray, and do not consent, if they invite you saying:<verse eid="PRO 1:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:11"/>"Come with us; partake in bloodshed, and let us hide a just man unjustly in the earth,<verse eid="PRO 1:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:12"/>and let us swallow him alive like Hades, and let us remove his remembrance from the earth;<verse eid="PRO 1:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:13"/>let us take his valuable possessions, and let us fill our homes with booty.<verse eid="PRO 1:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:14"/>But throw your lot among us, and let us all acquire a common purse, and let us have one wallet."<verse eid="PRO 1:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:15"/>Do not walk in the way with them, but keep your foot from their paths,<verse eid="PRO 1:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:16"/>for their feet run to evil and they are quick to shed blood,<verse eid="PRO 1:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:17"/>for nets are not spread without reason for winged creatures.<verse eid="PRO 1:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:18"/>For they who take part in murder store up evil for themselves, and the ruin of transgressing men is evil.<verse eid="PRO 1:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:19"/>These are the ways of all who perform lawless deeds, for by impiety they take away their own life.<verse eid="PRO 1:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:20"/>Wisdom sings hymns in the streets, and in the squares she leads frankly,<verse eid="PRO 1:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:21"/>and on the top of the walls she proclaims, and at the gates of the powerful she waits, and at the gates of the city she speaks boldly:<verse eid="PRO 1:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:22"/>"As long as the innocent hold on to righteousness, they will not be ashamed, but the fools, since they are lovers of pride, after they became impious they hated perception,<verse eid="PRO 1:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:23"/>and they became liable to reproofs. Look, I will bring forth to you the expression of my breath, and I will teach you my word.<verse eid="PRO 1:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:24"/>Since I would call but you did not heed and I would prolong words but you were not paying attention,<verse eid="PRO 1:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:25"/>but you would make my counsels invalid, and you disregarded my reproofs;<verse eid="PRO 1:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:26"/>therefore I in turn will also laugh at your destruction, and I will rejoice when ruin comes upon you.<verse eid="PRO 1:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:27"/>Yes, when confusion strikes you unexpectedly and destruction arrives like a whirlwind and when affliction and siege come upon you or when ruin comes upon you,<verse eid="PRO 1:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:28"/>for it shall be when you call upon me, then I will not listen to you; evil people will seek me but will not find me,<verse eid="PRO 1:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:29"/>for they hated wisdom and did not choose the fear of the Lord,<verse eid="PRO 1:29"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:30"/>nor were they willing to pay attention to my counsels but despised my reproofs.<verse eid="PRO 1:30"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:31"/>Therefore they shall eat the fruits of their own way and be filled with their own impiety,<verse eid="PRO 1:31"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:32"/>for, because they would wrong the simple, they will be murdered and an inquiry will ruin the impious.<verse eid="PRO 1:32"/>

<verse sid="PRO 1:33"/>But he who hears me will encamp in hope and will be at ease without fear of any evil."<verse eid="PRO 1:33"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 2">
<verse sid="PRO 2:1"/>My son, if, when you accept the saying of my commandment, you hide it with yourself,<verse eid="PRO 2:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:2"/>your ear will be attentive to wisdom, and you shall incline your heart to understanding; yes, you shall incline it to the admonition of your son.<verse eid="PRO 2:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:3"/>For if you call upon wisdom and raise your voice for understanding, as well as seek perception with a loud voice,<verse eid="PRO 2:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:4"/>and if you seek it like silver and search for it like treasures,<verse eid="PRO 2:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:5"/>then you will understand the fear of the Lord, and you will find divine knowledge.<verse eid="PRO 2:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:6"/>Because the Lord gives wisdom, also from his presence come knowledge and understanding,<verse eid="PRO 2:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:7"/>and he stores up salvation for those who succeed; he will shield their journey<verse eid="PRO 2:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:8"/>to guard the ways of righteous deeds, and he will protect the way of the ones who revere him.<verse eid="PRO 2:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:9"/>Then you will understand righteousness and judgment, and you will make all good courses straight.<verse eid="PRO 2:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:10"/>For if wisdom comes into your mind and perception seems pleasing to your soul,<verse eid="PRO 2:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:11"/>good counsel will guard you, and holy insight will protect you<verse eid="PRO 2:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:12"/>in order that it can rescue you from an evil way and from a man who speaks nothing reliable.<verse eid="PRO 2:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:13"/>Oh, those who abandon straight ways, to walk in ways of darkness,<verse eid="PRO 2:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:14"/>who rejoice in evil and are happy about evil perverseness,<verse eid="PRO 2:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:15"/>whose paths are crooked and their courses are bent<verse eid="PRO 2:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:16"/>in order to remove you far from the straight way and to make you a stranger to a righteous opinion.<verse eid="PRO 2:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:17"/>My son, do not let bad counsel overtake you, that which forsakes the teaching of youth and has forgotten the divine covenant;<verse eid="PRO 2:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:18"/>for it has set her house near death and its courses by Hades with the shades<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'dead'</char></note>;<verse eid="PRO 2:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:19"/>all those who walk in her will not come back, nor will they seize straight paths, for they are not being seized by years of life.<verse eid="PRO 2:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:20"/>For if they were walking good paths, they would have found the smooth paths of righteousness.<verse eid="PRO 2:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:21"/>The kind will be inhabitants of the earth, and the innocent will be left in it, because the upright will encamp on the earth and the holy will be left in it;<verse eid="PRO 2:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 2:22"/>the ways of the impious will perish from the earth, and the transgressors will be banished from it.<verse eid="PRO 2:22"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 3">
<verse sid="PRO 3:1"/>My son, do not forget my ordinances, but let your heart keep my sayings;<verse eid="PRO 3:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:2"/>for longevity and years of life, as well as peace, they will add to you.<verse eid="PRO 3:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:3"/>Let acts of charity and loyalty not fail you; rather fasten them on your neck, and you will find favor,<verse eid="PRO 3:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:4"/>and think of what is noble in the sight of the Lord and of people.<verse eid="PRO 3:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:5"/>Trust in God with all your heart, and do not be excited by your wisdom.<verse eid="PRO 3:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:6"/>In all your ways make her known, that she may make straight your ways, [and your foot will not stumble].<verse eid="PRO 3:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:7"/>Be not clever in your own eyes, but fear God, and turn away from every evil.<verse eid="PRO 3:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:8"/>Then it will be a healing to your body and treatment for your bones.<verse eid="PRO 3:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:9"/>Honor the Lord from your just labors, and offer him of your firstfruits of righteousness<verse eid="PRO 3:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:10"/>in order that your storerooms may be filled with an abundance of grain and that your vats may gush with wine.<verse eid="PRO 3:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:11"/>My son, do not belittle the Lord's discipline nor break down when you are reproved by him;<verse eid="PRO 3:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:12"/>for whom the Lord loves, he disciplines, and he punishes every son he accepts.<verse eid="PRO 3:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:13"/>Happy is the person who has found wisdom, and the mortal who perceived insight;<verse eid="PRO 3:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:14"/>for it is better to trade in her than in treasures of gold and silver.<verse eid="PRO 3:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:15"/>And she is more precious than precious stones; nothing evil shall resist her; she is well-known to all those who draw near to her, and nothing valuable is worthy of her;<verse eid="PRO 3:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:16"/>for longevity and years of life are in her right hand, and in her left hand are riches and repute; (16a) out of her mouth righteousness comes forth, and she carries law and mercy upon her tongue.<verse eid="PRO 3:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:17"/>Her ways are good ways, and all her paths are peaceful.<verse eid="PRO 3:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:18"/>She is a tree of life to all those who lay claim to her, and she is steadfast to those who lean upon her, as on the Lord.<verse eid="PRO 3:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:19"/>God by wisdom founded the earth, and he prepared the heavens by prudence.<verse eid="PRO 3:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:20"/>By perception the deeps were broken open, and the clouds poured dew.<verse eid="PRO 3:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:21"/>My son, do not break away, but keep my counsel and insight<verse eid="PRO 3:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:22"/>so that your soul may live and that there may be grace round your neck. (22a) And it shall be healing to your flesh and treatment for your bones,<verse eid="PRO 3:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:23"/>that you may walk all your ways confidently in peace and that your foot will not stumble.<verse eid="PRO 3:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:24"/>For if you sit down, you will be without fear, and when you lie down, you will sleep pleasantly.<verse eid="PRO 3:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:25"/>And you shall not be afraid of intimidation when it comes, nor of attacks of the impious, when they approach.<verse eid="PRO 3:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:26"/>For the Lord will be over all your ways and he will support your foot in order that you may not be unsettled.<verse eid="PRO 3:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:27"/>Do not withhold to do good to the needy, when your hand can help.<verse eid="PRO 3:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:28"/>Do not say. "Go, come back, and tomorrow I will give," when you are able to do good, for you do not know what the next day will bring.<verse eid="PRO 3:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:29"/>Do not plan evil against your friend when he lives besides you and trusts in you.<verse eid="PRO 3:29"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:30"/>Do not quarrel with anyone without a cause, lest he does some harm to you.<verse eid="PRO 3:30"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:31"/>Do not acquire the disgrace of evil men, and do not strive after their ways<verse eid="PRO 3:31"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:32"/>for every transgressor is impure before the Lord, and he does not sit in council among the righteous.<verse eid="PRO 3:32"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:33"/>A divine curse is in the homes of the impious, but the abodes of the just are blessed.<verse eid="PRO 3:33"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:34"/>The Lord resists the arrogant, but he gives grace to the humble.<verse eid="PRO 3:34"/>

<verse sid="PRO 3:35"/>The wise will inherit glory, but the impious have exalted disgrace.<verse eid="PRO 3:35"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 4">
<verse sid="PRO 4:1"/>Listen, children, to a father's discipline, and pay attention, that you may come to know insight,<verse eid="PRO 4:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:2"/>for I present to you a good gift; do not abandon my law.<verse eid="PRO 4:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:3"/>For I became a son, and I am obedient to my father and beloved in the eyes of my mother,<verse eid="PRO 4:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:4"/>who would speak and instruct me: "Let our word become fixed in your heart.<verse eid="PRO 4:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:5"/>Keep the commandments; do not forget nor disregard the saying of my mouth.<verse eid="PRO 4:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:6"/>Nor abandon her, and she will cleave to you; love her, and she will guard you.<verse eid="PRO 4:6"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 4:7"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 4:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:8"/>Secure her, and she will exalt you; honor her, that she may embrace you<verse eid="PRO 4:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:9"/>in order that she may grant your head a garland of graces and may protect you with a garland of delight."<verse eid="PRO 4:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:10"/>Listen, my son, and accept my words, and the years of your life shall be increased, that the ways of living may become many for you,<verse eid="PRO 4:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:11"/>for I teach you the ways of wisdom and I put you in straight tracks.<verse eid="PRO 4:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:12"/>For if you walk, your steps will not be hemmed in, and if you run, you will not grow weary.<verse eid="PRO 4:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:13"/>Take hold of my discipline; do not let go, but keep her for yourself for your life.<verse eid="PRO 4:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:14"/>Do not enter the ways of the impious, and do not covet the ways of transgressors.<verse eid="PRO 4:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:15"/>Wherever they put up camp, do not enter there, but turn from them, and pass by,<verse eid="PRO 4:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:16"/>for they will not sleep, unless they have done wrong; their sleep has been taken away, and they do not fall asleep,<verse eid="PRO 4:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:17"/>for these people eat the bread of impiety and they get drunk with illicit wine.<verse eid="PRO 4:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:18"/>But the ways of the righteous shine like a light; they proceed and give light until the day is fully dawned.<verse eid="PRO 4:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:19"/>The ways of the impious, however, are dark; they do not know how they stumble.<verse eid="PRO 4:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:20"/>My son, pay attention to my saying, and incline your ear to my words.<verse eid="PRO 4:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:21"/>So that your fountains may not fail you, keep them within your heart,<verse eid="PRO 4:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:22"/>for it is life to those who find them and healing to all their flesh.<verse eid="PRO 4:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:23"/>Keep your heart with all vigilance, for from these things are the issues of life.<verse eid="PRO 4:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:24"/>Remove from yourself a crooked mouth, and thrust unjust lips far away from you.<verse eid="PRO 4:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:25"/>Let your eyes look straight, and let your eyelids incline to just things.<verse eid="PRO 4:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:26"/>Make straight tracks for your feet, and straighten your ways.<verse eid="PRO 4:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 4:27"/>Do not incline to the right or to the left; rather turn away your foot from an evil way, (27a) for God knows the ways on the right, but those on the left are twisted. (27b) But it is he who will make your tracks straight, and he will guide your journeys in peace.<verse eid="PRO 4:27"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 5">
<verse sid="PRO 5:1"/>My son, pay attention to my wisdom, and incline your ear to my words,<verse eid="PRO 5:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:2"/>that you may keep insight, and I shall command perception of my lips unto you.<verse eid="PRO 5:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:3"/>Pay no attention to a worthless woman, for honey drips from the lips of a prostituting woman, who for a period pleases your palate.<verse eid="PRO 5:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:4"/>Later, however, you will find it more bitter than gall and sharper than a two-edged dagger;<verse eid="PRO 5:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:5"/>for the feet of folly bring down those who deal with her, to Hades with death, and her footprints are not being established,<verse eid="PRO 5:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:6"/>for she does not come to the ways of life, but her courses are slippery and unfamiliar.<verse eid="PRO 5:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:7"/>Now then, my son, listen to me, and do not make my words invalid.<verse eid="PRO 5:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:8"/>Make your way far from her; do not go near the doors of her houses<verse eid="PRO 5:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:9"/>in order that you will not give away your life to others and your living to the merciless,<verse eid="PRO 5:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:10"/>lest strangers be filled with your strength and your labors go into the homes of strangers.<verse eid="PRO 5:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:11"/>You, however, will repent at the end, when the flesh of your body is consumed,<verse eid="PRO 5:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:12"/>and you will say, "How I hated discipline, and my innermost turned away reproofs!<verse eid="PRO 5:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:13"/>I would not listen to the voice of one instructing me and teaching me, nor did I incline my ear.<verse eid="PRO 5:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:14"/>I was almost in every evil situation, in the midst of an assembly and congregation."<verse eid="PRO 5:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:15"/>Drink water from your vessels and from the cisterns of your well.<verse eid="PRO 5:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:16"/>Let not the waters out of your well overflow for you; rather let your waters flow into your streets.<verse eid="PRO 5:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:17"/>Let them be at the disposal of you alone, and let no stranger share with you.<verse eid="PRO 5:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:18"/>Let your well of water be solely your own, and rejoice with the woman from your youth.<verse eid="PRO 5:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:19"/>Let the fawn of your love and the foal of your favors consort with you, and let her be considered your very own and be with you on every occasion, for while indulging in her love you will be increased immeasurably.<verse eid="PRO 5:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:20"/>Do not be for long with a strange woman, nor be held in the arms of someone not your own;<verse eid="PRO 5:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:21"/>for the ways of a man are before the eyes of God, and he observes all their courses.<verse eid="PRO 5:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:22"/>Transgressions ensnare a man, and each one is bound by the ropes of his own sins.<verse eid="PRO 5:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 5:23"/>He comes to an end with the uninstructed, and he was cast forth from the abundance of his own sustenance and perished through folly.<verse eid="PRO 5:23"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 6">
<verse sid="PRO 6:1"/>My son, if you stand security for your friend, you will surrender your hand to an enemy,<verse eid="PRO 6:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:2"/>for a man's own lips are a strong snare, and he is caught by the lips of his own mouth.<verse eid="PRO 6:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:3"/>My son, do what I command you and save yourself, for through your friend you have fallen into the hands of evil; go; do not falter; rather spur on even your friend for whom you stood security.<verse eid="PRO 6:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:4"/>Give your eyes no sleep, nor slumber with your eyelids<verse eid="PRO 6:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:5"/>in order to rescue yourself like a gazelle from a noose and like a bird from a snare.<verse eid="PRO 6:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:6"/>Go to the ant, O lazybones, and zealously observe its ways, and become wiser than it;<verse eid="PRO 6:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:7"/>for without having any cultivated land nor anyone that forces it nor being under any master,<verse eid="PRO 6:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:8"/>it prepares its food in summer, and it makes its provision plentiful in harvest time. (8a) Or go to the bee, and learn how industrious she is and how seriously she performs her work (8b) whose products kings and commoners use for their health. Yes, she is desired by all and honored. (8c) Although she is physically weak, by honoring wisdom she was promoted.<verse eid="PRO 6:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:9"/>How long, lazybones, will you lie? And when will you be roused from your sleep?<verse eid="PRO 6:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:10"/>Indeed you sleep a little, and you sit a little, and you slumber a little, and you fold your arms over your breast a little.<verse eid="PRO 6:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:11"/>Then poverty will come upon you like an evil traveler, and want like a good runner. (11a) If, however, you are diligent, your harvest will arrive like a fountain, and want will desert you like a bad runner.<verse eid="PRO 6:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:12"/>A foolish and lawless man walks roads that are no good,<verse eid="PRO 6:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:13"/>and he winks with his eye and makes a sign with his foot, and he teaches with motions of his fingers.<verse eid="PRO 6:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:14"/>And with a perverse heart he plans evil at every opportunity; such a person concocts upheavals for a city.<verse eid="PRO 6:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:15"/>Therefore his destruction arrives suddenly, calamity and ruin beyond repair,<verse eid="PRO 6:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:16"/>for he rejoices in everything that the Lord hates; yes, he is ruined by impurity of soul.<verse eid="PRO 6:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:17"/>An eye of an insolent one, an unjust tongue, hands that shed blood of a righteous person<verse eid="PRO 6:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:18"/>and a heart that plans wicked schemes and feet that hurry to do evil.<verse eid="PRO 6:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:19"/>A false witness kindles falsehood and sows discord among kindred.<verse eid="PRO 6:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:20"/>My son, keep your father's laws, and do not forsake your mother's precepts.<verse eid="PRO 6:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:21"/>But always bind them upon your soul, and make them a collar on your neck.<verse eid="PRO 6:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:22"/>When you walk, bring it, and let it be with you, and when you lie down, let it watch over you in order that it may communicate with you when you awake,<verse eid="PRO 6:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:23"/>for the law's commandment is a lamp and a light and a way of life, reproof and discipline,<verse eid="PRO 6:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:24"/>to keep you from a married woman and from the slander of a strange tongue.<verse eid="PRO 6:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:25"/>Let not her desire for beauty conquer you, nor be captured by your eyes; neither be captivated by her eyelashes,<verse eid="PRO 6:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:26"/>for the price of a prostitute is just about as much as a loaf of bread and a men's lady hunts for precious souls.<verse eid="PRO 6:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:27"/>Can anyone put fire in his lap and not burn his clothes?<verse eid="PRO 6:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:28"/>Or can anyone walk on coals of fire and not scorch his feet?<verse eid="PRO 6:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:29"/>So is he who goes in to a married woman. He shall not be held guiltless, nor anyone who touches her.<verse eid="PRO 6:29"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:30"/>It is not to be marveled at if someone is caught stealing, for he steals in order to fill himself when he is hungry.<verse eid="PRO 6:30"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:31"/>Yet, if he is caught, he will pay sevenfold, and he will rescue himself by surrendering all his possessions.<verse eid="PRO 6:31"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:32"/>But the adulterer procures destruction to himself through lack of sense.<verse eid="PRO 6:32"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:33"/>He experiences both pain and disgrace, and his dishonor will never be wiped out;<verse eid="PRO 6:33"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:34"/>for filled with jealousy is the anger of her husband; he will show no constraint in the day of judgment;<verse eid="PRO 6:34"/>

<verse sid="PRO 6:35"/>neither will he take any compensation as exchange for his hate, nor will he at all be reconciled by many gifts.<verse eid="PRO 6:35"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 7">
<verse sid="PRO 7:1"/>My son, keep my words, and hide my commandments with yourself. (1a) My son, honor the Lord, and you will grow strong, and fear no other but him.<verse eid="PRO 7:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:2"/>Guard my commandments, and you will live, and my words like the apples of your eyes.<verse eid="PRO 7:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:3"/>And bind them on your fingers, and engrave them on the surface of your heart.<verse eid="PRO 7:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:4"/>Say that wisdom is your sister, and secure prudence as an intimate friend for yourself,<verse eid="PRO 7:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:5"/>that she may keep you from a strange and sinful woman, if she should assail you with words to charm;<verse eid="PRO 7:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:6"/>for from a window out of her house she peeps into the streets,<verse eid="PRO 7:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:7"/>at whom she may observe of the foolish children, a youngster lacking sense,<verse eid="PRO 7:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:8"/>passing by the corner in the passages of her dwellings<verse eid="PRO 7:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:9"/>and conversing in the evening twilight, when there happens to be nocturnal quiet and gloom.<verse eid="PRO 7:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:10"/>Then the woman meets him, looking like a prostitute, who causes the hearts of young men to flutter.<verse eid="PRO 7:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:11"/>And she is excited and debauched, and her feet cannot stay at home;<verse eid="PRO 7:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:12"/>for some time she roams outside, and at another time she lies in wait in the streets, at every corner.<verse eid="PRO 7:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:13"/>Then she seized and kissed him, and with a shameless face addressed him:<verse eid="PRO 7:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:14"/>"I have a peace offering; today I am paying my vows;<verse eid="PRO 7:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:15"/>therefore I came out to meet you, longing for your face; I have found you.<verse eid="PRO 7:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:16"/>With coverings I have spread my couch, and with double tapestry from Egypt I have decked it.<verse eid="PRO 7:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:17"/>I have sprinkled my bed with saffron and my house with cinnamon.<verse eid="PRO 7:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:18"/>Come, and let us enjoy love until the early morning; come here, and let us embrace in love,<verse eid="PRO 7:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:19"/>for my husband is not at home but has gone on a long journey,<verse eid="PRO 7:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:20"/>since he took a bag of money with him, after many days he will return to his house."<verse eid="PRO 7:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:21"/>And with a lot of chatting she seduced him, and with the snares of her lips she compelled him.<verse eid="PRO 7:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:22"/>And he followed her, ensnared; like an ox he is led to slaughter, and like a dog towards chains<verse eid="PRO 7:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:23"/>or like a deer shot with an arrow in the liver, and he hurries like a bird into a trap, not realizing that he is running for his life.<verse eid="PRO 7:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:24"/>Now then, my son, listen to me and pay attention to the words of my mouth.<verse eid="PRO 7:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:25"/>Do not let your heart incline to her ways,<verse eid="PRO 7:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:26"/>for many she has wounded and laid low and innumerable are those whom she has slain.<verse eid="PRO 7:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 7:27"/>Roads of Hades are her house, leading down to the chambers of death.<verse eid="PRO 7:27"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 8">
<verse sid="PRO 8:1"/>You will proclaim wisdom in order that prudence may be obedient to you;<verse eid="PRO 8:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:2"/>for on the highest tops she is, and between the paths she has taken her stand;<verse eid="PRO 8:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:3"/>for beside the gates of rulers she takes her seat, and at the entrances she sings hymns:<verse eid="PRO 8:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:4"/>"You, O people, I exhort, and I lift my voice to the sons of men.<verse eid="PRO 8:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:5"/>O innocent ones, be aware of trickery, and you uneducated take heart.<verse eid="PRO 8:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:6"/>Listen to me, for I will talk about serious things, and I will bring forth from my lips what is right;<verse eid="PRO 8:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:7"/>for my throat will declaim truth, but false lips are abominable to me.<verse eid="PRO 8:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:8"/>With righteousness are all the words of my mouth; in them nothing is twisted nor crooked.<verse eid="PRO 8:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:9"/>They are all straightforward to those who understand and upright to those who find knowledge.<verse eid="PRO 8:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:10"/>Take discipline and not silver, and knowledge rather than choice gold; yes, choose perception instead of pure gold,<verse eid="PRO 8:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:11"/>for wisdom is better than costly stones, and nothing valuable is worthy of her.<verse eid="PRO 8:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:12"/>I, wisdom, I encamped with counsel, and knowledge and insight I summoned."<verse eid="PRO 8:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:13"/>The fear of the Lord hates injustice, also pride and arrogance and the ways of the wicked; yes, it is I who hate the perverse ways of evil people.<verse eid="PRO 8:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:14"/>Mine are counsel and security, mine prudence and mine strength.<verse eid="PRO 8:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:15"/>Through me kings rule, and rulers prescribe justice.<verse eid="PRO 8:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:16"/>Through me nobles are magnified, and tyrants through me rule the earth.<verse eid="PRO 8:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:17"/>It is I who am fond of those who love me, and those who seek me find me.<verse eid="PRO 8:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:18"/>Wealth and honor are at my disposal, and the acquisition of many things and justice.<verse eid="PRO 8:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:19"/>To enjoy my fruits is better than gold and precious stone, and my yield better than choice silver.<verse eid="PRO 8:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:20"/>I walk in ways of justice, and along paths of what is right I wander<verse eid="PRO 8:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:21"/>in order that I may apportion possessions to those who love me and fill their treasuries with good things. (21a) If I report to you the things that happen daily, I will remember to enumerate the things of old.<verse eid="PRO 8:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:22"/>The Lord created me as the beginning of his ways, for the sake of his works.<verse eid="PRO 8:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:23"/>Before the present age he founded me, in the beginning.<verse eid="PRO 8:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:24"/>Before he made the earth and before he made the depths, before he brought forth the springs of the waters,<verse eid="PRO 8:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:25"/>before the mountains were established and before all the hills, he begets me.<verse eid="PRO 8:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:26"/>The Lord made countries and uninhabited spaces and the habitable heights of that beneath the sky.<verse eid="PRO 8:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:27"/>When he prepared the sky, I was present with him, and when he marked out his own throne on the winds.<verse eid="PRO 8:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:28"/>When he made strong the clouds above and when he made secure the springs beneath the sky,<verse eid="PRO 8:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:29"/>when he made strong the foundations of the earth,<verse eid="PRO 8:29"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:30"/>I was beside him, fitting together; it is I who was the one in whom he took delight. And each day I was glad in his presence at every moment,<verse eid="PRO 8:30"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:31"/>when he rejoiced after he had completed the world and rejoiced among the sons of men.<verse eid="PRO 8:31"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:32"/>Now then, my son, listen to me.<verse eid="PRO 8:32"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 8:33"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:33</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 8:33"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:34"/>Happy is the man who will listen to me and the person who will guard my ways, keeping watch at my doors daily, protecting the posts of my entrances.<verse eid="PRO 8:34"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:35"/>For my egressions are the egressions of life, and the incentive is prepared by the Lord.<verse eid="PRO 8:35"/>

<verse sid="PRO 8:36"/>But those who sin against me treat their own souls with impiety, and those who hate me love death.<verse eid="PRO 8:36"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 9">
<verse sid="PRO 9:1"/>Wisdom built herself a house and supported it with seven pillars.<verse eid="PRO 9:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:2"/>She slaughtered her own sacrificial victims; she mixed her own wine in a mixing bowl, and she prepared her own table.<verse eid="PRO 9:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:3"/>She sent out her slaves, summoning with a stately proclamation to the drinking feast, saying,<verse eid="PRO 9:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:4"/>"He who is a fool, let him turn aside to me," and to those lacking sense she said:<verse eid="PRO 9:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:5"/>"Come, eat of my bread, and drink wine, which I have mixed for you.<verse eid="PRO 9:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:6"/>Abandon folly, and you will live, and seek prudence in order that you may live, and erect understanding with knowledge."<verse eid="PRO 9:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:7"/>He who instructs evil people will gather disgrace unto himself, and he who rebukes an impious person will find fault with himself.<verse eid="PRO 9:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:8"/>Do not rebuke evil people, lest they should hate you; rebuke a wise person, and he will love you.<verse eid="PRO 9:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:9"/>Give a wise person an opportunity, and he will become wiser; inform a just person, and he will continue to receive.<verse eid="PRO 9:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:10"/>The beginning of wisdom is the fear of the Lord, and counsel of the saints is understanding, (10a) for to know the law is the sign of a sound mind;<verse eid="PRO 9:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:11"/>for in this way you will live a long time, and years of your life will be added to you.<verse eid="PRO 9:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:12"/>My son, if you become wise for yourself, you will be wise for your neighbors as well; however, if you turn out evil, you will bear the evil alone. (12a) He who supports himself with lies will as well herd winds, and the same person will pursue flying birds, (12b) for he has forsaken the ways of his vineyard and has caused the axles on his own farm to go astray. (12c) Yes, he travels through an arid wilderness and a land destined to drought and gathers barrenness with his hands.<verse eid="PRO 9:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:13"/>A foolish and audacious woman who knows no shame comes in need of a morsel of food.<verse eid="PRO 9:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:14"/>She sat at the doors of her own house, on a seat, openly in the streets,<verse eid="PRO 9:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:15"/>inviting those who are passing by and who are keeping straight in their ways.<verse eid="PRO 9:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:16"/>"He of you who is most foolish, let him turn aside to me, and to those that are in need of prudence I urge, saying,<verse eid="PRO 9:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:17"/>'Take secret bread gladly, and sweet water of theft.' "<verse eid="PRO 9:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 9:18"/>But he does not know that the shades<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'dead'</char></note> perish with her, and he meets up with a springboard of Hades. (18a) On the contrary, run away; do not linger in the place; neither fix your eye upon her, (18b) for so you will cross strange water and pass through a strange river. (18c) However, abstain from strange water, and do not drink from a strange well, (18d) that you may live for a long time and years of life may be added to you.<verse eid="PRO 9:18"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 10">
<verse sid="PRO 10:1"/>A wise son makes a father glad, but a foolish son is a mother's grief.<verse eid="PRO 10:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:2"/>Treasures shall not profit the lawless, but righteousness shall deliver from death.<verse eid="PRO 10:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:3"/>The Lord will not let a righteous person starve, but the life of the impious he will ruin.<verse eid="PRO 10:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:4"/>Poverty makes a man humble, but the hands of the vigorous enrich. (4a) A son who is instructed shall be wise, and he will use the fool as a servant.<verse eid="PRO 10:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:5"/>An intelligent son was rescued from heat of the day, but a transgressing son is blasted by the wind in harvest time.<verse eid="PRO 10:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:6"/>The blessing of the Lord is upon the head of the righteous, but the mouth of the impious will conceal untimely sorrow.<verse eid="PRO 10:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:7"/>The memory of the righteous comes with eulogies, but the name of the impious is extinguished.<verse eid="PRO 10:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:8"/>A wise of heart will accept commandments, but he who is unable to keep his mouth shut, being crooked, will be tripped up.<verse eid="PRO 10:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:9"/>He who walks in integrity walks confidently, but he who perverts his ways will be found out.<verse eid="PRO 10:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:10"/>He who winks with his eyes deceitfully garners grief for men, but he who reproves openly makes peace.<verse eid="PRO 10:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:11"/>A spring of life is in the hand of a righteous person, but destruction covers the mouth of the impious.<verse eid="PRO 10:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:12"/>Hatred stirs up strife, but friendship covers all who are not fond of strife.<verse eid="PRO 10:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:13"/>He who produces wisdom from his lips strikes a heartless man with a rod.<verse eid="PRO 10:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:14"/>The wise will conceal perception, but the mouth of the reckless brings ruin near.<verse eid="PRO 10:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:15"/>The possessions of the rich are a strong city, but poverty is the ruin of the impious.<verse eid="PRO 10:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:16"/>The deeds of the righteous produce life but the fruits of the impious sins.<verse eid="PRO 10:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:17"/>Discipline guards the ways of a righteous life, but unchastened instruction leads astray.<verse eid="PRO 10:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:18"/>Righteous lips conceal enmity, but they who utter slander are most foolish.<verse eid="PRO 10:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:19"/>By a multitude of words you will not escape sin, but if you restrain your lips, you will be intelligent.<verse eid="PRO 10:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:20"/>The tongue of the righteous is choice silver, but the heart of the impious will fail.<verse eid="PRO 10:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:21"/>The lips of the righteous are versed in sublime things, but fools die in want.<verse eid="PRO 10:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:22"/>The blessing of the Lord is upon the head of a righteous person; it enriches, and grief of heart will not be added to it.<verse eid="PRO 10:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:23"/>With laughter a fool practices evil, but wisdom gives birth to prudence for a man.<verse eid="PRO 10:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:24"/>An impious person is engulfed in destruction, but the desire of a righteous person is acceptable.<verse eid="PRO 10:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:25"/>When the tempest passes, an impious person vanishes, but a righteous person, since he turned aside, is saved for ever.<verse eid="PRO 10:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:26"/>As unripe grapes are harmful to the teeth, and smoke is to the eyes, so transgression is to those that practice it.<verse eid="PRO 10:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:27"/>The fear of the Lord adds days, but the years of the impious will be few.<verse eid="PRO 10:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:28"/>Gladness lingers with the righteous, but the hope of the impious will perish.<verse eid="PRO 10:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:29"/>The fear of the Lord is a stronghold for the devout, but ruin for those who do evil.<verse eid="PRO 10:29"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:30"/>The righteous will never give up, and the impious will not inhabit the land.<verse eid="PRO 10:30"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:31"/>The mouth of the righteous drips wisdom, but the tongue of the unjust will perish.<verse eid="PRO 10:31"/>

<verse sid="PRO 10:32"/>The lips of the righteous drip charm, but the mouth of the impious turns people away.<verse eid="PRO 10:32"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 11">
<verse sid="PRO 11:1"/>False balances are an abomination before the Lord, but a just weight is acceptable to him.<verse eid="PRO 11:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:2"/>Where pride enters, there will also be disgrace, but the mouth of the humble attends to wisdom.<verse eid="PRO 11:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:3"/>When a righteous person died, he left regret, but destruction of the impious is at hand, and joyous.<verse eid="PRO 11:3"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 11:4"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 11:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:5"/>Righteousness cuts out blameless paths, but impiety is beset with injustice.<verse eid="PRO 11:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:6"/>The righteousness of upright men rescues them, but transgressors are taken captive by their destruction.<verse eid="PRO 11:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:7"/>When a righteous man dies, hope does not perish, but the boast of the impious perishes.<verse eid="PRO 11:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:8"/>A righteous person eludes from a chase, and the impious is handed over in his stead.<verse eid="PRO 11:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:9"/>In the mouth of the impious is a snare to citizens, but the perception of the righteous is free from difficulties.<verse eid="PRO 11:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:10"/>By the good deeds of the righteous a city succeeded,<verse eid="PRO 11:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:11"/>but by the mouths of the impious it was leveled.<verse eid="PRO 11:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:12"/>A person who lacks sense scorns citizens, but an intelligent man keeps quiet.<verse eid="PRO 11:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:13"/>A double-tongued man discloses counsels in a meeting, but a person loyal in spirit conceals matters.<verse eid="PRO 11:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:14"/>They who have no direction fall like leaves, but in much counsel there is safety.<verse eid="PRO 11:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:15"/>A wicked person does evil whenever he mingles with a righteous person, and he hates the sound of security.<verse eid="PRO 11:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:16"/>A gracious wife procures honor for her husband, but a seat of dishonor is a woman who hates justice. The deficient shrink from wealth, but the diligent support themselves with wealth.<verse eid="PRO 11:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:17"/>A merciful man does good to his own self, but the merciless person destroys his body.<verse eid="PRO 11:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:18"/>An impious person performs unjust works, but the seed of the just is a reward of truth.<verse eid="PRO 11:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:19"/>A righteous son is born to life, but the pursuit of the impious leads to death.<verse eid="PRO 11:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:20"/>Crooked ways are an abomination to the Lord, but acceptable to him are all who are blameless in their ways.<verse eid="PRO 11:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:21"/>One who unjustly joins hands<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'unjustly joins hands':  I.e. 'assists in the making of false pledges'</char></note> will not go unpunished, but he who sows righteousness will receive an assured reward.<verse eid="PRO 11:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:22"/>Like a ring in a pig's snout, so is beauty to an imprudent woman.<verse eid="PRO 11:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:23"/>All the desire of the righteous is good, but the hope of the impious will perish.<verse eid="PRO 11:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:24"/>There are those who by distributing their livelihood increase it, and there are others who gather, yet have less.<verse eid="PRO 11:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:25"/>Every totally sincere person is blessed, but an ill-tempered man is not respected.<verse eid="PRO 11:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:26"/>May he who withholds grain leave it to the nations, and may a blessing be on the head of him who shares it.<verse eid="PRO 11:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:27"/>He who devises good seeks good favor, but as for him who seeks out evil, it will overtake him.<verse eid="PRO 11:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:28"/>As for him who puts his trust in wealth, he will fall, but as for him who supports the righteous, he will flourish.<verse eid="PRO 11:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:29"/>He who does not deal graciously with his own household will inherit wind, and the fool will be a slave to the intelligent.<verse eid="PRO 11:29"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:30"/>From the fruit of righteousness grows a tree of life, but the souls of transgressors are cut off untimely.<verse eid="PRO 11:30"/>

<verse sid="PRO 11:31"/>If the righteous is scarcely saved, where will the impious and the sinner appear?<verse eid="PRO 11:31"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 12">
<verse sid="PRO 12:1"/>He who loves discipline loves perception, but he who hates reproofs is a fool.<verse eid="PRO 12:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:2"/>He who finds favor with the Lord is superior, but a lawless man will be passed over in silence.<verse eid="PRO 12:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:3"/>No person will prosper from what is lawless, but the roots of the just will not be removed.<verse eid="PRO 12:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:4"/>A courageous wife is a crown to her husband, but like a worm in wood, so a mischievous wife destroys a man.<verse eid="PRO 12:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:5"/>The thoughts of the just are judgments, but the impious guides treachery.<verse eid="PRO 12:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:6"/>The words of the impious are crafty, but the mouth of the upright will deliver them.<verse eid="PRO 12:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:7"/>Wherever the impious turns, he disappears, but the households of the righteous endure.<verse eid="PRO 12:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:8"/>The mouth of an intelligent person is praised by a man, but the slow-on-the-uptake is mocked.<verse eid="PRO 12:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:9"/>Better is a man in dishonor, being a slave to himself, than one who confers honor upon himself while he lacks food.<verse eid="PRO 12:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:10"/>A just person takes pity on the lives of his cattle, but the feelings of the impious are without mercy.<verse eid="PRO 12:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:11"/>He who tills his own land shall be satisfied with food, but those who pursue vanities lack sense. (11a) He who enjoys himself in banquets of wine shall leave behind disgrace in his own strongholds.<verse eid="PRO 12:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:12"/>The desires of the impious are evil, but the roots of the pious are in secure places.<verse eid="PRO 12:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:13"/>Through the sin of his lips a sinner falls into snares, but a just person escapes from them. (13a) He who looks gentle will be pitied, but he who contends in the gates will afflict souls.<verse eid="PRO 12:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:14"/>From the fruit of the mouth a man's soul will be filled with good, and the rewards of his lips shall be given to him.<verse eid="PRO 12:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:15"/>The ways of fools are right in their own eyes, but a wise man listens to advice.<verse eid="PRO 12:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:16"/>A fool expresses his anger at once, but the prudent hides his own disgrace.<verse eid="PRO 12:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:17"/>A just person proclaims trust as it is, but the witness of unjust things is deceitful.<verse eid="PRO 12:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:18"/>Some, when they speak, wound with a dagger, but the tongues of wise men heal.<verse eid="PRO 12:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:19"/>Truthful lips establish testimony, but a hasty witness has a dishonest tongue.<verse eid="PRO 12:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:20"/>Deceit is in the heart of him who devises evil, but those who intend peace will rejoice.<verse eid="PRO 12:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:21"/>Nothing unjust will be pleasing to the just, but the impious will be filled with evil.<verse eid="PRO 12:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:22"/>False lips are an abomination to the Lord, but he who acts faithfully is acceptable to him.<verse eid="PRO 12:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:23"/>An intelligent man is a seat of perception, but the heart of fools will meet with curses.<verse eid="PRO 12:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:24"/>The hand of the elected will easily govern, but the deceitful will become a prey.<verse eid="PRO 12:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:25"/>Terrifying news troubles the heart of a just man, but a good message cheers him up.<verse eid="PRO 12:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:26"/>A just arbiter will be his own friend, but the opinions of the impious are unfair. Evil will pursue those that sin, and the way of the impious shall lead them astray.<verse eid="PRO 12:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:27"/>The deceitful will obtain no game, but a pure man a valuable possession.<verse eid="PRO 12:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 12:28"/>In the ways of justice there is life, but the ways of those who bear grudges lead to death.<verse eid="PRO 12:28"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 13">
<verse sid="PRO 13:1"/>A smart son is obedient to his father, but a disobedient son is on course to destruction.<verse eid="PRO 13:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:2"/>A good person will eat of the fruits of justice, but the souls of transgressors will perish untimely.<verse eid="PRO 13:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:3"/>He who guards his own mouth keeps his own life, but he who is rash with his lips will bring terror upon himself.<verse eid="PRO 13:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:4"/>Every lazy person has desires, but the hands of the courageous are diligent.<verse eid="PRO 13:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:5"/>A just person hates an unjust word, but the impious is ashamed and will have no confidence.<verse eid="PRO 13:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:6"/>Justice guards the innocent, but sin makes the impious worthless.<verse eid="PRO 13:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:7"/>There are some who, while having nothing, enrich themselves, and there are others who humble themselves in much wealth.<verse eid="PRO 13:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:8"/>A man's own wealth is the ransom of his soul, but the poor does not experience threat.<verse eid="PRO 13:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:9"/>The just always have light, but the light of the impious is extinguished. (9a) Crafty souls go astray in sins, but just people are compassionate and have pity.<verse eid="PRO 13:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:10"/>An evil person does evil with pride, but they that are judges of themselves are wise.<verse eid="PRO 13:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:11"/>Property gotten hastily with lawlessness is diminished, but he who gathers for himself with piety will be increased. A just person is compassionate and lends.<verse eid="PRO 13:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:12"/>Better is he that begins to help heartily than he that promises and leads another to hope, for a good desire is a tree of life.<verse eid="PRO 13:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:13"/>He who despises a matter will be despised by it, but as for him who fears the commandment, he is healthy. (13a) To a crafty son nothing will be good, but a wise domestic will have prosperous business, and his way shall be guided.<verse eid="PRO 13:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:14"/>The law of a wise man is a fountain of life, but he who is stupid will die by a snare.<verse eid="PRO 13:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:15"/>Sound discretion wins favor, and to know the law is the sign of a sound mind, but the ways of scorners end in destruction.<verse eid="PRO 13:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:16"/>Every smart person acts with knowledge, but the fool displayed his own evil.<verse eid="PRO 13:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:17"/>A rash king will fall into evil, but a reliable messenger will deliver him.<verse eid="PRO 13:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:18"/>Discipline removes poverty and disgrace, and he who rebukes will be honored.<verse eid="PRO 13:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:19"/>The desires of the pious sweeten his soul, but the deeds of the impious are far from knowledge.<verse eid="PRO 13:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:20"/>He who walks along with the wise will be wise, but he who walks along with fools will be known as one.<verse eid="PRO 13:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:21"/>Evil will pursue sinners, but good will overtake the just.<verse eid="PRO 13:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:22"/>A good man will leave an inheritance for his sons' sons, and the wealth of the impious is stored up for the righteous.<verse eid="PRO 13:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:23"/>The just will spend many years in wealth, but the unjust will perish suddenly.<verse eid="PRO 13:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:24"/>He who spares the staff hates his son, but he who loves him carefully disciplines him.<verse eid="PRO 13:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 13:25"/>A just man when eating satisfies his appetite, but the appetites of the impious are deficient.<verse eid="PRO 13:25"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 14">
<verse sid="PRO 14:1"/>Wise women built homes, but a foolish one tore it down with her hands.<verse eid="PRO 14:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:2"/>He who walks uprightly fears the Lord, but he who is devious in his ways will be dishonored.<verse eid="PRO 14:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:3"/>From the mouth of fools comes a staff of pride, but the lips of the wise preserve them.<verse eid="PRO 14:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:4"/>Where there are no oxen, the cribs are clean, but where there is much produce, the strength of an ox is apparent.<verse eid="PRO 14:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:5"/>A faithful witness does not lie, but an unjust witness kindles falsehoods.<verse eid="PRO 14:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:6"/>You may seek wisdom with evil men and will not find it, but perception is easily available among the clever.<verse eid="PRO 14:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:7"/>All things are against a foolish man, but wise lips are the weapons of perception.<verse eid="PRO 14:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:8"/>The wisdom of the smart will become familiar with their ways, but the folly of fools misleads.<verse eid="PRO 14:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:9"/>The homes of transgressors are subject to cleansing, but the homes of the just are acceptable.<verse eid="PRO 14:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:10"/>A man's heart is sensitive; his soul is grieved, and when he rejoices, he does not mingle with pride.<verse eid="PRO 14:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:11"/>The homes of the impious will be destroyed, but the tents of the upright will stand.<verse eid="PRO 14:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:12"/>There is a way that seems to be right among people, but its end reaches to the bottom of Hades.<verse eid="PRO 14:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:13"/>Grief mingles not with mirth, and joy in the end comes to sorrow.<verse eid="PRO 14:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:14"/>A bold-hearted person will be filled with his own ways, and a good man with his own thoughts.<verse eid="PRO 14:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:15"/>The innocent believes every word, but the smart comes to a change of mind.<verse eid="PRO 14:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:16"/>A wise man feared and turned away from evil, but the fool trusts in himself and associates with the lawless.<verse eid="PRO 14:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:17"/>A passionate person acts with thoughtlessness, but a sensible man endures many things.<verse eid="PRO 14:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:18"/>Fools will partake of evil, but the smart will lay hold of perception.<verse eid="PRO 14:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:19"/>The evil will fall down before the good, and the impious will serve at the gates of the just.<verse eid="PRO 14:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:20"/>Friends will hate poor friends, but the friends of the rich are many.<verse eid="PRO 14:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:21"/>He who dishonors the needy sins, but one who pities the poor is deemed most happy.<verse eid="PRO 14:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:22"/>They who go astray devise evil, but the good devise pity and truth. The planners of evil do not understand pity and loyalty, but acts of mercy and of loyalty are with planners for good.<verse eid="PRO 14:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:23"/>With everyone who is careful there is abundance, but the hedonist and indolent shall have want.<verse eid="PRO 14:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:24"/>A crown for the wise is a smart man, but the pastime of fools is evil.<verse eid="PRO 14:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:25"/>A faithful witness will rescue a soul from evil, but a deceitful person kindles falsehoods.<verse eid="PRO 14:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:26"/>In the fear of the Lord is hope in strength, and he leaves his children support.<verse eid="PRO 14:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:27"/>An ordinance of the Lord is a fountain of life, and it causes people to turn away from the snare of death.<verse eid="PRO 14:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:28"/>In a populous nation is a king's glory, but in the failing of people is the ruin of a ruler.<verse eid="PRO 14:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:29"/>A man slow to anger is abundant in prudence, but an impatient man is extremely foolish.<verse eid="PRO 14:29"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:30"/>A meek-spirited man is a healer of hearts, and a sensitive heart a moth<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">14:30</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'a cause of decay'</char></note> in the bones.<verse eid="PRO 14:30"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:31"/>He who cheats the needy upsets his maker, but he who honors him pities the poor.<verse eid="PRO 14:31"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:32"/>The impious will be driven away by his evil, but he who is secure in his own piety is just.<verse eid="PRO 14:32"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:33"/>There is wisdom in the good heart of a man, but in the heart of fools it is not discerned.<verse eid="PRO 14:33"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:34"/>Justice lifts up a nation, but sins diminish tribes.<verse eid="PRO 14:34"/>

<verse sid="PRO 14:35"/>A thoughtful subordinate is acceptable to a king, and by his own good behavior he removes disgrace.<verse eid="PRO 14:35"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 15">
<verse sid="PRO 15:1"/>Anger destroys even the prudent; yet a submissive answer turns away wrath, but a harsh word stirs up anger.<verse eid="PRO 15:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:2"/>The tongue of the wise understands what is good, but the mouth of the foolish will proclaim evil.<verse eid="PRO 15:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:3"/>The eyes of the Lord are in every place, beholding both the evil and the good.<verse eid="PRO 15:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:4"/>A tongue's healing is a tree of life, and he who keeps it will be filled with spirit.<verse eid="PRO 15:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:5"/>A fool scorns his father's discipline, but he who keeps commandments is smarter.<verse eid="PRO 15:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:6"/>In abounding righteousness is great strength, but the impious will be removed root and branch from the earth. In the homes of the righteous there is much strength, but the fruits of the impious will perish.<verse eid="PRO 15:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:7"/>The lips of the wise are devoted to perception, but the hearts of fools are not steadfast.<verse eid="PRO 15:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:8"/>The sacrifices of the impious are an abomination to the Lord, but the prayers of the upright are acceptable to him.<verse eid="PRO 15:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:9"/>The ways of the impious are an abomination to the Lord, but he loves those who pursue righteousness.<verse eid="PRO 15:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:10"/>The discipline of the innocent is known by passersby, but those who hate rebukes die disgracefully.<verse eid="PRO 15:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:11"/>Hades and destruction are manifest to the Lord; how much more also human hearts!<verse eid="PRO 15:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:12"/>An uninstructed person will not like those who rebuke him, and neither will he associate with the wise.<verse eid="PRO 15:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:13"/>When the heart rejoices the countenance is cheerful, but when it is in sorrow, the countenance is sad.<verse eid="PRO 15:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:14"/>An upright heart seeks perception, but the mouth of the uninstructed will know evil.<verse eid="PRO 15:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:15"/>The eyes of the wicked are continually expecting evil, but the good are always quiet.<verse eid="PRO 15:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:16"/>Better is a small portion with the fear of the Lord than great treasures without fear.<verse eid="PRO 15:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:17"/>Better is entertainment of vegetables with friendliness and kindness than a serving of calves with enmity.<verse eid="PRO 15:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:18"/>A passionate man stirs up fights, but he who is slow to anger appeases even an incipient one. (18a) A man slow to anger will extinguish disputes, but an impious person stirs them up exceedingly.<verse eid="PRO 15:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:19"/>The ways of the idle are strewn with thorns, but those of the courageous are beaten.<verse eid="PRO 15:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:20"/>A wise son gladdens his father, but a foolish son scorns his mother.<verse eid="PRO 15:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:21"/>The paths of the foolish are void of sense, but the prudent man proceeds in a straight course.<verse eid="PRO 15:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:22"/>They who do not honor councils delay deliberations, but counsel prevails in the hearts of those giving advice.<verse eid="PRO 15:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:23"/>The evil person will not heed it; neither will he say anything appropriate or good for the public.<verse eid="PRO 15:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:24"/>The thoughts of the intelligent person are ways of life in order that one turn aside and escape from Hades.<verse eid="PRO 15:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:25"/>The Lord tears down the homes of the insolent, but he established the border of the widow.<verse eid="PRO 15:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:26"/>An unjust thought is an abomination to the Lord, but the sayings of the pure are solemn.<verse eid="PRO 15:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:27"/>A receiver of bribes destroys himself, but he who hates the receiving of bribes is saved. (27a) By acts of mercy and by faithfulness sins are purged, but by the fear of the Lord everyone turns away from evil.<verse eid="PRO 15:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:28"/>The hearts of the righteous ponder faithfulness, but the mouth of the impious answers evil things. (28a) The ways of righteous persons are acceptable to the Lord, and through them even enemies become friends.<verse eid="PRO 15:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:29"/>God is far from the impious, but he hears the prayers of the righteous. (29a) Better is a small intake with righteousness than abundant produce with injustice. (29b) Let the heart of a man think righteous things, that his steps may be directed by God.<verse eid="PRO 15:29"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:30"/>The eye that observes good things rejoices the heart, and good news refreshes the bones.<verse eid="PRO 15:30"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 15:31"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">15:31</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 15:31"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:32"/>He who rejects discipline hates himself, but he who heeds rebukes loves his soul.<verse eid="PRO 15:32"/>

<verse sid="PRO 15:33"/>Fear of God is discipline and wisdom, and the beginning of glory will respond to it.<verse eid="PRO 15:33"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 16">
<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 16:1"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">16:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 16:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:2"/>All the works of the humble are manifest with God, but the impious shall perish in an evil day.<verse eid="PRO 16:2"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 16:3"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">16:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 16:3"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 16:4"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">16:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 16:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:5"/>Everyone who is arrogant is impure with God, and he who unjustly joins hands<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">16:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'unjustly joins hands':  I.e. 'assists in the making of false pledges'</char></note> will not be deemed innocent.<verse eid="PRO 16:5"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 16:6"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">16:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 16:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:7"/>The beginning of a good way is to do righteous things, and they are more acceptable with God than to bring sacrifices.<verse eid="PRO 16:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:8"/>He who seeks the Lord will find knowledge with righteousness, and they who seek him rightly will find peace.<verse eid="PRO 16:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:9"/>All the works of the Lord are done with righteousness, but the impious is kept for an evil day.<verse eid="PRO 16:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:10"/>There is an oracular shrine upon the lips of a king, and his mouth will not err in judgment.<verse eid="PRO 16:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:11"/>The tipping of the scale is righteousness with the Lord, and his works are righteous measures.<verse eid="PRO 16:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:12"/>An evildoer is an abomination to a king, for the throne of government is established by righteousness.<verse eid="PRO 16:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:13"/>Righteous lips are acceptable to a king, and he loves right words.<verse eid="PRO 16:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:14"/>The anger of a king is a messenger of death, but a wise man will pacify him.<verse eid="PRO 16:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:15"/>The son of a king is in the light of life, and they that are acceptable to him are like a late cloud.<verse eid="PRO 16:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:16"/>The young of wisdom are more desirable than gold, and the young of prudence more desirable than silver.<verse eid="PRO 16:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:17"/>The paths of life turn away from evil, and the ways of righteousness are length of existence. He who receives discipline will prosper, and he who heeds rebukes will become wise. He who heeds his ways preserves his own soul, and he who loves his life will spare his mouth.<verse eid="PRO 16:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:18"/>Pride goes before ruin, and malice before a fall.<verse eid="PRO 16:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:19"/>Better is a person of gentle mind with humility than he who divides spoils with the proud.<verse eid="PRO 16:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:20"/>One who is capable in business is a discoverer of good things, but he who trusts in God is most fortunate.<verse eid="PRO 16:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:21"/>Some call the wise and intelligent worthless, but they who are pleasant in speech will be heard more.<verse eid="PRO 16:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:22"/>Insight is a fountain of life to its possessors, but the discipline of fools is evil.<verse eid="PRO 16:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:23"/>The heart of the wise will consider what comes from his own mouth, and on his lips he will bear prudence.<verse eid="PRO 16:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:24"/>Noble words are honeycombs, and its sweetness a healing for the soul.<verse eid="PRO 16:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:25"/>There are ways that seem to be right for a man, but their ends look towards Hades' depth.<verse eid="PRO 16:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:26"/>A man at labor labors for himself and fences off his own destruction, but the crooked carries destruction in his own mouth.<verse eid="PRO 16:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:27"/>A foolish man digs up evil for himself, and treasures fire on his own lips.<verse eid="PRO 16:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:28"/>A crooked man spreads evil and will kindle with evil a torch of deceit, and he separates friends.<verse eid="PRO 16:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:29"/>A man who transgresses makes trial of friends and leads them in ways that are not good.<verse eid="PRO 16:29"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:30"/>He who fixes his eyes considers perverse things, and he marks out with his lips all evil; he is a furnace of evil.<verse eid="PRO 16:30"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:31"/>Old age is a crown of boasting; however, it is gained in the ways of righteousness.<verse eid="PRO 16:31"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:32"/>A man who is slow to anger is better than the mighty, and he who controls his temper better than one who captures a city.<verse eid="PRO 16:32"/>

<verse sid="PRO 16:33"/>All things come upon the unrighteous into their laps, but all righteous things come from the Lord.<verse eid="PRO 16:33"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 17">
<verse sid="PRO 17:1"/>Better is a morsel with pleasure in peace than a house full of many good things and unjust sacrifices with strife.<verse eid="PRO 17:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:2"/>An intelligent domestic will rule over foolish masters and will divide portions among brothers.<verse eid="PRO 17:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:3"/>As silver and gold are tried in a furnace, so are choice hearts with the Lord.<verse eid="PRO 17:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:4"/>A bad person listens to the tongue of transgressors, but a righteous person does not give heed to false lips.<verse eid="PRO 17:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:5"/>He who laughs at the poor provokes his maker, and he who rejoices at one being destroyed will not go unpunished. But he who has compassion will find mercy.<verse eid="PRO 17:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:6"/>Children's children are a crown for the aged, and their fathers are the boast of children. (6a) The faithful has the whole world full of money, but the faithless not even a farthing.<verse eid="PRO 17:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:7"/>Faithful lips will not suit a fool, nor false lips the righteous.<verse eid="PRO 17:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:8"/>Discipline is a gracious wage to them that use it, and wherever it turns, it will prosper.<verse eid="PRO 17:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:9"/>He who conceals wrongdoings seeks friendship, but he who hates to conceal them separates friends and family.<verse eid="PRO 17:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:10"/>A threat shatters the heart of a prudent person, but a fool, though whipped, does not comprehend.<verse eid="PRO 17:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:11"/>Every bad person stirs up controversies, but the Lord will send out against him a cruel messenger.<verse eid="PRO 17:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:12"/>Care will befall a man of understanding, but fools will consider evil.<verse eid="PRO 17:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:13"/>He who requites evil for good-- evil shall not be moved from his house.<verse eid="PRO 17:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:14"/>Righteous rule gives power to words, but sedition and strife precede want.<verse eid="PRO 17:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:15"/>He who judges the unjust just and the just unjust is unclean and abominable with God.<verse eid="PRO 17:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:16"/>Why should fools have money? For the heartless will not be able to buy wisdom. (16a) He who makes his own house high is looking for ruin, and the one who is too crooked to learn will fall into evil.<verse eid="PRO 17:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:17"/>You should have a friend for every season, but let brothers be supportive in distress, for on this account are they born.<verse eid="PRO 17:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:18"/>A foolish man applauds and rejoices over himself; as well, he who pledges himself ought to answer for his own friend.<verse eid="PRO 17:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:19"/>A lover of sin rejoices in fights,<verse eid="PRO 17:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:20"/>but the hard-hearted does not meet up with good things. A man who is fickle of tongue will fall into evil,<verse eid="PRO 17:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:21"/>and the heart of a fool is grief to its possessor. A father does not rejoice over an uninstructed son, but a prudent son gladdens his mother.<verse eid="PRO 17:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:22"/>A cheerful heart promotes well-being, but the bones of a depressed man dry up.<verse eid="PRO 17:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:23"/>The ways of one who unjustly receives bribes in his pocket do not prosper, and the impious perverts the ways of righteousness.<verse eid="PRO 17:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:24"/>The face of a wise person is intelligent, but the eyes of the fool are on the ends of the earth.<verse eid="PRO 17:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:25"/>A foolish son is a cause of anger to his father and a grief to her who bore him.<verse eid="PRO 17:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:26"/>It is not good to punish a righteous man, nor is it pious to plot against righteous rulers.<verse eid="PRO 17:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:27"/>He who is careful to utter a harsh word is discreet, and a patient man is sensible.<verse eid="PRO 17:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 17:28"/>Wisdom will be imputed to a silly person who asks after wisdom, but someone who keeps himself speechless will seem to be sensible.<verse eid="PRO 17:28"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 18">
<verse sid="PRO 18:1"/>A man who wishes to separate from friends is looking for excuses, but he will be liable to reproach at all times.<verse eid="PRO 18:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:2"/>A person lacking in sense feels no need for wisdom, for he is much more led by folly.<verse eid="PRO 18:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:3"/>When the impious comes into a depth of evils, he shows contempt, but disgrace and reproach come upon him.<verse eid="PRO 18:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:4"/>A word in the heart of a man is deep water, and a river and a fountain of life spring forth.<verse eid="PRO 18:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:5"/>It is not good to respect the person of the impious, nor is it pious to pervert justice in judgment.<verse eid="PRO 18:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:6"/>A fool's lips bring him into troubles, and his bold mouth calls upon death.<verse eid="PRO 18:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:7"/>A fool's mouth is his ruin, and his lips are a snare to his soul.<verse eid="PRO 18:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:8"/>Fear casts down the timid, and the souls of the effeminate will suffer hunger.<verse eid="PRO 18:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:9"/>He who does not cure himself by his labor is akin to him who injures himself.<verse eid="PRO 18:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:10"/>The name of the Lord is of majestic strength, and the righteous, when they run to it, are exalted.<verse eid="PRO 18:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:11"/>The substance of a rich man is a strong city, and its glory casts a huge shadow.<verse eid="PRO 18:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:12"/>Before ruin a man's heart is exalted, but before honor it is humble.<verse eid="PRO 18:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:13"/>He who gives an answer before listening-- it is folly and reproach to him.<verse eid="PRO 18:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:14"/>A sensible attendant calms a man's anger, but who can endure a faint-hearted man?<verse eid="PRO 18:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:15"/>The heart of the sensible acquires perception, and the ears of the wise seek insight.<verse eid="PRO 18:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:16"/>A person's gift gives him space and seats him among the powerful.<verse eid="PRO 18:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:17"/>The righteous accuses himself in his introduction, but when he attacks, the adversary is refuted.<verse eid="PRO 18:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:18"/>Casting the lot puts an end to disputes and decides between the powerful.<verse eid="PRO 18:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:19"/>A brother helped by a brother is like a fortified and lofty city and is as strong as a firmly founded palace.<verse eid="PRO 18:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:20"/>With the fruits of his mouth a man fills his belly, and with the fruits of his lips he will be satisfied.<verse eid="PRO 18:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:21"/>Death and life are in the power of the tongue, and they who control it will eat its fruits.<verse eid="PRO 18:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 18:22"/>He who has found a good wife has found favors and has received cheerfulness from God. (22a) He who rejects a good wife rejects the good, but he who keeps an adulteress is foolish and impious.<verse eid="PRO 18:22"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 19">
<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 19:1"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">19:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 19:1"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 19:2"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">19:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 19:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:3"/>A man's folly corrupts his ways; yet in his heart he blames God.<verse eid="PRO 19:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:4"/>Wealth adds many friends, but the poor is deserted even by the only friend he has.<verse eid="PRO 19:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:5"/>A false witness will not go unpunished, and he who accuses unjustly will not escape.<verse eid="PRO 19:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:6"/>Many render service to the persons of kings, but every evil one becomes a reproach to a man.<verse eid="PRO 19:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:7"/>Every one who hates a poor brother will also be far from friendship. Insight will draw near to them who know it, and a prudent man will find it. He who does much evil perfects wickedness, and he who uses provoking words will not be saved.<verse eid="PRO 19:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:8"/>He who procures prudence loves himself, and he who guards prudence will find good.<verse eid="PRO 19:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:9"/>A false witness will not go unpunished, and whosoever will kindle evil will perish by it.<verse eid="PRO 19:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:10"/>It is not fitting for a fool to have delights, nor if a domestic should begin to rule with hubris.<verse eid="PRO 19:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:11"/>A merciful man is long-suffering, and his boast comes upon transgressors.<verse eid="PRO 19:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:12"/>The threat of a king is like the roaring of a lion, but as dew on grass, so is his cheerfulness.<verse eid="PRO 19:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:13"/>A foolish son is a disgrace to his father, and vows from the price of a prostitute are not pure.<verse eid="PRO 19:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:14"/>Fathers distribute house and substance to their children, but a woman is joined to a man by God.<verse eid="PRO 19:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:15"/>Timidity restrains the effeminate, and the soul of the idle will suffer hunger.<verse eid="PRO 19:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:16"/>He who keeps a commandment preserves his own soul, but he who despises his own ways will perish.<verse eid="PRO 19:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:17"/>He who has compassion on the poor lends to God, and he will repay him according to his gift.<verse eid="PRO 19:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:18"/>Discipline your son, for thus he will be hopeful, but do not be roused in your soul to hubris.<verse eid="PRO 19:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:19"/>A malicious man will be severely punished, and if he causes injury, he will even add his soul.<verse eid="PRO 19:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:20"/>My son, listen to the discipline of your father, that you may become wise for the future.<verse eid="PRO 19:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:21"/>There are many thoughts in a man's heart, but the counsel of the Lord remains forever.<verse eid="PRO 19:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:22"/>Compassion is a profit for a man, and a poor righteous person is better than a rich liar.<verse eid="PRO 19:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:23"/>The fear of the Lord becomes life for a man, and he who is without fear will stay in places where knowledge does not keep watch.<verse eid="PRO 19:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:24"/>He who unjustly hides his hands in his bosom will never ever bring them to his mouth.<verse eid="PRO 19:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:25"/>When a pestiferous person is being whipped, a fool will become more crafty, but if you reprove a prudent man, he will gain perception.<verse eid="PRO 19:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:26"/>He who disgraces his father and drives away his mother will be put to shame and will become rebuked.<verse eid="PRO 19:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:27"/>The son who stops keeping the discipline of his father will contemplate evil sayings.<verse eid="PRO 19:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:28"/>He who gives surety for a foolish child will insult what is deemed right, and the mouth of the impious will devour judgments.<verse eid="PRO 19:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 19:29"/>Lashes are prepared for the intemperate, and flogging for the backs of the foolish.<verse eid="PRO 19:29"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 20">
<verse sid="PRO 20:1"/>Wine is an intemperate thing, and strong drink is something insolent, and everyone who mixes with it will not be wise.<verse eid="PRO 20:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:2"/>The threat of a king does not differ from the rage of a lion, and he who provokes him sins against his own life.<verse eid="PRO 20:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:3"/>It is good repute for a man to refrain from strife, but every fool is entangled in such things.<verse eid="PRO 20:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:4"/>Though the lazy is reproached, he is not ashamed; likewise also to the one who borrows grain in harvest.<verse eid="PRO 20:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:5"/>The counsel in a man's heart is deep water, but a sensible man will extract it.<verse eid="PRO 20:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:6"/>Humankind is something great, and a compassionate man something precious, but to find a faithful man is a chore.<verse eid="PRO 20:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:7"/>He who dwells blameless in righteousness will leave his children happy.<verse eid="PRO 20:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:8"/>When a righteous king sits on his throne, he does not oppose anything wicked with his eyes.<verse eid="PRO 20:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:9"/>Who can boast that he keeps his heart pure? Or who can declare confidently that he is pure from sins? (9a) The lamp of one who curses father or mother will be extinguished, and the pupils of his eyes will see darkness. (9b) A portion quickly acquired at first will not be blessed in the end. (9c) Do not say: I will repay my enemy, but wait for the Lord that he may help you.<verse eid="PRO 20:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:10"/>A large and a small weight, and double measures, are impure in the eyes of the Lord-- both of them,<verse eid="PRO 20:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:11"/>and he who makes these will be shackled by his practices. A young man in the company of a pious person-- straight indeed will be his way.<verse eid="PRO 20:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:12"/>The ear hears, and the eye sees; both are works of the Lord.<verse eid="PRO 20:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:13"/>Do not love calumny, lest you be destroyed; open your eyes, and be filled with bread.<verse eid="PRO 20:13"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 20:14"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">20:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 20:14"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 20:15"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">20:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 20:15"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 20:16"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">20:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 20:16"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 20:17"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">20:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 20:17"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 20:18"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">20:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 20:18"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 20:19"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">20:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 20:19"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 20:20"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">20:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 20:20"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 20:21"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">20:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 20:21"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 20:22"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">20:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 20:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:23"/>An ambiguous weight is an abomination to the Lord, and a false balance is not a good thing before him.<verse eid="PRO 20:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:24"/>A man's steps are directed by the Lord, and a mortal-- how could he understand his ways?<verse eid="PRO 20:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:25"/>Quickly to consecrate something of his own is a snare to a man, for after making a vow a change of mind can happen.<verse eid="PRO 20:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:26"/>A wise king is a winnower of the impious, and he will put a wheel on them.<verse eid="PRO 20:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:27"/>The light of the Lord is the breath of humans, he who searches the innermost parts of the belly.<verse eid="PRO 20:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:28"/>Compassion and truth are a guard to a king, and they will encircle his throne with righteousness.<verse eid="PRO 20:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:29"/>Wisdom is an ornament to young men, and grey hair the glory of the aged.<verse eid="PRO 20:29"/>

<verse sid="PRO 20:30"/>Bruises and wounds befall evil men, and plagues in the innermost parts of the belly.<verse eid="PRO 20:30"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 21">
<verse sid="PRO 21:1"/>Like a stream of water, so is the heart of a king in God's hand. Wherever he decides to turn it, thither he inclines it.<verse eid="PRO 21:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:2"/>Every man seems righteous to himself; however, the Lord directs hearts.<verse eid="PRO 21:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:3"/>To do right and to be truthful is more pleasing with God than blood of sacrifices.<verse eid="PRO 21:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:4"/>An arrogant person is bold-hearted in hubris, and sin is the lamp of the impious.<verse eid="PRO 21:4"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 21:5"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">21:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 21:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:6"/>He who obtains treasures by a lying tongue pursues vanity into the snares of death.<verse eid="PRO 21:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:7"/>Ruin will be entertained by the impious, because they do not want to do what is just.<verse eid="PRO 21:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:8"/>To the crooked God sends crooked ways, for his works are pure and upright.<verse eid="PRO 21:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:9"/>It is better to live in a corner in the open than in plastered quarters and in a shared<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">21:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'with a wife'</char></note> house with injustice.<verse eid="PRO 21:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:10"/>The soul of the impious will not receive compassion from anybody.<verse eid="PRO 21:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:11"/>When the intemperate is punished, the innocent becomes more wily, but a wise man understands he will gain knowledge.<verse eid="PRO 21:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:12"/>A righteous person understands the heart of the impious and despises the impious because of their evil.<verse eid="PRO 21:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:13"/>He who blocks his ears so as not to hear the weak will himself also call, and there will be nobody who listens.<verse eid="PRO 21:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:14"/>A secret gift averts anger, but he who is sparing with gifts arouses fierce wrath.<verse eid="PRO 21:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:15"/>It is a joy to the righteous to do justice, but according to evildoers a devout person is impure.<verse eid="PRO 21:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:16"/>A man who strays from the path of righteousness will rest in the gathering of giants.<verse eid="PRO 21:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:17"/>A needy man loves joy; he likes wine and oil in abundance.<verse eid="PRO 21:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:18"/>And a lawless person is the refuse of a righteous one.<verse eid="PRO 21:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:19"/>It is better to live in a desert land than with a quarrelsome and talkative and irritable wife.<verse eid="PRO 21:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:20"/>A desirable treasure will rest in the mouth of the wise, but foolish men will swallow it.<verse eid="PRO 21:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:21"/>A way of righteousness and compassion will find life and honor.<verse eid="PRO 21:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:22"/>A wise person attacked strong cities and demolished the strongholds in which the impious trusted.<verse eid="PRO 21:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:23"/>He who guards his mouth and tongue keeps his soul out of trouble.<verse eid="PRO 21:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:24"/>The bold and audacious and pretentious is called a pest, and he who contemplates evil is a transgressor of the law.<verse eid="PRO 21:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:25"/>Desires kill the lazy, for his hands choose not to do anything.<verse eid="PRO 21:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:26"/>The impious longs for wicked desires all day long, but the righteous has compassion and pity unsparingly.<verse eid="PRO 21:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:27"/>The sacrifice of the impious is an abomination to the Lord, for they even offer them unlawfully.<verse eid="PRO 21:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:28"/>A false witness will perish, but an obedient man will speak cautiously.<verse eid="PRO 21:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:29"/>An impious man impudently resists with his face, but the upright-- he understands his ways.<verse eid="PRO 21:29"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:30"/>There is no wisdom; there is no courage; there is no counsel against the impious.<verse eid="PRO 21:30"/>

<verse sid="PRO 21:31"/>A horse is prepared for the day of battle, but assistance is from the Lord.<verse eid="PRO 21:31"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 22">
<verse sid="PRO 22:1"/>A good name is a better choice than great wealth, and good favor is above silver and gold.<verse eid="PRO 22:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:2"/>The rich and the poor have encountered each other, but the Lord has made them both.<verse eid="PRO 22:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:3"/>When the clever sees the wicked severely punished, he himself is being educated, but the fools passed by and were penalized.<verse eid="PRO 22:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:4"/>The offspring of wisdom is the fear of the Lord as well as riches and honor and life.<verse eid="PRO 22:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:5"/>Thorns and snares are in crooked ways, but he who guards his own soul will keep far from them.<verse eid="PRO 22:5"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 22:6"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">22:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 22:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:7"/>The rich rule over the poor, but domestics will lend to their own masters.<verse eid="PRO 22:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:8"/>He who sows what is cheap will reap what is bad and will complete the impact of his deeds. (8a) God blesses a cheerful and generous man, but he will bring to an end the vanity of his deeds.<verse eid="PRO 22:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:9"/>He who has compassion over the poor will himself be nourished, because he gave his own food to the poor. (9a) He who hands out gifts secures victory and honor; moreover, he takes away the soul of those who have possessions.<verse eid="PRO 22:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:10"/>Expel from the council an irritating person and strife will exit with him, for when he takes a seat in the council, he disgraces all.<verse eid="PRO 22:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:11"/>The Lord loves devout hearts, and all the blameless are acceptable to him. A king herds with his lips.<verse eid="PRO 22:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:12"/>Now the eyes of the Lord keep watch over perception, but the transgressor holds words cheap.<verse eid="PRO 22:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:13"/>A lazy person makes excuses and says: "There is a lion on the roads and murderers in the streets!"<verse eid="PRO 22:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:14"/>The mouth of the transgressor is a deep hole, and he who is hated by the Lord will fall into it. (14a) There are bad ways before a man, and he prefers not to avoid them, even though he should avoid a crooked and bad way.<verse eid="PRO 22:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:15"/>Folly clings to the heart of a young boy, but the rod and discipline are far away from him.<verse eid="PRO 22:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:16"/>He who oppresses the needy makes many things his own, yet gives to the rich to make it less.<verse eid="PRO 22:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:17"/>Incline your ear to the words of the wise, and hear my word, and apply your heart, that you may know that they are good.<verse eid="PRO 22:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:18"/>And if you take them to heart, they will also give you pleasure on your lips<verse eid="PRO 22:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:19"/>in order that your hope be upon the Lord and that he may reveal to you his way.<verse eid="PRO 22:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:20"/>Now then, copy them for yourself three times over, for counsel and knowledge on the surface of your heart.<verse eid="PRO 22:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:21"/>Therefore I teach you a true word and good knowledge to heed in order that you may answer words of truth to them who question you.<verse eid="PRO 22:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:22"/>Do not treat the needy with violence, for he is poor, nor disgrace the weak at the gates.<verse eid="PRO 22:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:23"/>For the Lord will judge his case, and you shall rescue your life inviolate.<verse eid="PRO 22:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:24"/>Be no companion of a fierce man, nor associate with a passionate friend,<verse eid="PRO 22:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:25"/>lest you learn from his ways and take snares to your soul.<verse eid="PRO 22:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:26"/>Do not give yourself as surety because you feel shame before a person;<verse eid="PRO 22:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:27"/>for if you have nothing with which to pay, they will take the bed that is under your side.<verse eid="PRO 22:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:28"/>Do not remove ancient borders which your fathers set up.<verse eid="PRO 22:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 22:29"/>A man with vision and skilled in his work should serve before kings and should not serve slothful men.<verse eid="PRO 22:29"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 23">
<verse sid="PRO 23:1"/>If you sit down to eat at the table of rulers, observe carefully what has been set for you,<verse eid="PRO 23:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:2"/>and extend your hand, since you know that you will have to prepare such things.<verse eid="PRO 23:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:3"/>And if you are rather insatiate, do not desire his delicacies, for these pertain to a fake life.<verse eid="PRO 23:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:4"/>If you are poor, do not measure yourself with the rich, but be restrained by your own insight.<verse eid="PRO 23:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:5"/>If you set your eyes upon him, he will disappear totally, for he has been equipped with wings as of an eagle and he returns to the house of his master.<verse eid="PRO 23:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:6"/>Do not dine with a malicious man, nor should you desire his food.<verse eid="PRO 23:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:7"/>For in the same manner as one swallows a hair so he eats and drinks.<verse eid="PRO 23:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:8"/>Do not bring him in to you, nor eat your morsel with him, for he will vomit it up and will spoil your noble words.<verse eid="PRO 23:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:9"/>Say nothing in the ears of a fool, lest he despise your judicious words.<verse eid="PRO 23:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:10"/>Do not relocate ancient borders, nor enter the possession of orphans,<verse eid="PRO 23:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:11"/>for the Lord who redeems them is strong and he will plead their case with you.<verse eid="PRO 23:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:12"/>Give your heart to discipline, and prepare your ears for words of perception.<verse eid="PRO 23:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:13"/>Do not refrain from disciplining a child, for if you beat him with a rod, he will not die;<verse eid="PRO 23:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:14"/>for indeed you shall beat him with a rod and will rescue his soul from death.<verse eid="PRO 23:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:15"/>My son, if your heart is wise, you will gladden my heart as well.<verse eid="PRO 23:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:16"/>And your lips will hold conversation with my lips, if they are upright.<verse eid="PRO 23:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:17"/>Let your heart not envy sinners, but be in the fear of the Lord throughout the day.<verse eid="PRO 23:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:18"/>For if you keep these things you will have progeny, and your hope will not be removed.<verse eid="PRO 23:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:19"/>Listen my son, and become wise, and direct the insight of your heart.<verse eid="PRO 23:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:20"/>Be not a winebibber, nor prolong in shared meals or at the purchasing of meat.<verse eid="PRO 23:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:21"/>For every drunkard and glutton will become poor, and every sluggard will clothe himself with tatters and rags.<verse eid="PRO 23:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:22"/>Listen, my son, to your father who begot you, and do not despise her when your mother gets old.<verse eid="PRO 23:22"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="PRO 23:23"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">23:23</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="PRO 23:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:24"/>A righteous father raises well, and his soul rejoices in his wise son.<verse eid="PRO 23:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:25"/>Let father and mother be glad over you, and let her who bore you rejoice.<verse eid="PRO 23:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:26"/>My son, give me your heart, and let your eyes observe my ways.<verse eid="PRO 23:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:27"/>For a pierced cask is a strange house, and a strange well is narrow.<verse eid="PRO 23:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:28"/>For it will quickly perish, and every transgressor will be destroyed.<verse eid="PRO 23:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:29"/>Who has woe? Who has trouble? Who has strife? Who has vexations and squabbles? Who has wounds without reason? Who has blood-shot eyes?<verse eid="PRO 23:29"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:30"/>Are they not those who linger long over wine, who frequent places where drinking takes place?<verse eid="PRO 23:30"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:31"/>Do not get drunk from wine; rather converse with righteous people, and converse in public places; for if you give your eyes to saucers and goblets, you will afterwards walk around more naked than a pestle.<verse eid="PRO 23:31"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:32"/>But finally he stretches himself out like one struck by a snake, and venom is diffused in him as by a horned serpent.<verse eid="PRO 23:32"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:33"/>When your eyes see a strange woman, then your mouth will speak perversely.<verse eid="PRO 23:33"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:34"/>And you will lie as in the heart of the sea and like a navigator in a large wave.<verse eid="PRO 23:34"/>

<verse sid="PRO 23:35"/>Then you will say: "They struck me, but I felt no pain, and they insulted me, but I did not realize it. When will it be morning, that I may go and seek with whom I will go together?"<verse eid="PRO 23:35"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 24">
<verse sid="PRO 24:1"/>My son, do not envy wicked men, nor desire to be with them,<verse eid="PRO 24:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:2"/>for their hearts contemplate lies and their lips utter trouble.<verse eid="PRO 24:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:3"/>With wisdom a house is built, and with understanding it is established.<verse eid="PRO 24:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:4"/>With perception the storerooms are filled from all precious and beautiful riches.<verse eid="PRO 24:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:5"/>The wise is better than the strong, and a man who has prudence than he who has a large field.<verse eid="PRO 24:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:6"/>With strategic planning war is conducted, and help with a counseled heart.<verse eid="PRO 24:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:7"/>Wisdom and insight are to be found in the gates of the wise, and the wise do not turn away from the mouth of the Lord.<verse eid="PRO 24:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:8"/>But they caucus in the assemblies; death meets the uninstructed,<verse eid="PRO 24:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:9"/>and a fool dies by sin, and a pestilent man will be polluted by impurity<verse eid="PRO 24:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:10"/>in an evil day and a day of affliction until he deceases.<verse eid="PRO 24:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:11"/>Rescue them who are led to death, and buy back those who are to be slaughtered; do not delay!<verse eid="PRO 24:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:12"/>If you say: "I do not know this person," be aware that the Lord is familiar with the heart of everyone, and he who formed breath for all, he knows everything, he who will render to each according to his deeds.<verse eid="PRO 24:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:13"/>My son, eat honey, for the honeycomb is good, that your palate may be sweetened.<verse eid="PRO 24:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:14"/>Thus you shall perceive wisdom with your soul, for if you find it, your end will be good and hope will not forsake you.<verse eid="PRO 24:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:15"/>Do not lead the impious to the pastures of the righteous; also do not be misled by a full stomach.<verse eid="PRO 24:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:16"/>For the righteous may fall seven times, but he will rise again, but the impious will be powerless in evil.<verse eid="PRO 24:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:17"/>If your enemy falls, do not rejoice over him, nor be elated by his stumbling;<verse eid="PRO 24:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:18"/>for the Lord will observe it, and it will not please him, and he will turn away his anger from him.<verse eid="PRO 24:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:19"/>Do not rejoice over evildoers, nor envy sinners.<verse eid="PRO 24:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:20"/>For progeny of the wicked will not continue, and the lamp of the impious will be extinguished.<verse eid="PRO 24:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:21"/>My son, fear God and the king, and disobey neither of them,<verse eid="PRO 24:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:22"/>for they will unexpectedly punish the impious and who shall know their punishments? (22a) A son who keeps the word will be far removed from destruction, for he received it willingly. (22b) Let no falsehood be spoken to the king from the tongue, and no falsehood will proceed from his tongue. (22c) The tongue of the king is a dagger and not of flesh, and whoever is handed over will be destroyed; (22d) for if his anger is sharpened it kills people with thongs, (22e) and it devours the bones of people and consumes them like a flame so that they are not food for young eagles!<verse eid="PRO 24:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:23"/><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">24:23</char><char closed="false" style="ft">[30.1-14 precedes 24.23 and 30.15-31.9 follows 24.34]</char></note>Now these things I also say to you who are wise, that you know them: "It is not good to be in awe of a person in judgement."<verse eid="PRO 24:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:24"/>He who says of the impious "He is righteous" will be cursed by peoples and be hateful to nations.<verse eid="PRO 24:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:25"/>But those who rebuke will appear better, and a good blessing will come upon them.<verse eid="PRO 24:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:26"/>And they will kiss lips that answer good words.<verse eid="PRO 24:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:27"/>Prepare your work for your departure, and be fully prepared for the field; also follow behind me, and you will rebuild your house.<verse eid="PRO 24:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:28"/>Do not be a false witness against your fellow citizen, nor overstate with your lips.<verse eid="PRO 24:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:29"/>Do not say: "I will use him in the same way as he has used me, and I will punish him for the injustice he did to me."<verse eid="PRO 24:29"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:30"/>A foolish man is like a tilled field, and a person lacking sense is like a vineyard.<verse eid="PRO 24:30"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:31"/>If you leave it alone, it will become barren and will be totally overrun by weeds and neglected, and its stone fences will be broken down.<verse eid="PRO 24:31"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:32"/>Thereafter I repented; I looked around in order to glean discipline.<verse eid="PRO 24:32"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:33"/>I doze a little; then I slumber a little, and I fold my arms over my breast a little.<verse eid="PRO 24:33"/>

<verse sid="PRO 24:34"/>But if this is what you do, poverty will come over you, when it advances, and want like a good courier.<verse eid="PRO 24:34"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 25">
<verse sid="PRO 25:1"/>These are the miscellaneous systems of education of Salomon, which the friends of Hezekias, king of Judea, copied.<verse eid="PRO 25:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:2"/>Divine glory conceals a matter, but the glory of a king honors action.<verse eid="PRO 25:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:3"/>Heaven is high, and earth is deep, and a king's heart is unfathomable.<verse eid="PRO 25:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:4"/>Strike the unrefined silver, and everything pure will be purified.<verse eid="PRO 25:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:5"/>Cut off the impious from the presence of the king, and his throne will be established in righteousness.<verse eid="PRO 25:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:6"/>Do not boast in front of the king; and do not linger in the places of rulers,<verse eid="PRO 25:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:7"/>for it is better that it be said to you: "Come to me" than to humiliate you in the presence of a ruler. What your eyes have seen say.<verse eid="PRO 25:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:8"/>Do not get involved in a fight quickly in order that you may not regret it in the end. When your friend reproaches you,<verse eid="PRO 25:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:9"/>withdraw; do not show contempt,<verse eid="PRO 25:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:10"/>lest your friend reproach you and your quarrel and enmity will not end but will be tantamount to death. (10a) Favor and friendship bring freedom; keep them for yourself, that you may not be subject to reproach, but guard your ways with fair dealing.<verse eid="PRO 25:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:11"/>As an apple of gold in a necklace of Sardian stone, so it is to speak a word.<verse eid="PRO 25:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:12"/>A costly Sardian stone is fastened to a golden earring-- a wise word to an obedient ear!<verse eid="PRO 25:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:13"/>As snowfall during harvest is beneficial against the heat, so is a faithful messenger to those who sent him, for he benefits the souls of those who make use of him.<verse eid="PRO 25:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:14"/>As winds and clouds and rains are exceedingly apparent, so are they who boast over a false gift.<verse eid="PRO 25:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:15"/>With patience a king has a safe journey, and a soft tongue breaks bones.<verse eid="PRO 25:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:16"/>If you find honey eat just enough, lest you be sated and vomit.<verse eid="PRO 25:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:17"/>Lead your foot sparingly to your own friend, lest he get too much of you and hate you.<verse eid="PRO 25:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:18"/>Pointed is a nail and a dagger and an arrow; so also is a man who bears false witness against his friend.<verse eid="PRO 25:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:19"/>The ways of an evil person and the foot of a transgressor will be destroyed in an evil day.<verse eid="PRO 25:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:20"/>As vinegar is harmful to a wound, so a calamity that befalls the body pains the heart. (20a) As a moth is to a garment and a worm is to wood, so a man's pain hurts the heart.<verse eid="PRO 25:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:21"/>If your enemy is hungry, nourish him; if he is thirsty, give him to drink.<verse eid="PRO 25:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:22"/>For by doing this you will heap coals of fire on his head, and the Lord will reward you with good things.<verse eid="PRO 25:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:23"/>The north wind raises clouds, and an impudent face provokes the tongue.<verse eid="PRO 25:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:24"/>It is better to live in the corner of a room than with an abusive wife in a shared<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">25:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'with a wife'</char></note> house.<verse eid="PRO 25:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:25"/>As cold water is soothing to a thirsty soul, so is good news from a far away land.<verse eid="PRO 25:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:26"/>Just as, if one should block a fountain and destroy an outlet of water, so it is unseemly that a righteous person fall before the impious.<verse eid="PRO 25:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:27"/>It is not good to eat much honey, but it is necessary to honor notable words.<verse eid="PRO 25:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 25:28"/>As a city is with its walls cast down and unfortified, so is a man who does everything without counsel.<verse eid="PRO 25:28"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 26">
<verse sid="PRO 26:1"/>Like dew in harvest and like rain in summer, so honor is impossible to the fool.<verse eid="PRO 26:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:2"/>As birds fly-- and sparrows, so a vain curse will not come upon anyone.<verse eid="PRO 26:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:3"/>Like a whip for a horse and a goad for a donkey, so is the rod for a lawless nation.<verse eid="PRO 26:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:4"/>Do not answer a fool in accordance with his folly, lest you become like him.<verse eid="PRO 26:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:5"/>But answer a fool according to his folly, lest he appear to be wise to himself.<verse eid="PRO 26:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:6"/>He who sends a message through a foolish messenger, from his own feet he will imbibe reproach.<verse eid="PRO 26:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:7"/>As it is to take away traveling from legs, so is a proverb from the mouth of fools.<verse eid="PRO 26:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:8"/>He who ties down a stone in a sling is like him who gives glory to a fool.<verse eid="PRO 26:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:9"/>Thorns grow in the hand of the drunkard, and slavery in the hand of fools.<verse eid="PRO 26:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:10"/>All flesh of fools is much exposed to winter cold, for their trance is being shattered.<verse eid="PRO 26:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:11"/>Like a dog, when he returns to his vomit, also becomes the more hated, so is a fool, when by his own wickedness, he returns to his own sin. (11a) There is a sense of shame that leads to sin, and there is a sense of shame that is glory and grace.<verse eid="PRO 26:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:12"/>I have seen a man who thought himself to be wise, but there is more hope for a fool than for him.<verse eid="PRO 26:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:13"/>A lazy person being sent on a journey says: "There is a lion on the road."<verse eid="PRO 26:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:14"/>As a door turns on its socket, so is a lazy person on his couch.<verse eid="PRO 26:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:15"/>When a lazy person hides his hand in his bosom, he will not be able to bring it to his mouth.<verse eid="PRO 26:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:16"/>A lazy person to himself seems wiser than he who, with satisfaction, returns a message.<verse eid="PRO 26:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:17"/>Like one grabbing a dog's tail, so is he who champions a cause not his own.<verse eid="PRO 26:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:18"/>As those who are being treated propound tales to people and he who encounters the tale will be the first to be tripped up,<verse eid="PRO 26:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:19"/>so are all who trick their own friends, and when they are discovered, they say: "I did it in jest."<verse eid="PRO 26:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:20"/>With much wood a fire is fueled, but where there is no agitator strife ceases.<verse eid="PRO 26:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:21"/>A hearth is for coals, and wood for fire, and an abusive man is for stirring up strife.<verse eid="PRO 26:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:22"/>The words of knaves are soft, but they strike into the deepest of one's inwards.<verse eid="PRO 26:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:23"/>Silver given with deceit must be considered like a potsherd; smooth lips conceal a heart that causes sorrow.<verse eid="PRO 26:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:24"/>A weeping enemy consents to everything with his lips, but in his heart he devises deceit.<verse eid="PRO 26:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:25"/>If an enemy begs you with a loud voice, do not be convinced, for there are seven iniquities in his soul.<verse eid="PRO 26:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:26"/>He who conceals enmity contrives deceit, but he exposes his own sins, being well- known in the councils.<verse eid="PRO 26:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:27"/>He who digs a hole for his neighbor will fall into it, and he who rolls a stone rolls it on himself.<verse eid="PRO 26:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 26:28"/>A false tongue hates truth, and an unguarded mouth works instability.<verse eid="PRO 26:28"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 27">
<verse sid="PRO 27:1"/>Do not boast about tomorrow, for you do not know what the next day will bear.<verse eid="PRO 27:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:2"/>Let someone near to you praise you and not your mouth, a stranger, and not your lips.<verse eid="PRO 27:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:3"/>A stone is heavy and sand is weighty, but the rage of a fool is heavier than both.<verse eid="PRO 27:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:4"/>Wrath is merciless and anger is passionate, but jealousy can bear no one.<verse eid="PRO 27:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:5"/>Better is open rebuke than hidden love.<verse eid="PRO 27:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:6"/>More trustworthy are the wounds of a friend than the spontaneous kisses of an enemy.<verse eid="PRO 27:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:7"/>A soul in plenitude scorns honeycombs, but to the needy soul even bitter things appear sweet.<verse eid="PRO 27:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:8"/>Like when a bird flies down from its nest, so a person becomes a slave when he is driven from his own place.<verse eid="PRO 27:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:9"/>With ointments and wines and perfumes the heart is delighted, but through misfortunes the soul is torn to pieces.<verse eid="PRO 27:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:10"/>Do not forsake your friend nor the friend of your father, and do not go to the house of your brother when you have bad luck. A friend nearby is better than a brother who lives far away.<verse eid="PRO 27:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:11"/>My son, be wise that my heart may be gladdened, and remove from you reproachable words.<verse eid="PRO 27:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:12"/>When evils approached, a clever person hid, but fools proceed and will pay the penalty.<verse eid="PRO 27:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:13"/>Remove his garment, for he passed by-- an insolent person who destroys what belongs to others.<verse eid="PRO 27:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:14"/>Whoever blesses a friend early in the morning with a loud voice will seem not to be different from one who is cursing.<verse eid="PRO 27:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:15"/>Drops on a rainy day drive a person from his house, likewise also an abusive wife, from his very own house.<verse eid="PRO 27:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:16"/>The north wind is a harsh wind, even though it is called by an auspicious name.<verse eid="PRO 27:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:17"/>Iron sharpens iron, and one man spurs on the person of his fellow.<verse eid="PRO 27:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:18"/>He who plants a fig tree will eat its fruit, and he who guards his own master will be honored.<verse eid="PRO 27:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:19"/>As faces are not similar to other faces, so neither the hearts of people.<verse eid="PRO 27:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:20"/>Hades and destruction are never satisfied; likewise insatiable are the eyes of people. (20a) An abomination to the Lord is a person who fixates his eye, also the uneducated, unable to control their tongue.<verse eid="PRO 27:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:21"/>Burning is a test for silver and gold, but a man is tested by the mouth of them who praise him. (21a) The heart of a lawless person seeks out evil, but an upright heart seeks out knowledge.<verse eid="PRO 27:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:22"/>If you beat a fool when he is disgraced in the council, you will never remove his folly.<verse eid="PRO 27:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:23"/>You shall know well the souls of your flock, and you shall fasten your heart to your herds,<verse eid="PRO 27:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:24"/>for a man's power and strength do not last forever; neither can he transmit it from one generation to another.<verse eid="PRO 27:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:25"/>Take care of the greens on the plain, and you will cut grass; also gather the fodder from the hills,<verse eid="PRO 27:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:26"/>that you may have sheep for clothing. Value a plain that you may have lambs.<verse eid="PRO 27:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 27:27"/>My son, you have sayings from me powerful for your life and for the life of your attendants.<verse eid="PRO 27:27"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 28">
<verse sid="PRO 28:1"/>The impious flees when no one is pursuing, but the righteous is confident like a lion.<verse eid="PRO 28:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:2"/>By the sin of the impious disputes arise, but a clever man will quell them.<verse eid="PRO 28:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:3"/>A bold man blackmails the poor with impious acts. Like a violent and useless rain,<verse eid="PRO 28:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:4"/>so those who forsake the law praise impiety, but those who love the law build a wall around themselves.<verse eid="PRO 28:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:5"/>Evil men will not consider judgment, but those who seek the Lord will understand in everything.<verse eid="PRO 28:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:6"/>Better is a poor person who walks in truth than a rich liar.<verse eid="PRO 28:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:7"/>An intelligent son keeps the law, but he who feeds debauchery disgraces his father.<verse eid="PRO 28:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:8"/>He who increases his wealth with interest and excess gathers it for him who has empathy for the poor.<verse eid="PRO 28:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:9"/>He who turns away his ear not to listen to the law-- he too has made his prayer abominable.<verse eid="PRO 28:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:10"/>He who misleads the upright into an evil way will himself fall into destruction. And the lawless will pass through good things but will not enter into them.<verse eid="PRO 28:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:11"/>A rich man is wise in his own eyes, but an intelligent poor person will see through him.<verse eid="PRO 28:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:12"/>For helping the righteous there is great honor, but in the places of the impious people are trapped.<verse eid="PRO 28:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:13"/>He who conceals his own impiety will not prosper, but he who expounds reproofs will be loved.<verse eid="PRO 28:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:14"/>Happy is the man who reveres everything with discretion, but he who is hard of heart will fall into evil.<verse eid="PRO 28:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:15"/>A hungry lion and a thirsty wolf is he who rules a needy nation while he himself is poor.<verse eid="PRO 28:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:16"/>A king deficient in revenues is a great swindler, but he who hates injustice will live for a long time.<verse eid="PRO 28:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:17"/>He who acts as surety for a man charged with murder will be a fugitive but not in safety. (17a) Instruct a son, and he will love you, and he will give your soul an ornament. You shall not obey a lawless nation.<verse eid="PRO 28:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:18"/>He who walks righteously has been helped, but he who walks in crooked ways will get entangled.<verse eid="PRO 28:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:19"/>He who tills his own land will have plenty of bread, but he who pursues idleness will have plenty of need.<verse eid="PRO 28:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:20"/>A trustworthy man will be much praised, but the evil will not go unpunished.<verse eid="PRO 28:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:21"/>He who does not feel shame before the person of the righteous is not good; such a person will hand over a man for a piece of bread.<verse eid="PRO 28:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:22"/>An envious man is in a hurry to get rich and he does not know that one who is merciful will prevail over him.<verse eid="PRO 28:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:23"/>He who rebukes the ways of man will have greater favor than he who has a flattering tongue.<verse eid="PRO 28:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:24"/>He who rejects father and mother and thinks that he does not sin, he is indeed the partner of an impious man.<verse eid="PRO 28:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:25"/>A greedy man judges rashly, but he who trusts in the Lord will be attentive.<verse eid="PRO 28:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:26"/>He who trusts in a bold heart, such a one is a fool, but he who walks in wisdom will be saved.<verse eid="PRO 28:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:27"/>He who gives to the poor will not have want, but he who turns a blind eye will be in dire straits.<verse eid="PRO 28:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 28:28"/>In the places of the impious the righteous groan, but by the destruction of them the righteous will be multiplied.<verse eid="PRO 28:28"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 29">
<verse sid="PRO 29:1"/>A man who reproves is better than a stubborn man, for, when he is suddenly set on fire, there is no healing.<verse eid="PRO 29:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:2"/>When the righteous are praised, the people will rejoice, but when the impious rule, men groan.<verse eid="PRO 29:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:3"/>When a man loves wisdom, his father is glad, but he who cherishes prostitutes will squander wealth.<verse eid="PRO 29:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:4"/>A righteous king raises up a land, but a lawless man undermines it.<verse eid="PRO 29:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:5"/>He who prepares a net before the face of his own friend spreads it for his own feet.<verse eid="PRO 29:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:6"/>For a man who sins there is a great snare, but a righteous person will have joy and mirth.<verse eid="PRO 29:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:7"/>The righteous knows how to judge for the needy, but the impious will not understand knowledge, and the poor person does not have a discriminating mind.<verse eid="PRO 29:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:8"/>Pestilent men set a city aflame, but the wise turned away wrath.<verse eid="PRO 29:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:9"/>A wise man judges nations, but when a worthless man is angry he ridicules and has no fear.<verse eid="PRO 29:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:10"/>Men who are partakers in bloodshed will hate the devout, but the upright will seek out his soul.<verse eid="PRO 29:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:11"/>A fool declares his whole anger, but the wise reserves it in part.<verse eid="PRO 29:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:12"/>When a king listens to an unjust word, all under him are lawless.<verse eid="PRO 29:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:13"/>When creditor and debtor meet each other, the Lord makes an inspection of both.<verse eid="PRO 29:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:14"/>If a king judges the poor with truthfulness, his throne will be established as a testimony.<verse eid="PRO 29:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:15"/>Blows and reproofs bring wisdom, but a boy going astray disgraces his parents.<verse eid="PRO 29:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:16"/>When the impious multiply, sins become many, but when these stumble, the righteous become cautious.<verse eid="PRO 29:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:17"/>Instruct your son, and he will give you rest, and he will give your soul an ornament.<verse eid="PRO 29:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:18"/>A lawless nation has no interpreter, but he who keeps the law is most happy.<verse eid="PRO 29:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:19"/>A stubborn domestic will not be instructed by words, for even if he understands, he will nonetheless not obey.<verse eid="PRO 29:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:20"/>If you see a man hasty in speech, be sure there is more hope for a fool than for him.<verse eid="PRO 29:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:21"/>He who lives luxuriously from his childhood will be a domestic, but in the end he will be grieved over himself.<verse eid="PRO 29:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:22"/>A passionate man digs up strife, and a quick-tempered man digs out sins.<verse eid="PRO 29:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:23"/>Pride humbles a man, but the Lord supports the humble- minded with glory.<verse eid="PRO 29:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:24"/>He who shares with a thief hates his own soul, and if, having heard an oath proposed, they do not disclose it,<verse eid="PRO 29:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:25"/>since they were afraid and felt shame before people, they were tripped up. But the one who trusts in the Lord will be gladdened. Impiety gives a man a stumble, but he who trusts in his master will be saved.<verse eid="PRO 29:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:26"/>Many show deference to the persons of leaders, but from the Lord a man obtains that which is right.<verse eid="PRO 29:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 29:27"/>An unjust man is an abomination to the righteous, and the direct way is an abomination to the lawless.[30.1-14 precedes 24.23 and 30.15-31.9 follows 24.34]<verse eid="PRO 29:27"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 30">
<verse sid="PRO 30:1"/><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">30:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">[30.1-14 precedes 24.23</char></note>My son, fear my words, and repent when you receive them; this is what the man says to those who believe in God: Now I stop,<verse eid="PRO 30:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:2"/>for I am the most foolish of all people and I have not the prudence of people.<verse eid="PRO 30:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:3"/>God has taught me wisdom, and I have gained knowledge of holy things.<verse eid="PRO 30:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:4"/>Who has ascended to heaven and come down? Who has gathered the wind in his bosom? Who has wrapped the water in his garment? Who has taken control of all the ends of the earth? What is his name? Or the name of his children that you may know them?<verse eid="PRO 30:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:5"/>All divine words are tried by fire, and he himself shields those who revere him.<verse eid="PRO 30:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:6"/>Do not add to his words, lest he rebuke you and you become a liar.<verse eid="PRO 30:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:7"/>Two things I ask of you; do not remove my favor before I die.<verse eid="PRO 30:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:8"/>Put far from me a vain word and lies, and give me neither riches nor poverty, but order what is necessary and sufficient for me,<verse eid="PRO 30:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:9"/>lest I be filled and become a liar and say: "Who sees me?" Or lest I become poor and steal and swear by the name of God.<verse eid="PRO 30:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:10"/>Do not deliver a domestic in the hands of a master, lest he curse you and you vanish.<verse eid="PRO 30:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:11"/>Wicked progeny curses its father and does not bless its mother.<verse eid="PRO 30:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:12"/>Wicked progeny judges itself righteous but did not wash off its anus.<verse eid="PRO 30:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:13"/>Wicked progeny has lofty eyes, and it raises its eyebrows.<verse eid="PRO 30:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:14"/>Wicked progeny has daggers for teeth and knives for molars in order to destroy and to consume the humble from the earth and their needy from among mankind.<verse eid="PRO 30:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:15"/>The leech has three lovingly beloved daughters, but these three did not satisfy her, and the fourth was not pleased to say, "It is enough."<verse eid="PRO 30:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:16"/>Hades and love of a woman and Tartarus and earth not filled with water, water and fire also will never say, "It suffices."<verse eid="PRO 30:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:17"/>An eye that derides a father and scorns the old age of a mother-- may ravens from the ravines peck it out, and may the young eagles devour it.<verse eid="PRO 30:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:18"/>Now there are three things impossible for me to understand, and with the fourth I am not familiar:<verse eid="PRO 30:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:19"/>The tracks of a flying eagle and the ways of a snake on a rock and the paths of a ship passing through the sea and the ways of a man in his youth.<verse eid="PRO 30:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:20"/>Such is the way of an adulterous woman who, when she has performed the act, will wash herself and say that she has done nothing improper.<verse eid="PRO 30:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:21"/>Through three things the earth is shaken, and the fourth it is not able to bear:<verse eid="PRO 30:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:22"/>If a domestic becomes king and if a fool is filled with food,<verse eid="PRO 30:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:23"/>also a female domestic if she throws out her mistress, and a hateful woman if she finds a good husband.<verse eid="PRO 30:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:24"/>There are also four things on earth that are very small; yet they are wiser than the wise:<verse eid="PRO 30:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:25"/>The ants, which, though they are not strong, do prepare their food in summer;<verse eid="PRO 30:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:26"/>the hedgehogs are also not a strong species, who made their homes in the rocks;<verse eid="PRO 30:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:27"/>the grasshopper is without a king; yet they march orderly at the command of one;<verse eid="PRO 30:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:28"/>and the lizard, though dependent on its hands and being easily caught, it lives in the king's fortresses.<verse eid="PRO 30:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:29"/>There are indeed three things which move easily, and the fourth which walks well:<verse eid="PRO 30:29"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:30"/>a lion's whelp, strongest of the animals, which does not back-off nor fears any animal,<verse eid="PRO 30:30"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:31"/>also a cock strutting courageously among the hens, and the he-goat leading the herd, and a king making a speech in a nation.<verse eid="PRO 30:31"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:32"/>If you lose yourself in merriment and stretch out your hand in a fight, you will be disgraced.<verse eid="PRO 30:32"/>

<verse sid="PRO 30:33"/>Press out milk, and there will be butter, and if you squeeze nostrils, blood will come out, and if you extort words, quarrels and fights will ensue.<verse eid="PRO 30:33"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="PRO 31">
<verse sid="PRO 31:1"/><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">31:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">[30.15-31.9 follows 24.34]</char></note>My words have been spoken by God, the oracular response of a king, whom his mother instructed.<verse eid="PRO 31:1"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:2"/>What, my child, will you keep? What? Divine sayings. My firstborn, I speak to you, my son. What, child of my womb? What, child of my vows?<verse eid="PRO 31:2"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:3"/>Do not give your wealth to women and your mind and life to remorse.<verse eid="PRO 31:3"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:4"/>Do everything with counsel; drink wine with counsel. Those in power are wrathful, but let them not drink wine,<verse eid="PRO 31:4"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:5"/>lest they drink and forget wisdom and will not be able to judge the powerless rightly.<verse eid="PRO 31:5"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:6"/>Give strong drink to those who are in pain and wine to drink to those in sorrow,<verse eid="PRO 31:6"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:7"/>that they may forget their poverty and not remember their labor any more.<verse eid="PRO 31:7"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:8"/>Open your mouth with a divine word, and judge all fairly.<verse eid="PRO 31:8"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:9"/>Open your mouth, and judge justly, and plead the cause of the poor and weak.<verse eid="PRO 31:9"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:10"/>Who can find a courageous wife? Yes, such a one is more precious than valuable jewels.<verse eid="PRO 31:10"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:11"/>The heart of her husband is confident about her; such a one will have no need of good spoils,<verse eid="PRO 31:11"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:12"/>for she toils for the benefit of her husband all her life.<verse eid="PRO 31:12"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:13"/>After spinning wool and flax, she made it useful with her hands.<verse eid="PRO 31:13"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:14"/>She became like a ship that sails from afar, and it is she who gathers a livelihood.<verse eid="PRO 31:14"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:15"/>And she got up in the night and supplied food for her household and work for her attendants.<verse eid="PRO 31:15"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:16"/>After considering a field, she bought it, and with the fruits of her hands she planted the purchase.<verse eid="PRO 31:16"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:17"/>After strongly girding her loins, she strengthened her arms for work.<verse eid="PRO 31:17"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:18"/>She experienced that it was good to work, and her lamp is not extinguished the whole night.<verse eid="PRO 31:18"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:19"/>She extends her forearms to what is profitable, and she strengthens her hands at the spindle.<verse eid="PRO 31:19"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:20"/>And she opens her hands to the needy and reaches out her fruit to the poor.<verse eid="PRO 31:20"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:21"/>Her husband has no concern for his household, when he spends time somewhere, for all that are hers are being clothed.<verse eid="PRO 31:21"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:22"/>She duplicated cloaks for her husband, and for herself clothes of fine linen and purple.<verse eid="PRO 31:22"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:23"/>And her husband is admired in the gates, when he sits in the council with elderly inhabitants of the land.<verse eid="PRO 31:23"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:24"/>She made linen garments and sold them, and girdles for the Chananites.<verse eid="PRO 31:24"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:25"/>She opened her mouth cautiously and legitimately and reined in her tongue.<verse eid="PRO 31:25"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:26"/>She is clothed in strength and dignity, and she was happy in her last days.<verse eid="PRO 31:26"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:27"/>The way she ran her household was careful, and she did not eat the bread of idleness.<verse eid="PRO 31:27"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:28"/>And she opens her mouth wisely and lawfully, and her compassion built up her children, and they became rich, and her husband praised her:<verse eid="PRO 31:28"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:29"/>"Many daughters have obtained wealth; many did mighty things, but you, you have surpassed and transcended all."<verse eid="PRO 31:29"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:30"/>Allurements are false, and the beauty of a woman is vain, but an intelligent woman is spoken well of; yes, let her praise the fear of the Lord.<verse eid="PRO 31:30"/>

<verse sid="PRO 31:31"/>Give her of the fruits of her hands, and let her husband be praised in the gates!<verse eid="PRO 31:31"/>
</_X_chapter></_X_book></_X_usx>