<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<_X_usx version="2.0">
<para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
<_X_book code="SIR">





<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 1">
<verse sid="SIR 1:1"/>(a) Seeing that many and great things have been given to us through the Law and the Prophets and the others that followed them, for which reason it is necessary to commend Israel for education and wisdom, and whereas it is necessary that not only those who read them gain understanding, (5) but also that those who love learning be capable of service to outsiders, both when they speak and when they write, Iesous, my grandfather, since he had given himself increasingly both to the reading of the Law and the Prophets (10) and the other ancestral books and since he had acquired considerable proficiency in them, he too was led to compose something pertaining to education and wisdom in order that lovers of learning, when they come under their<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Antecedent unclear, referring either to his grandfather's book or to 'education and wisdom'</char></note> sway as well, might gain much more in living by the law. (15) You are invited, therefore, to a reading with goodwill and attention, and to exercise forbearance in cases where we may be thought (20) to be insipid with regard to some expressions that have been the object of great care in rendering; for what was originally expressed in Hebrew does not have the same force when it is in fact rendered in another language. And not only in this case, but also in the case of the Law itself and the Prophets (25) and the rest of the books the difference is not small when these are expressed in their own language. For in the thirty-eighth year, in the reign of Euergetes the king, when I had arrived in Egypt and stayed a while, when I had discovered an exemplar of no little education, (30) I myself too made it a most compulsory task to bring some speed and industry to the translating of this tome, meanwhile having contributed much sleeplessness and skill, with the aim of bringing the book to completion and to publish it also for those living abroad if they wish to become learned, preparing their character to live by the law. <para style="p"/><para style="p"/>(1) All wisdom is from the Lord, and with him it exists forever.<verse eid="SIR 1:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:2"/>Sand of seas and drops of rain and days of eternity-- who shall enumerate?<verse eid="SIR 1:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:3"/>The sky's height and earth's breadth and abyss and wisdom-- who will track?<verse eid="SIR 1:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:4"/>Before all things wisdom has been created, and understanding of prudence is from eternity.<verse eid="SIR 1:4"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 1:5"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 1:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:6"/>Wisdom's root-- to whom was it revealed? And her wondrous feats-- who knew?<verse eid="SIR 1:6"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 1:7"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 1:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:8"/>One who is wise, greatly feared, seated upon his throne.<verse eid="SIR 1:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:9"/>The Lord, he created her, and he saw and enumerated her and poured her out upon all his works,<verse eid="SIR 1:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:10"/>among all flesh according to his giving, and he furnished her abundantly to those who love him.<verse eid="SIR 1:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:11"/>Fear of the Lord is reputation and boasting and gladness and a garland of rejoicing.<verse eid="SIR 1:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:12"/>Fear of the Lord will delight the heart, and it will give gladness and joy and length of days.<verse eid="SIR 1:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:13"/>For the one who fears the Lord, it will be well at the end, and in the day of his death he will be blessed.<verse eid="SIR 1:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:14"/>Wisdom's beginning is to fear the Lord, and with the faithful in the womb-- she was created together with them.<verse eid="SIR 1:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:15"/>Among human beings she built her nest as an eternal foundation, and among their offspring she will be trusted.<verse eid="SIR 1:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:16"/>Wisdom's fullness is to fear the Lord, and she inebriates them with her fruits.<verse eid="SIR 1:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:17"/>Their every house she will fill with desirable things, and the reception halls<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'reception halls':  Perhaps 'storehouses'</char></note> from her produce.<verse eid="SIR 1:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:18"/>Wisdom's garland is fear of the Lord, sprouting peace and well-being for healing.<verse eid="SIR 1:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:19"/>Skill and knowledge of understanding she rained down, and the reputation of people who hold her fast she exalted.<verse eid="SIR 1:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:20"/>Wisdom's root is to fear the Lord, and her branches are length of days.<verse eid="SIR 1:20"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 1:21"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 1:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:22"/>Unjust anger can never be justified, for the weight of his<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the person who suffers from it'</char></note> anger is his<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the person who suffers from it'</char></note> downfall.<verse eid="SIR 1:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:23"/>Until the right time a patient person will restrain himself, and afterwards gladness will pay him back.<verse eid="SIR 1:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:24"/>Until the right time he will hide his words, and the lips of many will tell of his discernment.<verse eid="SIR 1:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:25"/>Among wisdom's treasures there is illustration of intelligence, but godliness is an abomination to a sinner.<verse eid="SIR 1:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:26"/>If you desire wisdom, keep the commandments, and the Lord will furnish her abundantly to you.<verse eid="SIR 1:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:27"/>For wisdom and education are the fear of the Lord, and his delight is fidelity and gentleness.<verse eid="SIR 1:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:28"/>Do not disobey the fear of the Lord, and do not approach him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:28</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'it'</char></note> with a double heart.<verse eid="SIR 1:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:29"/>Do not be a hypocrite in the mouths of humankind, and with your lips pay heed.<verse eid="SIR 1:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 1:30"/>Do not exalt yourself, lest you fall and bring dishonor to your soul, and the Lord will reveal your secrets, and in the midst of a gathering he will overthrow you, because you did not approach in the fear of the Lord and your heart was full of deceit.<verse eid="SIR 1:30"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 2">
<verse sid="SIR 2:1"/>Child, if you come to be subject to the Lord, prepare your soul for testing.<verse eid="SIR 2:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:2"/>Set straight your heart, and be steadfast, and do not be hasty in a time of distress.<verse eid="SIR 2:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:3"/>Cling to him, and do not stand aloof so that you may be strengthened at your end.<verse eid="SIR 2:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:4"/>Anything that might happen to you accept, and in the vicissitudes of your humiliation be patient,<verse eid="SIR 2:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:5"/>because with fire gold is tested, and acceptable people in the furnace of humiliation.<verse eid="SIR 2:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:6"/>Have faith in him, and he will support you, and make straight your ways, and hope in him.<verse eid="SIR 2:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:7"/>You who fear the Lord, wait for his mercy, and do not turn away, lest you fall.<verse eid="SIR 2:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:8"/>You who fear the Lord, have faith in him, and your wage will not be forfeited.<verse eid="SIR 2:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:9"/>You who fear the Lord, hope for good things and for everlasting gladness and mercy,<verse eid="SIR 2:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:10"/>Look to ancient generations, and see; who had faith in the Lord and was put to shame? Or who has held fast to fear of him and was forsaken? Or who called upon him, and he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the Lord'</char></note> despised him?<verse eid="SIR 2:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:11"/>For compassionate and merciful is the Lord, and he forgives sins and saves in a time of affliction.<verse eid="SIR 2:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:12"/>Woe to timid hearts and to slack hands and to a sinner when he treads on two paths.<verse eid="SIR 2:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:13"/>Woe to a faint heart, because it does not have faith; therefore it will not be sheltered.<verse eid="SIR 2:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:14"/>Woe to you who have lost endurance. And what will you do when the Lord makes his reckoning?<verse eid="SIR 2:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:15"/>Those who fear the Lord will not disobey his words, and those who love him will preserve his ways.<verse eid="SIR 2:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:16"/>Those who fear the Lord will seek his favor, and those who love him will be filled with the law.<verse eid="SIR 2:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:17"/>Those who fear the Lord will prepare their hearts, and before him they will humble their souls.<verse eid="SIR 2:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 2:18"/>We shall fall into the hands of the Lord and not into the hands of human beings! For as his majesty is, so also is his mercy.<verse eid="SIR 2:18"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 3">
<verse sid="SIR 3:1"/>Listen to a father's reproof, children, and act accordingly so that you may be safe.<verse eid="SIR 3:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:2"/>For the Lord has glorified father over children, and he has confirmed a mother's judgment over sons.<verse eid="SIR 3:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:3"/>He who honors father will atone for sins,<verse eid="SIR 3:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:4"/>and like one who lays up treasure is he who glorifies his mother.<verse eid="SIR 3:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:5"/>He who honors father will be gladdened by children, and in the day of his prayer he will be heard.<verse eid="SIR 3:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:6"/>He who glorifies father will prolong his days, and he who listens to the Lord will give rest to his mother.<verse eid="SIR 3:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:7"/>and among those who begot him he will act as a slave to masters<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'among those who begot him he will act as a slave to masters':  Greek uncertain</char></note>.<verse eid="SIR 3:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:8"/>By deed and word honor your father so that a blessing from him might come upon you.<verse eid="SIR 3:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:9"/>For a father's blessing supports children's houses, but a mother's curse uproots foundations.<verse eid="SIR 3:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:10"/>Do not glorify yourself by your father's disgrace, for you have no glory in a father's disgrace.<verse eid="SIR 3:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:11"/>For a person's repute comes from his father's honor, and a mother in ill repute is a reproach to children.<verse eid="SIR 3:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:12"/>Child, support your father in old age, and do not grieve him during his life.<verse eid="SIR 3:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:13"/>But if he fails in comprehension, excuse him, and do not dishonor him in the fullness of your strength.<verse eid="SIR 3:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:14"/>For charity for a father will not be forgotten, and it will be credited to you against sins.<verse eid="SIR 3:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:15"/>In a day of affliction it will be remembered of you; as fair weather upon frost, so will your sins be dissolved.<verse eid="SIR 3:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:16"/>Like a blasphemer is the one who neglects a father, and cursed by the Lord is the one who angers his mother.<verse eid="SIR 3:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:17"/>Child, in gentleness conduct your affairs, and you will be loved more than a person who gives.<verse eid="SIR 3:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:18"/>The greater you are, the more you should humble yourself, and before the Lord you will find favor.<verse eid="SIR 3:18"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 3:19"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 3:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:20"/>because great is the dominance of the Lord and by the humble he is glorified.<verse eid="SIR 3:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:21"/>Things too difficult for you do not seek, and things too strong for you do not scrutinize.<verse eid="SIR 3:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:22"/>The things that have been prescribed for you, think about these, for you have no need of hidden matters.<verse eid="SIR 3:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:23"/>With matters greater than your affairs do not meddle, for things beyond human understanding have been shown to you.<verse eid="SIR 3:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:24"/>For their presumption has led many astray, and their evil fancy has diminished their understanding.<verse eid="SIR 3:24"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 3:25"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 3:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:26"/>A hard heart will fare badly at the end, and he who loves danger will perish in it.<verse eid="SIR 3:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:27"/>A hard heart will be weighed down by troubles, and the sinner will add sin to sins.<verse eid="SIR 3:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:28"/>For the misery of the arrogant there is no healing, because a plant of wickedness has taken root in him.<verse eid="SIR 3:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:29"/>The heart of the intelligent will think of an illustration, and a hearer's ear is the desire of the wise.<verse eid="SIR 3:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:30"/>A blazing fire water will extinguish, and charity will atone for sins.<verse eid="SIR 3:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 3:31"/>He who repays favors gives thought to what comes after, and at the moment of a fall he will find support.<verse eid="SIR 3:31"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 4">
<verse sid="SIR 4:1"/>Child, the life of the poor do not defraud, and do not put off needy eyes.<verse eid="SIR 4:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:2"/>A hungry soul do not grieve, and do not anger a man in his difficulty.<verse eid="SIR 4:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:3"/>An angry heart do not trouble, and do not delay giving to one in need.<verse eid="SIR 4:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:4"/>A suppliant in distress do not keep rejecting, and do not turn your face away from the poor.<verse eid="SIR 4:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:5"/>From one who begs do not turn away an eye, and do not give him occasion to curse you.<verse eid="SIR 4:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:6"/>For if one curses you in bitterness of his soul, the one who made him will hear his petition.<verse eid="SIR 4:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:7"/>Make yourself beloved to a gathering, and for a nobleman bow your head.<verse eid="SIR 4:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:8"/>Incline your ear to the poor, and answer him peaceably with gentleness.<verse eid="SIR 4:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:9"/>Deliver the wronged from the hand of the wrongdoer, and do not be faint-hearted when you render judgment.<verse eid="SIR 4:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:10"/>Be like a father to orphans and instead of a husband to their mother, and you will be like a son of the Most High, and he will love you more than does your mother.<verse eid="SIR 4:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:11"/>Wisdom will exalt her sons and lays hold of those who seek her.<verse eid="SIR 4:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:12"/>He who loves her loves life, and those who turn to her early will be filled with gladness.<verse eid="SIR 4:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:13"/>He who holds her fast will inherit a reputation, and where he enters, the Lord blesses.<verse eid="SIR 4:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:14"/>Those who serve her will minister to one holy, and those who love her the Lord loves.<verse eid="SIR 4:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:15"/>He who obeys her will judge nations, and the one who gives heed to her will dwell in confidence.<verse eid="SIR 4:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:16"/>If he has faith, he will inherit her, and his descendants will be in possession of her<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'of her':  Lacking in Greek</char></note>.<verse eid="SIR 4:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:17"/>Because at first she will travel with him though he twist and turn, fear and dread she will bring upon him, and she will torment him with her training until she has faith in his soul, and she will test him with her statutes.<verse eid="SIR 4:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:18"/>And again she will return straight back to him and will make him glad and will reveal to him her secrets.<verse eid="SIR 4:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:19"/>If he goes astray, she will abandon him and hand him over to the grip of his fall.<verse eid="SIR 4:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:20"/>Watch for an opportune time, and beware of evil, and about your soul do not be ashamed.<verse eid="SIR 4:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:21"/>For there is a shame that brings on sin, and there is a shame that is glory and favor.<verse eid="SIR 4:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:22"/>Do not receive a person against your soul, and do not feel embarrassment to your fall.<verse eid="SIR 4:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:23"/>Do not hinder speech in a time of need,<verse eid="SIR 4:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:24"/>For by speech will wisdom be known, and education through a word of the tongue.<verse eid="SIR 4:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:25"/>Do not speak against the truth, and concerning your lack of education feel shame.<verse eid="SIR 4:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:26"/>Do not be ashamed to acknowledge your sins, and do not try to force a river's flow.<verse eid="SIR 4:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:27"/>Do not be subject to a foolish person, and do not accept the person of a ruler.<verse eid="SIR 4:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:28"/>Exert yourself to the death for the truth, and the Lord God will do battle for you.<verse eid="SIR 4:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:29"/>Do not become rash with your tongue or sluggish and remiss in your deeds.<verse eid="SIR 4:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:30"/>Do not be like a lion in your home, even conceiving vain fancies among your domestics.<verse eid="SIR 4:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 4:31"/>Do not let your hand be extended to receive and withdrawn when paying back.<verse eid="SIR 4:31"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 5">
<verse sid="SIR 5:1"/>Do not be occupied with your money, and do not say, "I am self-sufficient."<verse eid="SIR 5:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 5:2"/>Do not follow your soul and your strength, to walk in your heart's desires.<verse eid="SIR 5:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 5:3"/>And do not say, "Who shall hold power over me?" For the Lord, when he punishes, will punish.<verse eid="SIR 5:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 5:4"/>Do not say, "I sinned, and what has happened to me?" For the Lord is longsuffering.<verse eid="SIR 5:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 5:5"/>Do not become fearless concerning atonement, to add sin upon sins.<verse eid="SIR 5:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 5:6"/>And do not say, "His compassion is great; it will atone for the multitude of my sins"; for mercy and wrath are with him, and upon sinners will his anger rest.<verse eid="SIR 5:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 5:7"/>Do not wait to turn back to the Lord, and do not postpone it day after day; for suddenly the wrath of the Lord will go forth, and in the time of punishment you will perish.<verse eid="SIR 5:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 5:8"/>Do not be occupied with ill-gotten money, for it will not be of benefit in a day of distress.<verse eid="SIR 5:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 5:9"/>Do not winnow in every wind, and do not go on every short cut; thus is the double-tongued sinner.<verse eid="SIR 5:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 5:10"/>Be firm in your understanding, and let your speech be one.<verse eid="SIR 5:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 5:11"/>Be quick in your hearing, and with longsuffering utter a reply.<verse eid="SIR 5:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 5:12"/>If you have understanding, answer your fellow, but if not, let your hand be upon your mouth.<verse eid="SIR 5:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 5:13"/>Repute and dishonor are in speaking, and a person's tongue is his downfall.<verse eid="SIR 5:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 5:14"/>Do not be called a slanderer, and do not ambush with your tongue; for upon the thief is shame and grievous condemnation upon the double-tongued.<verse eid="SIR 5:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 5:15"/>In a great and a small matter do not remain ignorant.<verse eid="SIR 5:15"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 6">
<verse sid="SIR 6:1"/>And do not become an enemy instead of a friend, for a bad name will inherit shame and reproach; thus is the double-tongued sinner.<verse eid="SIR 6:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:2"/>Do not raise yourself up in your soul's deliberation, lest your strength be seized as a bull is seized<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'is seized':  Lacking in Greek</char></note>.<verse eid="SIR 6:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:3"/>Your leaves you will devour, and your fruit you will destroy, and you will leave yourself like a withered tree.<verse eid="SIR 6:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:4"/>An evil soul will destroy him who possesses it, and it will make him a laughingstock of enemies.<verse eid="SIR 6:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:5"/>A sweet throat<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'sweet throat':  Perhaps 'pleasant speech'</char></note> will multiply its friends, and a well-speaking tongue will multiply courtesies.<verse eid="SIR 6:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:6"/>Let those who are at peace with you be many, but let your advisors be one in a thousand.<verse eid="SIR 6:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:7"/>If you acquire a friend, acquire him through testing, and do not have faith in him hastily.<verse eid="SIR 6:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:8"/>For there is a friend when it suits him, and he will not remain in a day of affliction.<verse eid="SIR 6:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:9"/>And there is a friend who turns to enmity, and he will disclose strife to your disgrace.<verse eid="SIR 6:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:10"/>And there is a friend who is a table companion, and he will not remain in a day of affliction.<verse eid="SIR 6:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:11"/>And among your goods he will be as you are, and he will speak boldly to your domestics.<verse eid="SIR 6:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:12"/>If you are brought low, he will be against you, and he will hide himself from your face.<verse eid="SIR 6:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:13"/>From your enemies, keep your distance, and with your friends pay heed.<verse eid="SIR 6:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:14"/>A loyal friend is a sturdy shelter, and he who finds him has found a treasure.<verse eid="SIR 6:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:15"/>A loyal friend is priceless, and no one can weigh his worth.<verse eid="SIR 6:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:16"/>A loyal friend is life's drug, and those who fear the Lord will find him.<verse eid="SIR 6:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:17"/>He who fears the Lord directs his friendship aright, because like him, so also is his fellow.<verse eid="SIR 6:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:18"/>Child, from your youth welcome education, and until gray hairs you will find wisdom.<verse eid="SIR 6:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:19"/>Like him who plows and him who sows approach her, and wait for her good fruits; for in cultivation of her you will toil little, and you will soon eat of her produce.<verse eid="SIR 6:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:20"/>How harsh is wisdom to the uneducated, and the cowardly will not remain with her.<verse eid="SIR 6:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:21"/>Like a formidable stone of testing she will be upon him, and he will not delay to cast her aside.<verse eid="SIR 6:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:22"/>For wisdom is like her name, and she is not conspicuous to many.<verse eid="SIR 6:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:23"/>Listen, child, and accept my opinion, and do not reject my counsel.<verse eid="SIR 6:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:24"/>Put your feet into her fetters, and into her collar, your neck.<verse eid="SIR 6:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:25"/>Offer your shoulder, and carry her, and do not be offended at her bonds.<verse eid="SIR 6:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:26"/>With all your soul approach her, and with all your might keep her ways.<verse eid="SIR 6:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:27"/>Trace, and seek, and she will become known to you, and when you get a firm hold, do not let her go.<verse eid="SIR 6:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:28"/>For in the end you will find her repose, and she will be changed into gladness for you.<verse eid="SIR 6:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:29"/>And her fetters will be a shelter of strength for you, and her collars a robe of glory.<verse eid="SIR 6:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:30"/>For a golden ornament is upon her, and her bonds are a blue thread.<verse eid="SIR 6:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:31"/>You will wear her as a robe of glory, and you will put her on like a garland of joy.<verse eid="SIR 6:31"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:32"/>If you are willing, child, you will be instructed, and if you surrender your soul, you will be clever.<verse eid="SIR 6:32"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:33"/>If you love to listen, you will receive, and if you incline your ear, you will be wise.<verse eid="SIR 6:33"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:34"/>Stand in a crowd of elders, and cling to their wisdom.<verse eid="SIR 6:34"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:35"/>Be willing to listen to every godly discourse, and do not let proverbs of understanding escape you.<verse eid="SIR 6:35"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:36"/>If you see an intelligent person, turn to him early, and let your foot wear out the thresholds of his doors.<verse eid="SIR 6:36"/>

<verse sid="SIR 6:37"/>Exercise your thought in the Lord's ordinances, and on his commandments continually meditate. It is he who will make your heart firm, and the desire for wisdom will be given to you.<verse eid="SIR 6:37"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 7">
<verse sid="SIR 7:1"/>Do not do evil things, and an evil will not overtake you.<verse eid="SIR 7:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:2"/>Stay away from wrong, and it will turn away from you.<verse eid="SIR 7:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:3"/>Do not sow in the furrows of injustice, and you will not reap them<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Probable antecedent, 'evil things' (7.1)</char></note> sevenfold.<verse eid="SIR 7:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:4"/>Do not seek from the Lord authority or from a king a seat of honor.<verse eid="SIR 7:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:5"/>Do not assert righteousness before the Lord, and with a king do not display wisdom.<verse eid="SIR 7:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:6"/>Do not seek to become a judge; you might not have the strength to get rid of injustice, lest you have trepidation in the presence of one powerful, and you shall erect an obstacle to your uprightness.<verse eid="SIR 7:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:7"/>Do not sin against a city's multitude, and do not throw yourself down in a crowd.<verse eid="SIR 7:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:8"/>Do not bind up a sin twice, for in one you will not be innocent.<verse eid="SIR 7:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:9"/>Do not say, "He will have regard for the multitude of my gifts, and when I bring a gift to the Most High God, he will accept it."<verse eid="SIR 7:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:10"/>Do not be fainthearted in your prayer, and do not neglect to practice charity.<verse eid="SIR 7:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:11"/>Do not deride a person when he is embittered in spirit, for there is one who humbles and exalts.<verse eid="SIR 7:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:12"/>Do not cultivate a lie against your brother or do the same to a friend.<verse eid="SIR 7:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:13"/>Do not consent to concoct any lie, for the continuation of it results in no good.<verse eid="SIR 7:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:14"/>Do not babble in a great number of elders, and do not repeat a word in your prayer.<verse eid="SIR 7:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:15"/>Do not hate toilsome labor and tillage created by the Most High.<verse eid="SIR 7:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:16"/>Do not reckon yourself among the multitude of sinners; remember that wrath will not delay.<verse eid="SIR 7:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:17"/>Humble your soul greatly, because the punishment of the impious is fire and worm.<verse eid="SIR 7:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:18"/>Do not exchange a friend for cash or a real brother for gold of Souphir.<verse eid="SIR 7:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:19"/>Do not fail a wise and good wife, for her grace is beyond gold.<verse eid="SIR 7:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:20"/>Do not abuse a domestic when he truly works or a laborer when he gives his soul.<verse eid="SIR 7:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:21"/>Let your soul love an intelligent domestic; do not deprive him of freedom.<verse eid="SIR 7:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:22"/>Do you have cattle? Look after them, and if they are useful to you, let them remain with you.<verse eid="SIR 7:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:23"/>Do you have children? Educate them, and bend their neck from youth.<verse eid="SIR 7:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:24"/>Do you have daughters? Give heed to their body, and do not brighten your face towards them.<verse eid="SIR 7:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:25"/>Give a daughter in marriage, and you will have completed a great task, and present her to an understanding man.<verse eid="SIR 7:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:26"/>Do you have a wife like your soul? Do not divorce her, and do not entrust yourself to her when she is hated.<verse eid="SIR 7:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:27"/>With your whole heart honor your father, and a mother's birth pangs do not forget.<verse eid="SIR 7:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:28"/>Remember that you were born through them-- and how will you repay them what they have done for you?<verse eid="SIR 7:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:29"/>With your whole soul, revere the Lord, and admire his priests.<verse eid="SIR 7:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:30"/>With your whole might, love him who made you, and his ministers do not neglect.<verse eid="SIR 7:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:31"/>Fear the Lord, and honor a priest, and give him his portion, as it has been commanded of you: first fruits and concerning error<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">7:31</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'concerning error':  I.e. 'a sin offering'</char></note> and gift of forearms and sacrifice of sanctification and first fruits of holy things.<verse eid="SIR 7:31"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:32"/>And stretch out your hand to a poor person in order that your blessing may be complete.<verse eid="SIR 7:32"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:33"/>The kindness of something given is before everyone alive, and do not hinder kindness for a corpse.<verse eid="SIR 7:33"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:34"/>Do not lag behind those who weep, but mourn with those who mourn.<verse eid="SIR 7:34"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:35"/>Do not hesitate to visit a sick person, for because of such deeds you will be loved.<verse eid="SIR 7:35"/>

<verse sid="SIR 7:36"/>In all your words, remember the end, and you will not ever sin.<verse eid="SIR 7:36"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 8">
<verse sid="SIR 8:1"/>Do not contend with a powerful person, lest you fall into his hands.<verse eid="SIR 8:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:2"/>Do not quarrel with a rich person, lest he counter your weight; for gold has ruined many and has perverted hearts of kings.<verse eid="SIR 8:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:3"/>Do not contend with a garrulous person, and do not heap wood on his fire.<verse eid="SIR 8:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:4"/>Do not make fun of the uneducated, lest your ancestors be insulted.<verse eid="SIR 8:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:5"/>Do not reproach a person when he is turning away from sin; remember that we all are subject to rebuke.<verse eid="SIR 8:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:6"/>Do not disdain a person in his old age, for some of us, too, are growing old.<verse eid="SIR 8:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:7"/>Do not rejoice over a corpse; remember that we all pass away.<verse eid="SIR 8:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:8"/>Do not disregard a discourse of the wise, and turn to their proverbs, because from them you will learn instruction and how to minister to noblemen.<verse eid="SIR 8:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:9"/>Do not miss out on the discourse of the aged, for even they themselves learned from their fathers, because from them you will learn understanding and how to give an answer in time of need.<verse eid="SIR 8:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:10"/>Do not stoke a sinner's coals; do not be set afire by the fire of his flame.<verse eid="SIR 8:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:11"/>Do not vacate your seat before an insolent person, lest he sit down as an ambush to your mouth.<verse eid="SIR 8:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:12"/>Do not lend to a person stronger than you, and if you do lend, be as one who has lost.<verse eid="SIR 8:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:13"/>Do not give surety beyond your ability, and if you do give surety, regard it as a paying back.<verse eid="SIR 8:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:14"/>Do not go to law with a judge, for according to his status will they judge in his favor.<verse eid="SIR 8:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:15"/>With a reckless person do not travel on the road, lest your troubles weigh you down; for he will travel as he wants to, and by his folly you will perish as well.<verse eid="SIR 8:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:16"/>With a quick-tempered person do not pick a fight, and do not traverse the desert with him, because bloodshed is as nothing in his eyes, and where there is no help, he will cast you down.<verse eid="SIR 8:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:17"/>With a foolish one do not consult, for he cannot cover up a secret.<verse eid="SIR 8:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:18"/>In the presence of a stranger do not do something secret, for you do not know what he will bring forth.<verse eid="SIR 8:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 8:19"/>Do not expose your heart to any person, and do not let him return a favor to you.<verse eid="SIR 8:19"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 9">
<verse sid="SIR 9:1"/>Do not be jealous of the wife of your bosom, nor teach an evil lesson against yourself.<verse eid="SIR 9:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:2"/>Do not give your soul to a woman, to let her trample upon your strength.<verse eid="SIR 9:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:3"/>Do not meet with a female escort, lest you fall into her snares.<verse eid="SIR 9:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:4"/>With a female strummer do not dally, lest you become caught in her endeavors.<verse eid="SIR 9:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:5"/>Do not ogle a maiden, lest you be made to stumble in her rebukes.<verse eid="SIR 9:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:6"/>Do not give your soul to whores, lest you lose your inheritance.<verse eid="SIR 9:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:7"/>Do not look around in city alleyways, and in its deserted places do not wander.<verse eid="SIR 9:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:8"/>Turn an eye from a shapely woman, and do not ogle beauty belonging to another; by a woman's beauty many have gone astray, and from it fondness flares up like a fire.<verse eid="SIR 9:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:9"/>With a married woman do not sit down at all, and do not feast with her at wine, lest your soul incline to her and by your blood you slip into destruction.<verse eid="SIR 9:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:10"/>Do not abandon an old friend, for the recent one is not his equal; a new friend is like new wine; if it ages, you will drink it with merriment.<verse eid="SIR 9:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:11"/>Do not envy a sinner's good repute, for you do not know what his undoing will be.<verse eid="SIR 9:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:12"/>Do not delight in the success of the impious; remember that they will not be deemed righteous until Hades<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the grave'</char></note>.<verse eid="SIR 9:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:13"/>Keep far from a person who has authority to kill, and you will not be apprehensive of the fear of death, and if you approach him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note>, do not make a mistake, lest he take your life. Recognize that you are treading in the midst of snares, and you are walking about on a city's battlements.<verse eid="SIR 9:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:14"/>According to your strength take stock of your fellow, and consult with the wise.<verse eid="SIR 9:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:15"/>Let your discussion be with intelligent people, and all your exposition in the law of the Most High.<verse eid="SIR 9:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:16"/>Let righteous men be your dinner companions, and let your boast be in the fear of the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 9:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:17"/>In the hand of artisans a work will be praised, and the people's leader is wise by his word.<verse eid="SIR 9:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 9:18"/>Feared in his city is a garrulous man, and he who is reckless in his speech will be hated.<verse eid="SIR 9:18"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 10">
<verse sid="SIR 10:1"/>A wise judge will educate his people, and the rule of an intelligent person will be orderly.<verse eid="SIR 10:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:2"/>As the people's judge is, so also are his officials, and as the ruler of the city is, are all its inhabitants.<verse eid="SIR 10:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:3"/>An uneducated king will destroy his people, and a city will be populated by the intelligence of its<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> rulers.<verse eid="SIR 10:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:4"/>In the Lord's hand is the governance of the earth, and he will raise up over it the person useful for the time.<verse eid="SIR 10:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:5"/>In the Lord's hand is a man's success, and to a scribe's face he will add his reputation.<verse eid="SIR 10:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:6"/>For every wrong do not be angry with your neighbor, and do not do anything with acts of insolence.<verse eid="SIR 10:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:7"/>Hateful before the Lord and humans is pride, and to both injustice is wrong.<verse eid="SIR 10:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:8"/>Dominion is transferred from nation to nation on account of injustice and insolence and money.<verse eid="SIR 10:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:9"/>How can earth and ashes<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'earth and ashes':  I.e. 'a human being'</char></note> behave arrogantly?-- because in life I hurled his entrails<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'because in life I hurled his entrails':  Greek uncertain</char></note>.<verse eid="SIR 10:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:10"/>A long illness mocks a physician; today a king, and tomorrow he will die.<verse eid="SIR 10:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:11"/>For when a person dies, he inherits creeping things and beasts and worms.<verse eid="SIR 10:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:12"/>Pride's beginning for a human is to rebel against the Lord, and against him who made him his heart rebels,<verse eid="SIR 10:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:13"/>because pride's beginning is sin, and he who clings to it will pour out abomination. Therefore the Lord brought on incredible attacks and ruined him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> completely.<verse eid="SIR 10:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:14"/>Thrones of rulers the Lord brought down, and he seated the gentle in their place.<verse eid="SIR 10:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:15"/>Roots of nations the Lord plucked up, and he planted the humble in their place.<verse eid="SIR 10:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:16"/>Lands of nations the Lord ruined, and he destroyed them as far as earth's foundations.<verse eid="SIR 10:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:17"/>He removed some people and destroyed them, and he erased their memorial from earth.<verse eid="SIR 10:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:18"/>Pride was not created for human beings, nor violent anger for what is born of women.<verse eid="SIR 10:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:19"/>What kind of offspring is honorable? Human offspring. What kind of offspring is honorable? Those who fear the Lord. What kind of offspring is dishonorable? Human offspring. What kind of offspring is dishonorable? Those who transgress the commandments.<verse eid="SIR 10:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:20"/>In the midst of kin their leader is honorable, and those who, in his eyes, fear the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 10:20"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 10:21"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 10:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:22"/>Guest and stranger and poor person-- their boast is fear of the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 10:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:23"/>It is not right to dishonor an intelligent poor person, and it is not proper to glorify a sinful man.<verse eid="SIR 10:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:24"/>Noble and judge and ruler will be glorified, but none of them is greater than he who fears the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 10:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:25"/>Free persons will attend to a wise domestic, and a knowledgeable man will not grumble.<verse eid="SIR 10:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:26"/>Do not craftily perform your task, and do not extol yourself in your time of difficulty.<verse eid="SIR 10:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:27"/>Superior is a person who works and excels in all things to one who struts about extolling himself and lacks bread.<verse eid="SIR 10:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:28"/>Child, in meekness give repute to your soul, and give it value according to its worth.<verse eid="SIR 10:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:29"/>Him who errs against his own soul-- who will vindicate? And who will give repute to him who devalues his own life?<verse eid="SIR 10:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:30"/>A poor person has repute because of his knowledge, and a rich person has repute because of his wealth.<verse eid="SIR 10:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 10:31"/>He who has repute in poverty, how much more also in wealth? And he who is held in disrepute in wealth, how much more also in poverty?<verse eid="SIR 10:31"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 11">
<verse sid="SIR 11:1"/>A humble person's wisdom will raise up his head, and it will seat him in the midst of nobles.<verse eid="SIR 11:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:2"/>Do not praise a man for his good looks, and do not loathe a man for his appearance.<verse eid="SIR 11:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:3"/>Small among flying creatures is a bee, and the origin of sweet things is its produce.<verse eid="SIR 11:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:4"/>Do not boast about the putting-on of clothes, and do not exalt yourself in a day of glory, because the works of the Lord are wonderful, and his works are hidden among humans.<verse eid="SIR 11:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:5"/>Many tyrants have sat on the ground, but one not expected to was wearing a diadem.<verse eid="SIR 11:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:6"/>Many dynasts have been utterly dishonored, and people of high repute have been given over into the hands of others.<verse eid="SIR 11:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:7"/>Before you investigate, do not find fault; reflect first, and then rebuke.<verse eid="SIR 11:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:8"/>Before listening, do not answer, and in the middle of speaking, do not interrupt.<verse eid="SIR 11:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:9"/>About a matter that is of no use to you, do not quarrel, and in a trial of sinners, do not deliberate.<verse eid="SIR 11:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:10"/>Child, let not your actions entail many things; if you multiply them<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note>, you will not be held blameless, and if you pursue, you will not overtake, and you will not escape when you flee.<verse eid="SIR 11:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:11"/>There exists one who toils and struggles and hurries but is so much the more in want.<verse eid="SIR 11:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:12"/>There exists one who is sluggish and in need of assistance, lacking strength and abounding in poverty, and the eyes of the Lord looked upon him for good, and he restored him from his low estate<verse eid="SIR 11:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:13"/>and raised up his head, and many marveled at him.<verse eid="SIR 11:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:14"/>Good things and bad, life and death, poverty and wealth are from the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 11:14"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 11:15"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 11:15"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 11:16"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 11:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:17"/>The Lord's gift remains with the pious, and his favor will bring success forever.<verse eid="SIR 11:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:18"/>There exists one who becomes rich from his diligence and miserliness, and this is the portion of his recompense.<verse eid="SIR 11:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:19"/>When he says, "I have found rest, and now I will eat of my good things," even he does not know how time will pass by, and he will leave them to others and will die.<verse eid="SIR 11:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:20"/>Stand by your covenant<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'agreement'</char></note>, and attend to it, and in your work grow old.<verse eid="SIR 11:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:21"/>Do not wonder at the works of a sinner, but have faith in the Lord, and continue your labor, because it is easy in the eyes of the Lord quickly, suddenly, to make a needy person rich.<verse eid="SIR 11:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:22"/>The Lord's blessing is in the wage of a pious person, and in a short time his good pleasure flourishes.<verse eid="SIR 11:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:23"/>Do not say, "What is my need? And what will be my good things from now on?"<verse eid="SIR 11:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:24"/>Do not say, "I have enough, and what distress will I suffer from now on?"<verse eid="SIR 11:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:25"/>In a day of prosperity, adversity<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'prosperity, adversity':  Or 'good things, bad things'</char></note> is forgotten, and in a day of adversity, prosperity<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'adversity, prosperity':  Or 'bad things, good things'</char></note> will not be remembered,<verse eid="SIR 11:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:26"/>because it is easy with the Lord in a day of death to give back to a person according to his ways.<verse eid="SIR 11:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:27"/>An hour's misery engenders forgetfulness of luxury, and a person's end is a disclosure of his deeds.<verse eid="SIR 11:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:28"/>Before death call no one happy, and in his children a man will be known.<verse eid="SIR 11:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:29"/>Do not bring every person into your home, for many are the ambushes of the deceitful.<verse eid="SIR 11:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:30"/>A decoy partridge in a cage, so is the heart of an arrogant person, and like a spy he observes a downfall.<verse eid="SIR 11:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:31"/>For he lies in ambush turning good things into bad, and among choice things he adds disgrace<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:31</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'among choice things he adds disgrace':  Perhaps 'among chosen ones he sets disgrace'</char></note>.<verse eid="SIR 11:31"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:32"/>From a spark of fire coals are multiplied, and a sinful person lies in ambush for blood.<verse eid="SIR 11:32"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:33"/>Beware of a scoundrel-- for he devises wicked things-- lest he deliver to you disgrace forever.<verse eid="SIR 11:33"/>

<verse sid="SIR 11:34"/>Welcome a stranger, and he will twist you around in confusion and alienate you from your own.<verse eid="SIR 11:34"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 12">
<verse sid="SIR 12:1"/>If you do good, know for whom you do it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note>, and there will be gratitude for your good deeds.<verse eid="SIR 12:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:2"/>Do good to a pious person, and you will find repayment, and if not from him, then from the Most High.<verse eid="SIR 12:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:3"/>There is no good for him who persists in evil and for him who does not willingly offer charity.<verse eid="SIR 12:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:4"/>Give to the pious person, but do not assist the sinner.<verse eid="SIR 12:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:5"/>Treat the humble well, and do not give to an impious person; hold back loaves of bread, and do not give to him, lest by them he prevail over you; for you will get twice as many bad things for all the good things that you might do for him,<verse eid="SIR 12:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:6"/>because also the Most High hated sinners, and on the impious he will render punishment.<verse eid="SIR 12:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:7"/>Give to the good person, and do not assist the sinner.<verse eid="SIR 12:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:8"/>The friend will not be punished in good things, and the enemy will not be hidden in evil things.<verse eid="SIR 12:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:9"/>In a man's good things, his enemies are in pain, and in his evil things, a friend also will be separated.<verse eid="SIR 12:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:10"/>Never trust your enemy; for just as copper corrodes, so does his wickedness.<verse eid="SIR 12:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:11"/>And if he is brought low and walks stooped, trust your soul, and be on guard against him, and you shall be to him as one who wipes a mirror, and you shall know that it was not completely tarnished.<verse eid="SIR 12:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:12"/>Do not stand him next to you, lest, having overthrown you, he stand in your place; do not seat him at your right, lest he seek your seat, and at last you will understand my words and be pricked by my sayings.<verse eid="SIR 12:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:13"/>Who will pity a charmer bitten by a snake, or all who approach wild beasts?--<verse eid="SIR 12:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:14"/>so the one who goes near a man who sins and one who gets mixed up in his sins.<verse eid="SIR 12:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:15"/>For a time he will remain with you, and if you falter, he will not be steadfast.<verse eid="SIR 12:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:16"/>With his lips the enemy will speak sweetly, and in his heart he will plan to throw you into a trench. With his eyes the enemy will weep, and if he finds an opportunity, he will not be sated with blood.<verse eid="SIR 12:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:17"/>If harm meets you, you will find him there ahead of you, and pretending to help, he will trip your heel.<verse eid="SIR 12:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 12:18"/>He will shake his head and clap his hands and whisper many things and alter his face.<verse eid="SIR 12:18"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 13">
<verse sid="SIR 13:1"/>He who touches pitch will become dirty, and he who associates with a proud person will become like him.<verse eid="SIR 13:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:2"/>Do not lift what is too heavy for you, and do not associate with one stronger and richer than you. How will a clay pot associate with a cauldron? The former will strike against, and the former will be smashed.<verse eid="SIR 13:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:3"/>A rich person did wrong, and he was angry to boot; a poor person has been wronged, and he will plead.<verse eid="SIR 13:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:4"/>If you are useful, he will work with you, and if you are in want, he will abandon you.<verse eid="SIR 13:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:5"/>If you have something<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note>, he will live with you, and he will clean you out, and he will not suffer.<verse eid="SIR 13:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:6"/>He has need of you and will deceive you and will smile at you and will give you hope; he will speak nice things to you and say, "What do you need?"<verse eid="SIR 13:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:7"/>He will shame you with his foods until he cleans you out two or three times, and at last he will mock you; after these things, he will see you and leave you and will shake his head at you.<verse eid="SIR 13:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:8"/>Take care that you are not led astray, and do not be humiliated by your folly.<verse eid="SIR 13:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:9"/>When a powerful person invites you, be reserved, and he will invite you so much more.<verse eid="SIR 13:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:10"/>Do not be forward, lest you be rejected, and do not stand far off, lest you be forgotten.<verse eid="SIR 13:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:11"/>Do not aim to speak as an equal with him, and do not put faith in his rather many words; for with much talk he will test you, and as though smiling he will be examining you.<verse eid="SIR 13:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:12"/>Merciless is he who does not guard words, and he will not spare you from doing bad and imprisonment.<verse eid="SIR 13:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:13"/>Be on guard, and pay attention, because you are walking about with your own downfall.<verse eid="SIR 13:13"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 13:14"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 13:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:15"/>Every living thing loves what is like to it, and every person his fellow.<verse eid="SIR 13:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:16"/>All flesh congregates according to kind, and with one like himself will a man cleave.<verse eid="SIR 13:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:17"/>What will a wolf have in common with a lamb?-- so is<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> a sinner to a pious person.<verse eid="SIR 13:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:18"/>What peace is there between a hyena and a dog? And what peace between a rich person and a needy person?<verse eid="SIR 13:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:19"/>The prey of lions is onagers in the desert; thus the poor are the fodder of the rich.<verse eid="SIR 13:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:20"/>An abomination to a proud person is humility; thus an abomination to a rich person is a poor person.<verse eid="SIR 13:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:21"/>When a rich person totters, he is supported by friends, but when a humble person falls, he is pushed away by friends.<verse eid="SIR 13:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:22"/>When a rich person staggers, many are his helpers; he spoke things not to be spoken, and they justified him. A humble person staggered, and in addition they rebuked him; he uttered sense, and no place was given to him.<verse eid="SIR 13:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:23"/>A rich person spoke, and all kept silent, and they exalted his word up to the clouds. A poor person spoke, and they said, "Who is this?" And if he should stumble, they will even overturn him.<verse eid="SIR 13:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:24"/>Wealth in which there is no sin is good, but in the mouths of an impious person poverty is wicked.<verse eid="SIR 13:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:25"/>A person's heart changes his face, whether for good things or bad.<verse eid="SIR 13:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 13:26"/>A heart's footstep in good things is a cheerful face, and the invention of illustrations is conversations along with toils.<verse eid="SIR 13:26"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 14">
<verse sid="SIR 14:1"/>Happy is the man who did not slip with his mouth and was not stabbed with the pain of sins.<verse eid="SIR 14:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:2"/>Happy the one whose soul has not condemned him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">14:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> and who has not lost his hope.<verse eid="SIR 14:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:3"/>For a petty man wealth is not good, and to a begrudging person-- why is there money?<verse eid="SIR 14:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:4"/>He who constrains his appetite collects for others, and with his goods others will live luxuriously.<verse eid="SIR 14:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:5"/>He who is evil to himself, to whom will he be good? And he will never be gladdened by his money.<verse eid="SIR 14:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:6"/>There is none worse than he who begrudges himself, and this is repayment for his evil.<verse eid="SIR 14:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:7"/>Even if he acts well, he does it with forgetting, and in the end he reveals his evil.<verse eid="SIR 14:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:8"/>Wicked is the one who is grudging with the eye, when he turns away his<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">14:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> face and overlooks souls.<verse eid="SIR 14:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:9"/>The eye of the greedy is not satisfied with a portion, and wicked injustice withers the soul.<verse eid="SIR 14:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:10"/>An evil eye is envious over bread, and it is lacking on his<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">14:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'its'</char></note> table.<verse eid="SIR 14:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:11"/>Child, even as you have, treat yourself well, and bring offerings to the Lord worthily.<verse eid="SIR 14:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:12"/>Remember that death will not tarry, and the covenant of Hades has not been shown to you.<verse eid="SIR 14:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:13"/>Before you die, treat a friend well, and, according to your strength, reach out, and give to him.<verse eid="SIR 14:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:14"/>Do not withdraw from a good day, and do not let a share of a good desire pass you by.<verse eid="SIR 14:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:15"/>Will you not leave behind your toils to another and your toils to division by lot?<verse eid="SIR 14:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:16"/>Give, and take, and deceive your soul, because in Hades there is no seeking of luxury.<verse eid="SIR 14:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:17"/>All flesh becomes old like a garment, for the covenant of old is, "By death you shall die!"<verse eid="SIR 14:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:18"/>Like a sprouting leaf on a thickly leaved tree, some it sheds, but others it puts forth; so is a generation of flesh and blood, the one dies and the other is born.<verse eid="SIR 14:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:19"/>Every decaying deed ceases, and the one who does it will pass away with it.<verse eid="SIR 14:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:20"/>Happy is the man who will meditate on wisdom and who will converse with his understanding.<verse eid="SIR 14:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:21"/>He who considers her ways in his heart also will reflect on her obscurities.<verse eid="SIR 14:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:22"/>Go out after her like a tracker, and in her entranceways lie in wait!<verse eid="SIR 14:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:23"/>He who peers through her windows also will listen at her doorways.<verse eid="SIR 14:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:24"/>He who lodges near her house also will pitch a peg in her walls.<verse eid="SIR 14:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:25"/>He will set his tent according to her hand<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">14:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'according to her hand':  I.e. 'as she directs'</char></note>, and he will lodge in a lodging place of good things.<verse eid="SIR 14:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:26"/>He will place his children in her shelter, and under her boughs he will encamp.<verse eid="SIR 14:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 14:27"/>He will be sheltered by her from heat, and in her glory he will lodge.<verse eid="SIR 14:27"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 15">
<verse sid="SIR 15:1"/>He who fears the Lord will do it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">15:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Antecedent unclear</char></note>, and he who has a hold on the law will lay hold of her.<verse eid="SIR 15:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:2"/>And she will come to meet him like a mother, and like a woman of maidenhood, she will welcome him.<verse eid="SIR 15:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:3"/>She will feed him bread of understanding, and water of wisdom she will give him to drink.<verse eid="SIR 15:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:4"/>He will be propped up on her and will not lie down<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">15:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'lie down':  Or 'fall'</char></note>, and he will attend to her, and he will not be put to shame.<verse eid="SIR 15:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:5"/>And she will exalt him above his fellows, and in the midst of an assembly she will open his mouth.<verse eid="SIR 15:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:6"/>Gladness and a garland of rejoicing and an everlasting name will he inherit.<verse eid="SIR 15:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:7"/>Witless people will never lay hold of her, and sinful men will never see her.<verse eid="SIR 15:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:8"/>She is far from arrogance, and lying men will never remember her.<verse eid="SIR 15:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:9"/>A song of praise is not proper in the mouth of a sinner, because it has not been apportioned by the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 15:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:10"/>For in wisdom a song of praise will be uttered, and the Lord will make it prosper.<verse eid="SIR 15:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:11"/>Do not say, "On account of the Lord I fell away," for what he hates, he will not do.<verse eid="SIR 15:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:12"/>Do not say, "It was he who led me astray," for he has no need of a sinful man.<verse eid="SIR 15:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:13"/>Every abomination the Lord hated, and it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">15:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'abomination'</char></note> is not beloved to those who fear him.<verse eid="SIR 15:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:14"/>It was he who from the beginning made humankind, and he left him in the hand of his deliberation.<verse eid="SIR 15:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:15"/>If you want to, you shall preserve the commandments, and to keep faith is a matter of good pleasure.<verse eid="SIR 15:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:16"/>He has set aside for you fire and water; to whichever you want, you shall stretch out your hand.<verse eid="SIR 15:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:17"/>Before humans are life and death, and whichever one he desires will be given to him,<verse eid="SIR 15:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:18"/>because great is the wisdom of the Lord; he is mighty in dominance and one who sees everything.<verse eid="SIR 15:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:19"/>And his eyes are on those who fear him, and he will know every human deed.<verse eid="SIR 15:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 15:20"/>He did not command anyone to be impious, and he did not give anyone leave to sin.<verse eid="SIR 15:20"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 16">
<verse sid="SIR 16:1"/>Do not desire a multitude of useless children, and do not be glad over impious sons.<verse eid="SIR 16:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:2"/>If they multiply, do not be glad over them unless the fear of the Lord is with them.<verse eid="SIR 16:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:3"/>Do not have faith in their life, and do not be intent on the multitude of them. For better is one than a thousand, and to die childless rather than to have impious children.<verse eid="SIR 16:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:4"/>For by one intelligent person a city will be peopled, but a tribe of lawless people will be left without<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">16:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'without a city'</char></note>.<verse eid="SIR 16:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:5"/>Many such things has my eye seen, and more mighty things than these has my ear heard.<verse eid="SIR 16:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:6"/>In a gathering of sinners a fire will blaze out, and in a disobedient nation wrath has blazed out.<verse eid="SIR 16:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:7"/>He did not propitiate for the ancient giants, those who revolted in their strength.<verse eid="SIR 16:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:8"/>He did not spare the neighbors of Lot whom he loathed on account of their arrogance.<verse eid="SIR 16:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:9"/>He did not have mercy on a nation of destruction, those carried away by their sins.<verse eid="SIR 16:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:10"/>even so six hundred thousand foot soldiers, those assembled in their hardness of heart.<verse eid="SIR 16:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:11"/>Even if there might be one stiff-necked person, it would be a wonder if he would go unpunished; for mercy and wrath are with him, a dynast of propitiations and pouring out wrath.<verse eid="SIR 16:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:12"/>According to his great mercy, so also is his reproof; he will judge a man according to his deeds.<verse eid="SIR 16:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:13"/>A sinner will not escape with booty, and the endurance of the pious will never fail.<verse eid="SIR 16:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:14"/>He will make a place for every act of charity; each will get according to his deeds.<verse eid="SIR 16:14"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 16:15"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">16:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 16:15"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 16:16"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">16:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 16:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:17"/>Do not say, "I will be hidden from the Lord-- and from on high who will remember me?" Among a great many people I will not be known; for what is my soul in an immeasurable creation?<verse eid="SIR 16:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:18"/>Look, the sky and the sky of the sky, abyss and earth will totter at his visitation.<verse eid="SIR 16:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:19"/>At once the mountains and the foundations of the earth are being shaken together with trembling when he looks at them.<verse eid="SIR 16:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:20"/>And to them the heart will give no thought-- and his ways who has pondered?<verse eid="SIR 16:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:21"/>And a tempest there is, which person shall not see-- and most of his deeds are in secret.<verse eid="SIR 16:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:22"/>Acts of justice who will announce, or who will await? For the covenant is far off.<verse eid="SIR 16:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:23"/>One who is lacking in heart thinks these things, and a foolish and misled man thinks foolish things.<verse eid="SIR 16:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:24"/>Listen to me, child, and learn knowledge, and to my words apply your heart.<verse eid="SIR 16:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:25"/>I will disclose instruction by fixed standard, and with accuracy I will declare knowledge.<verse eid="SIR 16:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:26"/>In the Lord's creation are his works from the beginning, and from the making of them he defined their portions.<verse eid="SIR 16:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:27"/>He put in order their tasks forever and their rule for their generations; they neither hungered, nor did they grow weary, and they did not abandon their tasks.<verse eid="SIR 16:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:28"/>Each one did not crowd its fellow, and they will not ever disobey his dictum.<verse eid="SIR 16:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:29"/>And after these things, the Lord looked upon the earth, and he filled it with his good things.<verse eid="SIR 16:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 16:30"/>With the soul of every living thing he covered its face, and into it is their return.<verse eid="SIR 16:30"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 17">
<verse sid="SIR 17:1"/>The Lord created a human being out of earth, and he returned him into it again.<verse eid="SIR 17:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:2"/>He gave them days in number and a fixed time, and he gave them authority over the things upon it.<verse eid="SIR 17:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:3"/>He clothed them in a strength like himself, and in his image he made them.<verse eid="SIR 17:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:4"/>He placed the fear of him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">17:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. the first human</char></note> upon all flesh, even to have dominion over beasts and birds.<verse eid="SIR 17:4"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 17:5"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">17:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 17:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:6"/>Deliberation and a tongue and eyes, ears and a heart for thinking he gave them.<verse eid="SIR 17:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:7"/>With knowledge of understanding he filled them, and good things and bad he showed to them.<verse eid="SIR 17:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:8"/>He put the fear of him upon their hearts, to show them the majesty of his works.<verse eid="SIR 17:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:9"/>in order to recount the majesties of his works.<verse eid="SIR 17:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:10"/>And they shall praise a name of holiness<verse eid="SIR 17:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:11"/>He set before them knowledge, and a law of life he allotted to them<verse eid="SIR 17:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:12"/>A perpetual covenant he established with them, and his judgments he showed to them.<verse eid="SIR 17:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:13"/>Majesty of glory their eyes saw, and the glory of his voice their ear heard.<verse eid="SIR 17:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:14"/>And he said to them, "Be on guard against all wrong," and he commanded each of them concerning his fellow.<verse eid="SIR 17:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:15"/>Their ways are before him always; they will not be hidden from his eyes.<verse eid="SIR 17:15"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 17:16"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">17:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 17:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:17"/>for each nation he appointed a leader, and the Lord's portion is Israel,<verse eid="SIR 17:17"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 17:18"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">17:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 17:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:19"/>All of their works are before him like the sun, and his eyes are continually upon their ways.<verse eid="SIR 17:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:20"/>Their injustices were not hidden from him, and all their sins are before the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 17:20"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 17:21"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">17:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 17:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:22"/>A man's charity is like a signet with him, and a person's kindness he will preserve like the apple of his eye,<verse eid="SIR 17:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:23"/>After these things he will arise and repay them, and their repayment he will deliver upon their head.<verse eid="SIR 17:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:24"/>Except to those who repented he granted a return, and he exhorted those who were abandoning hope.<verse eid="SIR 17:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:25"/>Turn back to the Lord, and leave sins behind; petition in person, and minimize the offense.<verse eid="SIR 17:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:26"/>Return to the Most High, and turn away from injustice, and intensely hate abomination.<verse eid="SIR 17:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:27"/>Who will sing praises to the Most High in Hades instead of the living and those who give thanks?<verse eid="SIR 17:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:28"/>From a corpse, since it does not exist, acknowledgement has perished; a living and healthy person will praise the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 17:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:29"/>How great is the charity of the Lord and his propitiation to those who turn back to him.<verse eid="SIR 17:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:30"/>For not all things are able to be among humans, because a son of man is not immortal.<verse eid="SIR 17:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:31"/>What is brighter than the sun? Even this thing fails. And flesh and blood will ponder evil.<verse eid="SIR 17:31"/>

<verse sid="SIR 17:32"/>It is he who reviews the power of the sky's height, and all human beings are earth and ashes.<verse eid="SIR 17:32"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 18">
<verse sid="SIR 18:1"/>He who lives forever created everything in common.<verse eid="SIR 18:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:2"/>The Lord alone will be justified,<verse eid="SIR 18:2"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 18:3"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">18:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 18:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:4"/>He has permitted no one to announce his works-- and who can search out his majestic deeds?<verse eid="SIR 18:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:5"/>The power of his greatness who will enumerate? And who will add to recount his mercies?<verse eid="SIR 18:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:6"/>It is impossible to diminish or to increase them<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">18:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note>, and it is impossible to search out the wonders of the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 18:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:7"/>When a person finishes, then he is beginning, and when he stops, then he will be at a loss.<verse eid="SIR 18:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:8"/>What is a human being, and what is his use? What is his good, and what is his evil?<verse eid="SIR 18:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:9"/>The number of a person's days is as many as a hundred years,<verse eid="SIR 18:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:10"/>Like a drop of water from the sea and a grain of sand, so are a few years in a day of eternity.<verse eid="SIR 18:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:11"/>For this reason the Lord was longsuffering with them, and he poured out his mercy upon them.<verse eid="SIR 18:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:12"/>He saw and knew their end, that it is grievous; for this reason he multiplied his propitiation.<verse eid="SIR 18:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:13"/>A person's mercy is upon his fellow, but the mercy of the Lord is upon all flesh, when he corrects and instructs and teaches and turns as a shepherd does his flock.<verse eid="SIR 18:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:14"/>He shows mercy to those who accept discipline and who hasten to his judgments.<verse eid="SIR 18:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:15"/>Child, do not allow reproach among good deeds nor pain of words with every giving.<verse eid="SIR 18:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:16"/>Does not dew mitigate scorching heat? So better a word than a gift.<verse eid="SIR 18:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:17"/>Look! Does not a word exceed a good gift? And both are with a man who has been favored.<verse eid="SIR 18:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:18"/>A foolish person will upbraid ungraciously, and the giving of a grudging person melts eyes.<verse eid="SIR 18:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:19"/>Before speaking, learn, and before illness, take care of yourself.<verse eid="SIR 18:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:20"/>Before judgment, examine yourself, and in the hour of scrutiny you will find propitiation.<verse eid="SIR 18:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:21"/>Before you fall ill, humble yourself, and in a time of sinful actions demonstrate repentance.<verse eid="SIR 18:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:22"/>Do not be hindered from repaying a vow appropriately, and do not wait until death to be vindicated.<verse eid="SIR 18:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:23"/>Before making a vow, prepare yourself, and do not be like a person who tempts the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 18:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:24"/>Be mindful of wrath in days of death and of a time of vengeance in the turning away of a face<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">18:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'in the turning away of a face':  Or 'when he turns away (his) face'</char></note>.<verse eid="SIR 18:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:25"/>Be mindful of a time of hunger in a time of plenty, of poverty and want in days of wealth.<verse eid="SIR 18:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:26"/>From morning until evening opportunity changes, and all things are swift<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">18:26</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Perhaps 'fleeting'</char></note> before the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 18:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:27"/>A wise person will be cautious in everything, and in days of sins he will take heed against error.<verse eid="SIR 18:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:28"/>Every intelligent person recognized wisdom, and to him who finds her she<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">18:28</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'he'</char></note> will give acknowledgment.<verse eid="SIR 18:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:29"/>Persons who are intelligent with words also became wise themselves, and they poured forth apt proverbs. SELF CONTROL<verse eid="SIR 18:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:30"/>After your desires do not go, and from your appetites restrain yourself.<verse eid="SIR 18:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:31"/>If you furnish your soul with consent for desire, it will make you a laughingstock of your enemies.<verse eid="SIR 18:31"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:32"/>Do not be glad in great luxury; do not be made needy by its contact.<verse eid="SIR 18:32"/>

<verse sid="SIR 18:33"/>Do not become poor by feasting out of borrowing, and you have nothing in your pocket.<verse eid="SIR 18:33"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 19">
<verse sid="SIR 19:1"/>A drunken worker will not become rich, and he who despises few things will fall little by little.<verse eid="SIR 19:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:2"/>Wine and women will mislead intelligent men, and he who joins himself to prostitutes will be more reckless.<verse eid="SIR 19:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:3"/>Decay and worms will take possession of him, and a reckless soul will be carried off.<verse eid="SIR 19:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:4"/>He who trusts quickly is light in heart, and he who sins will do wrong to his soul.<verse eid="SIR 19:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:5"/>He who is gladdened by wickedness will be condemned,<verse eid="SIR 19:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:6"/>and he who hates discussion will be lacking in heart.<verse eid="SIR 19:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:7"/>Never repeat a word, and nothing will be lacking to you.<verse eid="SIR 19:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:8"/>Among friend and foe do not describe, and unless it is a sin for you, do not disclose.<verse eid="SIR 19:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:9"/>Suppose he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">19:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'friend' or 'foe'</char></note> has heard you and kept watch on you and in time will hate you.<verse eid="SIR 19:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:10"/>Have you heard a word? Let it perish along with you. Be brave! It will never make you burst.<verse eid="SIR 19:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:11"/>From a word, a foolish person will go into labor pains, as does she who is giving birth from a babe to be born.<verse eid="SIR 19:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:12"/>An arrow stuck in a thigh of flesh, so is a word in the gut of a foolish person.<verse eid="SIR 19:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:13"/>Question a friend; perhaps he didn't, and if he did something, lest perchance he add.<verse eid="SIR 19:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:14"/>Question your fellow; perhaps he didn't say, and if he has said, lest he repeat.<verse eid="SIR 19:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:15"/>Question a friend, for ofttimes it becomes slander, and do not believe every word.<verse eid="SIR 19:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:16"/>There exists one who slips, and it is not <note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">19:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'intentional'</char></note>from the soul<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">19:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'friend' or 'foe'</char></note>-- and who has not sinned with his tongue?<verse eid="SIR 19:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:17"/>Question your fellow before threatening, and give a place to the law of the Most High.<verse eid="SIR 19:17"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 19:18"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">19:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 19:18"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 19:19"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">19:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 19:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:20"/>All wisdom is fear of the Lord, and in all wisdom there is doing of the law<verse eid="SIR 19:20"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 19:21"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">19:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 19:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:22"/>There is no wisdom that is knowledge of wickedness, and there is no prudence in advice of sinners.<verse eid="SIR 19:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:23"/>There is cleverness that is also an abomination, and there is a fool lacking in wisdom.<verse eid="SIR 19:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:24"/>Better is a fearful person inferior in intelligence than one superior in prudence and transgressing the law.<verse eid="SIR 19:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:25"/>There exists exact cleverness that is also unjust, and there is one who perverts a favor in order to produce a judgment,<verse eid="SIR 19:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:26"/>There is one who acts wickedly, bent down with blackness, and what is inside him is full of treachery.<verse eid="SIR 19:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:27"/>As he lowers face and feigns deafness, when no one observes, he will outrun you.<verse eid="SIR 19:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:28"/>And if by lack of strength he is prevented from sinning, if he finds opportunity, he will do evil.<verse eid="SIR 19:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:29"/>From appearance a man will be recognized, and from a meeting in person a rational person will be recognized.<verse eid="SIR 19:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 19:30"/>A man's clothing and a laughter of teeth<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">19:30</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'laughter of teeth':  I.e. 'toothy laugh'</char></note> and a person's gait will announce things about him.<verse eid="SIR 19:30"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 20">
<verse sid="SIR 20:1"/>There is questioning that is not timely, and there is one who keeps silent, and he is prudent.<verse eid="SIR 20:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:2"/>How good it is to question rather than to be angry.<verse eid="SIR 20:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:3"/>And he who admits freely will be kept from disparagement.<verse eid="SIR 20:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:4"/>A eunuch's desire to violate a girl-- thus is he who makes judgments by force.<verse eid="SIR 20:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:5"/>There exists a person who keeps silent, who is found to be wise, and there is one who is hated from much talk.<verse eid="SIR 20:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:6"/>There exists one who keeps silent, for he does not have an answer, and there is one who keeps silent, since he knows the proper time.<verse eid="SIR 20:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:7"/>A wise person will be silent until a proper time, but the swaggerer and fool overstep a proper time.<verse eid="SIR 20:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:8"/>He who is excessive with speech will be loathed, and he who pretends to authority will be hated.<verse eid="SIR 20:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:9"/>A man has success in evil things, and there is a windfall resulting in loss.<verse eid="SIR 20:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:10"/>There exists giving that will not profit you, and there exists giving of which the repayment is double.<verse eid="SIR 20:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:11"/>There exists loss for the sake of reputation, and there exists a person who from a low estate raised his<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">20:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> head.<verse eid="SIR 20:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:12"/>There exists a person who buys much for a little and pays for it seven times.<verse eid="SIR 20:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:13"/>The wise person will make himself beloved in a few things, but favors of foolish ones will be poured out.<verse eid="SIR 20:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:14"/>A gift of a fool will not profit you, for his eyes are many instead of one.<verse eid="SIR 20:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:15"/>He will seldom give and reproach often, and he will open his mouth like a herald; today he will lend and ask back tomorrow; such a person is hateful.<verse eid="SIR 20:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:16"/>A foolish person says, "I do not have a friend, and there is no gratitude for my good deeds." Those who eat his bread are mean in tongue.<verse eid="SIR 20:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:17"/>How often and how many will ridicule him?<verse eid="SIR 20:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:18"/>A slip on the ground rather than of the tongue; so the downfall of evil persons will come speedily.<verse eid="SIR 20:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:19"/>An ungracious person, an untimely story, it will persist in the mouth of the uneducated.<verse eid="SIR 20:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:20"/>An illustration from the mouth of a foolish person will be rejected, for he will not tell it at its proper time.<verse eid="SIR 20:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:21"/>There exists a person who is prevented from sinning by indigence, and in his rest he will not be bewildered.<verse eid="SIR 20:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:22"/>There exists a person who destroys his life through shame, and he will destroy it due to a fool.<verse eid="SIR 20:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:23"/>There exists a person who promises to a friend a favor out of shame and made him an enemy to no purpose.<verse eid="SIR 20:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:24"/>A lie is an evil blemish on a person; it will persist in the mouth of the uneducated.<verse eid="SIR 20:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:25"/>Preferable is a thief over one who persists in a lie, but both will inherit destruction.<verse eid="SIR 20:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:26"/>A lying person's character is dishonor, and his shame is constantly with him. ILLUSTRATIVE SAYINGS<verse eid="SIR 20:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:27"/>The wise person will apply himself in few things, and a prudent person will please nobles.<verse eid="SIR 20:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:28"/>He who tills the soil will raise up his heap, and he who pleases nobles will atone for injustice.<verse eid="SIR 20:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:29"/>Friendly gift and presents<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">20:29</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'bribes'</char></note> blind the eyes of wise persons, and like a muzzle on a mouth they turn away reproofs.<verse eid="SIR 20:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:30"/>Hidden wisdom and unseen treasure, what profit is there in both?<verse eid="SIR 20:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 20:31"/>Better is a person who hides his foolishness than a person who hides his wisdom.<verse eid="SIR 20:31"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 21">
<verse sid="SIR 21:1"/>Child, you sinned; do not add any longer, and concerning your former ones petition.<verse eid="SIR 21:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:2"/>As from before a snake, flee from sin, for if you approach, it will bite you; it's teeth are lion's teeth, destroying people's lives.<verse eid="SIR 21:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:3"/>All lawlessness is like a two-edged sword; for its wound there is no healing.<verse eid="SIR 21:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:4"/>Consternation and insolence will desolate wealth; so an arrogant person's house will be uprooted.<verse eid="SIR 21:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:5"/>A poor person's petition is from the mouth to his<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">21:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. God's</char></note> ears, and his judgment comes speedily.<verse eid="SIR 21:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:6"/>One who hates reproof is in the footstep of a sinner, and he who fears the Lord will turn with the heart.<verse eid="SIR 21:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:7"/>Known from afar is he who is mighty in tongue, but he who is sensible knows when he makes a slip.<verse eid="SIR 21:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:8"/>He who builds his house with others' money is like one who gathers his stones for a burial mound.<verse eid="SIR 21:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:9"/>A gathering of the lawless is bundled flax, and a flame of fire is their end.<verse eid="SIR 21:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:10"/>A way of sinners is leveled out of stones, and at its end is a hole of Hades.<verse eid="SIR 21:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:11"/>He who keeps the law gains mastery over the object of his thought, and consummation of the fear of the Lord is wisdom.<verse eid="SIR 21:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:12"/>He who is not clever shall not be instructed, but there is a cleverness that increases bitterness.<verse eid="SIR 21:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:13"/>A wise person's knowledge will increase like a flood, and his counsel is like a spring of life.<verse eid="SIR 21:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:14"/>The inward parts<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">21:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> of a foolish person are like a broken vessel, and he will not master any knowledge.<verse eid="SIR 21:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:15"/>A wise word-- if one who understands hears it, he will praise it and will add to it. He who lives luxuriously heard and was displeased with it, and he turned it aside behind his back.<verse eid="SIR 21:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:16"/>A foolish person's explanation is like a burden on a journey, but upon the lips of an intelligent person grace will be found.<verse eid="SIR 21:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:17"/>The mouth of a prudent person will be sought in an assembly, and his words they will ponder in their<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">21:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> heart.<verse eid="SIR 21:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:18"/>Like a house that has been razed, so is wisdom to a foolish person, and an ignorant person's knowledge is meaningless words.<verse eid="SIR 21:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:19"/>On a thoughtless person's feet education is fetters, and like manacles on one's right hand.<verse eid="SIR 21:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:20"/>A foolish person raises his voice in laughter, but a clever man will scarcely smile in silence.<verse eid="SIR 21:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:21"/>Like a golden ornament is instruction to a prudent person, and like a bracelet on the right arm.<verse eid="SIR 21:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:22"/>A foolish person's foot is quick into a house, but an experienced person will feel restraint in front.<verse eid="SIR 21:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:23"/>A fool peeks into a house from a door, but an educated man will stand outside.<verse eid="SIR 21:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:24"/>It is lack of education for a person to listen at a door, but a prudent person will be weighed down by dishonor.<verse eid="SIR 21:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:25"/>Lips of strangers will tell tales with these things, but the words of prudent persons will be placed on a scale.<verse eid="SIR 21:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:26"/>In the mouth of foolish persons is their heart, but in the heart of wise persons is their mouth.<verse eid="SIR 21:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:27"/>When an impious person curses the satan, he curses his own soul.<verse eid="SIR 21:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 21:28"/>He who whispers defiles his own soul, and he will be hated in a neighborhood.<verse eid="SIR 21:28"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 22">
<verse sid="SIR 22:1"/>A sluggard has been compared to a filthy stone, and everyone will hiss at his dishonor.<verse eid="SIR 22:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:2"/>A sluggard has been compared to cow dung of dunghills; everyone who picks it up will shake off his<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">22:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> hand.<verse eid="SIR 22:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:3"/>A father's shame is in engendering an ineducable son<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">22:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note>, but a daughter is born at a loss.<verse eid="SIR 22:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:4"/>A prudent daughter will obtain a husband of her own, and she who is put to shame is as a grief for a begetter.<verse eid="SIR 22:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:5"/>The impudent woman shames father and husband, and she will be held in dishonor by both of them.<verse eid="SIR 22:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:6"/>Untimely narration is music during mourning, but whips and instruction<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">22:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'discipline'</char></note> are wisdom at any time.<verse eid="SIR 22:6"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 22:7"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">22:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 22:7"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 22:8"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">22:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 22:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:9"/>He who teaches a foolish person is one gluing together a potsherd, one arousing a sleeper out of a deep sleep.<verse eid="SIR 22:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:10"/>He who recounts to a foolish person is recounting to one who is drowsy, and at the conclusion he will say, "What is it?"<verse eid="SIR 22:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:11"/>Weep over a corpse, for he has left the light, and weep over a foolish person, for he has left understanding behind. Weep sweetly over a corpse, because he died, but the life of the foolish person is a sorry plight beyond death.<verse eid="SIR 22:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:12"/>Mourning for a corpse is for seven days, but for a foolish and impious person, it is all the days of his life.<verse eid="SIR 22:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:13"/>Do not increase speech with a fool, and do not go to an unintelligent person; keep away from him, lest you have trouble, and you will not be sullied by his shaking off; stay clear of him, and you will find rest, and you will never be wearied by his madness.<verse eid="SIR 22:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:14"/>What will be heavier than lead? And what name does he have but "foolish person"?<verse eid="SIR 22:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:15"/>Sand and salt and a lump of iron are easier to bear than an unintelligent person.<verse eid="SIR 22:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:16"/>A tie-beam fastened into a building will not be loosed by an earthquake; so a heart firmly set upon a thought from counsel will not be afraid at any time.<verse eid="SIR 22:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:17"/>A heart fixed upon thoughtful understanding is like an engraved ornament on a smooth wall.<verse eid="SIR 22:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:18"/>Pebbles lying on a high surface will never endure against a wind; so a heart in dread at the thought of a foolish person will never endure against any fear.<verse eid="SIR 22:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:19"/>He who pricks an eye will draw down tears, and he who pricks a heart brings to light feelings.<verse eid="SIR 22:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:20"/>He who throws a stone at birds scares them off, and he who insults a friend dissolves a friendship.<verse eid="SIR 22:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:21"/>If you draw a sword on a friend, do not despair, for a way back is possible.<verse eid="SIR 22:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:22"/>If you open your<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">22:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> mouth against a friend, be not concerned, for reconciliation is possible-- with the exception of reproach and arrogance and revealing a secret and a treacherous blow-- in these cases any friend will flee.<verse eid="SIR 22:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:23"/>Gain your fellow's trust in poverty so that in his prosperity you may be filled as well; in a time of distress stay with him so that in his inheritance you may be a joint heir.<verse eid="SIR 22:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:24"/>Preceding a fire there are a furnace's vapor and smoke; so preceding bloodshed there are abuses.<verse eid="SIR 22:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:25"/>I will not be ashamed to shelter a friend, and from before him I will never hide.<verse eid="SIR 22:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:26"/>And if bad things will happen to me on his account, everyone who hears will guard against him.<verse eid="SIR 22:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 22:27"/>Who will grant a guard upon my mouth and a shrewd seal upon my lips, lest I fall because of them and my tongue destroy me?<verse eid="SIR 22:27"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 23">
<verse sid="SIR 23:1"/>O Lord, Father and Master of my life, do not abandon me to their design, and do not let me fall among them.<verse eid="SIR 23:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:2"/>Who will set whips upon my thought and discipline of wisdom upon my heart so that they might not spare my faults of ignorance and he shall not let their sins go?--<verse eid="SIR 23:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:3"/>that my acts of ignorance may not be multiplied, and my sins may increase, and I will fall before my adversaries, and my enemy will rejoice over me.<verse eid="SIR 23:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:4"/>O Lord, Father and God of my life, do not give me a lifting up of eyes,<verse eid="SIR 23:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:5"/>and turn desire away from me.<verse eid="SIR 23:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:6"/>Let not the belly's appetite and sexual intercourse seize me, and do not give me over to a shameless soul. DISCIPLINE OF THE MOUTH<verse eid="SIR 23:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:7"/>Listen, children, to discipline of the mouth, and he who observes it will never be caught.<verse eid="SIR 23:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:8"/>By his lips a sinner will be seized, and an abusive person and an arrogant person will be made to stumble by them.<verse eid="SIR 23:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:9"/>Do not accustom your mouth to an oath, and do not become used to the naming of the Holy One.<verse eid="SIR 23:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:10"/>For just as a domestic who is constantly scrutinized will not be wanting for a bruise, so also he who swears and always speaks the name will never be cleansed from sin.<verse eid="SIR 23:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:11"/>A man of many oaths will be full of lawlessness, and a scourge will not depart from his house; if he errs, his sin is upon him, and if he disregards it, he has sinned doubly, and if he swore in vain, he will not be justified, for his house will be full of distress.<verse eid="SIR 23:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:12"/>There is a way of speaking that compares with death; let it not be found in the inheritance of Iakob; for all these things shall stand away from the pious, and they shall not wallow in sins.<verse eid="SIR 23:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:13"/>Do not let your mouth become used to lewd want of education, for there is in it a word of sin.<verse eid="SIR 23:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:14"/>Remember your father and mother, for you sit in council among nobles, lest you forget yourself before them and act foolishly by your habit, and you will wish that you were never born, and you will curse the day of your birth.<verse eid="SIR 23:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:15"/>A person who is accustomed to words of reproach, in all his days, will never be instructed.<verse eid="SIR 23:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:16"/>Two kinds multiply sins, and a third will bring on wrath. A hot temperament like a burning fire will never be quenched until it is consumed; a person who is sexually promiscuous with the body of his flesh<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">23:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'the body of his flesh':  I.e. 'his own flesh and blood'</char></note> will never cease until a fire burns out.<verse eid="SIR 23:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:17"/>To a sexually promiscuous person all bread is sweet; he will never grow weary until he dies.<verse eid="SIR 23:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:18"/>There is a person who transgresses against his bed, saying in his soul, "Who will see me? Darkness surrounds me, and the walls will hide me, and no one will see me. Why am I discreet? The Most High will never remember my sins."<verse eid="SIR 23:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:19"/>And people's eyes are his fear, and he was unaware that the eyes of the Lord are ten thousand times brighter than the sun, as they look upon all the ways of human beings and as they look into obscure parts.<verse eid="SIR 23:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:20"/>Before all things were created, they were known to him, so also after they were completed.<verse eid="SIR 23:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:21"/>This one will be punished in the streets of the city, and when he did not suspect it, he will be seized.<verse eid="SIR 23:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:22"/>So also a woman when she leaves her husband and presents an heir by another.<verse eid="SIR 23:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:23"/>Now, first, she disobeyed the law of the Most High, and second, she committed a wrong against her husband, and third, she committed adultery by an illicit act and presented children by another man.<verse eid="SIR 23:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:24"/>She herself shall be brought out into an assembly, and there will be a visitation on her children.<verse eid="SIR 23:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:25"/>Her children will not spread out into a root, and her branches will not bear fruit.<verse eid="SIR 23:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:26"/>She will leave behind her memory for a curse, and her reproach will not be blotted out.<verse eid="SIR 23:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 23:27"/>And those who are left behind will know that nothing is better than fear of the Lord, and nothing is sweeter than to heed commandments of the Lord. PRAISE OF WISDOM<verse eid="SIR 23:27"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 24">
<verse sid="SIR 24:1"/>Wisdom will praise her soul, and in the midst of her people she will boast.<verse eid="SIR 24:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:2"/>In an assembly of the Most High she will open her mouth, and before his power she will boast.<verse eid="SIR 24:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:3"/>"I came forth from the mouth of the Most High, and like a mist I covered earth.<verse eid="SIR 24:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:4"/>I encamped in the heights, and my throne was in a pillar of cloud.<verse eid="SIR 24:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:5"/>A circle of sky I encircled alone, and in the deep of abysses I walked.<verse eid="SIR 24:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:6"/>In the waves of the sea and in all the earth and in every people and nation I led.<verse eid="SIR 24:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:7"/>With all these I sought repose, and in whose inheritance I would settle.<verse eid="SIR 24:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:8"/>"Then the creator of all commanded me, and he who created me put down my tent and said, 'Encamp in Iakob, and in Israel let your inheritance be.'<verse eid="SIR 24:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:9"/>Before the age, from the beginning, he created me, and until the age I will never fail.<verse eid="SIR 24:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:10"/>In a holy tent I ministered before him, and thus in Sion I was firmly set.<verse eid="SIR 24:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:11"/>In a beloved city as well he put me down, and in Ierousalem was my authority.<verse eid="SIR 24:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:12"/>And I took root among a glorified people, in the portion of the Lord is my inheritance.<verse eid="SIR 24:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:13"/>"Like a cedar I was raised up in Lebanon, and like a cypress in the mountains of Aermon.<verse eid="SIR 24:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:14"/>Like a palm I was raised up in Aiggada, and like rosebushes in Iericho, like a good-looking olive tree in a plain, and I was raised up like a plane tree.<verse eid="SIR 24:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:15"/>Like cinnamon and camel's thorn for spices<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">24:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'of spices;' Rahlfs = + 'I gave off a fragrant smell'.</char></note>, and like choice myrrh I gave forth a fragrance, like galbanum and onycha and stacte and like the vapor of frankincense in a tent.<verse eid="SIR 24:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:16"/>I, like a terebinth, spread out my branches, and my branches were branches of glory and grace.<verse eid="SIR 24:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:17"/>I, like a vine, budded forth favor, and my blossoms were the fruit of glory and wealth.<verse eid="SIR 24:17"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 24:18"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">24:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 24:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:19"/>"Come to me, you who desire me, and from my produce be filled.<verse eid="SIR 24:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:20"/>For the memory of me is sweet beyond honey, and the inheritance of me beyond a honeycomb of honey.<verse eid="SIR 24:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:21"/>Those who eat me will hunger for more, and those who drink me will thirst for more.<verse eid="SIR 24:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:22"/>He who obeys me will not be ashamed, and those who work with me will not sin."<verse eid="SIR 24:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:23"/>All these things are the book of the covenant of the Most High God, a law that Moyses commanded us, an inheritance for the gatherings of Iakob.<verse eid="SIR 24:23"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 24:24"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">24:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 24:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:25"/>It fills wisdom like Phison and like Tigris in days of new things<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">24:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'spring'</char></note>.<verse eid="SIR 24:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:26"/>It supplies understanding like Euphrates and like Jordan in days of harvest,<verse eid="SIR 24:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:27"/>It shines forth education like light, like Geon in days of vintage.<verse eid="SIR 24:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:28"/>The first man did not complete knowing her<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">24:28</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'wisdom'</char></note>, and so the last one did not track her out;<verse eid="SIR 24:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:29"/>for her thought was filled from the sea, and her counsel from the great abyss.<verse eid="SIR 24:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:30"/>And I, like a canal from a river and a water channel, issued forth into an orchard.<verse eid="SIR 24:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:31"/>I said, "I will water my garden, and I will drench my flower bed." And look! The canal turned into a river for me, and my river turned into a sea.<verse eid="SIR 24:31"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:32"/>Still I will again make education enlighten like dawn, and I will shine them<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">24:32</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Antecedent unclear</char></note> forth to far off.<verse eid="SIR 24:32"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:33"/>Still I will again pour out teaching like prophecy, and I will leave it behind for generations of eternity.<verse eid="SIR 24:33"/>

<verse sid="SIR 24:34"/>See that I have not toiled for myself alone but for all who seek it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">24:34</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'her'</char></note> out.<verse eid="SIR 24:34"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 25">
<verse sid="SIR 25:1"/>My soul found passion in three things, and these are beautiful before the Lord and human beings: harmony of brothers and friendship of fellows and a wife and husband who accommodate each other.<verse eid="SIR 25:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:2"/>But three kinds my soul hates, and I was offended at their life: an arrogant poor person and a rich liar, an old adulterer lacking in understanding.<verse eid="SIR 25:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:3"/>If in youth you have not gathered, how then in your old age could you find?<verse eid="SIR 25:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:4"/>How beautiful a thing is judgment in gray- haired women, and to discover counsel in elderly men,<verse eid="SIR 25:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:5"/>How beautiful is the wisdom of aged persons and thought and counsel in venerable persons.<verse eid="SIR 25:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:6"/>A garland of aged persons is great experience, and their boast is fear of the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 25:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:7"/>Nine suppositions I deem happy in my<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">25:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> heart. and a tenth I will speak with my<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">25:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> tongue: a person who is glad over children, who lives and looks at the downfall of his enemies.<verse eid="SIR 25:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:8"/>Happy is he who dwells with a sensible wife and who did not slip with the tongue and who did not become a slave to one unworthy of himself.<verse eid="SIR 25:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:9"/>Happy is he who found prudence, and he who recounts to the ears of people who listen.<verse eid="SIR 25:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:10"/>How great is he who finds wisdom, but there is none above him who fears the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 25:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:11"/>Fear of the Lord surpassed everything; he who possesses it-- to whom shall he be compared?<verse eid="SIR 25:11"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 25:12"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">25:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 25:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:13"/>Any wound, and not a wound of the heart, and any wickedness, and not the wickedness of a woman;<verse eid="SIR 25:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:14"/>any attack, and not the attack of those who hate, and any vengeance, and not the vengeance of enemies.<verse eid="SIR 25:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:15"/>There is no head beyond a snake's head, and there is no anger beyond a woman's anger.<verse eid="SIR 25:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:16"/>I shall be content to live with lion and dragon, rather than to live with a wicked woman.<verse eid="SIR 25:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:17"/>A woman's wickedness alters her appearance, and it darkens her face like a bear.<verse eid="SIR 25:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:18"/>Among his neighbors her husband will recline and involuntarily groaned bitter things.<verse eid="SIR 25:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:19"/>Any evil is small touching a woman's evil; may a sinner's lot of befall her.<verse eid="SIR 25:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:20"/>A sandy ascent for the feet of an elderly man, so is a garrulous woman to a quiet husband.<verse eid="SIR 25:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:21"/>Do not fall down upon a woman's beauty, and do not yearn after a woman.<verse eid="SIR 25:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:22"/>Wrath and shamelessness and great disgrace is a wife if she provides for her husband.<verse eid="SIR 25:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:23"/>A dejected heart and a sullen face and a wound of the heart is a wicked wife; slack hands and weakened knees are from a woman who does not make her husband happy.<verse eid="SIR 25:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:24"/>From a woman is the beginning of sin, and because of her we all die.<verse eid="SIR 25:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:25"/>Do not give water an outlet nor freedom of speech to a wicked wife.<verse eid="SIR 25:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 25:26"/>If she does not walk according to your hands<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">25:26</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'according to your hands':  I.e. 'as you direct'</char></note>, cut her off from your flesh<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">25:26</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'cut her off from your flesh':  I.e. 'divorce her'</char></note>.<verse eid="SIR 25:26"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 26">
<verse sid="SIR 26:1"/>Happy is the husband of a good wife, and doubled is the number of his days.<verse eid="SIR 26:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:2"/>A courageous wife gladdens her husband, and he will fulfill his years in peace.<verse eid="SIR 26:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:3"/>A good wife is a good portion; she will be given as a portion to the one who fears the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 26:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:4"/>When rich or poor, a good heart, at every moment a cheerful face!<verse eid="SIR 26:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:5"/>Of three things was my heart wary, and in the face of a fourth I was frightened: a slander by a city, an assembly of a mob and false accusation, all miserable beyond death!<verse eid="SIR 26:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:6"/>Pain of heart and sorrow is a woman who is a rival to a wife, and a lash of a tongue is she who shares with everyone.<verse eid="SIR 26:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:7"/>A chafing ox-yoke is a wicked wife; he who holds her is like him who grasps a scorpion.<verse eid="SIR 26:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:8"/>A great wrath is a drunken wife, and her shameful conduct she will not hide.<verse eid="SIR 26:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:9"/>A wife's fornication is in her eyes' haughty looks, and it will be recognized in her eyelids.<verse eid="SIR 26:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:10"/>Over a wanton daughter keep strict watch, otherwise when she discovers release for herself, she will use it,<verse eid="SIR 26:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:11"/>After an impudent eye watch out, and do not be surprised if she does wrong to you.<verse eid="SIR 26:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:12"/>When a traveler is thirsty, he will open his mouth and will drink from any water that is near; she will sit opposite every stake<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'membrum virile'</char></note> and she will open quiver to arrow.<verse eid="SIR 26:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:13"/>A wife's charm will delight her husband, and her skill will put fat on his bones.<verse eid="SIR 26:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:14"/>A gift from the Lord is a silent wife, and there is no exchange for her disciplined soul.<verse eid="SIR 26:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:15"/>Charm upon charm is a modest wife, and there is no standard weight good enough for a self-controlled soul.<verse eid="SIR 26:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:16"/>When the sun rises in the heights of the Lord-- also a good wife's beauty, an ornament of her home.<verse eid="SIR 26:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:17"/>When a lamp shines forth upon a holy lampstand-- also beauty of face upon stable age.<verse eid="SIR 26:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:18"/>Golden pillars upon a silver base-- also beautiful legs upon well-balanced feet.<verse eid="SIR 26:18"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 26:19"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 26:19"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 26:20"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 26:20"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 26:21"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 26:21"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 26:22"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 26:22"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 26:23"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:23</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 26:23"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 26:24"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 26:24"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 26:25"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 26:25"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 26:26"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:26</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 26:26"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 26:27"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">26:27</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 26:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:28"/>By two things has my heart been grieved, and by a third anger came upon me: a warrior wanting on account of indigence and intelligent men when they are treated contemptuously: a person brought from righteousness to sin, the Lord will prepare him for the sword.<verse eid="SIR 26:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 26:29"/>A merchant will scarcely be delivered from wrongdoing, and a retailer will not be innocent of sin.<verse eid="SIR 26:29"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 27">
<verse sid="SIR 27:1"/>Many have sinned on account of cash, and he who seeks to increase will avert an eye.<verse eid="SIR 27:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:2"/>Between joints of stones a peg will be driven, and between selling and buying sin will be wedged.<verse eid="SIR 27:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:3"/>If one does not hold fast in fear of the Lord, quickly, with speed, his house will be overthrown.<verse eid="SIR 27:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:4"/>With a shaking of a sieve, refuse remains-- so a person's offal in his reasoning.<verse eid="SIR 27:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:5"/>A kiln tests a potter's vessels, and a person's test is in his deliberation.<verse eid="SIR 27:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:6"/>Its fruit brings to light a tree's cultivation-- so reasoning notions of a person's heart.<verse eid="SIR 27:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:7"/>Before reasoning do not commend a man, for this is the test of people.<verse eid="SIR 27:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:8"/>If you pursue what is just, you will take hold and wear it like a full-length robe of glory.<verse eid="SIR 27:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:9"/>Birds will nest with those like them, and truth will come back to those who practice it.<verse eid="SIR 27:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:10"/>A lion lies in wait for prey, so sin for people who practice injustices.<verse eid="SIR 27:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:11"/>The narrative of a pious person is always wisdom, but the fool changes like the moon.<verse eid="SIR 27:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:12"/>In the midst of unintelligent persons watch closely for occasion, but in the midst of thoughtful persons keep going.<verse eid="SIR 27:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:13"/>The narrative of foolish persons is an offense, and their laughter is in wantonness of sin.<verse eid="SIR 27:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:14"/>Talk with much swearing will make the hair stand on end, and their strife is a stopping up of ears.<verse eid="SIR 27:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:15"/>A shedding of blood is the strife of the arrogant, and their railing is miserable to hear.<verse eid="SIR 27:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:16"/>He who reveals secrets has destroyed trust and will never find a friend for his soul.<verse eid="SIR 27:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:17"/>Show a friend affection, and keep faith with him, but if you reveal his secrets, do not follow after him.<verse eid="SIR 27:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:18"/>For just as a person <note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">27:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek uncertain</char></note>destroyed his corpse<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">27:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note>, so you destroyed your fellow's friendship.<verse eid="SIR 27:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:19"/>And as you let a bird go free from your hand, so you let go of your fellow, and you will not catch him.<verse eid="SIR 27:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:20"/>Do not pursue him, because he has withdrawn far off, and he has escaped like a gazelle from a trap.<verse eid="SIR 27:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:21"/>Because it is possible to bind up a wound, there is also reconciliation for abuse, but he who revealed secrets was without hope.<verse eid="SIR 27:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:22"/>One who winks an eye devises evil things, and he who knows him will turn away from him.<verse eid="SIR 27:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:23"/>Before your eyes his mouth will be sweet, and at your words he will be amazed, but later he will distort his mouth, and with your words he will give offense.<verse eid="SIR 27:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:24"/>I hated many things, and I did not become like him, and the Lord will hate him.<verse eid="SIR 27:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:25"/>He who throws a stone high up throws on his head, and a treacherous blow will open up wounds.<verse eid="SIR 27:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:26"/>He who digs a hole will fall into it, and he who sets a trap will get caught in it.<verse eid="SIR 27:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:27"/>He who does wickedness-- it will be rolled onto him, and he will never recognize whence it has come to him.<verse eid="SIR 27:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:28"/>Mocking and reproach belong to an arrogant person, and vengeance, like a lion, will lie in wait for him.<verse eid="SIR 27:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:29"/>Those who are glad at the fall of pious persons will get caught in a snare, and sorrow will consume them before their death.<verse eid="SIR 27:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 27:30"/>Ire and anger, these also are abominations, and a sinful man will have possession of them.<verse eid="SIR 27:30"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 28">
<verse sid="SIR 28:1"/>He who avenges will discover vengeance from the Lord, and when he observes carefully, he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the Lord'</char></note> will carefully observe his sins.<verse eid="SIR 28:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:2"/>Forgive your neighbor a wrong, and then, when you petition, your sins will be pardoned.<verse eid="SIR 28:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:3"/>A person harbors wrath against a person-- and will he seek healing from the Lord?<verse eid="SIR 28:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:4"/>Does he not have mercy on a person like himself and petition concerning his sins?<verse eid="SIR 28:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:5"/>His being flesh maintains ire-- who will make atonement for his sins?<verse eid="SIR 28:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:6"/>Remember the end things, and cease to be at enmity; remember<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> corruption and death, and cleave to the commandments.<verse eid="SIR 28:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:7"/>Remember commandments, and do not be irate with your fellow, and remember<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> the covenant of the Most High, and overlook a mistake<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'sin of ignorance'</char></note>.<verse eid="SIR 28:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:8"/>Refrain from strife, and you will reduce sins, for a hot-tempered person will kindle strife<verse eid="SIR 28:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:9"/>and a sinful man will disturb friends, and among people at peace he will cast slander.<verse eid="SIR 28:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:10"/>In proportion to a fire's wood, so will it burn, and in proportion to the obstinacy of strife, it will increase; in proportion to a person's strength, will his anger be, and in proportion to his wealth, he will raise up his wrath.<verse eid="SIR 28:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:11"/>A quarrel being hastened kindles a fire, and strife in a hurry sheds blood.<verse eid="SIR 28:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:12"/>If you blow on a spark, it will flame up, and if you spit on it, it will be extinguished, and both will proceed out of your mouth.<verse eid="SIR 28:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:13"/>Curse a slanderous and double-tongued person, for he has destroyed many who are at peace.<verse eid="SIR 28:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:14"/><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'talk of a third party'</char></note> A third tongue<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'talk of a third party'</char></note> has shaken many and separated them from nation to nation and demolished strong cities and overturned the houses of nobles.<verse eid="SIR 28:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:15"/><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'talk of a third party'</char></note>A third tongue has cast out courageous women and deprived them of their labors.<verse eid="SIR 28:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:16"/>He who pays heed to it will never find rest, nor will he encamp with quiet.<verse eid="SIR 28:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:17"/>A whip's blow produces a welt, but a tongue's blow will break bones.<verse eid="SIR 28:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:18"/>Many have fallen by a dagger's edge, but not like those who have fallen because of a tongue.<verse eid="SIR 28:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:19"/>Happy is the one protected from it, who has not endured in its anger, who has not dragged its yoke and with its fetters has not been bound.<verse eid="SIR 28:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:20"/>For its yoke is a yoke of iron, and its fetters are fetters of bronze.<verse eid="SIR 28:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:21"/>A wicked death is its death, and Hades is more advantageous than it.<verse eid="SIR 28:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:22"/>It will never prevail over pious persons, and in its flame they will not be burned.<verse eid="SIR 28:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:23"/>Those who forsake the Lord will fall into it, and in them it will burn, and it will never be extinguished; it will be sent after them like a lion, and like a leopard it will injure them.<verse eid="SIR 28:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:24"/>See! Fence your property with thorns, (25b) and make for your mouth a door and a bolt.<verse eid="SIR 28:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:25"/>(24b) Lock up your silver and gold, (24b) and make for your words a balance and a weight.<verse eid="SIR 28:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 28:26"/>Take heed lest you slip by it; do not fall before one who lies in wait.<verse eid="SIR 28:26"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 29">
<verse sid="SIR 29:1"/>He who does mercy will lend to his fellow, and he who prevails with his hand keeps the commandments.<verse eid="SIR 29:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:2"/>Lend to your fellow in his time of need, and again pay back your fellow at the proper time.<verse eid="SIR 29:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:3"/>Firmly establish a word, and be trustworthy with him, and on every occasion you will find what you need.<verse eid="SIR 29:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:4"/>Many regarded a loan as a windfall, and they caused trouble for those who helped them.<verse eid="SIR 29:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:5"/>Until he receives it, he will kiss his hands, and about his fellow's money he lowers his<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">29:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> voice, and at the moment for repayment he will delay for time and will pay back words of apathy, and he will blame the time.<verse eid="SIR 29:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:6"/>If he is capable, he will recover scarcely half, and he will consider that as a windfall; but if not, he has defrauded him of his money, and he has needlessly made him an enemy; curses and insults he will repay him, and instead of glory he will repay him dishonor.<verse eid="SIR 29:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:7"/>Many turned away not because of wickedness; they were wary of being defrauded needlessly.<verse eid="SIR 29:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:8"/>Nevertheless, with a lowly person be patient, and do not make him wait for charity.<verse eid="SIR 29:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:9"/>On account of the commandment, assist a needy person, and according to his need do not turn him away empty.<verse eid="SIR 29:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:10"/>Lose silver for the sake of a brother and a friend, and do not let it corrode under the stone unto destruction.<verse eid="SIR 29:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:11"/>Dispose of your treasure according to the commandments of the Most High, and it will profit you more than gold.<verse eid="SIR 29:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:12"/>Store up charity in your treasuries, and it will deliver you from every affliction.<verse eid="SIR 29:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:13"/>More than a shield of might and more than a spear of weight, it will fight against your enemy on your behalf.<verse eid="SIR 29:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:14"/>A good man will give surety for his fellow, and he who lost shame will abandon him.<verse eid="SIR 29:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:15"/>A guarantor's kindness do not forget, for he gave his soul on your behalf.<verse eid="SIR 29:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:16"/>A guarantor's goods a sinner will ruin,<verse eid="SIR 29:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:17"/>and an ungrateful person will intentionally abandon one who rescues.<verse eid="SIR 29:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:18"/>Surety destroyed many who were prosperous and tossed them about like a wave of the sea; powerful men it exiled, and they wandered among foreign nations.<verse eid="SIR 29:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:19"/>A sinner will fall into surety, and as he pursues profit-taking, he will fall into lawsuits.<verse eid="SIR 29:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:20"/>Assist your fellow according to your ability, and take care for yourself that you do not fall.<verse eid="SIR 29:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:21"/>Life's beginning is water and bread and clothing and a house for hiding indecency.<verse eid="SIR 29:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:22"/>Better is the life of a poor person under a shelter of rafters than splendid foods among strangers.<verse eid="SIR 29:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:23"/>With little or much have contentment, and you will never hear reproach for being a sojourner.<verse eid="SIR 29:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:24"/>It is a miserable life going<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">29:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> from house to house, and where you will be a sojourner, you shall not open your mouth.<verse eid="SIR 29:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:25"/>You will entertain and provide drink for no thanks, and besides, you will hear bitter words such as these,<verse eid="SIR 29:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:26"/>"Come here, sojourner; prepare a table, and if there is something in your hand, feed me."<verse eid="SIR 29:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:27"/>"Go away, sojourner, because of good repute; my brother came to me for a visit; I need the house."<verse eid="SIR 29:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 29:28"/>These are hard things for a person with pride, criticism about being a sojourner and reproach from a money-lender. CONCERNING CHILDREN<verse eid="SIR 29:28"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 30">
<verse sid="SIR 30:1"/>He who loves his son will persist in whipping him so that he may be glad at his outcome.<verse eid="SIR 30:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:2"/>He who instructs his son will profit by him, and among acquaintances he will boast about him.<verse eid="SIR 30:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:3"/>He who teaches his son will make his enemy envious, and before friends he will exult in him.<verse eid="SIR 30:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:4"/>His father passed away and is as though he did not die, for he left behind him a person like himself.<verse eid="SIR 30:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:5"/>In his life he saw and was glad, and at his end he was not grieved.<verse eid="SIR 30:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:6"/>Against enemies he has left behind an avenger and one who repays a kindness to friends.<verse eid="SIR 30:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:7"/>When one cherishes a son, one will bind up his wounds, and with every cry one's insides will be troubled.<verse eid="SIR 30:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:8"/>An unbroken horse turns out stubborn, and a son when given free reign turns out rash.<verse eid="SIR 30:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:9"/>Coddle a child, and it will terrorize you; play with him, and he will grieve you.<verse eid="SIR 30:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:10"/>Do not laugh together with him, lest you suffer together, and in the end you will gnash your teeth.<verse eid="SIR 30:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:11"/>Do not give him license in his youth,<verse eid="SIR 30:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:12"/>Bruise his sides while he is an infant, lest, when he becomes stubborn, he will disobey you,<verse eid="SIR 30:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:13"/>Instruct your son, and work with him, lest by his disgraceful behavior you become offended.<verse eid="SIR 30:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:14"/>Better a poor person healthy and strong in constitution than a rich person scourged in his body.<verse eid="SIR 30:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:15"/>Health and vigor are better than any gold, and a robust spirit than boundless worldly weal. CONCERNING FOODS<verse eid="SIR 30:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:16"/>There is no wealth better than health of body, and there is no gladness beyond joy of heart.<verse eid="SIR 30:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:17"/>Better death than a bitter life, and eternal repose than chronic sickness.<verse eid="SIR 30:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:18"/>Good things poured out on a mouth that is shut are offerings of food set on a grave.<verse eid="SIR 30:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:19"/>Of what use is a fruit offering to an idol? For it will neither eat nor smell. (20) So is he who is banished by the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 30:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:20"/>(21) Whoever sees with the eyes and groans is like a eunuch who embraces a maiden and groans.<verse eid="SIR 30:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:21"/>(22) Do not give your soul to grief, and do not afflict yourself by your design.<verse eid="SIR 30:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:22"/>(23) Gladness of heart is life for a person, and exultation is a man's length of days.<verse eid="SIR 30:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:23"/>(24) Deceive your soul, and comfort your heart, and remove grief far from you. (25) For many has grief destroyed, and there is no advantage in it.<verse eid="SIR 30:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:24"/>(26) Jealousy and anger lessen days, and before the proper time anxiety brings old age.<verse eid="SIR 30:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 30:25"/>(27; 33.13b) A cheerful and good heart at meats will take care of its food.<verse eid="SIR 30:25"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 31">
<verse sid="SIR 31:1"/>(34).1 Wakefulness over wealth wastes away flesh, and anxiety about it removes sleep.<verse eid="SIR 31:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:2"/>Anxiety over wakefulness will remove sleepiness, and a severe illness will carry off sleep.<verse eid="SIR 31:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:3"/>A rich person toiled at the accumulation of money, and in rest he fills himself with his delicacies.<verse eid="SIR 31:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:4"/>A poor person toiled for a diminution of life, and in rest he becomes needy.<verse eid="SIR 31:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:5"/>He who loves gold will not be justified, and he who pursues profits will be led astray by them.<verse eid="SIR 31:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:6"/>Many were given over to ruin because of gold, and their destruction has happened in front of them.<verse eid="SIR 31:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:7"/>It is a block for stumbling for those who are possessed by it, and every fool will be taken captive by it.<verse eid="SIR 31:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:8"/>Happy is a rich person who was found blameless and who did not go after gold.<verse eid="SIR 31:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:9"/>Who is he and shall we call him happy? For he did wonders among his people.<verse eid="SIR 31:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:10"/>Who has been tested by it and been made perfect? And it will be as a boast for him. Who was able to transgress and did not transgress, and to do evil and did not do so?<verse eid="SIR 31:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:11"/>Therefore his good things will be confirmed, and his acts of charity an assembly will recount.<verse eid="SIR 31:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:12"/>Were you seated at a great table? Do not open your throat at it. (13) And do not say, "Indeed how many are the things on it!"<verse eid="SIR 31:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:13"/>(14) Remember that a wicked eye is an evil thing. (15) What was created more wicked than an eye? Therefore it sends tears from a whole face.<verse eid="SIR 31:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:14"/>(16) Do not extend a hand for whatever you see, (17) and do not crowd for it at a bowl.<verse eid="SIR 31:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:15"/>(18) Consider the things of your fellow from yourself<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">31:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'from yourself':  I.e. 'put yourself in his place'</char></note>, and about every matter be thoughtful.<verse eid="SIR 31:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:16"/>(19) Eat like a human being the things set before you, and do not chomp, lest you be hated.<verse eid="SIR 31:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:17"/>(20) Be the first to stop, due to your training, and do not be gluttonous, lest you give offense.<verse eid="SIR 31:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:18"/>(21) And if you sat among rather many, do not extend your hand before they do.<verse eid="SIR 31:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:19"/>(22) For the person of education the little is as enough, and upon his bed he does not gasp for breath.<verse eid="SIR 31:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:20"/>(24) A sleep of health due to a moderate bowel! He rose early and his soul with him. (23) The pain of sleeplessness and of nausea and colic are with the gluttonous man.<verse eid="SIR 31:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:21"/>(25) And if you were overpowered by foods, get up, and vomit a distance away, and you will have rest.<verse eid="SIR 31:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:22"/>(26) Listen, child, and do not scorn me, and in the end you will acquire my words; (27) in all of your works be skillful, and no illness will ever come upon you.<verse eid="SIR 31:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:23"/>(28) Lips will bless a person munificent with respect to bread, and trustworthy is the testimony to his fine quality.<verse eid="SIR 31:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:24"/>(29) The city will murmur about a wicked one for bread, and accurate is the testimony to his wickedness.<verse eid="SIR 31:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:25"/>(30) With wine do not be macho, for wine has destroyed many.<verse eid="SIR 31:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:26"/>(31) A furnace tests steel by dipping; thus wine tests<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">31:26</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> hearts in strife of the proud.<verse eid="SIR 31:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:27"/>(32) Equal to life is wine for human beings, if you drink it in its measure<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">31:27</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'its measure':  I.e. 'moderation'</char></note>. (33) What is life to one who lacks wine? (35) And it was created from the beginning for gladness.<verse eid="SIR 31:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:28"/>(36) Joy of heart and gladness of soul is sufficient wine drunk at the proper time.<verse eid="SIR 31:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:29"/>(39) Bitterness of soul is much wine drunk amid provocation and stumbling.<verse eid="SIR 31:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:30"/>(40) Drunkenness increases a fool's temper for hurt, since it reduces strength and adds wounds.<verse eid="SIR 31:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 31:31"/>(41) At a banquet of wine do not reprove your fellow, and do not scorn him in his gladness; (42) do not speak to him a word of reproach, and do not distress him with demanding repayment.<verse eid="SIR 31:31"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 32">
<verse sid="SIR 32:1"/>(35).1 They appointed you leader; do not exalt yourself; be among them as one of them; (2) take thought for them, and then sit down.<verse eid="SIR 32:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:2"/>And when you have performed all your service, recline (3) so that you may be merry on account of them, and due to your good conduct you might receive a garland.<verse eid="SIR 32:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:3"/>(4) Speak, O elderly person, for it is fitting for you, (5) with accurate knowledge, and do not interrupt the music.<verse eid="SIR 32:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:4"/>(6) Where there is entertainment, do not pour out talk, and do not be smart at an inopportune moment.<verse eid="SIR 32:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:5"/>(7) A ruby seal on a gold ornament is a concert of music at a banquet of wine.<verse eid="SIR 32:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:6"/>(8) An emerald seal in a gold setting is a melody of music with sweet wine.<verse eid="SIR 32:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:7"/>(10) Speak, O young person, if you have need, (11) only twice if you were asked;<verse eid="SIR 32:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:8"/>(12) Summarize your speech; in a few things there are many; be as one who knows and at the same time one who is silent.<verse eid="SIR 32:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:9"/>(13) In the midst of nobles do not exercise authority, and where there are old men, do not prate about many things.<verse eid="SIR 32:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:10"/>(14) Before thunder lightning hastens, and goodwill will go before a modest person.<verse eid="SIR 32:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:11"/>(15) Awaken in time, and do not bring up the rear; depart for home, and do not be idle.<verse eid="SIR 32:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:12"/>(16) There play, and do the things you desire, and do not sin by arrogant speech.<verse eid="SIR 32:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:13"/>(17) And in addition, bless the one who made you and intoxicates you with his good things.<verse eid="SIR 32:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:14"/>(18) He who fears the Lord will accept instruction, and those who rise early will find approval.<verse eid="SIR 32:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:15"/>(19) He who seeks the law will be filled with it, and he who is hypocritical will stumble on it.<verse eid="SIR 32:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:16"/>(20) Those who fear the Lord will get a verdict, and they will kindle right acts like a light.<verse eid="SIR 32:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:17"/>(21) A sinful person will turn away reproof, and according to his will, he will find a judgment.<verse eid="SIR 32:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:18"/>(22) A man of deliberation will never overlook a thought; the stranger and the arrogant will not cower from fear.<verse eid="SIR 32:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:19"/>(24) Do nothing without deliberation, and do not feel regret when you have acted.<verse eid="SIR 32:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:20"/>(25) On a path of stumbling do not go, and do not stumble on rocky ground.<verse eid="SIR 32:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:21"/>Do not trust an unexplored road,<verse eid="SIR 32:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:22"/>(26) and guard against your children.<verse eid="SIR 32:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:23"/>(27) In every deed trust your soul, for this as well is a means of keeping the commandments.<verse eid="SIR 32:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 32:24"/>(28) He who has faith in the law attends to the commandments, and he who trusts in the Lord will not suffer loss.<verse eid="SIR 32:24"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 33">
<verse sid="SIR 33:1"/>(36).1 No evil will befall him who fears the Lord, but in a test he will also be delivered in turn.<verse eid="SIR 33:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:2"/>A wise man will not hate the law, but he who is hypocritical with it is like a boat in a storm.<verse eid="SIR 33:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:3"/>An intelligent person will trust in a word, and the law for him is as trustworthy (4) as an inquiry of the clear ones.<verse eid="SIR 33:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:4"/>Prepare a speech, and so you will be heard; consolidate instruction, and reply.<verse eid="SIR 33:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:5"/>The emotions of a foolish person are like a wheel of a wagon, and his argument is like a turning axle.<verse eid="SIR 33:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:6"/>A horse for breeding<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">33:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'horse for breeding':  I.e. 'stallion'</char></note> is like a mocking friend; underneath anyone who sits on him, he whinnies.<verse eid="SIR 33:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:7"/>Why is a day superior to a day, when all the light of a day of a year is from the sun?<verse eid="SIR 33:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:8"/>By the Lord's knowledge they were marked off, and he made seasons and feasts different.<verse eid="SIR 33:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:9"/>(10) Some of them he exalted and hallowed, and some of them he established for a number of days.<verse eid="SIR 33:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:10"/>And all human beings are from the ground, and out of earth Adam was created.<verse eid="SIR 33:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:11"/>In fullness of knowledge the Lord marked them off and made their ways different.<verse eid="SIR 33:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:12"/>Some of them he blessed and exalted, and some of them he hallowed and brought near to himself; some of them he cursed and brought low and turned them out of their position.<verse eid="SIR 33:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:13"/>Like a potter's clay in his hand, (14) to fashion it according to his liking, so are human beings in the hand of him who made them, to repay them according to his judgment.<verse eid="SIR 33:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:14"/>(15) Good is opposite evil, and life is opposite death; so a sinner is opposite a pious person.<verse eid="SIR 33:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:15"/>And so look at all of the works of the Most High, two by two, one opposite the other one.<verse eid="SIR 33:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:16"/>As a last one, it was I who kept vigil, (30.25) as one who gleaned after the grape- pickers.<verse eid="SIR 33:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:17"/>(25) By the blessing of the Lord I arrived first, and like one who picks grapes I filled a wine vat.<verse eid="SIR 33:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:18"/>(26) Consider that I have not labored for myself alone but for all those who seek instruction.<verse eid="SIR 33:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:19"/>(27) Listen to me, nobles of the people, and leaders of the assembly, give ear.<verse eid="SIR 33:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:20"/>(28) To son and wife, to brother and friend do not give authority over you in your lifetime, and do not give your property to another, lest you change your mind and ask for it.<verse eid="SIR 33:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:21"/>(29) While you are still alive and there is breath in you, do not exchange yourself with any flesh.<verse eid="SIR 33:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:22"/>(30) For it is better that your children ask of you than that you should look to the hands of your sons.<verse eid="SIR 33:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:23"/>(31) In all your works be one who excels; do not bring a stain on your reputation.<verse eid="SIR 33:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:24"/>(32) In the day of the completion of the days of your life and at the moment of death, distribute an inheritance.<verse eid="SIR 33:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:25"/>(33) Fodder and a rod and burdens for a donkey; bread and instruction and work for a domestic.<verse eid="SIR 33:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:26"/>(34) Work with instruction, and you will find rest; let loose his hands, and he will seek freedom.<verse eid="SIR 33:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:27"/>(35) A yoke and a thong will bow a neck, and for a wicked domestic there are racks and tortures.<verse eid="SIR 33:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:28"/>(36) Put him to work so that he might not be unoccupied,<verse eid="SIR 33:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:29"/>(37) for lack of work has taught much evil.<verse eid="SIR 33:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:30"/>(38) Set him to work as is fitting for him, and if he does not obey, make his fetters heavy. And do not be excessive over any flesh, and without judgment do not do anything.<verse eid="SIR 33:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:31"/>(39) If you have a domestic, let him be like you, because with blood you acquired him; if you have a domestic, treat him like a brother, because you will need him like your own soul.<verse eid="SIR 33:31"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:32"/>(40) If you do him evil and he departs and runs away,<verse eid="SIR 33:32"/>

<verse sid="SIR 33:33"/>on which road will you seek him?<verse eid="SIR 33:33"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 34">
<verse sid="SIR 34:1"/>(31).1 A senseless man has empty and false hopes, and dreams excite fools.<verse eid="SIR 34:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:2"/>Like one who grasps a shadow and pursues wind, so is he who pays heed to dreams.<verse eid="SIR 34:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:3"/>An appearance in dreams is this against that<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">34:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'this against that':  Possibly 'a reflection'</char></note>, a likeness of a face opposite a face.<verse eid="SIR 34:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:4"/>Of an unclean thing what will become clean? And of a false thing what will be true?<verse eid="SIR 34:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:5"/>Divinations and omens and dreams are vain, and as of a woman in labor the heart fantasizes.<verse eid="SIR 34:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:6"/>Unless it has been sent from the Most High by a visitation, do not give your heart to them.<verse eid="SIR 34:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:7"/>For dreams have deceived many, and persons who hope in them have fallen.<verse eid="SIR 34:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:8"/>Without falsehood the law will be accomplished, and wisdom in a trustworthy mouth is completeness.<verse eid="SIR 34:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:9"/>Since a man roamed, he knew many things, and he who is experienced will tell with understanding.<verse eid="SIR 34:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:10"/>He who had no experience knows few things,<verse eid="SIR 34:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:11"/>but he who has roamed will increase cleverness.<verse eid="SIR 34:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:12"/>I have seen many things in my wandering, and more than my words is my understanding.<verse eid="SIR 34:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:13"/>Frequently I was in danger of death, and I was saved because of these things.<verse eid="SIR 34:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:14"/>The spirit of people who fear the Lord will live,<verse eid="SIR 34:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:15"/>for their hope is in the one who saves them.<verse eid="SIR 34:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:16"/>He who fears the Lord will be timid in nothing, and he will never be cowardly, because he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">34:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. God</char></note> is his hope.<verse eid="SIR 34:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:17"/>Happy is the soul of one who fears the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 34:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:18"/>Upon whom is he intent? And who is his support?<verse eid="SIR 34:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:19"/>The eyes of the Lord are upon those who love him, a shield of dominance and a support of strength, a shelter from the burning heat and shade from midday, a guard against stumbling and a help against falling,<verse eid="SIR 34:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:20"/>one who uplifts the soul and enlightens eyes, gives healing of life and blessing.<verse eid="SIR 34:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:21"/>When one sacrifices from someone unjust, it is a blameworthy offering,<verse eid="SIR 34:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:22"/>and the gifts of lawless persons are not for approval.<verse eid="SIR 34:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:23"/>The Most High is not pleased with the offerings of impious persons, nor by a multitude of sacrifices does he forgive sins.<verse eid="SIR 34:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:24"/>One who slaughters a son in front of his father is he who brings a sacrifice from the property of the needy.<verse eid="SIR 34:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:25"/>Bread is life for the poor when they are destitute; he who withholds it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">34:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'life'</char></note> is a person of blood.<verse eid="SIR 34:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:26"/>One who murders his fellow is he who takes away a way of living,<verse eid="SIR 34:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:27"/>and one who pours out blood is he who deprives the wages of a hired worker.<verse eid="SIR 34:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:28"/>One builds, and one tears down-- what did they gain more than hard labors?<verse eid="SIR 34:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:29"/>One prays, and one curses-- to whose voice will the master listen?<verse eid="SIR 34:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:30"/>When one bathes due to a corpse and when one touches it again-- what did he gain by his washing?<verse eid="SIR 34:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 34:31"/>So is a person when he fasts for his sins and goes again and does the same things; who will listen to his prayer, and what did he gain by humbling himself?<verse eid="SIR 34:31"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 35">
<verse sid="SIR 35:1"/>(32).1 He who keeps the Law multiplies offerings.<verse eid="SIR 35:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:2"/>One who makes a sacrifice for deliverance is he who pays heed to the commandments.<verse eid="SIR 35:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:3"/>One who repays a kindness is one who offers the finest flour,<verse eid="SIR 35:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:4"/>and he who does an act of charity is one who makes a sacrifice of praise.<verse eid="SIR 35:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:5"/>A good pleasure to the Lord it is to withdraw from wickedness, and it is atonement to withdraw from injustice.<verse eid="SIR 35:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:6"/>Do not be seen empty in the presence of the Lord,<verse eid="SIR 35:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:7"/>for all these things are for the sake of a commandment.<verse eid="SIR 35:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:8"/>An offering of a righteous person enriches the altar, and its pleasing odor is before the Most High.<verse eid="SIR 35:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:9"/>A righteous man's sacrifice is acceptable, and its memorial will not be forgotten.<verse eid="SIR 35:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:10"/>With a good eye<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">35:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'a good eye':  I.e. 'generosity'</char></note> glorify the Lord, and do not belittle the first fruit of your hands.<verse eid="SIR 35:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:11"/>With every act of giving brighten your face, and with gladness consecrate a tithe.<verse eid="SIR 35:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:12"/>Give to the Most High according to his giving and with a good eye<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">35:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'a good eye':  I.e. 'generosity'</char></note> according to that found at hand,<verse eid="SIR 35:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:13"/>because the Lord is the one who repays, and he will repay you sevenfold.<verse eid="SIR 35:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:14"/>Do not offer a bribe, for he will not accept it,<verse eid="SIR 35:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:15"/>and do not be intent on an unrighteous sacrifice, because the Lord is judge, and with him there is no reputation of person<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">35:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'face'</char></note>.<verse eid="SIR 35:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:16"/>He will not receive a person<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">35:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'generosity'</char></note> against a poor person<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">35:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'receive a person against a poor person': I.e. 'favor anyone over the poor'</char></note>, and he will listen to the petition of one who is wronged.<verse eid="SIR 35:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:17"/>He will never ignore an orphan's supplication, nor a widow, if she pours out speech.<verse eid="SIR 35:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:18"/>Do not a widow's tears run down upon her cheek,<verse eid="SIR 35:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:19"/>and is not her cry against the one who drew them down?<verse eid="SIR 35:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:20"/>One who serves with goodwill will be accepted, and his petition will reach to the clouds.<verse eid="SIR 35:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:21"/>A humble person's prayer passed through the clouds, and until it draws near, it will never relent, and it will never desist until the Most High takes notice.<verse eid="SIR 35:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:22"/>And he will adjudicate for righteous persons and will execute judgment. And the Lord will never be slow, nor will he ever be patient regarding them until he crushes the loins of unmerciful persons<verse eid="SIR 35:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:23"/>and will repay vengeance upon the nations, until he removes the multitude of insolent persons and will shatter the scepters of unrighteous persons,<verse eid="SIR 35:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:24"/>until he repays a person according to his deeds and the works of human beings according to their notions,<verse eid="SIR 35:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:25"/>until he judges the case of his people and will gladden them with his mercy.<verse eid="SIR 35:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 35:26"/>Timely is his mercy in a time of distress, as are clouds of rain in a time of drought.<verse eid="SIR 35:26"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 36">
<verse sid="SIR 36:1"/>(33).1 Have mercy on us, O Master, the god of all,<verse eid="SIR 36:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:2"/>and cast the fear of you upon all the nations.<verse eid="SIR 36:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:3"/>Lift up your hand against foreign nations, and let them see your dominance.<verse eid="SIR 36:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:4"/>Just as in their presence you have been made holy in us, so in our presence may you be magnified in them.<verse eid="SIR 36:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:5"/>And let them know you, just as also we have known that there is no god except you, O Lord.<verse eid="SIR 36:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:6"/>Renew signs, and change wonders;<verse eid="SIR 36:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:7"/>glorify hand and right arm.<verse eid="SIR 36:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:8"/>Raise up anger, and pour out wrath;<verse eid="SIR 36:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:9"/>destroy an adversary, and crush an enemy.<verse eid="SIR 36:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:10"/>Hasten the time, and remember your determination, and let them recount your mighty acts.<verse eid="SIR 36:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:11"/>In wrath of fire let him who survives be consumed, and may those who harm your people find destruction.<verse eid="SIR 36:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:12"/>Crush the heads of hostile rulers who say, "There is no one except us!"<verse eid="SIR 36:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:13"/>(33.13) Gather all the tribes of Iakob,<verse eid="SIR 36:13"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 36:14"/>&amp;#x2013;<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">36:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 36:14"/>

<verse _X_reasonEmpty="verseEmptyInThisTranslation" sid="SIR 36:15"/><char style="no">&amp;#x2013;</char><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">36:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">This verse is empty in this translation.</char></note><verse eid="SIR 36:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:16"/>(36.16) and give them an inheritance, as from the beginning.<verse eid="SIR 36:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:17"/>Have mercy on a people, O Lord, who have been called by your name, and on Israel, whom you likened to a first born.<verse eid="SIR 36:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:18"/>Have pity on the city of your holy precinct, Ierousalem the place of your rest.<verse eid="SIR 36:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:19"/>Fill Sion with a celebration of your mighty acts, and your shrine with your glory.<verse eid="SIR 36:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:20"/>Give testimony to your creations in the beginning, and raise up prophecies that were in your name.<verse eid="SIR 36:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:21"/>Give a reward to those who wait for you, and let your prophets be found trustworthy.<verse eid="SIR 36:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:22"/>Hear, O Lord, a petition of your domestics according to your good will concerning your people, and all who are upon the earth will know that you are the Lord, the God of the ages.<verse eid="SIR 36:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:23"/>Any food will the stomach eat, but there exists food finer than food.<verse eid="SIR 36:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:24"/>The throat makes proof of foods from a hunt; so an intelligent heart of false words.<verse eid="SIR 36:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:25"/>A perverse heart will give grief, but an experienced person will pay him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">36:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'it'; antecedent unclear</char></note> back.<verse eid="SIR 36:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:26"/>A woman will accept any male, but there exists a daughter better than a daughter.<verse eid="SIR 36:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:27"/>A woman's beauty brightens a face, and it surpasses a person's every desire.<verse eid="SIR 36:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:28"/>If mercy and gentleness are upon her tongue, her husband is not like the sons of human beings.<verse eid="SIR 36:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:29"/>He who acquires a wife makes a beginning of a possession, a helper corresponding to him and a pillar of rest.<verse eid="SIR 36:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:30"/>Where there is no fence, property will be plundered, and where there is no wife, he will groan as he wanders.<verse eid="SIR 36:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 36:31"/>For who will trust an unencumbered robber as he bounds from city to city?-- likewise a person who does not have a nest and who lodges wherever night falls.<verse eid="SIR 36:31"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 37">
<verse sid="SIR 37:1"/>Every friend will say, "I, too, have been a friend," but there is a friend who is a friend in name only.<verse eid="SIR 37:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:2"/>Will not grief approach unto death, when companion and friend turns into an enemy?<verse eid="SIR 37:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:3"/>O evil notion, how were you involved, to cover the dry land with deceit?<verse eid="SIR 37:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:4"/>A friend's companion delights in gladness, and in a time of distress he will be opposite.<verse eid="SIR 37:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:5"/>A companion suffers together with a friend for his stomach's sake, and in the face of battle he will take up a shield.<verse eid="SIR 37:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:6"/>Do not forget a friend in your soul, and do not be unmindful of him in your money.<verse eid="SIR 37:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:7"/>Every counselor exalts advice, but there is one who counsels for himself.<verse eid="SIR 37:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:8"/>Against a counselor guard your soul, and know beforehand what is his need, for he, too, will give advice for himself-- lest he cast a lot against you<verse eid="SIR 37:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:9"/>and say to you, "Your way is fair," and he will stand aside to see what will happen to you.<verse eid="SIR 37:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:10"/>Do not consult with him who views you with suspicion, and from those who are envious of you hide deliberation:<verse eid="SIR 37:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:11"/>with a woman about her rival and with a cowardly person about war, with a merchant about business and with one who buys about a sale, with a slanderer about gratitude and with an unmerciful person about generosity of heart, with an idle person about any work and with an annual laborer about finishing, with an idle domestic about a large task. Do not pay heed to these for any advice.<verse eid="SIR 37:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:12"/>But rather persevere with a pious man whom you know to be one who keeps commandments, who in his soul is like your soul, and if you stumble, he will suffer with you.<verse eid="SIR 37:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:13"/>And stand by your heart's counsel, for there is nothing more faithful to you than it.<verse eid="SIR 37:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:14"/>For a man's soul is accustomed to inform at times more than seven sentinels sitting high up on a look-out.<verse eid="SIR 37:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:15"/>And above all these, beseech the Most High so that he may make straight your way in truth.<verse eid="SIR 37:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:16"/>The beginning of every deed is discourse, and before every action is counsel.<verse eid="SIR 37:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:17"/>The track of change is the heart.<verse eid="SIR 37:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:18"/>Four destinies appear, good and evil, life and death, and that which continually is lord over them is the tongue.<verse eid="SIR 37:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:19"/>There exists a clever man who is an instructor of many, and to his own soul he is useless.<verse eid="SIR 37:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:20"/>There exists a person skilled in words who is hated; this one will be lacking any luxury.<verse eid="SIR 37:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:21"/>For charm has not been granted to him by the Lord, because he is deprived of any wisdom.<verse eid="SIR 37:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:22"/>There exists a person wise in his own soul, and the fruits of his good sense are <note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">37:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'evident to all to see'</char></note>on the body<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">37:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'it'; antecedent unclear</char></note>.<verse eid="SIR 37:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:23"/>A wise man will instruct his own people, and the fruits of his understanding are reliable.<verse eid="SIR 37:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:24"/>A wise man will be full of blessing, and all who see him will deem him happy.<verse eid="SIR 37:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:25"/>A man's life is in a number of days, and the days of Israel are without number.<verse eid="SIR 37:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:26"/>The wise person among his people will inherit honor, and his name will live forever.<verse eid="SIR 37:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:27"/>Child, during your life test your soul, and see what is bad for it, and do not give<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">37:27</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'what is bad'</char></note> to it.<verse eid="SIR 37:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:28"/>For not everything confers benefit to everyone, and every soul is not pleased by everything.<verse eid="SIR 37:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:29"/>Do not be greedy for every delicacy, and do not give yourself up to foods.<verse eid="SIR 37:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:30"/>For in much food there is illness, and gluttony will bring one near to cholera.<verse eid="SIR 37:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 37:31"/>Because of gluttony, many have died, but he who pays attention will add to life.<verse eid="SIR 37:31"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 38">
<verse sid="SIR 38:1"/>Honor a physician for his services, for indeed the Lord created him.<verse eid="SIR 38:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:2"/>For healing is from the Most High, and he will receive a gift from a king.<verse eid="SIR 38:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:3"/>A physician's skill will put up his head, and in the presence of nobles he will be admired.<verse eid="SIR 38:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:4"/>The Lord created remedies out of the earth, and a prudent man will not ignore them.<verse eid="SIR 38:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:5"/>Was not water made sweet from wood in order that his<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'its'</char></note> strength might be known?<verse eid="SIR 38:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:6"/>And it was he that gave skill to human beings in order to be glorified in his marvelous deeds.<verse eid="SIR 38:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:7"/>By them he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the physician'</char></note> cured and took away his<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the patient'</char></note> pain.<verse eid="SIR 38:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:8"/>He who prepares unguents will make a compound with them, and his works will never be finished, and peace from him is upon the surface of the earth.<verse eid="SIR 38:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:9"/>Child, in your illness do not look elsewhere, but pray to the Lord, and he will heal you.<verse eid="SIR 38:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:10"/>Withdraw from error, and direct your hands, and from all sin cleanse your heart.<verse eid="SIR 38:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:11"/>Give a sweet-smell and a memorial of fine flour, and enrich an offering .....<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'.....':  Greek uncertain</char></note>.<verse eid="SIR 38:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:12"/>And give a physician a place, for indeed the Lord created him, and do not let him withdraw from you, for indeed there is need of him.<verse eid="SIR 38:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:13"/>There is a time when success is in their hands as well.<verse eid="SIR 38:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:14"/>For they will also petition the Lord, that he might grant them success with rest and healing for the maintenance of life.<verse eid="SIR 38:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:15"/>He who sins before him who made him, may he fall into a physician's hands.<verse eid="SIR 38:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:16"/>Child, let your tears fall over a corpse, and as one suffering terribly begin a lament, but in accordance with his decision lay out his body, and do not neglect his<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'its'</char></note> burial.<verse eid="SIR 38:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:17"/>Make the weeping bitter and the beating fervent, and make mourning according to his dignity, for one day and two for the purpose of<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'for the purpose of':  Possibly 'to prevent'</char></note> slander, and be comforted for the sake of grief.<verse eid="SIR 38:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:18"/>For from grief issues death, and grief of the heart will cripple strength.<verse eid="SIR 38:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:19"/>In misery<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. Perhaps 'a process of reasoning'</char></note> grief too endures, and a poor person's life is a curse of the heart.<verse eid="SIR 38:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:20"/>Do not give your heart over to grief; withdraw from it, when you remember the end.<verse eid="SIR 38:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:21"/>Do not forget, for there is no return, and him you will not benefit, and yourself you will harm.<verse eid="SIR 38:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:22"/>Remember his judgment, because so is yours also. For me yesterday; for you today!<verse eid="SIR 38:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:23"/>In the resting of the corpse, put to rest his memorial, and be comforted by it in the departure of his spirit.<verse eid="SIR 38:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:24"/>A scribe's wisdom is in the opportunity for leisure, and he who does less business, it is he who will become wise.<verse eid="SIR 38:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:25"/>How shall he who takes hold of a plow and boasts in the shaft of a goad become wise, when he drives cattle and is engaged in their tasks and his talk is about the offspring of bulls?<verse eid="SIR 38:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:26"/>He will give his heart to producing furrows, and his sleeplessness is regarding fodder for heifers.<verse eid="SIR 38:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:27"/>So every artisan and master-artisan, who keeps going by night as by day, those who cut signets of seals, and his patience is to diversify ornamentation; he will give his heart to making a painting lifelike, and his sleeplessness is to complete the work.<verse eid="SIR 38:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:28"/>So a smith sitting near an anvil and examining closely works of iron; the vapor of the fire will melt his flesh, and with the heat of a furnace he will struggle; a hammer's sound will renew<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:28</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Perhaps 'hit again and again'</char></note> his ear, and his eyes are against<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:28</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Perhaps 'right on'</char></note> the pattern of the object; he will give his heart to completing works, and his sleeplessness is to decorate upon completion.<verse eid="SIR 38:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:29"/>So a potter sitting at his work and turning a wheel with his feet, who always lies down in anxiety about his work, and every work of his is taken into account.<verse eid="SIR 38:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:30"/>With his arm he will mold clay and in front of his feet he will bend its strength<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:30</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'bend its strength':  Possibly 'make it pliable'</char></note>; he will give over his heart to completing the glazing<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:30</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'color wash'</char></note>, and his sleeplessness is about cleaning the kiln.<verse eid="SIR 38:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:31"/>All of these relied on their hands, and each is skilled in his work.<verse eid="SIR 38:31"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:32"/>Without them a city will not be inhabited, and they will neither sojourn nor walk about, but they will not be sought for a council of the people.<verse eid="SIR 38:32"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:33"/>And they will not leap up<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:33</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'leap up':  I.e. 'gain prominence'</char></note> in the assembly. On the judge's seat they will not sit, and disposition of a legal decision they will not understand, and they will never shed light on instruction and judgment, and in illustrations<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">38:33</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'legal precedents'</char></note> they will not be found,<verse eid="SIR 38:33"/>

<verse sid="SIR 38:34"/>but they will support the foundation of an age, and their need is in the execution of a craft. Save for him who devotes his soul and who thinks about the law of the Most High!<verse eid="SIR 38:34"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 39">
<verse sid="SIR 39:1"/>He will seek out the wisdom of all the ancients, and he will be occupied with prophecies.<verse eid="SIR 39:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:2"/>He will preserve the narrative of famous men, and he will penetrate into the twists of illustrations.<verse eid="SIR 39:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:3"/>He will seek out the obscurities of proverbs, and he will be engaged with the riddles of illustrations.<verse eid="SIR 39:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:4"/>He will serve among nobles, and he will appear in front of rulers. He will travel in the land of foreign nations, for he has tested the good and bad things in people.<verse eid="SIR 39:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:5"/>He will devote his heart to rise early towards the Lord who made him, and he will petition in front of the Most High, and he will open his mouth in prayer, and concerning his sins he will petition.<verse eid="SIR 39:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:6"/>If the great Lord wants, he will be filled with a spirit of understanding. He will pour forth words of his wisdom, and in prayer he will acknowledge the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 39:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:7"/>He will direct counsel and knowledge, and on his hidden things he will think.<verse eid="SIR 39:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:8"/>He will illuminate the instruction of his teaching, and in the law of the Lord's covenant he will boast.<verse eid="SIR 39:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:9"/>Many will praise his understanding, and it will never be blotted out; his memorial will not depart, and his name will live for generations of generations.<verse eid="SIR 39:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:10"/>Nations will narrate his wisdom, and an assembly will proclaim his praise.<verse eid="SIR 39:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:11"/>If he abides, he will leave behind a name greater than a thousand, and if he rests, it will favorable for him.<verse eid="SIR 39:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:12"/>Yet being so disposed, I will tell in detail, and I was filled like the full moon.<verse eid="SIR 39:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:13"/>Listen to me, O devout sons, and blossom like a rose growing by a watery stream.<verse eid="SIR 39:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:14"/>Like incense send out a sweet fragrance, and send forth a blossom like a lily. Spread abroad a voice, and praise together, and bless the Lord for all his works.<verse eid="SIR 39:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:15"/>Give majesty to his name, and acknowledge with praise of him, with songs on the lips and with cinyras<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">39:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">= Hebrew 'kinnor' = 'lyre'</char></note>, and in this manner you will speak with acknowledgement.<verse eid="SIR 39:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:16"/>"All the works of the Lord, that they are very good, and every ordinance will occur in its time.<verse eid="SIR 39:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:17"/>It is not possible to say, 'What is this? To what end is this?' For everything will be sought out in its time. By his word water stood as a heap, and by an utterance of his mouth, reservoirs of water.<verse eid="SIR 39:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:18"/>By his ordinance is all good pleasure, and there is no one who will diminish his salvation.<verse eid="SIR 39:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:19"/>The works of all flesh are before him, and it is not possible to hide from his eyes.<verse eid="SIR 39:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:20"/>From age to age he watched, and nothing is a wonder before him.<verse eid="SIR 39:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:21"/>It is not possible to say, 'What is this? To what end is this?' For all things have been created for their uses.<verse eid="SIR 39:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:22"/>"His blessing has covered over like a river, and like a flood it has drenched dry land.<verse eid="SIR 39:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:23"/>Thus his anger will inherit nations as when he changed waters into salt water.<verse eid="SIR 39:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:24"/>His ways are straight for the devout; so for the lawless there are pitfalls.<verse eid="SIR 39:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:25"/>Good things have been created from the beginning for the good; so for sinners, evil things.<verse eid="SIR 39:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:26"/>The beginning of every necessity for a human being's life is water and fire and iron and salt and fine wheat flour and milk and honey, blood of a grape and oil and clothing.<verse eid="SIR 39:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:27"/>All these things belong to the pious for good; so for sinners they will be turned into evil.<verse eid="SIR 39:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:28"/>"There exist winds<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">39:28</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'spirits'</char></note> that have been created for vengeance, and in their wrath they made firm their scourges; at a time of consummation they will pour out strength, and the wrath of him who made them they will abate.<verse eid="SIR 39:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:29"/>Fire and hail and famine and death, all these have been created for vengeance.<verse eid="SIR 39:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:30"/>Teeth of wild beasts and scorpions and vipers and a sword taking vengeance on impious people for destruction.<verse eid="SIR 39:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:31"/>In his commandment they will be gladdened, and they will be prepared for service on the earth, and at their times they will not transgress a word."<verse eid="SIR 39:31"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:32"/>Therefore from the beginning I was determined, and I thought, and I left it in writing.<verse eid="SIR 39:32"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:33"/>The works of the Lord, all are good, and every need he will supply in its hour.<verse eid="SIR 39:33"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:34"/>And it is not possible to say, "This is worse than this," for all things will be highly esteemed at a right time.<verse eid="SIR 39:34"/>

<verse sid="SIR 39:35"/>And now with a whole heart and mouth sing hymns, and bless the name of the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 39:35"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 40">
<verse sid="SIR 40:1"/>A great engagement was created for every person, and a heavy yoke is on Adam's sons from the day of their exit from their mother's womb until the day of return to the mother of all:<verse eid="SIR 40:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:2"/>their considerations and fear of heart-- thought of apprehension, day of death.<verse eid="SIR 40:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:3"/>From the one sitting on a splendid throne, even to one humbled in earth and ashes,<verse eid="SIR 40:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:4"/>from one wearing blue and a garland, even to the one clothed in coarse linen--<verse eid="SIR 40:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:5"/>there are wrath and envy and confusion and unrest and fear of death and fury and strife. Even at the moment of rest upon a bed, sleep at night confuses his knowledge.<verse eid="SIR 40:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:6"/>There is as little as nothing in rest, and he grows weary of that in his sleep as he does in the day, having been troubled by a vision of his heart, like one who has escaped from before war.<verse eid="SIR 40:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:7"/>At the moment of his need, he awoke, even marveling at fear for nothing.<verse eid="SIR 40:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:8"/>With all flesh, from human to animal, and upon sinners seven times more than these<verse eid="SIR 40:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:9"/>are death and blood and strife and sword, calamities, famine and ruin and scourge.<verse eid="SIR 40:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:10"/>For the lawless all these things were created, and because of them the flood occurred.<verse eid="SIR 40:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:11"/>Everything that is of earth reverts to the earth, and everything<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">40:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> of water returns to the sea.<verse eid="SIR 40:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:12"/>Every gift and injustice will be blotted out, but good faith will stand forever.<verse eid="SIR 40:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:13"/>The money of the unjust will dry up like a river, and like loud thunder in a rain storm they will crash.<verse eid="SIR 40:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:14"/>When he opens his<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">40:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> hands, he will be glad; so those who transgress will fail at the end.<verse eid="SIR 40:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:15"/>The offspring of impious persons will not multiply branches, and they are foul roots upon a sheer rock.<verse eid="SIR 40:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:16"/>A reed by any water and river bank will be plucked up before any grass.<verse eid="SIR 40:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:17"/>Kindness is like an orchard with blessings, but an act of charity will endure forever.<verse eid="SIR 40:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:18"/>The life of a self-reliant and a hard-working person will be sweet, and above both is he who finds a treasure.<verse eid="SIR 40:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:19"/>Children and the building of a city firmly fix a name, and above both is a wife considered blameless.<verse eid="SIR 40:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:20"/>Wine and music gladden a heart, and above both is love of wisdom.<verse eid="SIR 40:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:21"/>Flute and harp make sweet melodies, and above both is a pleasant tongue.<verse eid="SIR 40:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:22"/>Grace and beauty the eye will desire, and above both are the first shoots of seed.<verse eid="SIR 40:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:23"/>Friend and companion meet at the right moment, and above both is a wife with a husband.<verse eid="SIR 40:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:24"/>Brothers and aid are for a time of distress, and more than both an act of charity will rescue.<verse eid="SIR 40:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:25"/>Gold and silver make a foot firm, and above both counsel is highly esteemed.<verse eid="SIR 40:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:26"/>Money and strength will lift up a heart, and above both is fear of the Lord; there is no want in the fear of the Lord, and with it there is no reason to seek aid.<verse eid="SIR 40:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:27"/>Fear of the Lord is like an orchard of blessing, and more than any glory it covers him.<verse eid="SIR 40:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:28"/>Child, a life of begging do not live; it is better to die than to beg.<verse eid="SIR 40:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:29"/>When a man looks to a table belonging to another, his manner of living is not by reckoning a life<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">40:29</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'by reckoning a life':  I.e. 'a good life'</char></note>; he will pollute his soul with food belonging to others, but a man who is intelligent and who has been instructed will be on guard.<verse eid="SIR 40:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 40:30"/>In the mouth of a shameless person begging will be sweet, and in his belly a fire will burn.<verse eid="SIR 40:30"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 41">
<verse sid="SIR 41:1"/>O death, how bitter is the remembrance of you to a person at peace with his possessions, to a man undistracted and prospering in everything and still having strength to welcome a luxury.<verse eid="SIR 41:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:2"/>O death, your judgment is good to a person who is needy and lacking strength, who is in extreme old age and is anxious about everything and who is disobedient and has lost hope.<verse eid="SIR 41:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:3"/>Do not be wary of death's judgment; remember those before you and the last ones.<verse eid="SIR 41:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:4"/>This is the judgment from the Lord for all flesh-- and why should you reject the good pleasure of the Most High? Whether ten or a hundred or a thousand years, in Hades there is no reproving of life.<verse eid="SIR 41:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:5"/>Abominable children are children of sinners, and living together in the enclaves of impious persons.<verse eid="SIR 41:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:6"/>The inheritance of the children of sinners will perish, and disgrace will continually be with their seed.<verse eid="SIR 41:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:7"/>Children will blame an impious father, because on his account they will be reproached.<verse eid="SIR 41:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:8"/>Woe to you, impious men, who have forsaken the law of the Most High.<verse eid="SIR 41:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:9"/>and if you are born, you will be born for a curse, and if you die, you will be apportioned a curse.<verse eid="SIR 41:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:10"/>Everything that is from the earth will go back into the earth; so impious persons are from a curse to destruction.<verse eid="SIR 41:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:11"/>The grief of human beings is in their bodies, but a no-good name of sinners will be blotted out.<verse eid="SIR 41:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:12"/>Have regard for a name, for it will endure for you rather than a thousand great treasures of gold.<verse eid="SIR 41:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:13"/>Of a good life there is a number of days, but a good name will endure forever.<verse eid="SIR 41:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:14"/>Maintain instruction in peace, children, but hidden wisdom and invisible treasure-- what profit is in either?<verse eid="SIR 41:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:15"/>Better is a person who conceals his foolishness than a person who conceals his wisdom.<verse eid="SIR 41:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:16"/>Therefore show respect for my judgment, for it is not good to guard against every shame, and not everything will be approved by all with confidence.<verse eid="SIR 41:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:17"/>Be ashamed before father and mother, of sexual immorality, and before leader and dynast, of falsehood,<verse eid="SIR 41:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:18"/>before judge and magistrate, of error, and before a gathering and people, of lawlessness, before partner and friend, of injustice,<verse eid="SIR 41:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:19"/>and before a place where you sojourn, of theft, before divine truth and covenant and before planting an elbow for bread, before damning in receiving and giving<verse eid="SIR 41:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:20"/>and before people who greet, of silence, before a look at a female escort<verse eid="SIR 41:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:21"/>and before turning away from the face of a relative, before taking away a portion and a gift and before ogling a married woman,<verse eid="SIR 41:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 41:22"/>before meddling with his servant girl-- and do not come upon her bed-- before friends, of words of reproach-- and after giving, do not reproach,<verse eid="SIR 41:22"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 42">
<verse sid="SIR 42:1"/>before repeating a word of hearsay and before disclosing secret words, and you will be truly modest and finding favor before every human. Do not be ashamed of these things, and do not receive a face<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">42:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'receive a face':  I.e. 'show partiality'</char></note> in order to sin:<verse eid="SIR 42:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:2"/>of the law of the Most High and covenant and of judgment so as to justify the impious,<verse eid="SIR 42:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:3"/>of an account of a partner or travelers and of giving an inheritance of others,<verse eid="SIR 42:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:4"/>of accuracy with scale and weights and of acquiring much or little,<verse eid="SIR 42:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:5"/>of profit from business of merchants and of much discipline of children and to draw blood from the side of a wicked domestic.<verse eid="SIR 42:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:6"/>In the case of a wicked wife, a seal is excellent, and where there are many hands, lock up.<verse eid="SIR 42:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:7"/>Whatever you hand over-- by number and weight and giving or receiving-- put everything in writing.<verse eid="SIR 42:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:8"/>Do not be ashamed<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">42:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'Do not be ashamed':  Lacking in Greek</char></note> of discipline for the stupid and foolish and for the aged guilty of sexual immorality, and you will have truly been trained and will have been approved before every living person.<verse eid="SIR 42:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:9"/>A daughter is a hidden sleeplessness to a father, and anxiety about her takes away sleep-- in her youth, lest she become past her prime, and having married, lest she be hated,<verse eid="SIR 42:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:10"/>in virginity, lest she be defiled and she become pregnant in her father's house, being with a man<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">42:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'husband'</char></note>, lest she transgress, and having married, lest she be barren.<verse eid="SIR 42:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:11"/>Over a wanton daughter keep strict guard, lest she make you a laughingstock to enemies, common talk in the city and summoned by the people, and she shame you in a multitude of many.<verse eid="SIR 42:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:12"/>Do not look at any person in terms of beauty, and in the midst of women do not deliberate.<verse eid="SIR 42:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:13"/>For from garments proceeds a moth, and from a woman, woman's wickedness.<verse eid="SIR 42:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:14"/>Better the wickedness of a man than a well- doing woman and a woman bringing shame to the point of reproach.<verse eid="SIR 42:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:15"/>I will indeed remember the works of the Lord, and what I have seen, I will narrate; by the words of the Lord are his works,<verse eid="SIR 42:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:16"/>The shining sun looked down upon everything, and its work is full of the glory of the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 42:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:17"/>He did not permit the holy ones of the Lord to recount all his wonders that the Lord the Almighty established so that the universe might stand firm in his glory.<verse eid="SIR 42:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:18"/>Abyss and heart he searched out, and he considered their wonderful feats; for the Most High knew all knowledge, and he saw into the sign of the age,<verse eid="SIR 42:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:19"/>relating the things that passed and the things that will be and revealing tracks of hidden things.<verse eid="SIR 42:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:20"/>No thought eluded him, and not one word was hidden from him.<verse eid="SIR 42:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:21"/>He set in order the splendors of his wisdom; since he is one before the age and forever, he was neither added to nor diminished, and he needed no one as a counselor.<verse eid="SIR 42:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:22"/>How desirable are all his works, and they are like a spark to behold.<verse eid="SIR 42:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:23"/>All these things live, and they remain forever, in all functions, and all obey.<verse eid="SIR 42:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:24"/>Everything is in pairs, one opposite one, and he did not make anything deficient.<verse eid="SIR 42:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 42:25"/>One firmed up the good things of the other-- nd who will be filled when he sees his glory?<verse eid="SIR 42:25"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 43">
<verse sid="SIR 43:1"/>Exultation of height, firmament of elegance, the form of the sky in a vision of glory!<verse eid="SIR 43:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:2"/>The sun in an appearance proclaiming in going out, a wondrous object, a work of the Most High!<verse eid="SIR 43:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:3"/>At its noontide, it parches land-- and before its burning heat who will endure?<verse eid="SIR 43:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:4"/>When one blows a furnace in works of burning heat, threefold is the sun when it burns up mountains. When it breathes out fiery vapors and when it shines forth rays, it blinds eyes.<verse eid="SIR 43:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:5"/>Great is the Lord who made it, and at his words it hastened on its journey.<verse eid="SIR 43:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:6"/>And the moon stands in its season, a proclamation of times and an everlasting sign.<verse eid="SIR 43:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:7"/>From the moon is a sign for a feast, a luminary that wanes upon completion.<verse eid="SIR 43:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:8"/>A month is according to its name, increasing marvelously in changing, an object on high for armies, shining in the firmament of the sky.<verse eid="SIR 43:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:9"/>The glory of the stars is the beauty of the sky, an ornament giving light in the heights of the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 43:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:10"/>By words of the Holy One they will stand according to decree, and they will never fail in their watches.<verse eid="SIR 43:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:11"/>See the rainbow, and bless him who made it exceedingly beautiful in its brightness.<verse eid="SIR 43:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:12"/>It ringed the sky in a circle of glory; the hands of the Most High stretched it out.<verse eid="SIR 43:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:13"/>By his ordinance he urges on snow and speeds the lightnings of his judgment.<verse eid="SIR 43:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:14"/>Therefore storehouses were opened, and clouds flew out like birds.<verse eid="SIR 43:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:15"/>In his majesty he made clouds strong, and stones of hail were broken apart.<verse eid="SIR 43:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:16"/>and at his appearance mountains will be shaken. By his will the south wind will blow, (17b) also a storm from the north and a whirlwind. Like birds flying down he sprinkles snow, and like a locust alighting is its descent.<verse eid="SIR 43:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:17"/>The voice of his thunder caused the earth to be in travail,<verse eid="SIR 43:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:18"/>An eye will marvel at the beauty of its whiteness, and a heart will be amazed by its rain.<verse eid="SIR 43:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:19"/>And frost, like salt, he pours upon the earth, and when it freezes, points of thorns occur.<verse eid="SIR 43:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:20"/>A cold north wind will blow, and ice will freeze on water; upon every gathering of water it will settle, and like a breastplate the water will put it on.<verse eid="SIR 43:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:21"/>He will consume mountains and will burn up wilderness, and he will extinguish grass like fire.<verse eid="SIR 43:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:22"/>A mist hastens healing for all things; a dew that comes out will refresh from the heat.<verse eid="SIR 43:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:23"/>By his reasoning he abated the abyss, and he planted islands in it.<verse eid="SIR 43:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:24"/>Those who sail the sea describe its danger, and we marvel at the reports of our ears.<verse eid="SIR 43:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:25"/>The incredible and amazing works are there, a variety of every living thing, a creation of sea monsters.<verse eid="SIR 43:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:26"/>Because of him, his messenger succeeds, and by his word all things hold together.<verse eid="SIR 43:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:27"/>Many things we might say, and we would never arrive, and the consummation of words is "He is the all."<verse eid="SIR 43:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:28"/>Where shall we find the strength to glorify? For he is the great one, beyond all of his works.<verse eid="SIR 43:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:29"/>Awesome is the Lord and very great, and marvelous is his dominance.<verse eid="SIR 43:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:30"/>Glorify the Lord, and exalt him as much as you can, for he will surpass even still, and exalt him, and increase in strength; do not grow weary, for you will never arrive.<verse eid="SIR 43:30"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:31"/>Who has seen him and will describe him? And who will magnify him as he is?<verse eid="SIR 43:31"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:32"/>Many things hidden are greater than these, for few of his works we have seen.<verse eid="SIR 43:32"/>

<verse sid="SIR 43:33"/>For the Lord made all things, and to the pious he gave wisdom.<verse eid="SIR 43:33"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 44">
<verse sid="SIR 44:1"/><note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">44:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">A HYMN TO THE FATHERS</char></note>Let us now praise famous men and our fathers by descent.<verse eid="SIR 44:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:2"/>The Lord created much glory, his majesty from eternity.<verse eid="SIR 44:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:3"/>When they ruled in their kingdoms, men also became noteworthy through power; when they counseled with their intelligence, when they announced through prophecies,<verse eid="SIR 44:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:4"/>when they led people by deliberations and with understanding of a people's scribal art-- wise words there are in their instruction--<verse eid="SIR 44:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:5"/>when they searched out musical tunes and set out verses in writing--<verse eid="SIR 44:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:6"/>rich men well endowed with strength, being at peace in their dwelling-places--<verse eid="SIR 44:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:7"/>all of these were glorified in generations and in their days were a boast.<verse eid="SIR 44:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:8"/>There were some of them who left behind a name so that their praises might be told in detail.<verse eid="SIR 44:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:9"/>And of others there is no memorial, and they perished as though they had not existed, and they became as those who had not been born, and their children after them.<verse eid="SIR 44:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:10"/>These, on the other hand, were men of compassion, whose righteous deeds were not forgotten.<verse eid="SIR 44:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:11"/>With their seed it will remain; a good inheritance is their offspring.<verse eid="SIR 44:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:12"/>In the covenants their seed stood, and their children for their sake.<verse eid="SIR 44:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:13"/>Forever will their seed remain, and their glory will not be blotted out.<verse eid="SIR 44:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:14"/>Their bodies were buried in peace, and their name lives for generations.<verse eid="SIR 44:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:15"/>Peoples will recount their wisdom, and an assembly will proclaim their praise.<verse eid="SIR 44:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:16"/>Henoch pleased God, and he was changed, an example of repentance for generations.<verse eid="SIR 44:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:17"/>Noe was found perfect, righteous; in a time of anger he became an exchange; because of him, there was a remnant for the earth, when a flood occurred.<verse eid="SIR 44:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:18"/>Covenants of eternity were added to him lest all flesh be blotted out by a flood.<verse eid="SIR 44:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:19"/>Abraam was a great father of a multitude of nations, and no blemish was found on his glory,<verse eid="SIR 44:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:20"/>who kept the law of the Most High, and he entered in a covenant with him; in his flesh he established a covenant, and in a trial he was found faithful.<verse eid="SIR 44:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:21"/>Therefore he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">44:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'God'</char></note> established by means of an oath with him that nations would be blessed by his seed, that he would multiply him as the dust of the earth and like the stars to exalt his seed and to give them an inheritance from sea to sea and from the river to the end of the earth.<verse eid="SIR 44:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:22"/>And with Isaak he likewise established, on account of Abraam his father. A blessing for all humankind and a covenant<verse eid="SIR 44:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 44:23"/>he put down upon the head of Iakob; he acknowledged him with his blessings, and he gave to him by an inheritance, and he divided his portions, and he allotted among twelve tribes. And he brought out of him a man of mercy, who found favor in the eyes of all flesh,<verse eid="SIR 44:23"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 45">
<verse sid="SIR 45:1"/>who was loved by God and human beings, Moyses, whose memorial is accompanied by blessings.<verse eid="SIR 45:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:2"/>He made him equal to the glory of holy ones, and he made him great by terror for enemies.<verse eid="SIR 45:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:3"/>By his words he hastened signs; he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">45:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'God'</char></note> glorified him in front of kings; he gave him commands for his people, and he showed him his glory.<verse eid="SIR 45:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:4"/>In faithfulness and meekness he consecrated him; he chose him out of all flesh.<verse eid="SIR 45:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:5"/>He caused him to hear his voice, and he led him into the deep darkness, and he gave him commandments face-to-face, a law of life and knowledge, to teach Iakob a covenant and Israel his judgments.<verse eid="SIR 45:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:6"/>He exalted Aaron, a holy person like him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">45:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Moyses'</char></note>, his brother from the tribe of Leui.<verse eid="SIR 45:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:7"/>He <note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">45:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'established with him an everlasting covenant'</char></note>established him as an everlasting covenant<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">45:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek is plural</char></note> and gave him a priesthood of the people; he pronounced him happy with decorum, and he girded him with a cloak of glory.<verse eid="SIR 45:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:8"/>He clothed him with perfection of boasting, and he crowned him with the implements of strength, breeches and a full-length robe and shoulder-strap.<verse eid="SIR 45:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:9"/>And he encircled him with pomegranates, with very many golden bells all around, to send forth a sound at his steps, to make an audible sound in the shrine for a memorial for the sons of his people,<verse eid="SIR 45:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:10"/>with the sacred vestment, with gold and blue and purple, a work of an embroiderer, with the oracle of judgment, for manifestations of truth,<verse eid="SIR 45:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:11"/>with twisted scarlet, a work of an artisan, with costly stones of an engraved seal in a setting of gold, a work of a jeweler, for a memorial in inscribed writing according to the number of the tribes of Israel,<verse eid="SIR 45:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:12"/>a crown of gold upon a turban, a carving of a seal of holiness, a boast of honor, a work of strength, objects of desire for the eyes, adorned.<verse eid="SIR 45:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:13"/>Before him such beautiful things did not exist. Until eternity, no alien put them on except his sons alone and his descendants in perpetuity.<verse eid="SIR 45:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:14"/>His sacrifices shall be wholly burned, twice each day continually.<verse eid="SIR 45:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:15"/>Moyses filled his hands and anointed him with holy oil; it became for him an everlasting covenant and in his seed for the days of the sky, to minister to him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">45:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'God'</char></note> and at the same time to be a priest and to bless his people in the name.<verse eid="SIR 45:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:16"/>He chose him out of everyone alive to offer a fruit sacrifice to the Lord, incense and a pleasing odor for a memorial, to make atonement for the people.<verse eid="SIR 45:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:17"/>By his commandments he gave him authority in covenants of judgments, to teach Iakob the testimonies and with his law to enlighten Israel.<verse eid="SIR 45:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:18"/>Strangers conspired against him, and they envied him in the wilderness, the men with Dathan and Abiron and the gathering of Kore in wrath and anger.<verse eid="SIR 45:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:19"/>The Lord saw and was not well pleased, and they were destroyed by wrath of anger; he performed wonders among them, to consume them in the fire of his flame.<verse eid="SIR 45:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:20"/>And he added glory to Aaron, and he gave him an inheritance; the first fruits of first products he allotted to him; bread with the first things he prepared in abundance.<verse eid="SIR 45:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:21"/>For also they shall eat sacrifices of the Lord, which he gave both to him and to his seed.<verse eid="SIR 45:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:22"/>But in the land of the people he will have no inheritance, and he has no portion for him among the people, for he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">45:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'God'</char></note> is your portion and inheritance.<verse eid="SIR 45:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:23"/>And Phinees son of Eleazar is third in glory, since he was zealous in the fear of the Lord and since he stood firm in the turning of the people, in the goodness of the eagerness of his soul; he also made atonement for Israel.<verse eid="SIR 45:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:24"/>Therefore there was established with him a covenant of peace to be in charge of holy things and of his people so that he and his seed might have the magnificence of the priesthood forever.<verse eid="SIR 45:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:25"/>Also a covenant with Dauid son of Iessai from the tribe of Iouda, an inheritance of the king for son from son only; Aaron's inheritance is also for his seed.<verse eid="SIR 45:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 45:26"/>May he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">45:26</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'God'</char></note> grant to you<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">45:26</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek is plural</char></note> wisdom in your heart, to judge his people in righteousness so that their good things might not vanish and their glory be to their generations.<verse eid="SIR 45:26"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 46">
<verse sid="SIR 46:1"/>Mighty in war was Iesous son of Naue and a successor of Moyses in prophecies, who was, like his name, great for the salvation of his<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">46:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'God's'</char></note> elect, to take vengeance on enemies when stirred up, so that he might give Israel an inheritance.<verse eid="SIR 46:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:2"/>How he was glorified when he lifted up his hands and when he extended a sword against cities!<verse eid="SIR 46:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:3"/>Who before him stood so? For it was he who led the wars of the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 46:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:4"/>Was it not by his hand that the sun was shackled, and one day became as two?<verse eid="SIR 46:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:5"/>He called upon the Most High, mighty one, when enemies pressed him all around, and the great Lord heard him with stones of hail of mighty power.<verse eid="SIR 46:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:6"/>He rushed down upon a nation in battle, and on a slope he destroyed those who resisted so that nations might know his armament, because their battle was against the Lord, for indeed he followed after a mighty one.<verse eid="SIR 46:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:7"/>And in the days of Moyses he did mercy, he and Chaleb son of Iephonne, to oppose an assembly, to restrain people from sin and to still grumbling of wickedness.<verse eid="SIR 46:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:8"/>And these were the two that escaped out of the six hundred thousand infantry to lead them<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">46:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the Israelites'</char></note> into an inheritance, into a land flowing with milk and honey.<verse eid="SIR 46:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:9"/>And the Lord gave Chaleb strength, and until old age it remained with him so that he went up to the height of the land and his seed obtained an inheritance<verse eid="SIR 46:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:10"/>in order that all the sons of Israel might see that it is good to walk behind the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 46:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:11"/>And the judges, each with his own name, whose heart did not commit fornication and who did not turn away from the Lord, may their memorial be for blessings.<verse eid="SIR 46:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:12"/>May their bones sprout anew out of their plot and their name be traded; may it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">46:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'their plot'</char></note> be renowne famong the sons of humankind.<verse eid="SIR 46:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:13"/>Having received glory of human beings, beloved by his Lord was Samouel<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">46:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Perhaps 'among the sons of humankind, having received glory of human beings. Beloved by his Lord was Samouel'</char></note>; a prophet of the Lord, he established a kingdom and anointed rulers over his people.<verse eid="SIR 46:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:14"/>By the law of the Lord he judged a gathering, and the Lord watched over Iakob.<verse eid="SIR 46:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:15"/>By his faithfulness he was made accurate as a prophet, and the trustworthiness of his vision was known in his words.<verse eid="SIR 46:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:16"/>And he called upon the Lord, a mighty one, when his enemies pressed all around, with an offering of a suckling lamb.<verse eid="SIR 46:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:17"/>And the Lord thundered from the sky, and with a great sound he made his voice heard.<verse eid="SIR 46:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:18"/>And he wiped out leaders of the Tyrians and all rulers of the Phylistiim.<verse eid="SIR 46:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:19"/>And before the time of eternal sleep he bore witness before the Lord and his anointed one, "No property, not even a pair shoes, have I taken from any flesh." And no person accused him.<verse eid="SIR 46:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 46:20"/>And after he fell asleep, he prophesied, and he showed the king his end, and he raised up his voice out of the ground in prophecy to blot out the lawlessness of the people.<verse eid="SIR 46:20"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 47">
<verse sid="SIR 47:1"/>And after this one Nathan rose up to prophecy in the days of Dauid.<verse eid="SIR 47:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:2"/>Just as fat set apart from deliverance<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">47:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'an offering of deliverance'</char></note>, so was Dauid from Israel's sons.<verse eid="SIR 47:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:3"/>He played with lions as with young goats and with bears as with lambs of the flocks.<verse eid="SIR 47:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:4"/>In his youth, did he not kill a giant and take away reproach from the people by raising his hand with a sling's stone and by striking down the arrogance of Goliath?<verse eid="SIR 47:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:5"/>For he called upon the Lord, the Most High, and he gave strength by his right arm, to remove a person able in war, to exalt his people's horn.<verse eid="SIR 47:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:6"/>So among the tens of thousands they glorified him, and they praised him with blessings of the Lord by bringing to him a diadem of glory.<verse eid="SIR 47:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:7"/>For he wiped out enemies all around, and he treated with contempt the Phylistiim, his adversaries, and he broke their horn until this day.<verse eid="SIR 47:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:8"/>In every deed of his he gave acknowledgement to the Holy One, the Most High, with a word of glory; with his whole heart he sang hymns, and he loved him who made him.<verse eid="SIR 47:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:9"/>He established harp-singers before the altar also to make sweet melodies with their ringing sounds,<verse eid="SIR 47:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:10"/>He gave dignity at the feasts, and he arranged seasons until completion, when they were praising his holy name, and from early morning the holy precinct was resounding.<verse eid="SIR 47:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:11"/>The Lord took away his sins, and he exalted his horn forever, and he gave him a covenant of kings and a throne of glory in Israel.<verse eid="SIR 47:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:12"/>After this one arose a knowledgeable son, and because of him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">47:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Dauid'</char></note>, he lodged in spaciousness.<verse eid="SIR 47:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:13"/>Salomon reigned in days of peace, to whom God gave rest all around so that he might establish a house to his<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">47:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'God's'</char></note> name and prepare a holy precinct forever.<verse eid="SIR 47:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:14"/>How wise were you in your youth, and you were filled like a river with understanding.<verse eid="SIR 47:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:15"/>Your soul covered the earth, and you were full with illustrations of riddles.<verse eid="SIR 47:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:16"/>To far-off islands did your name reach, and you were beloved in your peace.<verse eid="SIR 47:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:17"/>For songs and proverbs and illustrations and for explanations countries marveled at you.<verse eid="SIR 47:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:18"/>In the name of the Lord God, who is called God of Israel, you gathered gold like tin and amassed silver like lead.<verse eid="SIR 47:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:19"/>You bent your flanks for women, and you were brought into subjection by your body.<verse eid="SIR 47:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:20"/>You gave disgrace on your glory, and you defiled your seed, to bring wrath upon your children and to cause bewilderment by your folly<verse eid="SIR 47:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:21"/>so that sovereignty became divided, and a disobedient kingdom originates from Ephraim.<verse eid="SIR 47:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:22"/>But the Lord will never abandon his mercy and never caused any of his words to perish, and he will never blot out the descendants of his chosen one, and he will never take away the seed of the one who loved him, and he gave a remnant to Iakob, and to Dauid a root out of him.<verse eid="SIR 47:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:23"/>And Salomon rested with his fathers, and he left behind himself some of his seed, folly of the people and one lacking understanding, Roboam, who caused the people to revolt because of his plan, and Ieroboam son of Nabat, who made Israel sin, also gave Ephraim a path of sin.<verse eid="SIR 47:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:24"/>And their sins multiplied greatly to remove them from their land.<verse eid="SIR 47:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 47:25"/>And they sought out every wickedness until vengeance came upon them.<verse eid="SIR 47:25"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 48">
<verse sid="SIR 48:1"/>And Elias rose up, a prophet like fire, and his word was burning like a torch,<verse eid="SIR 48:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:2"/>who brought a famine upon them and by his zeal made them few.<verse eid="SIR 48:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:3"/>By a word of the Lord he shut up the sky; he thus brought down fire three times.<verse eid="SIR 48:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:4"/>How you were glorified, Elias, in your wondrous deeds! And who will boast as you can?<verse eid="SIR 48:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:5"/>He who raised a corpse from death and out of Hades by a word of the Most High.<verse eid="SIR 48:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:6"/>He who brought down kings to destruction and those who had been glorified from their bed.<verse eid="SIR 48:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:7"/>He who heard a rebuke at Sina and at Choreb judgments of vengeance.<verse eid="SIR 48:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:8"/>He who anointed kings for the purpose of retribution and prophets as successors after him.<verse eid="SIR 48:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:9"/>He who was taken up in a whirlwind of fire and in a chariot of fiery horses.<verse eid="SIR 48:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:10"/>He who was recorded ready for the times, to calm anger before wrath, to turn the heart of a father to a son and to restore the tribes of Iakob.<verse eid="SIR 48:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:11"/>Happy are those who saw you and those fallen asleep in loving<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">48:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly + 'you'</char></note>, for we too shall live by life.<verse eid="SIR 48:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:12"/>It was Elias who was enveloped in a whirlwind, and Elisaie was filled with his spirit, and in his days he did not tremble before any ruler, and no one oppressed him.<verse eid="SIR 48:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:13"/>No word surpassed him, and in sleep<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">48:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. death</char></note> his body prophesied.<verse eid="SIR 48:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:14"/>In his life he performed wonders, and in death his deeds were marvelous.<verse eid="SIR 48:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:15"/>In all these things, the people did not repent, and they did not withdraw from their sins until they were carried off from their land and they were scattered in all the earth. And the people were left few in number, and a ruler in the house of Dauid.<verse eid="SIR 48:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:16"/>Some of them did what was pleasing, but others multiplied sins.<verse eid="SIR 48:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:17"/>Hezekias fortified his city, and he brought water into its midst; he tunneled a rock with iron, and he built wells for water.<verse eid="SIR 48:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:18"/>In his days Sennacherim came up, and he sent Rapsakes and departed, and he raised up his hand against Sion and made great boasts in his arrogance.<verse eid="SIR 48:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:19"/>Then their hearts and hands were shaken, and they were in travail like women in labor.<verse eid="SIR 48:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:20"/>And they called upon the Lord who is merciful, spreading out their hands to him. And the Holy One quickly heard them from the sky, and he redeemed them by the hand of Esaias.<verse eid="SIR 48:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:21"/>He struck down the camp of the Assyrians, and his holy angel wiped them out.<verse eid="SIR 48:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:22"/>For Hezekias did what was pleasing to the Lord, and he prevailed in the ways of Dauid, his father, which Esaias the prophet commanded; he was great and reliable in his vision.<verse eid="SIR 48:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:23"/>In his days the sun stepped back, and he added to life for the king.<verse eid="SIR 48:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:24"/>By his great spirit he showed what would be, forever, and he comforted those who mourned in Sion.<verse eid="SIR 48:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 48:25"/>And to eternity he showed the things that will be and the hidden things before they even happened.<verse eid="SIR 48:25"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 49">
<verse sid="SIR 49:1"/>Iosias's memorial becomes a compounding of incense, prepared<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">49:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'memorial'</char></note> by the work of a perfumer; like honey in every mouth it will be sweet, and like music at a banquet of wine.<verse eid="SIR 49:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 49:2"/>He prospered in turning around the people, and he removed abominations of lawlessness.<verse eid="SIR 49:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 49:3"/>He directed his heart toward the Lord; in days of lawless people he strengthened piety.<verse eid="SIR 49:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 49:4"/>Except for Dauid and Hezekias and Iosias, all committed error, for they abandoned the law of the Most High; the kings of Iouda failed,<verse eid="SIR 49:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 49:5"/>for they gave their horn<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">49:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'power'</char></note> to others and their glory to a foreign nation.<verse eid="SIR 49:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 49:6"/>They set fire to the chosen city of the holy sanctuary and made desolate its streets by the hand<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">49:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'by the hand':  Perhaps 'because'</char></note> of Ieremias.<verse eid="SIR 49:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 49:7"/>For they mistreated him, and he was hallowed a prophet in the womb, to uproot and to ruin and to destroy, likewise to build and to plant.<verse eid="SIR 49:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 49:8"/>There was Iezekiel who saw a vision of glory that he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">49:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'God'</char></note> showed to him upon the chariot of Cheroubin.<verse eid="SIR 49:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 49:9"/>Indeed he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">49:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'God'</char></note> remembered his enemies in a thunderstorm, and to do good to those who make straight their ways.<verse eid="SIR 49:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 49:10"/>And may the bones of the twelve prophets sprout anew out of their place, for they comforted Iakob and they redeemed them in confidence of hope.<verse eid="SIR 49:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 49:11"/>How are we to magnify Zorobabel? He too was like a signet on the right hand,<verse eid="SIR 49:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 49:12"/>so Iesous son of Iosedek, who, in their days, built a house and raised a holy shrine to the Lord, prepared for everlasting glory.<verse eid="SIR 49:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 49:13"/>And the memorial of Neemias is lasting, he who raised our walls, which had fallen, and set up gates and bars and raised up our buildings.<verse eid="SIR 49:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 49:14"/>No one was created on the earth such as Henoch, for he too was taken up from the earth.<verse eid="SIR 49:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 49:15"/>Nor has there been born a man like Ioseph, a leader of brothers, a support of the people, and they watched over his bones.<verse eid="SIR 49:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 49:16"/>Sem and Seth were glorified among human beings, and above every living thing in creation was Adam.<verse eid="SIR 49:16"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 50">
<verse sid="SIR 50:1"/>Simon son of Onias was the great priest, he who in his life repaired a house and in his days fortified a shrine.<verse eid="SIR 50:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:2"/>And by him the height of the courtyard was founded, a high retaining structure of the temple enclosure.<verse eid="SIR 50:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:3"/>In his days a cistern for water was quarried, a reservoir like the circumference of a sea.<verse eid="SIR 50:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:4"/>He who gave heed to his people out of calamity and strengthened the city in a siege,<verse eid="SIR 50:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:5"/>how he was glorified as he spun around the shrine, as he exited from the house of the veil.<verse eid="SIR 50:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:6"/>Like a morning star in the midst of a cloud, like the full moon in the days of a feast,<verse eid="SIR 50:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:7"/>like the sun shining on the shrine of the Most High, like the rainbow gleaming in clouds of glory,<verse eid="SIR 50:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:8"/>like a blossom of roses in days of new things<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">50:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'new things':  I.e. spring</char></note>, like lilies at exits of water, like a new shoot of Lebanon in days of summer,<verse eid="SIR 50:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:9"/>like fire and incense in a fire-pan, like a gold vessel of beaten metal, adorned with every precious stone,<verse eid="SIR 50:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:10"/>like an olive tree sprouting forth fruit and like a cypress towering in the clouds.<verse eid="SIR 50:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:11"/>When he put on a robe of glory and when he put on himself with the perfection of a boast, in ascending the holy altar, he glorified the enclosure of the holy precinct.<verse eid="SIR 50:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:12"/>But as he received portions from priests' hands and when he stood by the altar'sc hearth, all around him was a garland of brothers like a growth of cedars on Lebanon, and they surrounded him like trunks of palm trees.<verse eid="SIR 50:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:13"/>And all Aaron's sons were in their glory, and the Lord's offering was in their hands before the entire assembly of Israel,<verse eid="SIR 50:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:14"/>and as he was ministering a conclusion upon the altars<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">50:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Greek = bômos</char></note>, to arrange an offering for the Most High, the Almighty,<verse eid="SIR 50:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:15"/>he stretched out his hand to a libation bowl and made a libation of grape blood; he poured at the foundations of the altar an odor of fragrance to the Most High, the King of All.<verse eid="SIR 50:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:16"/>Then the sons of Aaron cheered; they sounded on trumpets of beaten metal; they made heard a great sound as a memorial before the Most High.<verse eid="SIR 50:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:17"/>Then all the people hurried with one accord, and they fell face down on the ground, to do obeisance to their Lord, the Almighty, God Most High.<verse eid="SIR 50:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:18"/>And the harp-singers sang praises with their voices; a melody was made sweet with a full tone.<verse eid="SIR 50:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:19"/>And the people petitioned the Lord Most High<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">50:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'petitioned the Lord Most High':  Possibly 'of the Lord Most High petitioned'</char></note> with prayer before the Merciful One until the Lord's arrangement was completed and they finished his ministrations.<verse eid="SIR 50:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:20"/>Then as he descended, he raised up his hands over the entire assembly of Israel's sons, to give a blessing of the Lord from his lips and to boast in his name.<verse eid="SIR 50:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:21"/>And they repeated an act of obeisance, to receive the blessing from the Most High.<verse eid="SIR 50:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:22"/>And now bless the God of all things, him who does great things everywhere, him who exalts our days from the womb and does with us according to his mercy.<verse eid="SIR 50:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:23"/>May he give us gladness of heart, that there also be peace in our days in Israel according to the days of the age.<verse eid="SIR 50:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:24"/>May he entrust with us his mercy, and in our days let him redeem us.<verse eid="SIR 50:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:25"/>My soul was offended at two nations, and the third is not a nation:<verse eid="SIR 50:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:26"/>those who settled on Mount Samaria and Phylistiim and the foolish people who live in Sikima.<verse eid="SIR 50:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:27"/>Instruction of understanding and knowledge I have inscribed in this book, Iesous son of Sirach, Eleazar the Hierosolymite, who poured forth wisdom from his heart.<verse eid="SIR 50:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:28"/>Happy is he who is engaged in these things, and when he has placed them on his heart, he will be wise.<verse eid="SIR 50:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 50:29"/>For if he does them, he will have strength for anything, because his route is the fear of the Lord, A PRAYER OF IESOUS SON OF SIRACH<verse eid="SIR 50:29"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="SIR 51">
<verse sid="SIR 51:1"/>I will acknowledge you, O Lord and King, and I will praise you as God my Savior. I acknowledge your name,<verse eid="SIR 51:1"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:2"/>because you have been my protector and helper, and you have redeemed my body from destruction and from a trap of a slanderous tongue, from lips that fabricate a lie, and against those who stand by<verse eid="SIR 51:2"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:3"/>you have been a help, and you have redeemed me, according to an abundance of mercy and your name, from nooses prepared for food, from the hand of persons seeking my soul, from rather many troubles, which I had,<verse eid="SIR 51:3"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:4"/>from a choking of a pyre all around and from the midst of fire, which I did not kindle,<verse eid="SIR 51:4"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:5"/>from the deep of Hades' belly and from an unclean tongue and a lying word<verse eid="SIR 51:5"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:6"/>and a missile of a tongue of an unrighteous person. My soul drew near to death, and my life was on the brink of Hades below.<verse eid="SIR 51:6"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:7"/>They surrounded me on every side, and there was no one who helped; I looked for assistance from human beings, and there was none.<verse eid="SIR 51:7"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:8"/>And I remembered your mercy, O Lord, and your beneficence from of old, because you raise up those who wait for you and you save them from the hand of wicked persons.<verse eid="SIR 51:8"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:9"/>And I raised up my supplication from the earth, and I begged for deliverance from death.<verse eid="SIR 51:9"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:10"/>I called upon the Lord, Father of my lord, not to forsake me in days of affliction, in a time of helplessness from acts of arrogance.<verse eid="SIR 51:10"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:11"/>"I will praise your name continually, and I will sing hymns with acknowledgement." And my petition was heard,<verse eid="SIR 51:11"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:12"/>for you saved me from destruction and delivered me from an evil time. For this reason I will acknowledge and praise you, and I will bless the name of the Lord.<verse eid="SIR 51:12"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:13"/>When I was still young, before I wandered, I sought wisdom plainly in my prayer.<verse eid="SIR 51:13"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:14"/>Before the shrine I asked for her, and until the final things I will seek her.<verse eid="SIR 51:14"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:15"/>When the grape was putting out flowers to the point of ripening, my heart was glad in her; my foot stepped in rectitude; from my youth I would track her.<verse eid="SIR 51:15"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:16"/>I inclined my ear a little, and I received, and I found for myself much instruction.<verse eid="SIR 51:16"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:17"/>I made progress in her; to him who gives me wisdom I will give glory.<verse eid="SIR 51:17"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:18"/>For I intended to practice her, and I sought the good, and I will never be ashamed.<verse eid="SIR 51:18"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:19"/>My soul has grappled with her, and in the performance of the law I was exacting. I spread out my hands on high, and I thought about ignorance of her.<verse eid="SIR 51:19"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:20"/>I directed my soul to her, and in purification I found her. I acquired a heart with her from the beginning. For this reason I will never be forsaken,<verse eid="SIR 51:20"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:21"/>and my belly was stirred to seek her out; for this reason I gained a good possession.<verse eid="SIR 51:21"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:22"/>The Lord gave a tongue to me as my wage, and with it I will praise him.<verse eid="SIR 51:22"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:23"/>Draw near to me, you who are uneducated, and lodge in a house of instruction.<verse eid="SIR 51:23"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:24"/>Why are you still lacking in these things, and your souls thirst greatly?<verse eid="SIR 51:24"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:25"/>I opened my mouth, and I said, "Acquire for yourselves without money.<verse eid="SIR 51:25"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:26"/>Place your neck under a yoke, and let your soul receive instruction. It is near to find it."<verse eid="SIR 51:26"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:27"/>See with your eyes that I labored little, and I found for myself much rest.<verse eid="SIR 51:27"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:28"/>Partake of instruction with a great sum of silver, and you will acquire much gold by it.<verse eid="SIR 51:28"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:29"/>May your soul be glad in his mercy, and may you never be ashamed in his praise.<verse eid="SIR 51:29"/>

<verse sid="SIR 51:30"/>Accomplish your work in good time, and he will give your wage in his time.<verse eid="SIR 51:30"/>
</_X_chapter></_X_book></_X_usx>