<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<_X_usx version="2.0">
<para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
<_X_book code="ZEP">





<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="ZEP 1">
<verse sid="ZEP 1:1"/>A word of the Lord that came to Sophonias the son of Chousi son of Godolias son of Amarias son of Hezekias in the days of King Iosias son of Amon of Ioudas.<verse eid="ZEP 1:1"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:2"/>With extinction, let it become extinct from the face of the earth, says the Lord.<verse eid="ZEP 1:2"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:3"/>Let humanity become extinct, and cattle; let the birds of the air become extinct, and the fish of the sea. And I will remove humans from the face of the earth, says the Lord.<verse eid="ZEP 1:3"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:4"/>And I will stretch out my hand against Ioudas and against all the inhabitants of Ierousalem, and I will remove from this place the names of the goddess Baal and the names of the priests<verse eid="ZEP 1:4"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:5"/>and those who do obeisance on the roofs to the host of the sky and those who swear by the Lord and those who swear by their king<verse eid="ZEP 1:5"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:6"/>and those who turn aside from the Lord and those who do not seek the Lord and those who do not cling to the Lord.<verse eid="ZEP 1:6"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:7"/>Show reverence before the Lord God! For the day of the Lord is near; because the Lord has prepared his sacrifice, he has consecrated his called ones.<verse eid="ZEP 1:7"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:8"/>And it shall be on the day of the Lord's sacrifice that I will punish the rulers and the king's house and all who dress themselves in foreign dress.<verse eid="ZEP 1:8"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:9"/>And on that day I will publicly punish all in the gateway, who fill the house of the Lord their God with impiety and fraud.<verse eid="ZEP 1:9"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:10"/>And it shall be on that day, says the Lord, there shall be a sound of clamor from the gate of men slaying and a moaning from the second<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'gate'</char></note> and a loud crash from the hills.<verse eid="ZEP 1:10"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:11"/>Lament, you who inhabit the destroyed part<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note>, because all the people were made like Chanaan; all those buoyed by silver were utterly destroyed.<verse eid="ZEP 1:11"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:12"/>And it shall be on that day, I will search Ierousalem with a lamp, and I will punish the men who despise their ordinances, who say in their hearts, "The Lord will not do good, nor will he do harm."<verse eid="ZEP 1:12"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:13"/>And their power shall become plunder, and their houses annihilation. And they will build houses and shall not inhabit them, and they will plant vineyards and shall not drink their wine.<verse eid="ZEP 1:13"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:14"/>For the great day of the Lord is near, near and very swift; the sound of the day of the Lord is bitter and harsh; it has been made powerful.<verse eid="ZEP 1:14"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:15"/>That day will be a day of wrath, a day of affliction and anguish, a day of untimely fate and annihilation, a day of darkness and gloom, a day of clouds and fog,<verse eid="ZEP 1:15"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:16"/>a day of trumpet and shouting against the fortified cities and against the lofty corners.<verse eid="ZEP 1:16"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:17"/>And I will afflict people, and they shall walk like the blind, because they sinned against the Lord, and he shall pour out their blood like dust and their flesh like cow dung.<verse eid="ZEP 1:17"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 1:18"/>Neither their silver nor their gold will be able to deliver them in the day of the Lord's wrath, and in the fire of his zeal the whole earth shall be consumed, for he will bring about a swift end upon all the inhabitants of the earth.<verse eid="ZEP 1:18"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="ZEP 2">
<verse sid="ZEP 2:1"/>Gather together, and bind yourselves together, you uneducated nation,<verse eid="ZEP 2:1"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 2:2"/>before you become like a transient flower, before there comes upon you the Lord's anger, before there comes upon you the day of the Lord's wrath.<verse eid="ZEP 2:2"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 2:3"/>Seek the Lord, all you humble of the earth; work judgment, and seek justice, and distinguish them, that you might be sheltered on the day of the Lord's wrath.<verse eid="ZEP 2:3"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 2:4"/>For Gaza shall be plundered, and Ascalon shall become an annihilation, and Azotus shall be cast out at noon, and Akkaron shall be uprooted.<verse eid="ZEP 2:4"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 2:5"/>Woe, you that inhabit the strip of the sea, resident aliens of the Cretans! A word of the Lord is against you, O Chanaan, land of allophyles, and I will wipe you out of a dwelling place.<verse eid="ZEP 2:5"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 2:6"/>And Crete shall be a pasture for flocks and a fold for sheep.<verse eid="ZEP 2:6"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 2:7"/>And the strip of the sea shall belong to the remnant of the house of Ioudas; they shall pasture upon them<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Antecedent unclear</char></note> in the houses of Ascalon; in late afternoon they shall lodge before the sons of Ioudas, because the Lord, their God, has looked upon them and returned their captivity.<verse eid="ZEP 2:7"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 2:8"/>I heard the taunts of Moab and the revilings of the sons of Ammon with which they taunted my people and made boasts against my borders.<verse eid="ZEP 2:8"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 2:9"/>Therefore, I live, says the Lord God of Israel, Moab shall become like Sodoma, and the sons of Ammon like Gomorra, and Damascus shall be abandoned like a mound of salt, and it shall be annihilated forever. And the remnant of my people shall plunder them, and the remnant of my nation shall possess them.<verse eid="ZEP 2:9"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 2:10"/>She<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Perhaps 'Damascus'</char></note> shall be theirs in return for their pride, for they scoffed and boasted against the Lord the Almighty.<verse eid="ZEP 2:10"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 2:11"/>The Lord will appear against them, and he will utterly destroy all the gods of the nations of the earth, and all the islands of the nations shall do obeisance to him, each in its place.<verse eid="ZEP 2:11"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 2:12"/>You also, O Ethiopians, are victims of my sword.<verse eid="ZEP 2:12"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 2:13"/>And he will stretch out his hand against the north and destroy the Assyrian, and he will make Nineue an annihilation, dry like a wilderness.<verse eid="ZEP 2:13"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 2:14"/>And flocks shall pasture in its midst, and all the wild animals of the earth. And chameleons and hedgehogs shall sleep in its compartments, and wild beasts shall cry in its burrows, ravens in its gates, for its rise is that of a cedar.<verse eid="ZEP 2:14"/>
</_X_chapter>




<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<_X_chapter sid="ZEP 3">
<verse sid="ZEP 3:1"/>(2.15) This is the city, the one that despises, that dwells in hope, that says in its heart: "I am, and there is no one else after me." How it has become an annihilation, a pasture for wild animals. Everyone who passes through it will hiss and wave his hands.<verse eid="ZEP 3:1"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:2"/>(3.1) Ah, distinguished and ransomed, the city, the dove! (2) It listened to no voice. It accepted no correction. It trusted not in the Lord and did not draw near to its God.<verse eid="ZEP 3:2"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:3"/>Its rulers within it are like roaring lions, its judges like wolves of Arabia; they left nothing until the morning.<verse eid="ZEP 3:3"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:4"/>Its prophets are puffs of wind<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'puffs of wind':  Perhaps 'moved by spirits'</char></note>, scornful men; its priests profane the sacred things and desecrate law.<verse eid="ZEP 3:4"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:5"/>But the Lord within it is just and will do no injustice. Morning by morning, he will render his judgment and no injustice unto victory<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'no injustice unto victory':  Perhaps 'never injustice'</char></note>.<verse eid="ZEP 3:5"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:6"/>I pulled down the haughty with ruin; their corners were annihilated; I altogether laid waste their roads so that no one travels through; their cities failed, because no one existed or lived there.<verse eid="ZEP 3:6"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:7"/>I said, "But fear me, and accept correction, and you will not be destroyed before its eyes, in regard to all the things for which I punished it. Prepare yourself eagerly." All their gleaning is corrupt.<verse eid="ZEP 3:7"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:8"/>Therefore, wait for me, says the Lord, for the day of my arising as a witness. For my judgment is for gatherings of nations, to welcome kings, to pour out upon them all the wrath of my anger; for in the fire of my zeal all the earth shall be consumed.<verse eid="ZEP 3:8"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:9"/>Because then I will change the tongue for peoples in its generation, that all might call upon the name of the Lord to be subject to him under one yoke.<verse eid="ZEP 3:9"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:10"/>From the ends of the rivers of Ethiopia they shall bring my offerings.<verse eid="ZEP 3:10"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:11"/>On that day you shall not be put to shame as a result of all your deeds by which you have acted impiously against me, because then I will remove from you the contempt of your pride, and you shall no longer add to boast against my holy mountain.<verse eid="ZEP 3:11"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:12"/>And I will leave in you a people meek and humble. And the remnant of Israel will beware of the name of the Lord.<verse eid="ZEP 3:12"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:13"/>And they will do no injustice nor speak vanity, nor shall a deceitful tongue be found in their mouth; for they will pasture and lie down, and no one shall make them afraid.<verse eid="ZEP 3:13"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:14"/>Rejoice, O daughter Sion! Proclaim, O daughter Ierousalem! Be glad, and be delighted with your whole heart, O daughter Ierousalem!<verse eid="ZEP 3:14"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:15"/>The Lord has taken away your injustices; he has redeemed you from the hand of your enemies. The king of Israel, the Lord, is in your midst; you shall see disaster no more.<verse eid="ZEP 3:15"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:16"/>At that time the Lord will say to Ierousalem: Courage, O Sion; do not let your hands grow weak.<verse eid="ZEP 3:16"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:17"/>The Lord your God is in you; a mighty one will save you; he will bring gladness to you and renew you in his affection, and he will be glad over you with delight as on a day of a feast.<verse eid="ZEP 3:17"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:18"/>And I will gather those who are shattered. Alas, who took up a reproach against her?<verse eid="ZEP 3:18"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:19"/>Behold, I will act in you for your sake in that time, says the Lord, and I will save her who has been thrust out and her who has been rejected; I will welcome and make them objects of boasting and renowned in all the earth.<verse eid="ZEP 3:19"/>

<verse sid="ZEP 3:20"/>And they will be ashamed in that time, when I do well with you and in the time when I accept you; for I will make you renowned and objects of boasting among all the peoples of the earth, when I return your captivity before you, says the Lord.<verse eid="ZEP 3:20"/>
</_X_chapter></_X_book></_X_usx>