<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="1JN" style="id">- New International Readers Version 2014</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1995, 1996, 1998, 2014 by Biblica, Inc.</para>
  <para style="h">1 John</para>
  <para style="toc1">1 John</para>
  <para style="toc2">1 John</para>
  <para style="toc3">1Jn</para>
  <para style="mt1">1 John</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">The apostle John who was also a disciple of Jesus wrote this book. It is a caring letter sent to believers that he calls his “dear children.”</para>
  <para style="ip">These believers were in the middle of an unsettling situation. Some of them had left the faith in Jesus that they had been taught. They couldn’t believe that God had come to earth in a human body. There was a common Greek idea that the physical body was evil. The Greek thinkers said that only the spirit was good. So they thought if Jesus became human then he couldn’t be God. Soon these people denied that Jesus was the Messiah. They lived lives that were immoral. And they did not take care of each other. Yet, they still said they knew God and belonged to him. They even said that their spiritual understanding was better than the rest of the group. And so they left that group of believers.</para>
  <para style="ip">The believers who were left behind were hurt and upset. They even wondered if what they had been taught about Jesus was true. So John wrote this letter to encourage all these believers. He states that everything they learned from the very beginning is true. It is true that Jesus came as a human being. And it is true that Jesus is the Messiah. He shows that the Greek thinkers are wrong. John then encourages them to show their true love for God. They are to show it by living good lives and by caring for each other.</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="1JN 1"/>
  <para style="s1">The Word of Life Became a Human Being</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1JN 1:1"/>Here is what we announce to everyone about the Word of life. The Word was already here from the beginning. We have heard him. We have seen him with our eyes. We have looked at him. Our hands have touched him. <verse eid="1JN 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1JN 1:2"/>This life has appeared. We have seen him. We are witnesses about him. And we announce to you this same eternal life. He was already with the Father. He has appeared to us. <verse eid="1JN 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1JN 1:3"/>We announce to you what we have seen and heard. We do it so you can share life together with us. And we share life with the Father and with his Son, Jesus Christ. <verse eid="1JN 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1JN 1:4"/>We are writing this to make our joy complete.<verse eid="1JN 1:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Walking in the Light</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1JN 1:5"/>Here is the message we have heard from him and announce to you. God is light. There is no darkness in him at all. <verse eid="1JN 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1JN 1:6"/>Suppose we say that we share life with God but still walk in the darkness. Then we are lying. We are not living out the truth. <verse eid="1JN 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1JN 1:7"/>But suppose we walk in the light, just as he is in the light. Then we share life with one another. And the blood of Jesus, his Son, makes us pure from all sin.<verse eid="1JN 1:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1JN 1:8"/>Suppose we claim we are without sin. Then we are fooling ourselves. The truth is not in us. <verse eid="1JN 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1JN 1:9"/>But God is faithful and fair. If we confess our sins, he will forgive our sins. He will forgive every wrong thing we have done. He will make us pure. <verse eid="1JN 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1JN 1:10"/>If we claim we have not sinned, we are calling God a liar. His word is not in us.<verse eid="1JN 1:10"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1JN 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="1JN 2"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1JN 2:1"/>My dear children, I’m writing this to you so that you will not sin. But suppose someone does sin. Then we have a friend who speaks to the Father for us. He is Jesus Christ, the Blameless One. <verse eid="1JN 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1JN 2:2"/>He gave his life to pay for our sins. But he not only paid for our sins. He also paid for the sins of the whole world.<verse eid="1JN 2:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Instructions About Loving and Hating Other Believers</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1JN 2:3"/>We know that we have come to know God if we obey his commands. <verse eid="1JN 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1JN 2:4"/>Suppose someone says, “I know him.” But suppose this person does not do what God commands. Then this person is a liar and is not telling the truth. <verse eid="1JN 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1JN 2:5"/>But if anyone obeys God’s word, then that person truly loves God. Here is how we know we belong to him. <verse eid="1JN 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1JN 2:6"/>Those who claim to belong to him must live just as Jesus did.<verse eid="1JN 2:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1JN 2:7"/>Dear friends, I’m not writing you a new command. Instead, I’m writing one you have heard before. You have had it since the beginning. <verse eid="1JN 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1JN 2:8"/>But I am writing what amounts to a new command. Its truth was shown in how Jesus lived. It is also shown in how you live. That’s because the darkness is passing away. And the true light is already shining.<verse eid="1JN 2:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1JN 2:9"/>Suppose someone claims to be in the light but hates a brother or sister. Then they are still in the darkness. <verse eid="1JN 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1JN 2:10"/>Anyone who loves their brother and sister lives in the light. There is nothing in them to make them fall into sin. <verse eid="1JN 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1JN 2:11"/>But anyone who hates a brother or sister is in the darkness. They walk around in the darkness. They don’t know where they are going. The darkness has made them blind.<verse eid="1JN 2:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Reasons for Writing</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1JN 2:12"/>Dear children, I’m writing to you</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1JN 2:12">because your sins have been forgiven.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1JN 2:12">They have been forgiven because of what Jesus has done.<verse eid="1JN 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1JN 2:13"/>Fathers, I’m writing to you</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1JN 2:13">because you know the one who is from the beginning.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1JN 2:13">Young men, I’m writing to you</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1JN 2:13">because you have won the battle over the evil one.<verse eid="1JN 2:13"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1JN 2:14"/>Dear children, I’m writing to you</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1JN 2:14">because you know the Father.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1JN 2:14">Fathers, I’m writing to you</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1JN 2:14">because you know the one who is from the beginning.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1JN 2:14">Young men, I’m writing to you</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1JN 2:14">because you are strong.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1JN 2:14">God’s word lives in you.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1JN 2:14">You have won the battle over the evil one.<verse eid="1JN 2:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Do Not Love the World</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1JN 2:15"/>Do not love the world or anything in it. If anyone loves the world, love for the Father is not in them. <verse eid="1JN 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1JN 2:16"/>Here is what people who belong to this world do. They try to satisfy what their sinful desires want to do. They long for what their sinful eyes look at. They take pride in what they have and what they do. All of this comes from the world. None of it comes from the Father. <verse eid="1JN 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1JN 2:17"/>The world and its evil desires are passing away. But whoever does what God wants them to do lives forever.<verse eid="1JN 2:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Warnings About Saying No to the Son</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1JN 2:18"/>Dear children, we are living in the last days. You have heard that the great enemy of Christ is coming. But even now many enemies of Christ have already come. That’s how we know that these are the last days. <verse eid="1JN 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1JN 2:19"/>These enemies left our community of believers. They didn’t really belong to us. If they had belonged to us, they would have remained with us. But by leaving they showed that none of them belonged to us.<verse eid="1JN 2:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1JN 2:20"/>You have received the Spirit from the Holy One. And all of you know the truth. <verse eid="1JN 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1JN 2:21"/>I’m not writing to you because you don’t know the truth. I’m writing because you do know it. I’m writing to you because no lie comes from the truth. <verse eid="1JN 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1JN 2:22"/>Who is the liar? It is anyone who says that Jesus is not the Christ. The person who says this is the great enemy of Christ. They say no to the Father and the Son. <verse eid="1JN 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1JN 2:23"/>The person who says no to the Son doesn’t belong to the Father. But anyone who says yes to the Son belongs to the Father also.<verse eid="1JN 2:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1JN 2:24"/>Make sure that you don’t forget what you have heard from the beginning. Then you will remain joined to the Son and to the Father. <verse eid="1JN 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1JN 2:25"/>And here is what God has promised us. He has promised us eternal life.<verse eid="1JN 2:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1JN 2:26"/>I’m writing these things to warn you. I am warning you about people trying to lead you astray. <verse eid="1JN 2:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1JN 2:27"/>But you have received the Holy Spirit from God. He continues to live in you. So you don’t need anyone to teach you. God’s Spirit teaches you about everything. What he says is true. He doesn’t lie. Remain joined to Christ, just as you have been taught by the Spirit.<verse eid="1JN 2:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God’s Children and Sin</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1JN 2:28"/>Dear children, remain joined to Christ. Then when he comes, we can be bold. We will not be ashamed to meet him when he comes.<verse eid="1JN 2:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1JN 2:29"/>You know that God is right and always does what is right. And you know that everyone who does what is right is God’s child.<verse eid="1JN 2:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1JN 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="1JN 3"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1JN 3:1"/>See what amazing love the Father has given us! Because of it, we are called children of God. And that’s what we really are! The world doesn’t know us because it didn’t know him. <verse eid="1JN 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1JN 3:2"/>Dear friends, now we are children of God. He still hasn’t let us know what we will be. But we know that when Christ appears, we will be like him. That’s because we will see him as he really is. <verse eid="1JN 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1JN 3:3"/>Christ is pure. All who hope to be like him make themselves pure.<verse eid="1JN 3:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1JN 3:4"/>Everyone who sins breaks the law. In fact, breaking the law is sin. <verse eid="1JN 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1JN 3:5"/>But you know that Christ came to take our sins away. And there is no sin in him. <verse eid="1JN 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1JN 3:6"/>No one who remains joined to him keeps on sinning. No one who keeps on sinning has seen him or known him.<verse eid="1JN 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1JN 3:7"/>Dear children, don’t let anyone lead you astray. The person who does what is right is holy, just as Christ is holy. <verse eid="1JN 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1JN 3:8"/>The person who does what is sinful belongs to the devil. That’s because the devil has been sinning from the beginning. But the Son of God came to destroy the devil’s work. <verse eid="1JN 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1JN 3:9"/>Those who are God’s children will not keep on sinning. God’s very nature remains in them. They can’t go on sinning. That’s because they are God’s children. <verse eid="1JN 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1JN 3:10"/>Here is how you can tell the difference between God’s children and the devil’s children. Anyone who doesn’t do what is right isn’t God’s child. And anyone who doesn’t love their brother or sister isn’t God’s child either.<verse eid="1JN 3:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">More Instructions About Loving and Hating One Another</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1JN 3:11"/>From the beginning we have heard that we should love one another. <verse eid="1JN 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1JN 3:12"/>Don’t be like Cain. He belonged to the evil one. He murdered his brother. And why did he murder him? Because the things Cain had done were wrong. But the things his brother had done were right. <verse eid="1JN 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1JN 3:13"/>My brothers and sisters, don’t be surprised if the world hates you. <verse eid="1JN 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1JN 3:14"/>We know that we have left our old dead way of life. And we have entered into new life. We know this because we love one another. Anyone who doesn’t love still lives in their old condition. <verse eid="1JN 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1JN 3:15"/>Anyone who hates their brother or sister is a murderer. And you know that no murderer has eternal life.<verse eid="1JN 3:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1JN 3:16"/>We know what love is because Jesus Christ gave his life for us. So we should give our lives for our brothers and sisters. <verse eid="1JN 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1JN 3:17"/>Suppose someone sees a brother or sister in need and is able to help them. And suppose that person doesn’t take pity on these needy people. Then how can the love of God be in that person? <verse eid="1JN 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1JN 3:18"/>Dear children, don’t just talk about love. Put your love into action. Then it will truly be love.<verse eid="1JN 3:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1JN 3:19"/>Here’s how we know that we hold to the truth. And here’s how we put our hearts at rest, knowing that God is watching. <verse eid="1JN 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1JN 3:20"/>If our hearts judge us, we know that God is greater than our hearts. And he knows everything. <verse eid="1JN 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1JN 3:21"/>Dear friends, if our hearts do not judge us, we can be bold with God. <verse eid="1JN 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1JN 3:22"/>And he will give us anything we ask. That’s because we obey his commands. We do what pleases him. <verse eid="1JN 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1JN 3:23"/>God has commanded us to believe in the name of his Son, Jesus Christ. He has also commanded us to love one another. <verse eid="1JN 3:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1JN 3:24"/>The one who obeys God’s commands remains joined to him. And he remains joined to them. Here is how we know that God lives in us. We know it because of the Holy Spirit he gave us.<verse eid="1JN 3:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1JN 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="1JN 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Came as a Human Being</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1JN 4:1"/>Dear friends, do not believe every spirit. Test the spirits to see if they belong to God. Many false prophets have gone out into the world. <verse eid="1JN 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1JN 4:2"/>Here is how you can recognize the Spirit of God. Every spirit agreeing that Jesus Christ came in a human body belongs to God. <verse eid="1JN 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1JN 4:3"/>But every spirit that doesn’t agree with this does not belong to God. You have heard that the spirit of the great enemy of Christ is coming. Even now it is already in the world.<verse eid="1JN 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1JN 4:4"/>Dear children, you belong to God. You have not accepted the teachings of the false prophets. That’s because the one who is in you is powerful. He is more powerful than the one who is in the world. <verse eid="1JN 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1JN 4:5"/>False prophets belong to the world. So they speak from the world’s point of view. And the world listens to them. <verse eid="1JN 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1JN 4:6"/>We belong to God. And those who know God listen to us. But those who don’t belong to God don’t listen to us. That’s how we can tell the difference between the Spirit of truth and the spirit of lies.<verse eid="1JN 4:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">We Love Because God Loved Us</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1JN 4:7"/>Dear friends, let us love one another, because love comes from God. Everyone who loves has become a child of God and knows God. <verse eid="1JN 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1JN 4:8"/>Anyone who does not love does not know God, because God is love. <verse eid="1JN 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1JN 4:9"/>Here is how God showed his love among us. He sent his one and only Son into the world. He sent him so we could receive life through him. <verse eid="1JN 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1JN 4:10"/>Here is what love is. It is not that we loved God. It is that he loved us and sent his Son to give his life to pay for our sins. <verse eid="1JN 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1JN 4:11"/>Dear friends, since God loved us this much, we should also love one another. <verse eid="1JN 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1JN 4:12"/>No one has ever seen God. But if we love one another, God lives in us. His love is made complete in us.<verse eid="1JN 4:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1JN 4:13"/>Here’s how we know that we are joined to him and he to us. He has given us his Holy Spirit. <verse eid="1JN 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1JN 4:14"/>The Father has sent his Son to be the Savior of the world. We have seen it and are witnesses to it. <verse eid="1JN 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1JN 4:15"/>God lives in anyone who agrees that Jesus is the Son of God. This kind of person remains joined to God. <verse eid="1JN 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1JN 4:16"/>So we know that God loves us. We depend on it.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1JN 4:16">God is love. Anyone who leads a life of love is joined to God. And God is joined to them. <verse eid="1JN 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1JN 4:17"/>Suppose love is fulfilled among us. Then we can be without fear on the day God judges the world. Love is fulfilled among us when in this world we are like Jesus. <verse eid="1JN 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1JN 4:18"/>There is no fear in love. Instead, perfect love drives away fear. That’s because fear has to do with being punished. The one who fears does not have perfect love.<verse eid="1JN 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1JN 4:19"/>We love because he loved us first. <verse eid="1JN 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1JN 4:20"/>Suppose someone claims to love God but hates a brother or sister. Then they are a liar. They don’t love their brother or sister, whom they have seen. So they can’t love God, whom they haven’t seen. <verse eid="1JN 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1JN 4:21"/>Here is the command God has given us. Anyone who loves God must also love their brother and sister.<verse eid="1JN 4:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1JN 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="1JN 5"/>
  <para style="s1">Faith in God’s Son Who Became a Human Being</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1JN 5:1"/>Everyone who believes that Jesus is the Christ is a child of God. And everyone who loves the Father loves his children as well. <verse eid="1JN 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1JN 5:2"/>Here is how we know that we love God’s children. We know it when we love God and obey his commands. <verse eid="1JN 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1JN 5:3"/>In fact, here is what it means to love God. We love him by obeying his commands. And his commands are not hard to obey. <verse eid="1JN 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1JN 5:4"/>That’s because everyone who is a child of God has won the battle over the world. Our faith has won the battle for us. <verse eid="1JN 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1JN 5:5"/>Who is it that has won the battle over the world? Only the person who believes that Jesus is the Son of God.<verse eid="1JN 5:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1JN 5:6"/>Jesus Christ was born as we are, and he died on the cross. He wasn’t just born as we are. He also died on the cross. The Holy Spirit is a truthful witness about him. That’s because the Spirit is the truth. <verse eid="1JN 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1JN 5:7"/>There are three that are witnesses about Jesus. <verse eid="1JN 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1JN 5:8"/>They are the Holy Spirit, the birth of Jesus, and the death of Jesus. And the three of them agree. <verse eid="1JN 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1JN 5:9"/>We accept what people say when they are witnesses. But it’s more important when God is a witness. That’s because it is what God says about his Son. <verse eid="1JN 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1JN 5:10"/>Whoever believes in the Son of God accepts what God says about him. Whoever does not believe God is calling him a liar. That’s because they have not believed what God said about his Son. <verse eid="1JN 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1JN 5:11"/>Here is what God says about the Son. God has given us eternal life. And this life is found in his Son. <verse eid="1JN 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1JN 5:12"/>Whoever belongs to the Son has life. Whoever doesn’t belong to the Son of God doesn’t have life.<verse eid="1JN 5:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Final Words</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1JN 5:13"/>I’m writing these things to you who believe in the name of the Son of God. I’m writing so you will know that you have eternal life. <verse eid="1JN 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1JN 5:14"/>Here is what we can be sure of when we come to God in prayer. If we ask anything in keeping with what he wants, he hears us. <verse eid="1JN 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1JN 5:15"/>If we know that God hears what we ask for, we know that we have it.<verse eid="1JN 5:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1JN 5:16"/>Suppose you see any brother or sister commit a sin. But this sin is not the kind that leads to death. Then you should pray, and God will give them life. I’m talking about someone whose sin does not lead to death. But there is a sin that does lead to death. I’m not saying you should pray about that sin. <verse eid="1JN 5:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1JN 5:17"/>Every wrong thing we do is sin. But there are sins that do not lead to death.<verse eid="1JN 5:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1JN 5:18"/>We know that those who are children of God do not keep on sinning. The Son of God keeps them safe. The evil one can’t harm them. <verse eid="1JN 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1JN 5:19"/>We know that we are children of God. We know that the whole world is under the control of the evil one. <verse eid="1JN 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1JN 5:20"/>We also know that the Son of God has come. He has given us understanding. So we can know the God who is true. And we belong to the true God by belonging to his Son, Jesus Christ. He is the true God and eternal life.<verse eid="1JN 5:20"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1JN 5:21"/>Dear children, keep away from statues of gods.<verse eid="1JN 5:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1JN 5"/>
</usx>
