<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="1PE" style="id">- New International Readers Version 2014</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1995, 1996, 1998, 2014 by Biblica, Inc.</para>
  <para style="h">1 Peter</para>
  <para style="toc1">1 Peter</para>
  <para style="toc2">1 Peter</para>
  <para style="toc3">1Pe</para>
  <para style="mt1">1 Peter</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">The apostle Peter was one of Jesus’ twelve disciples. Later, Peter traveled to Rome. Peter spent the final years of his life and ministry in Rome. And he became a leader of the church there.</para>
  <para style="ip">Peter learned that churches in other parts of the Roman Empire were experiencing hard times. So he wrote to encourage these believers to remain faithful to Jesus. Peter’s letter was brought to these churches by Silas. Silas was a man who also worked with the apostle Paul. In this letter Peter introduces Silas and explains that Silas helped write the letter.</para>
  <para style="ip">After the opening part, the letter has three main sections. First, Peter tells his readers to be holy in everything they do. As Gentiles they once lived not knowing the ways of God. But now they are a holy nation. They are part of God’s own people. So they are called to a new way of life.</para>
  <para style="ip">Second, Peter explains how this new way of life may affect those who see it. Some people who don’t believe in Jesus may attack believers. But these attackers will see the good lives of the believers.</para>
  <para style="ip">Finally, Peter states that he knows his readers are suffering for their faith. He explains that this is to be expected. Jesus Christ himself experienced suffering. And believers all over the world face suffering. But even in their suffering believers can show they belong to God. Their strength is found in the grace and strength of God through faith in Jesus the Messiah.</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="1PE 1"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1PE 1:1"/>I, Peter, am writing this letter. I am an apostle of Jesus Christ.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="1PE 1:1"/>
  <para style="p" vid="1PE 1:1">I am sending this letter to you, God’s chosen people. You are people who have had to wander in the world. You are scattered all over the areas of Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia and Bithynia. <verse eid="1PE 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1PE 1:2"/>You have been chosen in keeping with what God the Father had planned. That happened through the Spirit’s work to make you pure and holy. God chose you so that you might obey Jesus Christ. God wanted you to be in a covenant relationship with him. He established this relationship by the blood of Christ.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="1PE 1:2"/>
  <para style="p" vid="1PE 1:2">May more and more grace and peace be given to you.<verse eid="1PE 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="s1">Peter Praises God for a Living Hope</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1PE 1:3"/>Give praise to the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ. In his great mercy he has given us a new birth and a living hope. This hope is living because Jesus Christ rose from the dead. <verse eid="1PE 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1PE 1:4"/>He has given us new birth so that we might share in what belongs to him. This is a gift that can never be destroyed. It can never spoil or even fade away. It is kept in heaven for you. <verse eid="1PE 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1PE 1:5"/>Through faith you are kept safe by God’s power. Your salvation is going to be completed. It is ready to be shown to you in the last days. <verse eid="1PE 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1PE 1:6"/>Because you know all this, you have great joy. You have joy even though you may have had to suffer for a little while. You may have had to suffer sadness in all kinds of trouble. <verse eid="1PE 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1PE 1:7"/>Your troubles have come in order to prove that your faith is real. Your faith is worth more than gold. That’s because gold can pass away even when fire has made it pure. Your faith is meant to bring praise, honor and glory to God. This will happen when Jesus Christ returns. <verse eid="1PE 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1PE 1:8"/>Even though you have not seen him, you love him. Though you do not see him now, you believe in him. You are filled with a glorious joy that can’t be put into words. <verse eid="1PE 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1PE 1:9"/>You are receiving the salvation of your souls. This salvation is the final result of your faith.<verse eid="1PE 1:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1PE 1:10"/>The prophets searched very hard and with great care to find out about this salvation. They spoke about the grace that was going to come to you. <verse eid="1PE 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1PE 1:11"/>They wanted to find out when and how this salvation would come. The Spirit of Christ in them was telling them about the sufferings of the Messiah. These were his sufferings that were going to come. The Spirit of Christ was also telling them about the glory that would follow. <verse eid="1PE 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1PE 1:12"/>It was made known to the prophets that they were not serving themselves. Instead, they were serving you when they spoke about the things that you have now heard. Those who have preached the good news to you have told you these things. They have done it with the help of the Holy Spirit sent from heaven. Even angels long to look into these things.<verse eid="1PE 1:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Be Holy</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1PE 1:13"/>So be watchful, and control yourselves completely. In this way, put your hope in the grace that lies ahead. This grace will be brought to you when Jesus Christ returns. <verse eid="1PE 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1PE 1:14"/>You should obey your Father. You shouldn’t give in to evil desires. They controlled your life when you didn’t know any better. <verse eid="1PE 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1PE 1:15"/>The God who chose you is holy. So you should be holy in all that you do. <verse eid="1PE 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1PE 1:16"/>It is written, “Be holy, because I am holy.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="LEV 11:44">Leviticus 11:44</ref>,<ref loc="LEV 11:45">45</ref>; <ref loc="LEV 19:2">19:2</ref>)</char><verse eid="1PE 1:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1PE 1:17"/>You call on a Father who judges each person’s work without favoring one over another. So live as outsiders during your time here. Live with the highest respect for God. <verse eid="1PE 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1PE 1:18"/>You were set free from an empty way of life. This way of life was handed down to you by your own people of long ago. You know that you were not bought with things that can pass away, like silver or gold. <verse eid="1PE 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1PE 1:19"/>Instead, you were bought with the priceless blood of Christ. He is a perfect lamb. He doesn’t have any flaws at all. <verse eid="1PE 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1PE 1:20"/>He was chosen before God created the world. But he came into the world for your sake in these last days. <verse eid="1PE 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1PE 1:21"/>Because of what Christ has done, you believe in God. It was God who raised him from the dead. And it was God who gave him glory. So your faith and hope are in God.<verse eid="1PE 1:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1PE 1:22"/>You have made yourselves pure by obeying the truth. So you have an honest and true love for each other. So love one another deeply, from your hearts. <verse eid="1PE 1:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1PE 1:23"/>You have been born again by means of the living word of God. His word lasts forever. You were not born again from a seed that will die. You were born from a seed that can’t die. <verse eid="1PE 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1PE 1:24"/>It is written,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1PE 1:24">“All people are like grass.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1PE 1:24">All their glory is like the flowers in the field.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1PE 1:24">The grass dries up. The flowers fall to the ground.<verse eid="1PE 1:24"/></para>
  <para style="q2">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1PE 1:25"/>But the word of the Lord lasts forever.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 40:6-8">Isaiah 40:6–8</ref>)</char></para>
  <para style="m" vid="1PE 1:25">And this is the word that was preached to you.<verse eid="1PE 1:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1PE 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="1PE 2"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1PE 2:1"/>So get rid of every kind of evil, and stop telling lies. Don’t pretend to be something you are not. Stop wanting what others have, and don’t speak against one another. <verse eid="1PE 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1PE 2:2"/>Like newborn babies, you should long for the pure milk of God’s word. It will help you grow up as believers. <verse eid="1PE 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1PE 2:3"/>You can do this now that you have tasted how good the Lord is.<verse eid="1PE 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Living Stone and a Chosen People</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1PE 2:4"/>Christ is the living Stone. People did not accept him, but God chose him. God places the highest value on him. <verse eid="1PE 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1PE 2:5"/>You also are like living stones. As you come to Christ, you are being built into a house for worship. There you will be holy priests. You will offer spiritual sacrifices. God will accept them because of what Jesus Christ has done. <verse eid="1PE 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1PE 2:6"/>In Scripture it says,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1PE 2:6">“Look! I am placing a stone in Zion.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1PE 2:6">It is a chosen and very valuable stone.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1PE 2:6">It is the most important stone in the building.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1PE 2:6">The one who trusts in him</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1PE 2:6">will never be put to shame.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 28:16">Isaiah 28:16</ref>)</char><verse eid="1PE 2:6"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1PE 2:7"/>This stone is very valuable to you who believe. But to people who do not believe,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1PE 2:7">“The stone the builders did not accept</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1PE 2:7">has become the most important stone of all.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 118:22">Psalm 118:22</ref>)</char><verse eid="1PE 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1PE 2:8"/>And,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1PE 2:8">“It is a stone that causes people to trip.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1PE 2:8">It is a rock that makes them fall.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 8:14">Isaiah 8:14</ref>)</char></para>
  <para style="m" vid="1PE 2:8">They trip and fall because they do not obey the message. That is also what God planned for them.<verse eid="1PE 2:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1PE 2:9"/>But God chose you to be his people. You are royal priests. You are a holy nation. You are God’s special treasure. You are all these things so that you can give him praise. God brought you out of darkness into his wonderful light. <verse eid="1PE 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1PE 2:10"/>Once you were not a people. But now you are the people of God. Once you had not received mercy. But now you have received mercy.<verse eid="1PE 2:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Living Godly Lives Among People Who Don’t Believe</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1PE 2:11"/>Dear friends, you are outsiders and those who wander in this world. So I’m asking you not to give in to your sinful desires. They fight against your soul. <verse eid="1PE 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1PE 2:12"/>People who don’t believe might say you are doing wrong. But lead good lives among them. Then they will see your good deeds. And they will give glory to God on the day he comes to judge.<verse eid="1PE 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1PE 2:13"/>Follow the lead of every human authority. Do this for the Lord’s sake. Obey the emperor. He is the highest authority. <verse eid="1PE 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1PE 2:14"/>Obey the governors. The emperor sends them to punish those who do wrong. He also sends them to praise those who do right. <verse eid="1PE 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1PE 2:15"/>By doing good you will put a stop to the talk of foolish people. They don’t know what they are saying. <verse eid="1PE 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1PE 2:16"/>Live as free people. But don’t use your freedom to cover up evil. Live as people who are God’s slaves. <verse eid="1PE 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1PE 2:17"/>Show proper respect to everyone. Love the family of believers. Have respect for God. Honor the emperor.<verse eid="1PE 2:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1PE 2:18"/>Slaves, obey your masters out of deep respect for God. Obey not only those who are good and kind. Obey also those who are not kind. <verse eid="1PE 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1PE 2:19"/>Suppose a person suffers pain unfairly because they want to obey God. This is worthy of praise. <verse eid="1PE 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1PE 2:20"/>But suppose you receive a beating for doing wrong, and you put up with it. Will anyone honor you for this? Of course not. But suppose you suffer for doing good, and you put up with it. God will praise you for this. <verse eid="1PE 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1PE 2:21"/>You were chosen to do good even if you suffer. That’s because Christ suffered for you. He left you an example that he expects you to follow. <verse eid="1PE 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1PE 2:22"/>Scripture says,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1PE 2:22">“He didn’t commit any sin.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1PE 2:22">No lies ever came out of his mouth.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 53:9">Isaiah 53:9</ref>)</char><verse eid="1PE 2:22"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1PE 2:23"/>People shouted at him and made fun of him. But he didn’t do the same thing back to them. When he suffered, he didn’t say he would make them suffer. Instead, he trusted in the God who judges fairly. <verse eid="1PE 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1PE 2:24"/>“He himself carried our sins” in his body on the cross. <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 53:5">Isaiah 53:5</ref>)</char> He did it so that we would die as far as sins are concerned. Then we would lead godly lives. “His wounds have healed you.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 53:5">Isaiah 53:5</ref>)</char> <verse eid="1PE 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1PE 2:25"/>“You were like sheep wandering away.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 53:6">Isaiah 53:6</ref>)</char> But now you have returned to the Shepherd. He is the one who watches over your souls.<verse eid="1PE 2:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1PE 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="1PE 3"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1PE 3:1"/>Wives, follow the lead of your own husbands. Suppose some of them don’t believe God’s word. Then let them be won to Christ without words by seeing how their wives behave. <verse eid="1PE 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1PE 3:2"/>Let them see how pure you are. Let them see that your lives are full of respect for God. <verse eid="1PE 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1PE 3:3"/>Fancy hairstyles don’t make you beautiful. Wearing gold jewelry or fine clothes doesn’t make you beautiful. <verse eid="1PE 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1PE 3:4"/>Instead, your beauty comes from inside you. It is the beauty of a gentle and quiet spirit. Beauty like this doesn’t fade away. God places great value on it. <verse eid="1PE 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1PE 3:5"/>This is how the holy women of the past used to make themselves beautiful. They put their hope in God. And they followed the lead of their own husbands. <verse eid="1PE 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1PE 3:6"/>Sarah was like that. She obeyed Abraham. She called him her master. Do you want to be like her? Then do what is right. And don’t give in to fear.<verse eid="1PE 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1PE 3:7"/>Husbands, consider the needs of your wives. They are weaker than you. So treat them with respect. Honor them as those who will share with you the gracious gift of life. Then nothing will stand in the way of your prayers.<verse eid="1PE 3:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Suffering for Doing Good</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1PE 3:8"/>Finally, I want all of you to agree with one another. Be understanding. Love one another. Be kind and tender. Be humble. <verse eid="1PE 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1PE 3:9"/>Don’t pay back evil with evil. Don’t pay back unkind words with unkind words. Instead, pay back evil with kind words. This is what you have been chosen to do. You will receive a blessing by doing this. <verse eid="1PE 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1PE 3:10"/>Scripture says,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1PE 3:10">“Suppose someone wants to love life</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1PE 3:10">and see good days.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1PE 3:10">Then they must keep their tongues from speaking evil.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1PE 3:10">They must keep their lips from telling lies.<verse eid="1PE 3:10"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1PE 3:11"/>They must turn away from evil and do good.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1PE 3:11">They must look for peace and go after it.<verse eid="1PE 3:11"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1PE 3:12"/>The Lord’s eyes look on godly people, and he blesses them.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1PE 3:12">His ears are open to their prayers.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1PE 3:12">But the Lord doesn’t bless those who do evil.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 34:12-16">Psalm 34:12–16</ref>)</char><verse eid="1PE 3:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1PE 3:13"/>Who is going to hurt you if you really want to do good? <verse eid="1PE 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1PE 3:14"/>But suppose you do suffer for doing what is right. Even then you will be blessed. Scripture says, “Don’t fear what others say they will do to hurt you. Don’t be afraid.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 8:12">Isaiah 8:12</ref>)</char> <verse eid="1PE 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1PE 3:15"/>But make sure that in your hearts you honor Christ as Lord. Always be ready to give an answer to anyone who asks you about the hope you have. Be ready to give the reason for it. But do it gently and with respect. <verse eid="1PE 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1PE 3:16"/>Live so that you don’t have to feel you’ve done anything wrong. Some people may say evil things about your good conduct as believers in Christ. If they do, they will be put to shame for speaking like this about you. <verse eid="1PE 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1PE 3:17"/>God may want you to suffer for doing good. That’s better than suffering for doing evil. <verse eid="1PE 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1PE 3:18"/>Christ also suffered once for sins. The one who did what is right suffered for those who don’t do right. He suffered to bring you to God. His body was put to death. But the Holy Spirit brought him back to life. <verse eid="1PE 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1PE 3:19"/>After that, Christ went and made an announcement to the spirits in prison. <verse eid="1PE 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1PE 3:20"/>Long ago these spirits did not obey. That was when God was patient while Noah was building the ark. And only a few people went into the ark. In fact, there were only eight. Those eight people were saved through water. <verse eid="1PE 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1PE 3:21"/>The water of the flood is a picture. It is a picture of the baptism that now saves you too. This baptism has nothing to do with removing dirt from your body. Instead, it promises God that you will keep a clear sense of right and wrong. This baptism saves you by the same power that raised Jesus Christ from the dead. <verse eid="1PE 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1PE 3:22"/>He has gone into heaven. He is at God’s right hand. Angels, authorities and powers are under his control.<verse eid="1PE 3:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1PE 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="1PE 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Living for God</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1PE 4:1"/>Christ suffered in his body. So prepare yourselves to think in the same way Christ did. Do this because whoever suffers in their body is finished with sin. <verse eid="1PE 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1PE 4:2"/>As a result, they don’t live the rest of their earthly life for evil human desires. Instead, they live to do what God wants. <verse eid="1PE 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1PE 4:3"/>You have spent enough time in the past doing what ungodly people choose to do. You lived a wild life. You longed for evil things. You got drunk. You went to wild parties. You worshiped statues of gods, which the Lord hates. <verse eid="1PE 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1PE 4:4"/>Ungodly people are surprised that you no longer join them in what they do. They want you to join them in their wild and wasteful living. So they say bad things about you. <verse eid="1PE 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1PE 4:5"/>But they will have to explain their actions to God. He is ready to judge those who are alive and those who are dead. <verse eid="1PE 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1PE 4:6"/>That’s why the good news was preached even to people who are now dead. It was preached to them for two reasons. It was preached so that their bodies might be judged. This judgment is made by human standards. But the good news was also preached so that their spirits might live. This life comes by means of God’s power.<verse eid="1PE 4:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1PE 4:7"/>The end of all things is near. So be watchful and control yourselves. Then you may pray. <verse eid="1PE 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1PE 4:8"/>Most of all, love one another deeply. Love erases many sins by forgiving them. <verse eid="1PE 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1PE 4:9"/>Welcome others into your homes without complaining. <verse eid="1PE 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1PE 4:10"/>God’s gifts of grace come in many forms. Each of you has received a gift in order to serve others. You should use it faithfully. <verse eid="1PE 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1PE 4:11"/>If anyone speaks, they should do it as one speaking God’s words. If anyone serves, they should do it with the strength God provides. Then in all things God will be praised through Jesus Christ. Glory and power belong to him for ever and ever. Amen.<verse eid="1PE 4:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Suffering for Being a Christian</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1PE 4:12"/>Dear friends, don’t be surprised by the terrible things happening to you. The trouble you are having has come to test you. So don’t feel as if something strange were happening to you. <verse eid="1PE 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1PE 4:13"/>Instead, be joyful that you are taking part in Christ’s sufferings. Then you will have even more joy when Christ returns in glory. <verse eid="1PE 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1PE 4:14"/>Suppose people say bad things about you because you believe in Christ. Then you are blessed, because God’s Spirit rests on you. He is the Spirit of glory. <verse eid="1PE 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1PE 4:15"/>If you suffer, it shouldn’t be because you are a murderer. It shouldn’t be because you are a thief or someone who does evil things. It shouldn’t be because you interfere with other people’s business. <verse eid="1PE 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1PE 4:16"/>But suppose you suffer for being a Christian. Then don’t be ashamed. Instead, praise God because you are known by the name of Christ. <verse eid="1PE 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1PE 4:17"/>It is time for judgment to begin with the household of God. And since it begins with us, what will happen to people who don’t obey God’s good news? <verse eid="1PE 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1PE 4:18"/>Scripture says,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1PE 4:18">“Suppose it is hard for godly people to be saved.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1PE 4:18">Then what will happen to ungodly people and sinners?” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PRO 11:31">Proverbs 11:31</ref>)</char><verse eid="1PE 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1PE 4:19"/>Here is what people who suffer because of God’s plan should do. They should commit themselves to their faithful Creator. And they should continue to do good.<verse eid="1PE 4:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1PE 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="1PE 5"/>
  <para style="s1">To Older and Younger Believers</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1PE 5:1"/>I’m speaking to the elders among you. I was a witness of Christ’s sufferings. And I will also share in the glory that is going to come. I’m making my appeal to you as one who is an elder together with you. <verse eid="1PE 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1PE 5:2"/>Be shepherds of God’s flock, the believers under your care. Watch over them, though not because you have to. Instead, do it because you want to. That’s what God wants you to do. Don’t do it because you want to get money in dishonest ways. Do it because you really want to serve. <verse eid="1PE 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1PE 5:3"/>Don’t act as if you were a ruler over those under your care. Instead, be examples to the flock. <verse eid="1PE 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1PE 5:4"/>The Chief Shepherd will come again. Then you will receive the crown of glory. It is a crown that will never fade away.<verse eid="1PE 5:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1PE 5:5"/>In the same way, I’m speaking to you who are younger. Follow the lead of those who are older. All of you, put on a spirit free of pride toward one another. Put it on as if it were your clothes. Do this because Scripture says,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1PE 5:5">“God opposes those who are proud.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1PE 5:5">But he gives grace to those who are humble.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PRO 3:34">Proverbs 3:34</ref>)</char><verse eid="1PE 5:5"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1PE 5:6"/>So make yourselves humble. Put yourselves under God’s mighty hand. Then he will honor you at the right time. <verse eid="1PE 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1PE 5:7"/>Turn all your worries over to him. He cares about you.<verse eid="1PE 5:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1PE 5:8"/>Be watchful and control yourselves. Your enemy the devil is like a roaring lion. He prowls around looking for someone to swallow up. <verse eid="1PE 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1PE 5:9"/>Stand up to him. Remain strong in what you believe. You know that you are not alone in your suffering. The family of believers throughout the world is going through the same thing.<verse eid="1PE 5:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1PE 5:10"/>God always gives you all the grace you need. So you will only have to suffer for a little while. Then God himself will build you up again. He will make you strong and steady. And he has chosen you to share in his eternal glory because you belong to Christ. <verse eid="1PE 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1PE 5:11"/>Give him the power for ever and ever. Amen.<verse eid="1PE 5:11"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="s1">Final Greetings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1PE 5:12"/>I consider Silas to be a faithful brother. With his help I have written you this short letter. I have written it to encourage you. And I have written to speak the truth about the true grace of God. Remain strong in it.<verse eid="1PE 5:12"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1PE 5:13"/>The members of the church in Babylon send you their greetings. They were chosen together with you. Mark, my son in the faith, also sends you his greetings.<verse eid="1PE 5:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1PE 5:14"/>Greet each other with a kiss of friendship.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="1PE 5:14"/>
  <para style="p" vid="1PE 5:14">May God give peace to all of you who believe in Christ.<verse eid="1PE 5:14"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1PE 5"/>
</usx>
