<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="1SA" style="id">- New International Readers Version 2014</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1995, 1996, 1998, 2014 by Biblica, Inc.</para>
  <para style="h">1 Samuel</para>
  <para style="toc1">1 Samuel</para>
  <para style="toc2">1 Samuel</para>
  <para style="toc3">1Sa</para>
  <para style="mt1">1 Samuel</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="is2">Invitation to Samuel–Kings</para>
  <para style="im">The books of 1 &amp; 2 Samuel and 1 &amp; 2 Kings used to be one long book. They were later separated. That’s because of the length of the old scrolls on which the books were written. A scroll was only long enough to hold part of this big book.</para>
  <para style="ip">These books have a form that repeats itself. The form begins with the age of the king when he began his rule. Then it tells where and how long the king ruled. It gives some facts about this king as a person. And it describes some important events that happened while he ruled.</para>
  <para style="ip">The books of Samuel were named after Samuel the prophet. Samuel was also the last judge to guide the Israelites as a nation. The book of 1 Samuel tells about the birth of Samuel. It ends with the death of King Saul. Saul was Israel’s first king. Saul was chosen by God to be king. At first, Saul followed God’s commands. But later he did not follow God faithfully. So God announces that he will look for another man to rule Israel. God will choose a man who will be faithful to him. The book of 2 Samuel tells about the rule of King David. He was king of Israel after King Saul.</para>
  <para style="ip">God made a promise to King David. God tells David that a member of his family line would always rule in Israel. But they would have to obey God’s rules, laws and commands. The kings that came after David, however, did not always obey God’s commands. Some kings did not lead the Israelites to love God and obey his commands. A few kings did lead the people back to obeying God. But that usually did not last long. This pattern repeated itself over and over again.</para>
  <para style="ip">Finally, God allows powerful nations from the East to take the Israelites away. These strangers take the Israelites away from their homes. They take them as prisoners and slaves to another country. At this point Israel’s story has not gone well. But God has made his promise. He will bring his people back home. God will bring a new king from David’s line. Through Israel he will heal the world.</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="1SA 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Samuel Is Born</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 1:1"/>A certain man from Ramathaim in the hill country of Ephraim was named Elkanah. He was the son of Jeroham. Jeroham was the son of Elihu. Elihu was the son of Tohu. Tohu was the son of Zuph. Elkanah belonged to the family line of Zuph. Elkanah lived in the territory of Ephraim. <verse eid="1SA 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 1:2"/>Elkanah had two wives. One was named Hannah. The other was named Peninnah. Peninnah had children, but Hannah didn’t.<verse eid="1SA 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 1:3"/>Year after year Elkanah went up from his town to Shiloh. He went there to worship and sacrifice to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> who rules over all. Hophni and Phinehas served as priests of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> at Shiloh. They were the two sons of Eli. <verse eid="1SA 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 1:4"/>Every year at Shiloh, the day would come for Elkanah to offer a sacrifice. On that day, he would give a share of the meat to his wife Peninnah. He would also give a share to each of her sons and daughters. <verse eid="1SA 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 1:5"/>But he would give two shares of meat to Hannah. That’s because he loved her. He also gave her two shares because the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had kept her from having children. <verse eid="1SA 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 1:6"/>Peninnah teased Hannah to make her angry. She did it because the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had kept Hannah from having children. <verse eid="1SA 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 1:7"/>Peninnah teased Hannah year after year. Every time Hannah would go up to the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, Elkanah’s other wife would tease her. She would keep doing it until Hannah cried and wouldn’t eat. <verse eid="1SA 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 1:8"/>Her husband Elkanah would say to her, “Hannah, why are you crying? Why don’t you eat? Why are you so unhappy? Don’t I mean more to you than ten sons?”<verse eid="1SA 1:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 1:9"/>One time when they had finished eating and drinking in Shiloh, Hannah stood up. Eli the priest was sitting on his chair by the doorpost of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s house. <verse eid="1SA 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 1:10"/>Hannah was very sad. She wept and wept. She prayed to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="1SA 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 1:11"/>She made a promise to him. She said, “<char style="nd">Lord</char>, you rule over all. Please see how I’m suffering! Show concern for me! Don’t forget about me! Please give me a son! If you do, I’ll give him back to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Then he will serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char> all the days of his life. He’ll never use a razor on his head. He’ll never cut his hair.”<verse eid="1SA 1:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 1:12"/>As Hannah kept on praying to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, Eli watched her lips. <verse eid="1SA 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 1:13"/>She was praying in her heart. Her lips were moving. But she wasn’t making a sound. Eli thought Hannah was drunk. <verse eid="1SA 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 1:14"/>He said to her, “How long are you going to stay drunk? Stop drinking your wine.”<verse eid="1SA 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 1:15"/>“That’s not true, sir,” Hannah replied. “I’m a woman who is deeply troubled. I haven’t been drinking wine or beer. I was telling the <char style="nd">Lord</char> all my troubles. <verse eid="1SA 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 1:16"/>Don’t think of me as an evil woman. I’ve been praying here because I’m very sad. My pain is so great.”<verse eid="1SA 1:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 1:17"/>Eli answered, “Go in peace. May the God of Israel give you what you have asked him for.”<verse eid="1SA 1:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 1:18"/>She said, “May you be pleased with me.” Then she left and had something to eat. Her face wasn’t sad anymore.<verse eid="1SA 1:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 1:19"/>Early the next morning Elkanah and his family got up. They worshiped the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Then they went back to their home in Ramah. Elkanah slept with his wife Hannah. And the <char style="nd">Lord</char> blessed her. <verse eid="1SA 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 1:20"/>So after some time, Hannah became pregnant. She had a baby boy. She said, “I asked the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for him.” So she named him Samuel.<verse eid="1SA 1:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Hannah Gives Samuel to the <char style="nd">Lord </char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 1:21"/>Elkanah went up to Shiloh to offer the yearly sacrifice to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He also went there to keep a promise he had made. His whole family went with him. <verse eid="1SA 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 1:22"/>But Hannah didn’t go. She said to her husband, “When the boy doesn’t need me to breast-feed him anymore, I’ll take him to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s house. I’ll give him to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> there. He’ll stay there for the rest of his life.”<verse eid="1SA 1:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 1:23"/>Her husband Elkanah told her, “Do what you think is best. Stay here at home until Samuel doesn’t need you to breast-feed him anymore. May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> make his promise to you come true.” So Hannah stayed home. She breast-fed her son until he didn’t need her milk anymore.<verse eid="1SA 1:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 1:24"/>When the boy didn’t need her to breast-feed him anymore, she took him with her to Shiloh. She took him there even though he was still very young. She brought him to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s house. She brought along a bull that was three years old. She brought 36 pounds of flour. She also brought a bottle of wine. The bottle was made out of animal skin. <verse eid="1SA 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 1:25"/>After the bull was sacrificed, Elkanah and Hannah brought the boy to Eli. <verse eid="1SA 1:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 1:26"/>Hannah said to Eli, “Pardon me, sir. I’m the woman who stood here beside you praying to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. And that’s just as sure as you are alive. <verse eid="1SA 1:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 1:27"/>I prayed for this child. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has given me what I asked him for. <verse eid="1SA 1:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 1:28"/>So now I’m giving him to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. As long as he lives he’ll be given to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.” And there Eli worshiped the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="1SA 1:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="1SA 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Hannah’s Prayer</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 2:1"/>Then Hannah prayed. She said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:1">“The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has filled my heart with joy.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:1">He has made me strong.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:1">I can laugh at my enemies.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:1">I’m so glad he saved me.<verse eid="1SA 2:1"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 2:2"/>“There isn’t anyone holy like the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:2">There isn’t anyone except him.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:2">There isn’t any Rock like our God.<verse eid="1SA 2:2"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 2:3"/>“Don’t keep talking so proudly.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:3">Don’t let your mouth say such proud things.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:3">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is a God who knows everything.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:3">He judges everything people do.<verse eid="1SA 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 2:4"/>“The bows of great heroes are broken.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:4">But those who trip and fall are made strong.<verse eid="1SA 2:4"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 2:5"/>Those who used to be full have to work for food.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:5">But those who used to be hungry aren’t hungry anymore.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:5">The woman who couldn’t have children has seven of them now.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:5">But the woman who has had many children is sad now because hers have died.<verse eid="1SA 2:5"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 2:6"/>“The <char style="nd">Lord</char> causes people to die. He also gives people life.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:6">He brings people down to the grave. He also brings people up from death.<verse eid="1SA 2:6"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 2:7"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> makes people poor. He also makes people rich.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:7">He brings people down. He also lifts people up.<verse eid="1SA 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 2:8"/>He raises poor people up from the trash pile.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:8">He lifts needy people out of the ashes.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:8">He lets them sit with princes.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:8">He gives them places of honor.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="1SA 2:8"/>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:8">“The foundations of the earth belong to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:8">On them he has set the world.<verse eid="1SA 2:8"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 2:9"/>He guards the paths of his faithful servants.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:9">But evil people will lie silent in their dark graves.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="1SA 2:9"/>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:9">“People don’t win just because they are strong.<verse eid="1SA 2:9"/></para>
  <para style="q2">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 2:10"/>Those who oppose the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will be totally destroyed.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:10">The Most High God will thunder from heaven.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:10">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will judge the earth from one end to the other.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="1SA 2:10"/>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:10">“He will give power to his king.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:10">He will give honor to his anointed one.”<verse eid="1SA 2:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 2:11"/>Then Elkanah went home to Ramah. But the boy Samuel served the <char style="nd">Lord</char> under the direction of Eli the priest.<verse eid="1SA 2:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Eli’s Evil Sons</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 2:12"/>Eli’s sons were good for nothing. They didn’t honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="1SA 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 2:13"/>When any of the people came to offer a sacrifice, here is what the priests would do. While the meat was being boiled, the servant of the priest would come with a large fork in his hand. <verse eid="1SA 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 2:14"/>He would stick the fork into the pan or pot or small or large kettle. Then the priest would take for himself everything the fork brought up. That’s how Eli’s sons treated all the Israelites who came to Shiloh. <verse eid="1SA 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 2:15"/>Even before the fat was burned, the priest’s servant would come over. He would speak to the person who was offering the sacrifice. He would say, “Give the priest some meat to cook. He won’t accept boiled meat from you. He’ll only accept raw meat.”<verse eid="1SA 2:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 2:16"/>Sometimes the person would say to him, “Let the fat be burned first. Then take what you want.” But the servant would answer, “No. Hand it over right now. If you don’t, I’ll take it away from you by force.”<verse eid="1SA 2:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 2:17"/>That sin of Eli’s sons was very great in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s sight. That’s because they were not treating his offering with respect.<verse eid="1SA 2:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 2:18"/>But the boy Samuel served the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He wore a sacred linen apron. <verse eid="1SA 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 2:19"/>Each year his mother made him a little robe. She took it to him when she went up to Shiloh with her husband. She did it when her husband went to offer the yearly sacrifice. <verse eid="1SA 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 2:20"/>Eli would bless Elkanah and his wife. He would say, “May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> give you children by this woman. May they take the place of the boy she prayed for and gave to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.” Then they would go home. <verse eid="1SA 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 2:21"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> was gracious to Hannah. Over a period of years she had three more sons and two daughters. During that whole time the boy Samuel grew up serving the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="1SA 2:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 2:22"/>Eli was very old. He kept hearing about everything his sons were doing to all the Israelites. He also heard how his sons were sleeping with the women who served at the entrance to the tent of meeting. <verse eid="1SA 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 2:23"/>So Eli said to his sons, “Why are you doing these things? All the people are telling me about the evil things you are doing. <verse eid="1SA 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 2:24"/>No, my sons. The report I hear isn’t good. And it’s spreading among the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s people. <verse eid="1SA 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 2:25"/>If a person sins against someone else, God can help that sinner. But if anyone sins against the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, who can help them?” In spite of what their father Eli said, his sons didn’t pay any attention to his warning. That’s because the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had already decided to put them to death.<verse eid="1SA 2:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 2:26"/>The boy Samuel continued to grow stronger. He also became more and more pleasing to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> and to people.<verse eid="1SA 2:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Prophecy Against Eli’s Family</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 2:27"/>A man of God came to Eli. He told him, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> says, ‘I made myself clearly known to your relatives who lived long ago. I did it when they were in Egypt under Pharaoh’s rule. <verse eid="1SA 2:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 2:28"/>At that time, I chose Aaron from your family line to be my priest. I chose him out of all the tribes of Israel. I told him to go up to my altar. I told him to burn incense. I chose him to wear a linen apron when he served me. I also gave his family all the food offerings presented by the Israelites. <verse eid="1SA 2:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 2:29"/>Why don’t you treat my sacrifices and offerings with respect? I require them to be brought to the house where I live. Why do you honor your sons more than me? Why do you fatten yourselves on the best parts of every offering that is made by my people Israel?’<verse eid="1SA 2:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1SA 2:30"/>“The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is the God of Israel. He announced, ‘I promised that members of your family line would serve me as priests forever.’ But now the <char style="nd">Lord</char> announces, ‘I will not let that happen! I will honor those who honor me. But I will turn away from those who look down on me. <verse eid="1SA 2:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1SA 2:31"/>The time is coming when I will cut your life short. I will also cut short the lives of those in your family line of priests. No one in your family line will grow old. <verse eid="1SA 2:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1SA 2:32"/>You will see nothing but trouble in the house where I live. Good things will still happen to Israel. But no one in your family line will ever grow old. <verse eid="1SA 2:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1SA 2:33"/>I will prevent the members of your family from serving me at my altar. I will destroy the eyesight of all of you I allow to live. I will also cause you to lose your strength. And everyone in your family line will die while they are still young.<verse eid="1SA 2:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1SA 2:34"/>“ ‘Something is going to happen to your two sons, Hophni and Phinehas. When it does, it will show you that what I am saying is true. They will both die on the same day. <verse eid="1SA 2:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1SA 2:35"/>I will raise up for myself a faithful priest. He will do what my heart and mind want him to do. I will make his family line of priests very secure. They will always serve as priests to my anointed king. <verse eid="1SA 2:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1SA 2:36"/>Everyone left in your family line will come and bow down to him. They will beg him for a piece of silver and a loaf of bread. They will say, “Please give me a place to serve among the priests. Then I can have food to eat.” ’ ”<verse eid="1SA 2:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="1SA 3"/>
  <para style="s1">The <char style="nd">Lord </char>Calls Out to Samuel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 3:1"/>The boy Samuel served the <char style="nd">Lord</char> under the direction of Eli. In those days the <char style="nd">Lord</char> didn’t give many messages to his people. He didn’t give them many visions.<verse eid="1SA 3:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 3:2"/>One night Eli was lying down in his usual place. His eyes were becoming so weak he couldn’t see very well. <verse eid="1SA 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 3:3"/>Samuel was lying down in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s house. That’s where the ark of God was kept. The lamp of God was still burning. <verse eid="1SA 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 3:4"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> called out to Samuel.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 3:4">Samuel answered, “Here I am.” <verse eid="1SA 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 3:5"/>He ran over to Eli and said, “Here I am. You called out to me.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 3:5">But Eli said, “I didn’t call you. Go back and lie down.” So he went and lay down.<verse eid="1SA 3:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 3:6"/>Again the <char style="nd">Lord</char> called out, “Samuel!” Samuel got up and went to Eli. He said, “Here I am. You called out to me.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 3:6">“My son,” Eli said, “I didn’t call you. Go back and lie down.”<verse eid="1SA 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 3:7"/>Samuel didn’t know the <char style="nd">Lord</char> yet. That’s because the <char style="nd">Lord</char> still hadn’t given him a message.<verse eid="1SA 3:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 3:8"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> called out for the third time. He said, “Samuel!” Samuel got up and went to Eli. He said, “Here I am. You called out to me.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 3:8">Then Eli realized that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> was calling the boy. <verse eid="1SA 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 3:9"/>So Eli told Samuel, “Go and lie down. If someone calls out to you again, say, ‘Speak, <char style="nd">Lord</char>. I’m listening.’ ” So Samuel went and lay down in his place.<verse eid="1SA 3:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 3:10"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> came and stood there. He called out, just as he had done the other times. He said, “Samuel! Samuel!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 3:10">Then Samuel replied, “Speak. I’m listening.”<verse eid="1SA 3:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 3:11"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Samuel, “Pay attention! I am about to do something terrible in Israel. It will make the ears of everyone who hears about it tingle. <verse eid="1SA 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 3:12"/>At that time I will do everything to Eli and his family that I said I would. I will finish what I have started. <verse eid="1SA 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 3:13"/>I told Eli I would punish his family forever. He knew his sons were sinning. He knew they were saying bad things about me. In spite of that, he did not stop them. <verse eid="1SA 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 3:14"/>So I made a promise to the family of Eli. I said, ‘The sins of Eli’s family will never be paid for by bringing sacrifices or offerings.’ ”<verse eid="1SA 3:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 3:15"/>Samuel lay down until morning. Then he opened the doors of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s house. He was afraid to tell Eli about the vision he had received. <verse eid="1SA 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 3:16"/>But Eli called out to him. He said, “Samuel, my son.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 3:16">Samuel answered, “Here I am.”<verse eid="1SA 3:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 3:17"/>“What did the <char style="nd">Lord</char> say to you?” Eli asked. “Don’t hide from me anything he told you. If you do, may God punish you greatly.” <verse eid="1SA 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 3:18"/>So Samuel told him everything. He didn’t hide anything from him. Then Eli said, “He is the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Let him do what he thinks is best.”<verse eid="1SA 3:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 3:19"/>As Samuel grew up, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> was with him. He made everything Samuel said come true. <verse eid="1SA 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 3:20"/>So all the Israelites recognized that Samuel really was a prophet of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Everyone from Dan all the way to Beersheba knew it. <verse eid="1SA 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 3:21"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> continued to appear at Shiloh. There he made himself known to Samuel through the messages he gave him.<verse eid="1SA 3:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="1SA 4"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 4:1"/>And Samuel gave those messages to all the Israelites.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="1SA 4:1">The Philistines Capture the Ark</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 4:1">The Israelites went out to fight against the Philistines. The Israelites camped at Ebenezer. The Philistines camped at Aphek. <verse eid="1SA 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 4:2"/>The Philistines brought their forces together to fight against Israel. As the fighting spread, the Israelites lost the battle to the Philistines. The Philistines killed about 4,000 of them on the field of battle. <verse eid="1SA 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 4:3"/>The rest of the Israelite soldiers returned to camp. Then the elders asked them, “Why did the <char style="nd">Lord</char> let the Philistines win the battle over us today? Let’s bring the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s covenant from Shiloh. Let’s take it with us. Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will save us from the power of our enemies.”<verse eid="1SA 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 4:4"/>So the people sent men to Shiloh. They brought back the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s covenant law. He sits there on his throne between the cherubim. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is the one who rules over all. Eli’s two sons, Hophni and Phinehas, were with the ark of God’s covenant law. The ark was in Shiloh.<verse eid="1SA 4:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 4:5"/>The ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s covenant law was brought into the camp. Then all the Israelites shouted so loudly that the ground shook. <verse eid="1SA 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 4:6"/>The Philistines heard the noise. They asked, “What’s all that shouting about in the Hebrew camp?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 4:6">Then the Philistines found out that the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had come into the camp. <verse eid="1SA 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 4:7"/>So they were afraid. “A god has come into their camp,” they said. “Oh no! Nothing like this has ever happened before. <verse eid="1SA 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 4:8"/>How terrible it will be for us! Who will save us from the power of these mighty gods? They struck down the people of Egypt in the desert. They sent all kinds of plagues on them. <verse eid="1SA 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 4:9"/>Philistines, be strong! Fight like men! If you don’t, you will come under the control of the Hebrews. You will become their slaves, just as they have been your slaves. Fight like men!”<verse eid="1SA 4:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 4:10"/>So the Philistines fought. The Israelites lost the battle, and every man ran back to his tent. A large number of them were killed. Israel lost 30,000 soldiers who were on foot. <verse eid="1SA 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 4:11"/>The ark of God was captured. And Eli’s two sons Hophni and Phinehas died.<verse eid="1SA 4:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Eli Dies</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 4:12"/>That same day a man from the tribe of Benjamin ran from the front lines of the battle. He went to Shiloh. His clothes were torn. He had dust on his head. <verse eid="1SA 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 4:13"/>When he arrived, there was Eli sitting on his chair. He was by the side of the road. He was watching because his heart was really concerned about the ark of God. The man entered the town and told everyone what had happened. Then the whole town cried out.<verse eid="1SA 4:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 4:14"/>Eli heard the people crying out. He asked, “What’s the meaning of all this noise?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 4:14">The man hurried over to Eli. <verse eid="1SA 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 4:15"/>Eli was 98 years old. His eyes were so bad he couldn’t see. <verse eid="1SA 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 4:16"/>The man told Eli, “I’ve just come from the front lines of the battle. I just ran away from there today.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 4:16">Eli asked, “What happened, son?”<verse eid="1SA 4:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 4:17"/>The man who brought the news replied, “Israel ran away from the Philistines. Large numbers of men in the army were wounded or killed. Your two sons Hophni and Phinehas are also dead. And the ark of God has been captured.”<verse eid="1SA 4:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 4:18"/>When the man spoke about the ark of God, Eli fell backward off his chair. He had been sitting by the side of the gate. When he fell, he broke his neck and died. He was old and fat. He had led Israel for 40 years.<verse eid="1SA 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 4:19"/>The wife of Phinehas was pregnant. She was Eli’s daughter-in-law. It was near the time for her baby to be born. She heard the news that the ark of God had been captured. She heard that her father-in-law and her husband were dead. So she went into labor and had her baby. Her pain was more than she could bear. <verse eid="1SA 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 4:20"/>As she was dying, the women helping her spoke up. They said, “Don’t be afraid. You have had a son.” But she didn’t reply. She didn’t pay any attention.<verse eid="1SA 4:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 4:21"/>She named the boy Ichabod. She said, “The God of glory has left Israel.” She said it because the ark of God had been captured. She also said it because her father-in-law and her husband had died. <verse eid="1SA 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 4:22"/>She said, “The God of glory has left Israel.” She said it because the ark of God had been captured.<verse eid="1SA 4:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="1SA 5"/>
  <para style="s1">The Ark in Ashdod and Ekron</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 5:1"/>The Philistines had captured the ark of God. They took it from Ebenezer to Ashdod. <verse eid="1SA 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 5:2"/>They carried the ark into the temple of their god Dagon. They set it down beside the statue of Dagon. <verse eid="1SA 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 5:3"/>The people of Ashdod got up early the next day. They saw the statue of Dagon. There it was, lying on the ground! It had fallen on its face in front of the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. So they picked up the statue of Dagon. They put it back in its place. <verse eid="1SA 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 5:4"/>But the following morning when they got up, they saw the statue of Dagon. There it was, lying on the ground again! It had fallen on its face in front of the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Its head and hands had been broken off. Only the body of the statue was left. Its head and hands were lying in the doorway of the temple. <verse eid="1SA 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 5:5"/>That’s why to this day no one steps on the bottom part of the doorway of Dagon’s temple at Ashdod. Not even the priests of Dagon step there.<verse eid="1SA 5:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 5:6"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s power was against the people of Ashdod and the settlements near it. He destroyed them. He made them suffer with growths in their bodies. <verse eid="1SA 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 5:7"/>The people of Ashdod saw what was happening. They said, “The ark of the god of Israel must not stay here with us. His power is against us and against our god Dagon.” <verse eid="1SA 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 5:8"/>So they called together all the rulers of the Philistines. They asked them, “What should we do with the ark of the god of Israel?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 5:8">The rulers answered, “Have the ark moved to Gath.” So they moved it.<verse eid="1SA 5:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 5:9"/>But after the people of Ashdod had moved the ark, the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s power was against Gath. That threw its people into a great panic. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> made them break out with growths in their bodies. It happened to young people and old people alike. <verse eid="1SA 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 5:10"/>So the ark of God was sent to Ekron.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 5:10">As the ark was entering Ekron, the people of the city cried out. They shouted, “They’ve brought the ark of the god of Israel to us. They want to kill us and our people.” <verse eid="1SA 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 5:11"/>So they called together all the rulers of the Philistines. They said, “Send the ark of the god of Israel away. Let it go back to its own place. If you don’t, it will kill us and our people.” The death of so many people had filled the city with panic. God’s power was against the city. <verse eid="1SA 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 5:12"/>Those who didn’t die suffered with growths in their bodies. The people of Ekron cried out to heaven for help.<verse eid="1SA 5:12"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="1SA 6"/>
  <para style="s1">The Philistines Return the Ark to Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 6:1"/>The ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had been in Philistine territory for seven months. <verse eid="1SA 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 6:2"/>The Philistines called for the priests and for those who practice evil magic. They wanted their advice. They said to them, “What should we do with the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>? Tell us how we should send it back to its place.”<verse eid="1SA 6:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 6:3"/>They answered, “If you return the ark of the god of Israel, don’t send it back to him without a gift. Be sure you send a guilt offering to their god along with it. Then you will be healed. You will find out why his power has continued to be against you.”<verse eid="1SA 6:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 6:4"/>The Philistines asked, “What guilt offering should we send to him?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 6:4">Their advisers replied, “There are five Philistine rulers. So send five gold rats. Also send five gold models of the growths in your bodies. Do it because the same plague has struck you and your rulers alike. <verse eid="1SA 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 6:5"/>Make models of the rats and the growths that are destroying the country. Give honor to Israel’s god. Then perhaps his power will no longer be against you, your gods and your land. <verse eid="1SA 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 6:6"/>Why are you stubborn, as Pharaoh and the people of Egypt were? Israel’s god was very hard on them. Only then did they send the Israelites out. Only then did they let them go on their way.<verse eid="1SA 6:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 6:7"/>“Now then, get a new cart ready. Get two cows that have just had calves. Be sure the cows have never pulled a cart before. Tie the cart to them. But take their calves away and put them in a pen. <verse eid="1SA 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 6:8"/>Then put the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> on the cart. Put the gold models in a chest beside the ark. Send them back to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as a guilt offering. Send the cart on its way. <verse eid="1SA 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 6:9"/>But keep an eye on the cart. See if it goes up toward Beth Shemesh to its own territory. If it does, then it’s the <char style="nd">Lord</char> who has brought this horrible trouble on us. But if it doesn’t, then we’ll know it wasn’t his hand that struck us. We’ll know it happened to us by chance.”<verse eid="1SA 6:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 6:10"/>So that’s what they did. They took the two cows and tied the cart to them. They put the calves in a pen. <verse eid="1SA 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 6:11"/>They placed the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> on the cart. They put the chest there along with it. The chest held the gold models of the rats and of the growths. <verse eid="1SA 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 6:12"/>Then the cows went straight up toward Beth Shemesh. They stayed on the road. They were mooing all the way. They didn’t turn to the right or the left. The Philistine rulers followed them all the way to the border of Beth Shemesh.<verse eid="1SA 6:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 6:13"/>The people of Beth Shemesh were working in the valley. They were gathering their wheat crop. They looked up and saw the ark. When they saw it, they were filled with joy. <verse eid="1SA 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 6:14"/>The cart came to the field of Joshua of Beth Shemesh. It stopped there beside a large rock. The people chopped up the wood the cart was made out of. They sacrificed the cows as a burnt offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="1SA 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 6:15"/>Some Levites had taken the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> off the cart. They had also taken off the chest that held the gold models. They placed them on the large rock. On that day the people of Beth Shemesh offered burnt offerings to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They also made sacrifices to him. <verse eid="1SA 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 6:16"/>The five Philistine rulers saw everything that happened. On that same day they returned to Ekron.<verse eid="1SA 6:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 6:17"/>The Philistines sent gold models of growths as a guilt offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. There was one each for Ashdod, Gaza, Ashkelon, Gath and Ekron. <verse eid="1SA 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 6:18"/>They also sent five gold models of rats. There was one for each of the Philistine towns that belonged to the five rulers. Each of those towns had high walls around it. The towns also had country villages around them. The Levites set the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> on the large rock. To this day the rock is a witness to what happened there. It’s in the field of Joshua of Beth Shemesh.<verse eid="1SA 6:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 6:19"/>But some of the people of Beth Shemesh looked into the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. So he struck them down. He put 70 of them to death. The rest of the people were filled with sorrow. That’s because the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had killed so many of them. <verse eid="1SA 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 6:20"/>The people of Beth Shemesh said, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is a holy God. Who can stand in front of him? Where can the ark go up to from here?”<verse eid="1SA 6:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 6:21"/>Then messengers were sent to the people of Kiriath Jearim. The messengers said, “The Philistines have returned the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Come down and take it up to your town.”<verse eid="1SA 6:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="1SA 7"/>
  <para style="nb">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 7:1"/>So the men of Kiriath Jearim came and got the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They brought it up to Abinadab’s house on the hill. They set his son Eleazar apart to guard the ark. <verse eid="1SA 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 7:2"/>The ark remained at Kiriath Jearim for a long time. It was there for a full 20 years.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="1SA 7:2">Samuel Brings the Philistines Under Israel’s Control</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 7:2">Then all the Israelites turned back to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="1SA 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 7:3"/>So Samuel spoke to all the Israelites. He said, “Do you really want to return to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> with all your hearts? If you do, get rid of your false gods. Get rid of your statues of female gods that are named Ashtoreth. Commit yourselves to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Serve him only. Then he will save you from the power of the Philistines.” <verse eid="1SA 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 7:4"/>So the Israelites put away their statues of gods that were named Baal. They put away their statues of female gods that were named Ashtoreth. They served the <char style="nd">Lord</char> only.<verse eid="1SA 7:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 7:5"/>Then Samuel said, “Gather all the Israelites together at Mizpah. I will pray to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for you.” <verse eid="1SA 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 7:6"/>When the people had come together at Mizpah, they went to the well and got water. They poured it out in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. On that day they didn’t eat any food. They admitted they had sinned. They said, “We’ve sinned against the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.” Samuel was serving as the leader of Israel at Mizpah.<verse eid="1SA 7:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 7:7"/>The Philistines heard that Israel had gathered together at Mizpah. So the Philistine rulers came up to attack them. When the Israelites heard about it, they were afraid. <verse eid="1SA 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 7:8"/>They said to Samuel, “Don’t stop crying out to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God to help us. Keep praying that he’ll save us from the power of the Philistines.” <verse eid="1SA 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 7:9"/>Then Samuel got a very young lamb. He sacrificed it as a whole burnt offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He cried out to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> to help Israel. And the <char style="nd">Lord</char> answered his prayer.<verse eid="1SA 7:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 7:10"/>The Philistines came near to attack Israel. At that time Samuel was sacrificing the burnt offering. But that day the <char style="nd">Lord</char> thundered loudly against the Philistines. He threw them into such a panic that the Israelites were able to chase them away. <verse eid="1SA 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 7:11"/>The men of Israel rushed out of Mizpah. They chased the Philistines all the way to a point below Beth Kar. They killed them all along the way.<verse eid="1SA 7:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 7:12"/>Then Samuel got a big stone. He set it up between Mizpah and Shen. He named it Ebenezer. He said, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has helped us every step of the way.”<verse eid="1SA 7:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 7:13"/>So the Philistines were brought under Israel’s control. The Philistines didn’t attack their territory again. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> used his power against the Philistines as long as Samuel lived. <verse eid="1SA 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 7:14"/>The Philistines had captured many towns between Ekron and Gath. But they had to give all of them back. Israel took back the territories near those towns from the control of the Philistines. During that time Israel and the Amorites were friendly toward each other.<verse eid="1SA 7:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 7:15"/>Samuel continued to lead Israel all the days of his life. <verse eid="1SA 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 7:16"/>From year to year he traveled from Bethel to Gilgal to Mizpah. He served Israel as judge in all those places. <verse eid="1SA 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 7:17"/>But he always went back to Ramah. That’s where his home was. He served Israel as judge there too. And he built an altar there to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="1SA 7:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="1SA 8"/>
  <para style="s1">Israel Asks for a King</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 8:1"/>When Samuel became old, he appointed his sons as Israel’s leaders. <verse eid="1SA 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 8:2"/>The name of his oldest son was Joel. The name of his second son was Abijah. They served as judges at Beersheba. <verse eid="1SA 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 8:3"/>But his sons didn’t live as he did. They were only interested in making money. They accepted money from people who wanted special favors. They made things that were wrong appear to be right.<verse eid="1SA 8:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 8:4"/>So all the elders of Israel gathered together. They came to Samuel at Ramah. <verse eid="1SA 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 8:5"/>They said to him, “You are old. Your sons don’t live as you do. So appoint a king to lead us. We want a king just like the kings all the other nations have.”<verse eid="1SA 8:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 8:6"/>Samuel wasn’t pleased when they said, “Give us a king to lead us.” So he prayed to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="1SA 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 8:7"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> told him, “Listen to everything the people are saying to you. You are not the one they have turned their backs on. I am the one they do not want as their king. <verse eid="1SA 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 8:8"/>They are doing just as they have always done. They have deserted me and served other gods. They have done that from the time I brought them up out of Egypt until this day. Now they are deserting you too. <verse eid="1SA 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 8:9"/>Let them have what they want. But give them a strong warning. Let them know what the king who rules over them will expect to be done for him.”<verse eid="1SA 8:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 8:10"/>Samuel told the people who were asking him for a king everything the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had said. <verse eid="1SA 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 8:11"/>Samuel told them, “Here’s what the king who rules over you will expect to be done for him. He will take your sons. He’ll make them serve with his chariots and horses. They will run in front of his chariots. <verse eid="1SA 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 8:12"/>He’ll choose some of your sons to be commanders of thousands of men. Some will be commanders of fifties. Others will have to plow his fields and gather his crops. Still others will have to make weapons of war and parts for his chariots. <verse eid="1SA 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 8:13"/>He’ll also take your daughters. Some will have to make perfume. Others will be forced to cook and bake. <verse eid="1SA 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 8:14"/>He will take away your best fields and vineyards and olive groves. He’ll give them to his attendants. <verse eid="1SA 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 8:15"/>He will take a tenth of your grain and a tenth of your grapes. He’ll give it to his officials and attendants. <verse eid="1SA 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 8:16"/>He will also take your male and female servants. He’ll take your best cattle and donkeys. He’ll use all of them any way he wants to. <verse eid="1SA 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 8:17"/>He will take a tenth of your sheep and goats. You yourselves will become his slaves. <verse eid="1SA 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 8:18"/>When that time comes, you will cry out for help because of the king you have chosen. But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> won’t answer you at that time.”<verse eid="1SA 8:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 8:19"/>In spite of what Samuel said, the people refused to listen to him. “No!” they said. “We want a king to rule over us. <verse eid="1SA 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 8:20"/>Then we’ll be like all the other nations. We’ll have a king to lead us. He’ll go out at the head of our armies and fight our battles.”<verse eid="1SA 8:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 8:21"/>Samuel heard everything the people said. He told the <char style="nd">Lord</char> about it. <verse eid="1SA 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 8:22"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> answered, “Listen to them. Give them a king.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 8:22">Then Samuel said to the Israelites, “Each of you go back to your own town.”<verse eid="1SA 8:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="1SA 9"/>
  <para style="s1">Samuel Anoints Saul to Be Israel’s King</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 9:1"/>There was a man named Kish from the tribe of Benjamin. Kish was a very important person. He was the son of Abiel, the son of Zeror. Zeror was the son of Bekorath, the son of Aphiah from the tribe of Benjamin. <verse eid="1SA 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 9:2"/>Kish had a son named Saul. Saul was a handsome young man. He was more handsome than anyone in Israel. And he was a head taller than anyone else.<verse eid="1SA 9:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 9:3"/>The donkeys that belonged to Saul’s father Kish were lost. So Kish spoke to his son Saul. He said, “Go and look for the donkeys. Take one of the servants with you.” <verse eid="1SA 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 9:4"/>Saul and his servant went through the hill country of Ephraim. They also went through the area around Shalisha. But they didn’t find the donkeys. So they went on into the area of Shaalim. But the donkeys weren’t there either. Then Saul went through the territory of Benjamin. But they still didn’t find the donkeys.<verse eid="1SA 9:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 9:5"/>When Saul and the servant with him reached the area of Zuph, Saul spoke to the servant. He said, “Come on. Let’s go back. If we don’t, my father will stop thinking about the donkeys. Instead, he’ll start worrying about us.”<verse eid="1SA 9:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 9:6"/>But the servant replied, “There’s a man of God here in Ramah. People have a lot of respect for him. Everything he says comes true. So let’s go and see him now. Perhaps he’ll tell us which way to go.”<verse eid="1SA 9:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 9:7"/>Saul said to his servant, “If we go to see the man, what can we give him? There isn’t any food in our sacks. We don’t have a gift for the man of God. So what can we give him?”<verse eid="1SA 9:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 9:8"/>The servant answered Saul again. “Look,” he said. “I’ve got a tenth of an ounce of silver. I’ll give it to the man of God. Then maybe he’ll tell us which way to go.” <verse eid="1SA 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 9:9"/>In Israel, prophets used to be called seers. So if someone wanted to ask God for advice, they would say, “Come on. Let’s go to the seer.”<verse eid="1SA 9:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 9:10"/>Saul said to his servant, “That’s a good idea. Come on. Let’s go and ask the seer.” So they started out for the town where the man of God lived.<verse eid="1SA 9:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 9:11"/>They were going up the hill toward the town. Along the way they met some young women who were coming out to get water from the well. Saul and his servant asked them, “Is the seer here?”<verse eid="1SA 9:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 9:12"/>“Yes, he is,” they answered. “In fact, he’s just up ahead of you. So hurry along. He has just come to our town today. The people are going to offer a sacrifice at the high place where they worship. <verse eid="1SA 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 9:13"/>As soon as you enter the town, you will find him. He’ll be there until he goes up to the high place to eat. The people won’t start eating until he gets there. He must bless the sacrifice first. After that, those who are invited will eat. So go on up. You should find him there just about now.”<verse eid="1SA 9:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 9:14"/>They went up to the town. As they were entering it, they saw Samuel. He was coming toward them. He was on his way up to the high place.<verse eid="1SA 9:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 9:15"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> had spoken to Samuel the day before Saul came. He had said, <verse eid="1SA 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 9:16"/>“About this time tomorrow I will send you a man. He is from the land of Benjamin. Anoint him to be the king of my people Israel. He will save them from the power of the Philistines. I have seen how much my people are suffering. Their cry for help has reached me.”<verse eid="1SA 9:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 9:17"/>When Samuel saw a man coming toward him, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Samuel again. He said, “He is the man I told you about. His name is Saul. He will govern my people.”<verse eid="1SA 9:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 9:18"/>Saul approached Samuel at the gate of the town. He asked Samuel, “Can you please show me the seer’s house?”<verse eid="1SA 9:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 9:19"/>“I’m the seer,” Samuel replied. “Go on up to the high place ahead of me. I want you and your servant to eat with me today. Tomorrow morning I’ll tell you what’s on your mind. Then I’ll send you on your way. <verse eid="1SA 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 9:20"/>Don’t worry about the donkeys you lost three days ago. They’ve already been found. But who do all the Israelites want? You and your father’s whole family!”<verse eid="1SA 9:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 9:21"/>Saul answered, “But I’m from the tribe of Benjamin. It’s the smallest tribe in Israel. And my family group is the least important in the whole tribe of Benjamin. So why are you saying that to me?”<verse eid="1SA 9:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 9:22"/>Then Samuel brought Saul and his servant into the room where they would be eating. He seated them at the head table. About 30 people had been invited. <verse eid="1SA 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 9:23"/>Samuel said to the cook, “Bring the piece of meat I gave you. It’s the one I told you to put to one side.”<verse eid="1SA 9:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 9:24"/>So the cook went and got a choice piece of thigh. He set it in front of Saul. Samuel said, “Here is what has been kept for you. Eat it. It was put to one side for you for this special occasion. We’ve saved it for you ever since I invited the guests.” And Saul ate with Samuel that day.<verse eid="1SA 9:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 9:25"/>They came down from the high place to the town. After that, Samuel talked with Saul on the roof of Samuel’s house. <verse eid="1SA 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 9:26"/>The next day they got up at about the time the sun was rising. Samuel called out to Saul on the roof. He said, “Get ready. Then I’ll send you on your way.” So Saul got ready. And he and Samuel went outside together. <verse eid="1SA 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 9:27"/>As they were on their way down to the edge of town, Samuel spoke to Saul. He said, “Tell the servant to go ahead of us.” So the servant went on ahead. Then Samuel continued, “Stay here for a while. I’ll give you a message from God.”<verse eid="1SA 9:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="1SA 10"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 10:1"/>Then Samuel took a bottle of olive oil. He poured it on Saul’s head and kissed him. He said, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has anointed you to be the king of his people. <verse eid="1SA 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 10:2"/>When you leave me today, you will meet two men. They will be near Rachel’s tomb at Zelzah on the border of Benjamin. They’ll say to you, ‘The donkeys you have been looking for have been found. Now your father has stopped thinking about them. Instead, he’s worried about you. He’s asking, “What can I do to find my son?” ’<verse eid="1SA 10:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 10:3"/>“You will go on from Zelzah until you come to the large tree at Tabor. Three men will meet you there. They’ll be on their way up to Bethel to worship God. One of them will be carrying three young goats. Another will be carrying three loaves of bread. A third will be carrying a bottle of wine. It will be a bottle made out of animal skin. <verse eid="1SA 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 10:4"/>The men will greet you. They’ll offer you two loaves of bread. You will accept the loaves from them.<verse eid="1SA 10:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 10:5"/>“After that, you will go to Gibeah of God. Some Philistine soldiers are stationed there. As you approach the town, you will meet a group of prophets. They’ll be coming down from the high place where they worship. People will be playing lyres, tambourines, flutes and harps at the head of the group. The prophets will be prophesying. <verse eid="1SA 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 10:6"/>The Spirit of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will come powerfully on you. Then you will prophesy along with them. You will become a different person. <verse eid="1SA 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 10:7"/>All these things will happen. Then do what you want to do. God is with you.<verse eid="1SA 10:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 10:8"/>“Go down ahead of me to Gilgal. You can be sure that I’ll come down to you there. I’ll come and sacrifice burnt offerings and friendship offerings. But you must wait there for seven days until I come to you. Then I’ll tell you what to do.”<verse eid="1SA 10:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Saul Becomes King of Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 10:9"/>As Saul turned to leave Samuel, God changed Saul’s heart. All these things happened that day. <verse eid="1SA 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 10:10"/>When Saul and his servant arrived at Gibeah, a group of prophets met Saul. Then the Spirit of God came powerfully on him. He prophesied along with them. <verse eid="1SA 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 10:11"/>Those who had known Saul before saw him prophesying with the prophets. They asked one another, “What has happened to the son of Kish? Is Saul also one of the prophets?”<verse eid="1SA 10:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 10:12"/>A man who lived in Gibeah answered, “Yes, he is. In fact, he’s their leader.” That’s why people say, “Is Saul also one of the prophets?” <verse eid="1SA 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 10:13"/>After Saul stopped prophesying, he went to the high place to worship.<verse eid="1SA 10:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 10:14"/>Later, Saul’s uncle spoke to him and his servant. He asked, “Where have you been?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 10:14">“Looking for the donkeys,” Saul said. “But we couldn’t find them. So we went to Samuel.”<verse eid="1SA 10:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 10:15"/>Saul’s uncle said, “Tell me what Samuel said to you.”<verse eid="1SA 10:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 10:16"/>Saul replied, “He told us the donkeys had been found.” But Saul didn’t tell his uncle that Samuel had said he would become king.<verse eid="1SA 10:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 10:17"/>Samuel sent a message to the Israelites. He told them to meet with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> at Mizpah. <verse eid="1SA 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 10:18"/>He said to them, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is the God of Israel. He says, ‘Israel, I brought you up out of Egypt. I saved you from their power. I also saved you from the power of all the kingdoms that had treated you badly.’ <verse eid="1SA 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 10:19"/>But now you have turned your backs on your God. He saves you out of all your trouble and suffering. In spite of that, you have said, ‘We refuse to listen. Place a king over us.’ So now gather together to meet with the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Do it tribe by tribe and family group by family group.”<verse eid="1SA 10:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 10:20"/>Then Samuel had each tribe of Israel come forward. The tribe of Benjamin was chosen by casting lots. <verse eid="1SA 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 10:21"/>Next he had the tribe of Benjamin come forward, family group by family group. Matri’s group was chosen. Finally Saul, the son of Kish, was chosen. But when people looked for him, they realized he wasn’t there. <verse eid="1SA 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 10:22"/>They needed more help from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. So they asked him, “Has the man come here yet?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 10:22">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said, “Yes. He has hidden himself among the supplies.”<verse eid="1SA 10:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 10:23"/>So they ran over there and brought him out. When he stood up, the people saw that he was a head taller than any of them. <verse eid="1SA 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 10:24"/>Samuel spoke to all the people. He said, “Look at the man the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has chosen! There isn’t anyone like him among all the people.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 10:24">Then the people shouted, “May the king live a long time!”<verse eid="1SA 10:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 10:25"/>Samuel explained to the people the rights and duties of the king who ruled over them. He wrote them down in a book. He placed it in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> in the holy tent. Then he sent the people away. He sent each of them to their own homes.<verse eid="1SA 10:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 10:26"/>Saul also went to his home in Gibeah. Some brave men whose hearts God had touched went with Saul. <verse eid="1SA 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 10:27"/>But some people who wanted to stir up trouble said, “How can this fellow save us?” They looked down on him. They didn’t bring him any gifts. But Saul kept quiet about it.<verse eid="1SA 10:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="1SA 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Saul Rescues the City of Jabesh Gilead</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 11:1"/>Nahash was the king of Ammon. He and his army went up to Jabesh Gilead. They surrounded it and got ready to attack it. All the men of Jabesh spoke to Nahash. They said, “Make a peace treaty with us. Then we’ll be under your control.”<verse eid="1SA 11:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 11:2"/>Nahash, the king of Ammon, replied, “I will make a peace treaty with you. But I’ll do it only on one condition. You must let me put out the right eye of every one of you. I want to bring shame on the whole nation of Israel.”<verse eid="1SA 11:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 11:3"/>The elders of Jabesh said to him, “Give us seven days to report back to you. We’ll send messengers all through Israel. If no one comes to save us, we’ll hand ourselves over to you.”<verse eid="1SA 11:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 11:4"/>The messengers came to Gibeah of Saul. They reported to the people the terms Nahash had required. Then all the people wept out loud. <verse eid="1SA 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 11:5"/>Just then Saul was coming in from the fields. He was walking behind his oxen. He asked, “What’s wrong with everyone? Why are they weeping?” He was told what the men of Jabesh had said.<verse eid="1SA 11:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 11:6"/>When Saul heard their words, the Spirit of God came powerfully on him. He became very angry. <verse eid="1SA 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 11:7"/>He got a pair of oxen and cut them into pieces. He sent the pieces by messengers all through Israel. They announced, “You must follow Saul and Samuel. If you don’t, this is what will happen to your oxen.” The terror of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> fell on the people. So all of them came together with one purpose in mind. <verse eid="1SA 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 11:8"/>Saul brought his army together at Bezek. There were 300,000 men from Israel and 30,000 from Judah.<verse eid="1SA 11:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 11:9"/>The messengers who had come were told, “Go back and report to the men of Jabesh Gilead. Tell them, ‘By the hottest time of the day tomorrow, you will be rescued.’ ” The messengers went and reported it to the men of Jabesh. It made those men very happy. <verse eid="1SA 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 11:10"/>They said to the people of Ammon, “Tomorrow we’ll hand ourselves over to you. Then you can do to us whatever you like.”<verse eid="1SA 11:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 11:11"/>The next day Saul separated his men into three groups. While it was still dark, they broke into the camp of the Ammonite army. They kept killing the men of Ammon until the hottest time of the day. Those who got away were scattered. There weren’t two of them left together anywhere.<verse eid="1SA 11:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The People Agree to Have Saul as King</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 11:12"/>The people said to Samuel, “Who asked, ‘Is Saul going to rule over us?’ Turn these men over to us. We’ll put them to death.”<verse eid="1SA 11:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 11:13"/>But Saul said, “No one will be put to death today! After all, this is the day the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has rescued Israel.”<verse eid="1SA 11:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 11:14"/>Then Samuel said to the people, “Come on. Let’s go to Gilgal. There we’ll agree again to have Saul as our king.” <verse eid="1SA 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 11:15"/>So all the people went to Gilgal. There, with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as witness, they made Saul their king. There they sacrificed friendship offerings to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. And there Saul and all the Israelites celebrated with great joy.<verse eid="1SA 11:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="1SA 12"/>
  <para style="s1">Samuel’s Final Speech to Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 12:1"/>Samuel spoke to all the Israelites. He said, “I’ve done everything you asked me to do. I’ve placed a king over you. <verse eid="1SA 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 12:2"/>Now you have a king as your leader. But I’m old. My hair is gray. My sons are here with you. I’ve been your leader from the time I was young until this day. <verse eid="1SA 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 12:3"/>Here I stand. Bring charges against me if you can. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is a witness. And so is his anointed king. Whose ox have I taken? Whose donkey have I taken? Have I cheated anyone? Have I treated anyone badly? Have I accepted money from anyone who wanted special favors? If I’ve done any of these things, I’ll make it right.”<verse eid="1SA 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 12:4"/>“You haven’t cheated us,” they replied. “You haven’t treated us badly. You haven’t taken anything from anyone.”<verse eid="1SA 12:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 12:5"/>Samuel said to them, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is a witness against you this day. And so is his anointed king. They are witnesses that I haven’t taken anything from any of you.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 12:5">“The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is a witness,” they said.<verse eid="1SA 12:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 12:6"/>Then Samuel said to the people, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> appointed Moses and Aaron. He brought out of Egypt your people who lived long ago. <verse eid="1SA 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 12:7"/>Now then, stand here. I’m going to remind you of all the good things the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has done for you and your people. He is a witness.<verse eid="1SA 12:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 12:8"/>“After Jacob’s family entered Egypt, they cried out to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for help. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> sent Moses and Aaron. They brought your people out of Egypt. They had them make their homes in this land.<verse eid="1SA 12:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 12:9"/>“But the people forgot the <char style="nd">Lord</char> their God. So he put them under the control of Sisera. Sisera was the commander of the army of Hazor. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> also put the Israelites under the control of the Philistines and the king of Moab. All those nations fought against Israel. <verse eid="1SA 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 12:10"/>So the people cried out to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They said, ‘We have sinned. We’ve deserted the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. We’ve served gods that are named Baal. We’ve served female gods that are named Ashtoreth. But save us now from the power of our enemies. Then we will serve you.’ <verse eid="1SA 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 12:11"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> sent Gideon, Barak, Jephthah and me. He saved you from the power of your enemies who were all around you. So you lived in safety.<verse eid="1SA 12:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 12:12"/>“But then you saw that Nahash, the king of Ammon, was about to attack you. So you said to me, ‘No! We want a king to rule over us.’ You said it even though the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God was your king. <verse eid="1SA 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 12:13"/>Now here is the king you have chosen. He’s the one you asked for. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has placed a king over you. <verse eid="1SA 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 12:14"/>But you must have respect for the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. You must serve him and obey him. You must not say no to his commands. Both you and the king who rules over you must obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. If you do, that’s good. <verse eid="1SA 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 12:15"/>But you must not disobey him. You must not say no to his commands. If you do, his power will be against you. That’s what happened to your people who lived before you.<verse eid="1SA 12:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 12:16"/>“So stand still. Watch the great thing the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is about to do right here in front of you! <verse eid="1SA 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 12:17"/>It’s time to gather in the wheat, isn’t it? I’ll call out to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> to send thunder and rain. Then you will realize what an evil thing you did in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. You shouldn’t have asked for a king.”<verse eid="1SA 12:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 12:18"/>Samuel called out to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. That same day the <char style="nd">Lord</char> sent thunder and rain. So all the people had great respect for the <char style="nd">Lord</char> and for Samuel.<verse eid="1SA 12:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 12:19"/>They said to Samuel, “Pray to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God for us. Pray that we won’t die because we asked for a king. That was an evil thing to do. We added it to all our other sins.”<verse eid="1SA 12:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 12:20"/>“Don’t be afraid,” Samuel replied. “It’s true that you have done all these evil things. But don’t turn away from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Serve him with all your heart. <verse eid="1SA 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 12:21"/>Don’t turn away and worship statues of gods. They are useless. They can’t do you any good. They can’t save you either. They are completely useless. <verse eid="1SA 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 12:22"/>But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will be true to his great name. He won’t turn his back on his people. That’s because he was pleased to make you his own people. <verse eid="1SA 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 12:23"/>I would never sin against the <char style="nd">Lord</char> by failing to pray for you. I’ll teach you to live in a way that is good and right. <verse eid="1SA 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 12:24"/>But be sure to have respect for the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Serve him faithfully. Do it with all your heart. Think about the great things he has done for you. <verse eid="1SA 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 12:25"/>But don’t be stubborn. Don’t continue to do what is evil. If you do, both you and your king will be destroyed.”<verse eid="1SA 12:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="1SA 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Samuel Judges Saul’s Sin</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 13:1"/>Saul was 30 years old when he became king. He ruled over Israel for 42 years.<verse eid="1SA 13:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 13:2"/>Saul chose 3,000 of Israel’s men. Two thousand of them were with him at Mikmash and in the hill country of Bethel. One thousand were with Jonathan at Gibeah in the land of Benjamin. Saul sent the rest back to their homes.<verse eid="1SA 13:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 13:3"/>Some Philistine soldiers were stationed at Geba. Jonathan attacked them. The other Philistines heard about it. Saul announced, “Let the Hebrew people hear about what has happened!” He had trumpets blown all through the land. <verse eid="1SA 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 13:4"/>So all the Israelites heard the news. They were told, “Saul has attacked the Philistine army camp at Geba. Now the Philistines can’t stand the Israelites.” The Israelites were called out to join Saul at Gilgal.<verse eid="1SA 13:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 13:5"/>The Philistines gathered together to fight against Israel. They had 3,000 chariots and 6,000 chariot drivers. Their soldiers were as many as the grains of sand on the seashore. They went up and camped at Mikmash. It was east of Beth Aven. <verse eid="1SA 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 13:6"/>The Israelites saw that their army was in deep trouble. So they hid in caves. They hid among bushes and rocks. They also hid in pits and empty wells. <verse eid="1SA 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 13:7"/>Some of them even went across the Jordan River. They went to the lands of Gad and Gilead.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 13:7">Saul remained at Gilgal. All the troops with him were shaking with fear. <verse eid="1SA 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 13:8"/>He waited seven days, just as Samuel had told him to. But Samuel didn’t come to Gilgal. And Saul’s men began to scatter. <verse eid="1SA 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 13:9"/>So he said, “Bring me the burnt offering and the friendship offerings.” Then he offered up the burnt offering. <verse eid="1SA 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 13:10"/>Just as Saul finished offering the sacrifice, Samuel arrived. Saul went out to greet him.<verse eid="1SA 13:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 13:11"/>“What have you done?” asked Samuel.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 13:11">Saul replied, “I saw that the men were scattering. I saw that the Philistines were gathering together at Mikmash. You didn’t come when you said you would. <verse eid="1SA 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 13:12"/>So I thought, ‘Now the Philistines will come down to attack me at Gilgal. And I haven’t asked the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for his blessing.’ So I felt I had to sacrifice the burnt offering.”<verse eid="1SA 13:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 13:13"/>“You have done a foolish thing,” Samuel said. “You haven’t obeyed the command the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God gave you. If you had, he would have made your kingdom secure over Israel for all time to come. <verse eid="1SA 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 13:14"/>But now your kingdom won’t last. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has already looked for a man who is dear to his heart. He has appointed him king of his people. That’s because you haven’t obeyed the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s command.”<verse eid="1SA 13:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 13:15"/>Then Samuel left Gilgal and went up to Gibeah in the land of Benjamin. Saul counted the men who were with him. The total number was about 600.<verse eid="1SA 13:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Israel Doesn’t Have Weapons</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 13:16"/>Saul and his son Jonathan were staying in Gibeah in the land of Benjamin. The men who remained in the army were there with them. At the same time, the Philistines camped at Mikmash. <verse eid="1SA 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 13:17"/>Three groups of soldiers went out from the Philistine camp to attack Israel. One group turned and went toward Ophrah in the area of Shual. <verse eid="1SA 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 13:18"/>Another went toward Beth Horon. The third went toward the border that looked out over the Valley of Zeboim. That valley faces the desert.<verse eid="1SA 13:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 13:19"/>There weren’t any blacksmiths in the whole land of Israel. That’s because the Philistines had said, “The Hebrews might hire them to make swords or spears!” <verse eid="1SA 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 13:20"/>So all the Israelites had to go down to the Philistines. They had to go to them to get their plows, hoes, axes and sickles sharpened. <verse eid="1SA 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 13:21"/>It cost a fourth of an ounce of silver to sharpen a plow or a hoe. It cost an eighth of an ounce to sharpen a pitchfork or an axe. That’s also what it cost to put new tips on the large sticks used to drive oxen.<verse eid="1SA 13:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 13:22"/>So the Israelite soldiers went out to battle without swords or spears in their hands. That was true for all of Saul’s and Jonathan’s soldiers. Only Saul and his son Jonathan had those weapons.<verse eid="1SA 13:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jonathan Attacks the Philistines</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 13:23"/>A group of Philistine soldiers had gone out to the pass at Mikmash.<verse eid="1SA 13:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="1SA 14"/>
  <para style="nb">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 14:1"/>One day Jonathan, the son of Saul, spoke to the young man carrying his armor. “Come on,” he said. “Let’s go over to the Philistine army camp on the other side of the pass.” But he didn’t tell his father about it.<verse eid="1SA 14:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 14:2"/>Saul was staying just outside Gibeah. He was under a pomegranate tree in Migron. He had about 600 men with him. <verse eid="1SA 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 14:3"/>Ahijah was one of them. He was wearing a sacred linen apron. He was a son of Ichabod’s brother Ahitub. Ahitub was the son of Eli’s son Phinehas. Eli had been the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s priest in Shiloh. No one was aware that Jonathan had left.<verse eid="1SA 14:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 14:4"/>Jonathan planned to go across the pass to reach the Philistine camp. But there was a cliff on each side of the pass. One cliff was called Bozez. The other was called Seneh. <verse eid="1SA 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 14:5"/>One cliff stood on the north side of the pass toward Mikmash. The other stood on the south side toward Geba.<verse eid="1SA 14:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 14:6"/>Jonathan spoke to the young man carrying his armor. He said, “Come on. Let’s go over to the camp of those fellows who aren’t circumcised. Perhaps the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will help us. If he does, it won’t matter how many or how few of us there are. That won’t keep the <char style="nd">Lord</char> from saving us.”<verse eid="1SA 14:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 14:7"/>“Go ahead,” the young man said. “Do everything you have in mind. I’m with you all the way.”<verse eid="1SA 14:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 14:8"/>Jonathan said, “Come on, then. We’ll go across the pass toward the Philistines and let them see us. <verse eid="1SA 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 14:9"/>Suppose they say to us, ‘Wait there until we come to you.’ Then we’ll stay where we are. We won’t go up to them. <verse eid="1SA 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 14:10"/>But suppose they say, ‘Come up to us.’ Then we’ll climb up. That will show us that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has handed them over to us.”<verse eid="1SA 14:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 14:11"/>So Jonathan and the young man let the soldiers in the Philistine camp see them. “Look!” said the Philistines. “Some of the Hebrews are crawling out of the holes they were hiding in.” <verse eid="1SA 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 14:12"/>The men in the Philistine camp shouted to Jonathan and the young man carrying his armor. They said, “Come on up here. We’ll teach you a thing or two.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 14:12">So Jonathan said to the young man, “Climb up after me. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has handed them over to Israel.”<verse eid="1SA 14:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 14:13"/>Using his hands and feet, Jonathan climbed up. The young man was right behind him. Jonathan struck down the Philistines. The young man followed him and killed those who were still alive. <verse eid="1SA 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 14:14"/>In that first attack, Jonathan and the young man killed about 20 men. They did it in an area of about half an acre.<verse eid="1SA 14:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Israel Chases the Philistines Away</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 14:15"/>Then panic struck the whole Philistine army. It struck those who were in the camp and those in the field. It struck those who were at the edge of the camp. It also struck those who were in the groups that had been sent out to attack Israel. The ground shook. It was a panic that God had sent.<verse eid="1SA 14:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 14:16"/>Saul’s lookouts at Gibeah in the land of Benjamin saw what was happening. They saw the Philistine army melting away in all directions. <verse eid="1SA 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 14:17"/>Then Saul spoke to the men with him. He said, “Bring the troops together. See who has left our camp.” When they did, they discovered that Jonathan and the young man carrying his armor weren’t there.<verse eid="1SA 14:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 14:18"/>Saul said to Ahijah the priest, “Bring the ark of God.” At that time it was with the Israelites. <verse eid="1SA 14:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 14:19"/>While Saul was talking to the priest, the noise in the Philistine camp got louder and louder. So Saul said to the priest, “Stop what you are doing.”<verse eid="1SA 14:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 14:20"/>Then Saul and all his men gathered together. They went to the battle. They saw that the Philistines were in total disorder. They were striking one another with their swords. <verse eid="1SA 14:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 14:21"/>At an earlier time some of the Hebrews had been on the side of the Philistines. They had gone up with them to their camp. But now they changed sides. They joined the Israelites who were with Saul and Jonathan. <verse eid="1SA 14:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 14:22"/>Some of the Israelites had hidden in the hill country of Ephraim. They heard that the Philistines were running away. They quickly joined the battle and chased after them. <verse eid="1SA 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 14:23"/>So on that day the <char style="nd">Lord</char> saved Israel. And the fighting continued on past Beth Aven.<verse eid="1SA 14:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jonathan Eats Honey</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 14:24"/>The Israelites became very hungry that day. That’s because Saul had forced the army to make a promise. He had said, “None of you must eat any food before evening comes. You must not eat until I’ve paid my enemies back for what they did. If you do, may you be under a curse!” So none of the troops ate any food at all.<verse eid="1SA 14:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 14:25"/>The whole army entered the woods. There was honey on the ground. <verse eid="1SA 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 14:26"/>When they went into the woods, they saw the honey dripping out of a honeycomb. No one put any of the honey in his mouth. They were afraid of the curse that would come if they broke their promise. <verse eid="1SA 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 14:27"/>But Jonathan hadn’t heard that his father had forced the army to make a promise. Jonathan had a long stick in his hand. He reached out and dipped the end of it into the honeycomb. He put some honey in his mouth. It gave him new life. <verse eid="1SA 14:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 14:28"/>Then one of the soldiers told him, “Your father forced the army to make a promise that everyone must obey. He said, ‘None of you must eat any food today. If you do, may you be under a curse!’ That’s why the men are weak and ready to faint.”<verse eid="1SA 14:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 14:29"/>Jonathan said, “My father has made trouble for the country. See how I gained new life after I tasted a little of this honey. <verse eid="1SA 14:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1SA 14:30"/>Our soldiers took food from their enemies today. Suppose they had eaten some of it. How much better off they would have been! Even more Philistines would have been killed.”<verse eid="1SA 14:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1SA 14:31"/>That day the Israelites struck down the Philistines. They killed them from Mikmash to Aijalon. By that time they were tired and worn out. <verse eid="1SA 14:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1SA 14:32"/>They grabbed what they had taken from their enemies. They killed some of the sheep, cattle and calves right there on the ground. They ate the meat while the blood was still in it. <verse eid="1SA 14:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1SA 14:33"/>Then someone said to Saul, “Look! The men are sinning against the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They’re eating meat that still has blood in it.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 14:33">Saul said to them, “You have broken your promise. Roll a large stone over here at once.” <verse eid="1SA 14:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1SA 14:34"/>He continued, “Go out among the men. Tell them, ‘Each of you bring me your cattle and sheep. Kill them here and eat them. Don’t sin against the <char style="nd">Lord</char> by eating meat that still has blood in it.’ ”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 14:34">So that night everyone brought the ox he had taken and killed it there. <verse eid="1SA 14:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1SA 14:35"/>Then Saul built an altar to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It was the first time he had done that.<verse eid="1SA 14:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="1SA 14:36"/>Saul said, “Let’s go down and chase after the Philistines tonight. Let’s not leave even one of them alive. Let’s take everything they have before morning.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 14:36">“Do what you think is best,” they replied.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 14:36">But the priest said, “Let’s ask God for advice first.”<verse eid="1SA 14:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="1SA 14:37"/>So Saul asked God, “Should I go down and chase after the Philistines? Will you hand them over to Israel?” But God didn’t answer him that day.<verse eid="1SA 14:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="1SA 14:38"/>Saul said to the leaders of the army, “Come here. Let’s find out what sin has been committed today. <verse eid="1SA 14:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1SA 14:39"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is the one who rescues Israel. You can be sure that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> lives. And you can be just as sure that the sinner must die. He must die even if he’s my son Jonathan.” But no one said anything.<verse eid="1SA 14:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="1SA 14:40"/>Then Saul said to all the Israelites, “You stand over there. I and my son Jonathan will stand over here.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 14:40">“Do what you think is best,” they replied.<verse eid="1SA 14:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="1SA 14:41"/>Then Saul prayed to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, the God of Israel. He said, “Why haven’t you answered your servant today? If I or my son Jonathan is to blame, answer with Urim. But if the Israelites are to blame, answer with Thummim.” Jonathan and Saul were chosen by casting lots. The other men were cleared of blame. <verse eid="1SA 14:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1SA 14:42"/>Saul said, “Cast the lot to find out whether I or my son Jonathan is to blame.” And Jonathan was chosen.<verse eid="1SA 14:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="1SA 14:43"/>Then Saul said to Jonathan, “Tell me what you have done.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 14:43">So Jonathan told him, “I used the end of my stick to get a little honey and taste it. And now do I have to die?”<verse eid="1SA 14:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="1SA 14:44"/>Saul said, “Jonathan, I must certainly put you to death. If I don’t, may God punish me greatly.”<verse eid="1SA 14:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="1SA 14:45"/>But the men said to Saul, “Should Jonathan be put to death? Never! He has saved Israel in a wonderful way. He did it today with God’s help. You can be sure that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> lives. And you can be just as sure that not even one hair on Jonathan’s head will fall to the ground.” So the men rescued Jonathan. He wasn’t put to death.<verse eid="1SA 14:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="1SA 14:46"/>Then Saul stopped chasing the Philistines. They went back to their own land.<verse eid="1SA 14:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="1SA 14:47"/>After Saul became the king of Israel, he fought against Israel’s enemies who were all around them. He went to war against Moab, Ammon and Edom. He fought against the kings of Zobah and the Philistines. No matter where he went, he punished his enemies. <verse eid="1SA 14:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="1SA 14:48"/>He fought bravely. He won the battle over the Amalekites. He saved Israel from the power of those who had carried off what belonged to Israel.<verse eid="1SA 14:48"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Saul’s Family</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="1SA 14:49"/>Saul’s sons were Jonathan, Ishvi and Malki-Shua. Saul’s older daughter was named Merab. His younger daughter was named Michal. <verse eid="1SA 14:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="1SA 14:50"/>Saul’s wife was named Ahinoam. She was the daughter of Ahimaaz. The commander of Saul’s army was named Abner. He was the son of Ner. Ner was Saul’s uncle. <verse eid="1SA 14:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="1SA 14:51"/>Saul’s father Kish and Abner’s father Ner were sons of Abiel.<verse eid="1SA 14:51"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="52" style="v" sid="1SA 14:52"/>As long as Saul was king, he had to fight hard against the Philistines. So every time Saul saw a strong or brave man, he took him into his army.<verse eid="1SA 14:52"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="1SA 15"/>
  <para style="s1">The <char style="nd">Lord </char>Is Sad That He Made Saul King</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 15:1"/>Samuel said to Saul, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> sent me to anoint you as king over his people Israel. So listen now to a message from him. <verse eid="1SA 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 15:2"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> who rules over all says, ‘I will punish the Amalekites because of what they did to Israel. As the Israelites came up from Egypt, the Amalekites attacked them. <verse eid="1SA 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 15:3"/>Now go. Attack the Amalekites. Completely destroy all that belongs to them. Do not spare the Amalekites. Put the men and women to death. Put the children and babies to death. Also kill the cattle, sheep, camels and donkeys.’ ”<verse eid="1SA 15:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 15:4"/>So Saul brought his men together at Telaim. The total number was 200,000 soldiers on foot from Israel and 10,000 from Judah. <verse eid="1SA 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 15:5"/>Saul went to the city of Amalek. Then Saul had some of his men hide and wait in the valley. <verse eid="1SA 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 15:6"/>Then Saul said to the Kenites, “You were kind to all the Israelites when they came up out of Egypt. Get away from the Amalekites. Then I won’t have to destroy you along with them.” So the Kenites moved away from the Amalekites.<verse eid="1SA 15:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 15:7"/>Saul attacked the Amalekites. He struck them down all the way from Havilah to Shur. Shur was near the eastern border of Egypt. <verse eid="1SA 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 15:8"/>Saul captured Agag, the king of the Amalekites. But he and his men totally destroyed with their swords all Agag’s people. <verse eid="1SA 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 15:9"/>So Saul and the army spared Agag. They spared the best of the sheep and cattle. They spared the fat calves and lambs. They spared everything that was valuable. They weren’t willing to completely destroy any of those things. But they totally destroyed everything that was worthless and weak.<verse eid="1SA 15:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 15:10"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave Samuel a message. He said, <verse eid="1SA 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 15:11"/>“I am very sad I have made Saul king. He has turned away from me. He has not done what I directed him to do.” When Samuel heard that, he was angry. He cried out to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> during that whole night.<verse eid="1SA 15:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 15:12"/>Early the next morning Samuel got up. He went to see Saul. But Samuel was told, “Saul went to Carmel. There he set up a monument in his own honor. Now he has gone on down to Gilgal.”<verse eid="1SA 15:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 15:13"/>When Samuel got there, Saul said, “May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> bless you. I’ve done what he directed me to do.”<verse eid="1SA 15:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 15:14"/>But Samuel said, “Then why do I hear the baaing of sheep? Why do I hear the mooing of cattle?”<verse eid="1SA 15:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 15:15"/>Saul answered, “The soldiers brought them from the Amalekites. They spared the best of the sheep and cattle. They did it to sacrifice them to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. But we totally destroyed everything else.”<verse eid="1SA 15:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 15:16"/>“That’s enough!” Samuel said to Saul. “Let me tell you what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to me last night.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 15:16">“Tell me,” Saul replied.<verse eid="1SA 15:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 15:17"/>Samuel said, “There was a time when you didn’t think you were important. But you became the leader of the tribes of Israel. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> anointed you to be king over Israel. <verse eid="1SA 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 15:18"/>He sent you to do something for him. He said, ‘Go and completely destroy the Amalekites. Go and destroy those evil people. Fight against them until you have wiped them out.’ <verse eid="1SA 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 15:19"/>Why didn’t you obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char>? Why did you keep for yourselves what you had taken from your enemies? Why did you do what is evil in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>?”<verse eid="1SA 15:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 15:20"/>“But I did obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char>,” Saul said. “I went to do what he sent me to do. I completely destroyed the Amalekites. I brought back Agag, their king. <verse eid="1SA 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 15:21"/>The soldiers took sheep and cattle from what had been taken from our enemies. They took the best of what had been set apart to God. They wanted to sacrifice them to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God at Gilgal.”<verse eid="1SA 15:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 15:22"/>But Samuel replied,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 15:22">“What pleases the <char style="nd">Lord</char> more?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 15:22">Burnt offerings and sacrifices, or obeying the <char style="nd">Lord</char>?</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 15:22">It is better to obey than to offer a sacrifice.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 15:22">It is better to do what he says than to offer the fat of rams.<verse eid="1SA 15:22"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 15:23"/>Refusing to obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is as sinful as using evil magic.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 15:23">Being proud is as evil as worshiping statues of gods.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 15:23">You have refused to do what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> told you to do.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 15:23">So he has refused to have you as king.”<verse eid="1SA 15:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 15:24"/>Then Saul said to Samuel, “I have sinned. I’ve broken the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s command. I haven’t done what you directed me to do. I was afraid of the men. So I did what they said I should do. <verse eid="1SA 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 15:25"/>Now I beg you, forgive my sin. Come back into town with me so I can worship the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 15:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 15:26"/>But Samuel said to him, “I won’t go back with you. You have refused to do what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> told you to do. So he has refused to have you as king over Israel!”<verse eid="1SA 15:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 15:27"/>Samuel turned to leave. But Saul grabbed the hem of his robe, and it tore. <verse eid="1SA 15:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 15:28"/>Samuel said to Saul, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has torn the kingdom of Israel away from you today. He has given it to one of your neighbors. He has given it to someone better than you. <verse eid="1SA 15:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 15:29"/>The God who is the Glory of Israel does not lie. He doesn’t change his mind. That’s because he isn’t a mere human being. If he were, he might change his mind.”<verse eid="1SA 15:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1SA 15:30"/>Saul replied, “I have sinned. But please honor me in front of the elders of my people and in front of Israel. Come back with me so I can worship the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.” <verse eid="1SA 15:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1SA 15:31"/>So Samuel went back with Saul. And Saul worshiped the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="1SA 15:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1SA 15:32"/>Then Samuel said, “Bring me Agag, the king of the Amalekites.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 15:32">Agag was in chains when he came to Samuel. Agag thought, “The time for me to be put to death must have passed by now.”<verse eid="1SA 15:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1SA 15:33"/>But Samuel said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 15:33">“Your sword has killed the children of other women.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 15:33">So the child of your mother will be killed.”</para>
  <para style="m" vid="1SA 15:33">Samuel put Agag to death at Gilgal in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="1SA 15:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1SA 15:34"/>Then Samuel left to go to Ramah. But Saul went up to his home in Gibeah of Saul. <verse eid="1SA 15:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1SA 15:35"/>Until the day Samuel died, he didn’t go to see Saul again. Samuel was filled with sorrow because of Saul. And the <char style="nd">Lord</char> was very sad he had made Saul king over Israel.<verse eid="1SA 15:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="1SA 16"/>
  <para style="s1">Samuel Anoints David to Be Israel’s King</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 16:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Samuel, “How long will you be filled with sorrow because of Saul? I have refused to have him as king over Israel. Fill your animal horn with olive oil and go on your way. I am sending you to Jesse in Bethlehem. I have chosen one of his sons to be king.”<verse eid="1SA 16:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 16:2"/>But Samuel said, “How can I go? Suppose Saul hears about it. Then he’ll kill me.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 16:2">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said, “Take a young cow with you. Tell the elders of Bethlehem, ‘I’ve come to offer a sacrifice to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.’ <verse eid="1SA 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 16:3"/>Invite Jesse to the sacrifice. Then I will show you what to do. You must anoint for me the one I point out to you.”<verse eid="1SA 16:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 16:4"/>Samuel did what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said. He arrived at Bethlehem. The elders of the town met him. They were trembling with fear. They asked, “Have you come in peace?”<verse eid="1SA 16:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 16:5"/>Samuel replied, “Yes, I’ve come in peace. I’ve come to offer a sacrifice to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Set yourselves apart to him and come to the sacrifice with me.” Then he set Jesse and his sons apart to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He invited them to the sacrifice.<verse eid="1SA 16:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 16:6"/>When they arrived, Samuel saw Eliab. He thought, “This has to be the one the <char style="nd">Lord</char> wants me to anoint for him.”<verse eid="1SA 16:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 16:7"/>But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Samuel, “Do not consider how handsome or tall he is. I have not chosen him. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> does not look at the things people look at. People look at the outside of a person. But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> looks at what is in the heart.”<verse eid="1SA 16:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 16:8"/>Then Jesse called for Abinadab. He had him walk in front of Samuel. But Samuel said, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> hasn’t chosen him either.” <verse eid="1SA 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 16:9"/>Then Jesse had Shammah walk by. But Samuel said, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> hasn’t chosen him either.” <verse eid="1SA 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 16:10"/>Jesse had seven of his sons walk in front of Samuel. But Samuel said to him, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> hasn’t chosen any of them.” <verse eid="1SA 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 16:11"/>So he asked Jesse, “Are these the only sons you have?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 16:11">“No,” Jesse answered. “My youngest son is taking care of the sheep.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 16:11">Samuel said, “Send for him. We won’t sit down to eat until he arrives.”<verse eid="1SA 16:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 16:12"/>So Jesse sent for his son and had him brought in. He looked very healthy. He had a fine appearance and handsome features.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 16:12">Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said, “Get up and anoint him. This is the one.”<verse eid="1SA 16:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 16:13"/>So Samuel got the animal horn that was filled with olive oil. He anointed David in front of his brothers. From that day on, the Spirit of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> came powerfully on David. Samuel went back to Ramah.<verse eid="1SA 16:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">David Serves Saul</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 16:14"/>The Spirit of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had left Saul. And an evil spirit sent by the <char style="nd">Lord</char> terrified him.<verse eid="1SA 16:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 16:15"/>Saul’s attendants said to him, “An evil spirit sent by God is terrifying you. <verse eid="1SA 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 16:16"/>Give us an order to look for someone who can play the harp. He will play it when the evil spirit sent by God comes on you. Then you will feel better.”<verse eid="1SA 16:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 16:17"/>So Saul said to his attendants, “Find someone who plays the harp well. Bring him to me.”<verse eid="1SA 16:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 16:18"/>One of the servants said, “I’ve seen someone who knows how to play the harp. He is a son of Jesse from Bethlehem. He’s a brave man. He would make a good soldier. He’s a good speaker. He’s very handsome. And the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is with him.”<verse eid="1SA 16:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 16:19"/>Then Saul sent messengers to Jesse. He said, “Send me your son David, the one who takes care of your sheep.” <verse eid="1SA 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 16:20"/>So Jesse got some bread and a bottle of wine. The bottle was made out of animal skin. He also got a young goat. He loaded everything on the back of a donkey. He sent all of it to Saul with his son David.<verse eid="1SA 16:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 16:21"/>David went to Saul and began to serve him. Saul liked him very much. David became one of the men who carried Saul’s armor. <verse eid="1SA 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 16:22"/>Saul sent a message to Jesse. Saul said, “Let David stay here. I want him to serve me. I’m pleased with him.”<verse eid="1SA 16:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 16:23"/>When the evil spirit sent by God would come on Saul, David would get his harp and play it. That would help Saul. He would feel better, and the evil spirit would leave him.<verse eid="1SA 16:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="1SA 17"/>
  <para style="s1">David and Goliath</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 17:1"/>The Philistines gathered their army together for war. They came to Sokoh in Judah. They set up camp at Ephes Dammim. It was between Sokoh and Azekah. <verse eid="1SA 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 17:2"/>Saul and the army of Israel gathered together. They camped in the Valley of Elah. They lined up their men to fight against the Philistines. <verse eid="1SA 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 17:3"/>The Philistine army was camped on one hill. Israel’s army was on another. The valley was between them.<verse eid="1SA 17:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 17:4"/>A mighty hero named Goliath came out of the Philistine camp. He was from Gath. He was more than nine feet tall. <verse eid="1SA 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 17:5"/>He had a bronze helmet on his head. He wore bronze armor that weighed 125 pounds. <verse eid="1SA 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 17:6"/>On his legs he wore bronze guards. He carried a bronze javelin on his back. <verse eid="1SA 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 17:7"/>His spear was as big as a weaver’s rod. Its iron point weighed 15 pounds. The man who carried his shield walked along in front of him.<verse eid="1SA 17:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 17:8"/>Goliath stood there and shouted to the soldiers of Israel. He said, “Why do you come out and line up for battle? I’m a Philistine. You are servants of Saul. Choose one of your men. Have him come down and face me. <verse eid="1SA 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 17:9"/>If he’s able to fight and kill me, we’ll become your slaves. But if I win and kill him, you will become our slaves and serve us.” <verse eid="1SA 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 17:10"/>Goliath continued, “This day I dare the soldiers of Israel to send a man down to fight against me.” <verse eid="1SA 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 17:11"/>Saul and the whole army of Israel heard what the Philistine said. They were terrified.<verse eid="1SA 17:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 17:12"/>David was the son of an Ephrathite whose name was Jesse. Jesse was from Bethlehem in Judah and had eight sons. When Saul was king, Jesse was already very old. <verse eid="1SA 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 17:13"/>Jesse’s three oldest sons had followed Saul into battle. The oldest son was Eliab. The second was Abinadab. The third was Shammah. <verse eid="1SA 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 17:14"/>David was the youngest. The three oldest sons followed Saul. <verse eid="1SA 17:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 17:15"/>But David went back and forth from Saul’s camp to Bethlehem. He went to Bethlehem to take care of his father’s sheep.<verse eid="1SA 17:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 17:16"/>Every morning and evening Goliath came forward and stood there. He did it for 40 days.<verse eid="1SA 17:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 17:17"/>Jesse said to his son David, “Get at least half a bushel of grain that has been cooked. Also get ten loaves of bread. Take all of it to your brothers. Hurry to their camp. <verse eid="1SA 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 17:18"/>Take along these ten chunks of cheese to the commander of their military group. Find out how your brothers are doing. Bring me back some word about them. <verse eid="1SA 17:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 17:19"/>They are with Saul and all the men of Israel. They are in the Valley of Elah. They are fighting against the Philistines.”<verse eid="1SA 17:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 17:20"/>Early in the morning David left his father’s flock in the care of a shepherd. David loaded up the food and started out, just as Jesse had directed. David reached the camp as the army was going out to its battle positions. The soldiers were shouting the war cry. <verse eid="1SA 17:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 17:21"/>The Israelites and the Philistines were lining up their armies for battle. The armies were facing each other. <verse eid="1SA 17:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 17:22"/>David left what he had brought with the man who took care of the supplies. He ran to the battle lines and asked his brothers how they were. <verse eid="1SA 17:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 17:23"/>As David was talking with them, Goliath stepped forward from his line. Goliath was a mighty Philistine hero from Gath. He again dared someone to fight him, and David heard it. <verse eid="1SA 17:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 17:24"/>Whenever Israel’s army saw Goliath, all of them ran away from him. That’s because they were so afraid.<verse eid="1SA 17:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 17:25"/>The Israelites had been saying, “Just look at how this man keeps daring Israel to fight him! The king will make the man who kills Goliath very wealthy. The king will also give his own daughter to be that man’s wife. The king won’t require anyone in the man’s family to pay any taxes in Israel.”<verse eid="1SA 17:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 17:26"/>David spoke to the men standing near him. He asked them, “What will be done for the man who kills this Philistine? Goliath is bringing shame on Israel. What will be done for the one who removes it? This Philistine isn’t even circumcised. He dares the armies of the living God to fight him. Who does he think he is?”<verse eid="1SA 17:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 17:27"/>The men told David what Israel’s soldiers had been saying. The men told him what would be done for the man who killed Goliath.<verse eid="1SA 17:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 17:28"/>David’s oldest brother Eliab heard him speaking with the men. So Eliab became very angry with him. Eliab asked David, “Why have you come down here? Who is taking care of those few sheep in the desert for you? I know how proud you are. I know how evil your heart is. The only reason you came down here was to watch the battle.”<verse eid="1SA 17:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 17:29"/>“What have I done now?” said David. “Can’t I even speak?” <verse eid="1SA 17:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1SA 17:30"/>Then he turned away to speak to some other men. He asked them the same question he had asked before. And they gave him the same answer. <verse eid="1SA 17:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1SA 17:31"/>Someone heard what David said and reported it to Saul. So Saul sent for David.<verse eid="1SA 17:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1SA 17:32"/>David said to Saul, “Don’t let anyone lose hope because of that Philistine. I’ll go out and fight him.”<verse eid="1SA 17:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1SA 17:33"/>Saul replied, “You aren’t able to go out there and fight that Philistine. You are too young. He’s been a warrior ever since he was a boy.”<verse eid="1SA 17:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1SA 17:34"/>But David said to Saul, “I’ve been taking care of my father’s sheep. Sometimes a lion or a bear would come and carry off a sheep from the flock. <verse eid="1SA 17:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1SA 17:35"/>Then I would go after it and hit it. I would save the sheep it was carrying in its mouth. If it turned around to attack me, I would grab its hair. I would strike it down and kill it. <verse eid="1SA 17:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1SA 17:36"/>In fact, I’ve killed both a lion and a bear. I’ll do the same thing to this Philistine. He isn’t even circumcised. He has dared the armies of the living God to fight him. <verse eid="1SA 17:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1SA 17:37"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> saved me from the paw of the lion. He saved me from the paw of the bear. And he’ll save me from the powerful hand of this Philistine too.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 17:37">Saul said to David, “Go. And may the <char style="nd">Lord</char> be with you.”<verse eid="1SA 17:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="1SA 17:38"/>Then Saul dressed David in his own military clothes. He put a coat of armor on him. He put a bronze helmet on his head. <verse eid="1SA 17:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1SA 17:39"/>David put on Saul’s sword over his clothes. He walked around for a while in all that armor because he wasn’t used to it.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 17:39">“I can’t go out there in all this armor,” he said to Saul. “I’m not used to it.” So he took it off. <verse eid="1SA 17:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1SA 17:40"/>Then David picked up his wooden staff. He went down to a stream and chose five smooth stones. He put them in the pocket of his shepherd’s bag. Then he took his sling in his hand and approached Goliath.<verse eid="1SA 17:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="1SA 17:41"/>At that same time, the Philistine kept coming closer to David. The man carrying Goliath’s shield walked along in front of him. <verse eid="1SA 17:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1SA 17:42"/>Goliath looked David over. He saw how young he was. He also saw how healthy and handsome he was. And he hated him. <verse eid="1SA 17:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1SA 17:43"/>He said to David, “Why are you coming at me with sticks? Do you think I’m only a dog?” The Philistine cursed David in the name of his gods. <verse eid="1SA 17:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="1SA 17:44"/>“Come over here,” he said. “I’ll feed your body to the birds and wild animals!”<verse eid="1SA 17:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="1SA 17:45"/>David said to Goliath, “You are coming to fight against me with a sword, a spear and a javelin. But I’m coming against you in the name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> who rules over all. He is the God of the armies of Israel. He’s the one you have dared to fight against. <verse eid="1SA 17:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="1SA 17:46"/>This day the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will give me the victory over you. I’ll strike you down. I’ll cut your head off. This day I’ll feed the bodies of the Philistine army to the birds and wild animals. Then the whole world will know there is a God in Israel. <verse eid="1SA 17:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="1SA 17:47"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> doesn’t rescue people by using a sword or a spear. And everyone here will know it. The battle belongs to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He will hand all of you over to us.”<verse eid="1SA 17:47"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="1SA 17:48"/>As the Philistine moved closer to attack him, David ran quickly to the battle line to meet him. <verse eid="1SA 17:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="1SA 17:49"/>He reached into his bag. He took out a stone. He put it in his sling. He slung it at Goliath. The stone hit him on the forehead and sank into it. He fell to the ground on his face.<verse eid="1SA 17:49"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="1SA 17:50"/>So David won the fight against Goliath with a sling and a stone. He struck down the Philistine and killed him. He did it without even using a sword.<verse eid="1SA 17:50"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="51" style="v" sid="1SA 17:51"/>David ran and stood over him. He picked up Goliath’s sword and cut off his head with it.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 17:51">The Philistines saw that their hero was dead. So they turned around and ran away. <verse eid="1SA 17:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="1SA 17:52"/>Then the men of Israel and Judah shouted and rushed forward. They chased the Philistines to the entrance of Gath. They chased them to the gates of Ekron. Bodies of dead Philistines were scattered all along the road to Gath and Ekron. That’s the road that leads to Shaaraim. <verse eid="1SA 17:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="1SA 17:53"/>Israel’s army returned from chasing the Philistines. They had taken everything from the Philistine camp.<verse eid="1SA 17:53"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="1SA 17:54"/>David picked up Goliath’s head. He brought it to Jerusalem. He put Goliath’s weapons in his own tent.<verse eid="1SA 17:54"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="55" style="v" sid="1SA 17:55"/>Saul had been watching David as he went out to meet the Philistine. He spoke to Abner, the commander of the army. Saul said to him, “Abner, whose son is that young man?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 17:55">Abner replied, “Your Majesty, I don’t know. And that’s just as sure as you are alive.”<verse eid="1SA 17:55"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="56" style="v" sid="1SA 17:56"/>The king said, “Find out whose son that young man is.”<verse eid="1SA 17:56"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="57" style="v" sid="1SA 17:57"/>After David killed Goliath, he returned to the camp. Then Abner brought him to Saul. David was still carrying Goliath’s head.<verse eid="1SA 17:57"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="58" style="v" sid="1SA 17:58"/>“Young man, whose son are you?” Saul asked him.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 17:58">David said, “I’m the son of Jesse from Bethlehem.”<verse eid="1SA 17:58"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="1SA 18"/>
  <para style="s1">Saul’s Growing Fear of David</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 18:1"/>David finished talking with Saul. After that, Jonathan and David became close friends. Jonathan loved David just as he loved himself. <verse eid="1SA 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 18:2"/>From that time on, Saul kept David with him. He didn’t let him return home to his family. <verse eid="1SA 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 18:3"/>Jonathan made a covenant with David because he loved him just as he loved himself. <verse eid="1SA 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 18:4"/>Jonathan took off the robe he was wearing and gave it to David. He also gave him his military clothes. He even gave him his sword, his bow and his belt.<verse eid="1SA 18:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 18:5"/>David did everything Saul sent him to do. He did it so well that Saul gave him a high rank in the army. That pleased Saul’s whole army, including his officers.<verse eid="1SA 18:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 18:6"/>After David had killed Goliath, the men of Israel returned home. The women came out of all the towns of Israel to meet King Saul. They danced and sang joyful songs. They played harps and tambourines. <verse eid="1SA 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 18:7"/>As they danced, they sang,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 18:7">“Saul has killed thousands of men.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 18:7">David has killed tens of thousands.”<verse eid="1SA 18:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 18:8"/>That song made Saul very angry. It really upset him. He said to himself, “They are saying David has killed tens of thousands of men. But they are saying I’ve killed only thousands. The only thing left for him to get is the kingdom itself.” <verse eid="1SA 18:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 18:9"/>From that time on, Saul watched David closely.<verse eid="1SA 18:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 18:10"/>The next day an evil spirit sent by God came powerfully on Saul. Saul began to prophesy in his house. At that same time David began to play the harp, just as he usually did. Saul was holding a spear. <verse eid="1SA 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 18:11"/>He threw it at David. As he did, he said to himself, “I’ll pin David to the wall.” But David got away from him twice.<verse eid="1SA 18:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 18:12"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> had left Saul and was with David. So Saul was afraid of David. <verse eid="1SA 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 18:13"/>He sent David away. He put him in command of 1,000 men. David led the troops in battle. <verse eid="1SA 18:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 18:14"/>In everything he did, he was very successful. That’s because the <char style="nd">Lord</char> was with him. <verse eid="1SA 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 18:15"/>When Saul saw how successful David was, he became afraid of him. <verse eid="1SA 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 18:16"/>But all the troops of Israel and Judah loved David. That’s because he led them in battle.<verse eid="1SA 18:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 18:17"/>Saul said to David, “Here is my older daughter Merab. I’ll give her to you to be your wife. Just serve me bravely and fight the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s battles.” Saul said to himself, “I won’t have to lift my hand to strike him down. The Philistines will do that!”<verse eid="1SA 18:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 18:18"/>But David said to Saul, “Who am I? Is anyone in my whole family that important in Israel? Am I worthy to become the king’s son-in-law?” <verse eid="1SA 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 18:19"/>The time came for Saul to give his daughter Merab to David. Instead, Saul gave her to Adriel from Meholah to be his wife.<verse eid="1SA 18:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 18:20"/>Saul’s daughter Michal was in love with David. When they told Saul about it, he was pleased. <verse eid="1SA 18:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 18:21"/>“I’ll give her to David to be his wife,” Saul said to himself. “Then maybe she’ll trap him. And maybe the Philistines will strike him down.” So Saul said to David, “Now you have a second chance to become my son-in-law.”<verse eid="1SA 18:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 18:22"/>Then Saul gave an order to his attendants. He said, “Speak to David in private. Tell him, ‘The king likes you. All his attendants love you. So become his son-in-law.’ ”<verse eid="1SA 18:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 18:23"/>Saul’s attendants spoke those very words to David. But David said, “Do you think it’s a small thing to become the king’s son-in-law? I’m only a poor man. I’m not very well known.”<verse eid="1SA 18:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 18:24"/>Saul’s attendants told him what David had said. <verse eid="1SA 18:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 18:25"/>Saul said, “Tell David, ‘Here’s the price the king wants for the bride. He wants you to kill 100 Philistines. Then bring back the skins you cut off when you circumcise them. That’s how Saul will get even with his enemies.’ ” Saul hoped that the Philistines would strike David down.<verse eid="1SA 18:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 18:26"/>Saul’s attendants also told David those things. Then David was pleased to become the king’s son-in-law. So before the wedding day, <verse eid="1SA 18:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 18:27"/>David and his men went out and killed 200 Philistines. They circumcised the Philistines. Then David brought back all the skins. They counted out the full number and gave them to the king. By doing that, David could become the king’s son-in-law. So Saul gave David his daughter Michal to be his wife.<verse eid="1SA 18:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 18:28"/>Saul realized that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> was with David. He also realized that his daughter Michal loved David. <verse eid="1SA 18:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 18:29"/>So Saul became even more afraid of him. As long as Saul lived, he remained David’s enemy.<verse eid="1SA 18:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1SA 18:30"/>The Philistine commanders kept on going out to battle. Every time they did, David had more success against them than the rest of Saul’s officers. So his name became well known.<verse eid="1SA 18:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="1SA 19"/>
  <para style="s1">Saul Tries to Kill David</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 19:1"/>Saul told his son Jonathan and all the attendants to kill David. But Jonathan liked David very much. <verse eid="1SA 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 19:2"/>So Jonathan warned him, “My father Saul is looking for a chance to kill you. Be very careful tomorrow morning. Find a place to hide and stay there. <verse eid="1SA 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 19:3"/>My father and I will come and stand in the field where you are hiding. I’ll speak to him about you. Then I’ll tell you what I find out.”<verse eid="1SA 19:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 19:4"/>Jonathan told his father Saul some good things about David. He said to him, “Please don’t do anything to harm David. He hasn’t done anything to harm you. And what he’s done has helped you a lot. <verse eid="1SA 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 19:5"/>He put his own life in danger when he killed Goliath. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> used him to win a great battle for the whole nation of Israel. When you saw it, you were glad. So why would you do anything to harm a man like David? He isn’t guilty of doing anything to harm you. Why would you want to kill him without any reason?”<verse eid="1SA 19:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 19:6"/>Saul paid attention to Jonathan. Saul made a promise. He said, “You can be sure that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> lives. And you can be just as sure that David will not be put to death.”<verse eid="1SA 19:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 19:7"/>So Jonathan sent for David and told him everything he and Saul had said. Then he brought David to Saul. David served Saul as he had done before.<verse eid="1SA 19:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 19:8"/>Once more war broke out. So David went out and fought against the Philistines. He struck them down with so much force that they ran away from him.<verse eid="1SA 19:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 19:9"/>But an evil spirit sent by the <char style="nd">Lord</char> came on Saul. It happened as he was sitting in his house and holding his spear. While David was playing the harp, <verse eid="1SA 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 19:10"/>Saul tried to pin him to the wall with his spear. But David got away from him just as Saul drove the spear into the wall. That night David escaped.<verse eid="1SA 19:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 19:11"/>Saul sent some men to watch David’s house. He told them to kill David the next morning. But David’s wife Michal warned him. She said, “You must run for your life tonight. If you don’t, tomorrow you will be killed.” <verse eid="1SA 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 19:12"/>So Michal helped David escape through a window. He ran and got away. <verse eid="1SA 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 19:13"/>Then Michal got a statue of a god. She laid it on David’s bed. She covered it with clothes. And she put some goat hair at the place where David’s head would have been.<verse eid="1SA 19:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 19:14"/>Saul sent the men to capture David. But Michal told them, “He’s sick.”<verse eid="1SA 19:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 19:15"/>Then Saul sent the men back to see David. He told them, “Bring him up here to me in his bed. Then I’ll kill him.” <verse eid="1SA 19:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 19:16"/>But when the men entered, the only thing they found in the bed was the statue. Some goat hair was at the place where David’s head would have been.<verse eid="1SA 19:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 19:17"/>Saul said to Michal, “Why did you trick me like this? Why did you help my enemy escape?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 19:17">Michal told him, “He said to me, ‘Help me get away. If you don’t, I’ll kill you.’ ”<verse eid="1SA 19:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 19:18"/>After David had run away and escaped, he went to Samuel at Ramah. He told him everything Saul had done to him. Then David and Samuel went to Naioth and stayed there. <verse eid="1SA 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 19:19"/>Saul was told, “David is in Naioth at Ramah.” <verse eid="1SA 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 19:20"/>So Saul sent some men to capture him. When they got there, they saw a group of prophets who were prophesying. Samuel was standing there as their leader. Then the Spirit of God came on Saul’s men. So they also began to prophesy. <verse eid="1SA 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 19:21"/>Saul was told about it. So he sent some more men. They began to prophesy too. Saul sent some men a third time. And they also began to prophesy. <verse eid="1SA 19:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 19:22"/>Finally, Saul decided to go to Ramah himself. He went to the large well at Seku. He asked some people, “Where are Samuel and David?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 19:22">“Over in Naioth at Ramah,” they said.<verse eid="1SA 19:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 19:23"/>So Saul went to Naioth at Ramah. But the Spirit of God even came on him. He walked along and prophesied until he came to Naioth. <verse eid="1SA 19:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 19:24"/>There he took off his clothes. Then he also prophesied in front of Samuel. He lay there without his clothes on all that day and night. That’s why people say, “Is Saul also one of the prophets?”<verse eid="1SA 19:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="1SA 20"/>
  <para style="s1">David and Jonathan</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 20:1"/>David was in Naioth at Ramah. He ran away from there to where Jonathan was. He asked him, “What have I done? What crime have I committed? I haven’t done anything to harm your father. So why is he trying to kill me?”<verse eid="1SA 20:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 20:2"/>“That will never happen!” Jonathan replied. “You aren’t going to die! My father doesn’t do anything at all without letting me know. So why would he hide this from me? He isn’t going to kill you!”<verse eid="1SA 20:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 20:3"/>But David strongly disagreed. He said, “Your father knows very well that you are pleased with me. He has said to himself, ‘I don’t want Jonathan to know I’m planning to kill David. If he finds out, he’ll be very sad.’ But I’m very close to being killed. And that’s just as sure as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> and you are alive.”<verse eid="1SA 20:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 20:4"/>Jonathan said to David, “I’ll do anything you want me to do for you.”<verse eid="1SA 20:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 20:5"/>So David said, “Tomorrow is the time for the New Moon feast. I’m supposed to eat with the king. But let me go and hide in the field. I’ll stay there until the evening of the day after tomorrow. <verse eid="1SA 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 20:6"/>Your father might miss me. If he does, then tell him, ‘David begged me to let him hurry home to Bethlehem. A yearly sacrifice is being offered there for his whole family group.’ <verse eid="1SA 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 20:7"/>Your father might say, ‘That’s all right.’ If he does, it will mean I’m safe. But he might become very angry. If he does, you can be sure he’s made up his mind to harm me. <verse eid="1SA 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 20:8"/>Please be kind to me. You have made a covenant with me in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. If I’m guilty, kill me yourself! Don’t hand me over to your father!”<verse eid="1SA 20:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 20:9"/>“I would never do that!” Jonathan said. “Suppose I had even the smallest clue that my father had made up his mind to harm you. Then I would tell you.”<verse eid="1SA 20:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 20:10"/>David asked, “Who will tell me if your father answers you in a mean way?”<verse eid="1SA 20:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 20:11"/>“Come on,” Jonathan said. “Let’s go out to the field.” So they went there together.<verse eid="1SA 20:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 20:12"/>Then Jonathan spoke to David. He said, “I promise you that I’ll find out what my father is planning to do. I’ll find out by this time the day after tomorrow. The <char style="nd">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, is my witness. Suppose my father has kind feelings toward you. Then I’ll send you a message and let you know. <verse eid="1SA 20:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 20:13"/>But suppose he wants to harm you. And I don’t let you know about it. Suppose I don’t help you get away in peace. Then may the <char style="nd">Lord</char> punish me greatly. May he be with you, just as he has been with my father. <verse eid="1SA 20:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 20:14"/>But always be kind to me, just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is. Be kind to me as long as I live. Then I won’t be killed. <verse eid="1SA 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 20:15"/>And never stop being kind to my family. Don’t stop even when the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has cut off every one of your enemies from the face of the earth.”<verse eid="1SA 20:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 20:16"/>So Jonathan made a covenant of friendship with David and his family. He said, “May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> hold David’s enemies responsible for what they’ve done.” <verse eid="1SA 20:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 20:17"/>Jonathan had David promise his friendship again because he loved him. In fact, Jonathan loved David just as he loved himself.<verse eid="1SA 20:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 20:18"/>Then Jonathan said to David, “Tomorrow is the time for the New Moon feast. You will be missed, because your seat at the table will be empty. <verse eid="1SA 20:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 20:19"/>Go to the place where you hid when all this trouble began. Go there the day after tomorrow, when evening is approaching. There’s a stone out there called Ezel. <verse eid="1SA 20:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 20:20"/>Wait by it. I’ll shoot three arrows to one side of the stone. I’ll pretend I’m practicing my shooting. <verse eid="1SA 20:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 20:21"/>Then I’ll send a boy out there. I’ll tell him, ‘Go and find the arrows.’ Suppose I say to him, ‘The arrows are on this side of you. Bring them here.’ Then come. That will mean you are safe. You won’t be in any danger. And that’s just as sure as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is alive. <verse eid="1SA 20:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 20:22"/>But suppose I tell the boy, ‘The arrows are far beyond you.’ Then go. That will mean the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is sending you away. <verse eid="1SA 20:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 20:23"/>And remember what we talked about. Remember that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is a witness between you and me forever.”<verse eid="1SA 20:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 20:24"/>So David hid in the field. When the time for the New Moon feast came, the king sat down to eat. <verse eid="1SA 20:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 20:25"/>He sat in his usual place by the wall. Jonathan sat across from him. Abner sat next to Saul. But David’s place was empty. <verse eid="1SA 20:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 20:26"/>Saul didn’t say anything that day. He said to himself, “Something must have happened to David to make him ‘unclean.’ That must be why he isn’t here.” <verse eid="1SA 20:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 20:27"/>But the next day, David’s place was empty again. It was the second day of the month. Finally, Saul spoke to his son Jonathan. He said, “Why hasn’t the son of Jesse come to the meal? He hasn’t been here yesterday or today.”<verse eid="1SA 20:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 20:28"/>Jonathan replied, “David begged me to let him go to Bethlehem. <verse eid="1SA 20:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 20:29"/>He said, ‘Let me go. Our family is offering a sacrifice in the town. My brother has ordered me to be there. Are you pleased with me? If you are, let me go and see my brothers.’ That’s why he hasn’t come to eat at your table.”<verse eid="1SA 20:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1SA 20:30"/>Saul became very angry with Jonathan. He said to him, “You are an evil son. You have refused to obey me. I know that you are on the side of Jesse’s son. You should be ashamed of that. And your mother should be ashamed of having a son like you. <verse eid="1SA 20:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1SA 20:31"/>You will never be king as long as Jesse’s son lives on this earth. And you will never have a kingdom either. So send someone to bring the son of Jesse to me. He must die!”<verse eid="1SA 20:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1SA 20:32"/>“Why do you want to put him to death?” Jonathan asked his father. “What has he done?” <verse eid="1SA 20:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1SA 20:33"/>But Saul threw his spear at Jonathan to kill him. Then Jonathan knew that his father wanted to kill David.<verse eid="1SA 20:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1SA 20:34"/>So Jonathan got up from the table. He was very angry. On that second day of the feast, he refused to eat. He was very sad that his father was treating David so badly.<verse eid="1SA 20:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="1SA 20:35"/>The next morning Jonathan went out to the field to meet David. He took a young boy with him. <verse eid="1SA 20:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1SA 20:36"/>He said to the boy, “Run and find the arrows I shoot.” As the boy ran, Jonathan shot an arrow far beyond him. <verse eid="1SA 20:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1SA 20:37"/>The boy came to the place where Jonathan’s arrow had fallen. Then Jonathan shouted to him, “The arrow went far beyond you, didn’t it?” <verse eid="1SA 20:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1SA 20:38"/>He continued, “Hurry up! Run fast! Don’t stop!” The boy picked up the arrow and returned to his master. <verse eid="1SA 20:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1SA 20:39"/>The boy didn’t know what was going on. Only Jonathan and David knew. <verse eid="1SA 20:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1SA 20:40"/>Jonathan gave his weapons to the boy. He told him, “Go back to town. Take the weapons with you.”<verse eid="1SA 20:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="1SA 20:41"/>After the boy had gone, David got up from the south side of the stone. He bowed down in front of Jonathan with his face to the ground. He did it three times. Then they kissed each other and cried. But David cried more than Jonathan did.<verse eid="1SA 20:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="1SA 20:42"/>Jonathan said to David, “Go in peace. In the name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> we’ve promised to be friends. We have said, ‘The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is a witness between you and me. He’s a witness between your children and my children forever.’ ” Then David left, and Jonathan went back to the town.<verse eid="1SA 20:42"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="1SA 21"/>
  <para style="s1">David at Nob</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 21:1"/>David went to Ahimelek the priest at Nob. Ahimelek trembled with fear when he met him. He asked David, “Why are you alone? Why isn’t anyone with you?”<verse eid="1SA 21:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 21:2"/>David answered Ahimelek the priest, “The king gave me a special job to do. He said to me, ‘I don’t want anyone to know what I’m sending you to do. So don’t say anything about it.’ I’ve told my men to meet me at a certain place. <verse eid="1SA 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 21:3"/>Do you have anything for us to eat? Give me five loaves of bread, or anything else you can find.”<verse eid="1SA 21:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 21:4"/>But the priest answered David, “I don’t have any bread that isn’t holy. I only have some holy bread here. But it’s for men who haven’t slept with women recently.”<verse eid="1SA 21:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 21:5"/>David replied, “Well, we haven’t slept with women recently. That’s the way it is every time I lead my men out to battle. We keep ourselves holy even when we do jobs that aren’t holy. And that’s even more true today.” <verse eid="1SA 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 21:6"/>So the priest gave him the holy bread. It was the only bread he had. It had been removed from the table that was in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. On the same day, hot bread had been put in its place.<verse eid="1SA 21:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 21:7"/>One of Saul’s servants was there that day. He had been made to stay at the holy tent for a while. He was Doeg from Edom. Doeg was Saul’s chief shepherd.<verse eid="1SA 21:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 21:8"/>David asked Ahimelek, “Don’t you have a spear or sword here? I haven’t brought my sword or any other weapon. That’s because the job the king gave me to do had to be done right away.”<verse eid="1SA 21:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 21:9"/>The priest replied, “The sword of Goliath, the Philistine, is here. You killed him in the Valley of Elah. His sword is wrapped in a cloth. It’s behind the sacred linen apron. If you want it, take it. It’s the only sword here.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 21:9">David said, “There isn’t any sword like it. Give it to me.”<verse eid="1SA 21:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">David at Gath</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 21:10"/>That day David ran away from Saul. He went to Achish, the king of Gath. <verse eid="1SA 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 21:11"/>But the servants of Achish spoke to him. They said, “Isn’t this David, the king of the land? Isn’t he the one the Israelites sing about when they dance? They sing,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 21:11">“ ‘Saul has killed thousands of men.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 21:11">David has killed tens of thousands.’ ”<verse eid="1SA 21:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 21:12"/>David paid close attention to what the servants were saying. He became very much afraid of what Achish, the king of Gath, might do. <verse eid="1SA 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 21:13"/>So he pretended to be out of his mind when he was with them. As long as he was in Gath, he acted like a crazy person. He made marks on the doors of the city gate. He let spit run down his beard.<verse eid="1SA 21:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 21:14"/>Achish said to his servants, “Just look at the man! He’s out of his mind! Why are you bringing him to me? <verse eid="1SA 21:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 21:15"/>Don’t I have enough crazy people around me already? So why do you have to bring this fellow here? Just look at how he’s carrying on in front of me! Why do you have to bring this man into my house?”<verse eid="1SA 21:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="1SA 22"/>
  <para style="s1">David at Adullam and Mizpah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 22:1"/>David left Gath and escaped to the cave of Adullam. His brothers and the other members of his family heard about it. So they went down to join him there. <verse eid="1SA 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 22:2"/>Everyone who was in trouble or owed money or was unhappy gathered around him. He became their commander. About 400 men were with him.<verse eid="1SA 22:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 22:3"/>From there David went to Mizpah in Moab. He spoke to the king of Moab. He said, “Please let my father and mother come and stay with you. Let them stay until I learn what God will do for me.” <verse eid="1SA 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 22:4"/>So David left his parents with the king of Moab. They stayed with him as long as David was in his usual place of safety.<verse eid="1SA 22:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 22:5"/>But the prophet Gad spoke to David. He said, “Don’t stay in your usual place of safety. Go into the land of Judah.” So David left and went to the forest of Hereth.<verse eid="1SA 22:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Saul Kills the Priests at Nob</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 22:6"/>Saul heard that the place where David and his men were hiding had been discovered. Saul was sitting under a tamarisk tree on the hill at Gibeah. He was holding his spear. All his officials were standing at his side. <verse eid="1SA 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 22:7"/>Saul said to them, “Men of Benjamin, listen to me! Do you think Jesse’s son will give all of you fields and vineyards? Do you think he’ll make some of you commanders of thousands of men? Do you think he’ll make the rest of you commanders of hundreds? <verse eid="1SA 22:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 22:8"/>Is that why all of you have joined together against me? No one tells me when my son makes a covenant with Jesse’s son. None of you is concerned about me. No one tells me that my son has stirred up Jesse’s son to hide and wait to attack me. But that’s exactly what’s happening now.”<verse eid="1SA 22:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 22:9"/>Doeg was standing with Saul’s officials. He was from Edom. He said, “I saw Jesse’s son David come to Ahimelek at Nob. Ahimelek is the son of Ahitub. <verse eid="1SA 22:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 22:10"/>Ahimelek asked the <char style="nd">Lord</char> a question for David. He also gave him food and the sword of Goliath, the Philistine.”<verse eid="1SA 22:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 22:11"/>Then the king sent for the priest Ahimelek, the son of Ahitub. The king also sent for all the men in his family. They were the priests at Nob. All of them came to the king. <verse eid="1SA 22:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 22:12"/>Saul said, “Son of Ahitub, listen to me.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 22:12">“Yes, master,” he answered.<verse eid="1SA 22:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 22:13"/>Saul said to him, “Why have you and Jesse’s son joined together against me? Why did you give him bread and a sword? Why did you ask God a question for him? Now he has turned against me. He is hiding and waiting to attack me right now.”<verse eid="1SA 22:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 22:14"/>Ahimelek answered the king, “David is faithful to you. In fact, he’s more faithful to you than anyone else who serves you. He’s your own son-in-law. He’s the captain of your own personal guards. He’s highly respected by everyone in your palace. <verse eid="1SA 22:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 22:15"/>Was that day the first time I asked God a question for him? Of course not! Please don’t bring charges against me. Please don’t bring charges against anyone in my family. I don’t know anything at all about this whole matter.”<verse eid="1SA 22:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 22:16"/>But the king said, “Ahimelek, you will certainly be put to death. You and your whole family will be put to death.”<verse eid="1SA 22:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 22:17"/>Then the king gave an order to the guards at his side. He said, “Go and kill the priests of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They are on David’s side too. They knew he was running away from me. And they didn’t even tell me.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 22:17">But the king’s officials wouldn’t raise a hand to strike down the priests of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="1SA 22:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 22:18"/>Then the king ordered Doeg, “You go and strike down the priests.” So Doeg, the Edomite, went and struck them down. That day he killed 85 priests who wore linen aprons. <verse eid="1SA 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 22:19"/>He also killed the people of Nob with his sword. Nob was a town where priests lived. Doeg killed its men and women. He killed its children and babies. He also destroyed its cattle, donkeys and sheep.<verse eid="1SA 22:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 22:20"/>But Abiathar, a son of Ahimelek, escaped. Ahimelek was the son of Ahitub. Abiathar ran away and joined David. <verse eid="1SA 22:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 22:21"/>He told David that Saul had killed the priests of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="1SA 22:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 22:22"/>Then David said to Abiathar, “One day I was at Nob. I saw Doeg, the Edomite, there. I knew he would be sure to tell Saul. Your whole family has been killed. And I’m responsible for it. <verse eid="1SA 22:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 22:23"/>So stay with me. Don’t be afraid. The man who wants to kill you wants to kill me too. You will be safe with me.”<verse eid="1SA 22:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="1SA 23"/>
  <para style="s1">David Saves the People of Keilah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 23:1"/>David was told, “The Philistines are fighting against the town of Keilah. They are stealing grain from the threshing floors.” <verse eid="1SA 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 23:2"/>So he asked the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for advice. He said, “Should I go and attack those Philistines?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 23:2">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> answered him, “Go and attack them. Save Keilah.”<verse eid="1SA 23:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 23:3"/>But David’s men said to him, “We’re afraid here in Judah. Suppose we go to Keilah and fight against the Philistine army. Then we’ll be even more afraid.”<verse eid="1SA 23:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 23:4"/>Once again David asked the <char style="nd">Lord</char> what he should do. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> answered him, “Go down to Keilah. I am going to hand the Philistines over to you.” <verse eid="1SA 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 23:5"/>So David and his men went to Keilah. They fought against the Philistines and carried off their livestock. David wounded and killed large numbers of Philistines. And he saved the people of Keilah. <verse eid="1SA 23:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 23:6"/>Abiathar, the son of Ahimelek, had brought down the sacred linen apron with him from Nob. He did it when he ran away to David at Keilah.<verse eid="1SA 23:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Saul Chases David</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 23:7"/>Saul was told that David had gone to Keilah. He said, “God has handed him over to me. David has trapped himself by entering a town that has gates with metal bars.” <verse eid="1SA 23:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 23:8"/>So Saul brought together all his soldiers to go to battle. He ordered them to go down to Keilah. He told them to surround David and his men. He told them to get ready to attack them.<verse eid="1SA 23:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 23:9"/>David learned that Saul was planning to attack him. So he said to Abiathar the priest, “Bring the linen apron.” <verse eid="1SA 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 23:10"/>Then David said, “<char style="nd">Lord</char>, you are the God of Israel. I know for sure that Saul plans to come to Keilah. He plans to destroy the town because of me. <verse eid="1SA 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 23:11"/>Will the citizens of Keilah hand me over to him? Will Saul come down here, as I’ve heard he would? <char style="nd">Lord</char>, you are the God of Israel. Please answer me.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 23:11">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said, “He will come down.”<verse eid="1SA 23:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 23:12"/>Again David asked, “Will the citizens of Keilah hand me and my men over to Saul?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 23:12">And the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said, “They will.”<verse eid="1SA 23:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 23:13"/>So David and his men left Keilah. The total number of them was about 600. They kept moving from place to place. Saul was told that David had escaped from Keilah. So he didn’t go there.<verse eid="1SA 23:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 23:14"/>Sometimes David stayed in places of safety in the desert. At other times he stayed in the hills of the Desert of Ziph. Day after day Saul looked for him. But God didn’t hand David over to him.<verse eid="1SA 23:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 23:15"/>David was at Horesh in the Desert of Ziph. There he learned that Saul had come out to kill him. <verse eid="1SA 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 23:16"/>Saul’s son Jonathan went to David at Horesh. He told David that God would make him strong. <verse eid="1SA 23:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 23:17"/>“Don’t be afraid,” he said. “My father Saul won’t harm you. You will be king over Israel. And I will be next in command. Even my father Saul knows this.” <verse eid="1SA 23:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 23:18"/>The two of them made a covenant of friendship in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Then Jonathan went home. But David remained at Horesh.<verse eid="1SA 23:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 23:19"/>The people of Ziph went up to Saul at Gibeah. They said, “David is hiding among us. He’s hiding in places of safety at Horesh. Horesh is south of Jeshimon on the hill of Hakilah. <verse eid="1SA 23:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 23:20"/>Your Majesty, come down when it pleases you to come. It will be our duty to hand David over to you.”<verse eid="1SA 23:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 23:21"/>Saul replied, “May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> bless you because you were concerned about me. <verse eid="1SA 23:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 23:22"/>Make sure you are right. Go and check things out again. Find out where David usually goes. Find out who has seen him there. People tell me he’s very tricky. <verse eid="1SA 23:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 23:23"/>Find out about all the hiding places he uses. Come back to me with all the facts. I’ll go with you. Suppose he’s in the area. Then I’ll track him down among all the family groups of Judah.”<verse eid="1SA 23:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 23:24"/>So they started out. They went to Ziph ahead of Saul. David and his men were in the Desert of Maon. Maon is south of Jeshimon in the Arabah Valley. <verse eid="1SA 23:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 23:25"/>Saul and his men started out to look for David. David was told about it. So he went down to a rock in the Desert of Maon to hide. Saul heard he was there. So he went into the Desert of Maon to chase David.<verse eid="1SA 23:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 23:26"/>Saul was going along one side of the mountain. David and his men were on the other side. They were hurrying to get away from Saul. Saul and his army were closing in on David and his men. They were about to capture them. <verse eid="1SA 23:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 23:27"/>Just then a messenger came to Saul. He said, “Come quickly! The Philistines are attacking the land.” <verse eid="1SA 23:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 23:28"/>So Saul stopped chasing David. He went to fight against the Philistines. That’s why they call that place Sela Hammahlekoth. <verse eid="1SA 23:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 23:29"/>David left that place. He went and lived in places of safety near En Gedi.<verse eid="1SA 23:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="1SA 24"/>
  <para style="s1">David Doesn’t Kill Saul When He Has the Chance</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 24:1"/>Saul returned from chasing the Philistines. Then he was told, “David is in the Desert of En Gedi.” <verse eid="1SA 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 24:2"/>So Saul took 3,000 of the best soldiers from the whole nation of Israel. He started out to look for David and his men. He planned to look near the Rocky Cliffs of the Wild Goats.<verse eid="1SA 24:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 24:3"/>He came to some sheep pens along the way. A cave was there. Saul went in to go to the toilet. David and his men were far back in the cave. <verse eid="1SA 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 24:4"/>David’s men said, “This is the day the <char style="nd">Lord</char> told you about. He said to you, ‘I will hand your enemy over to you. Then you can deal with him as you want to.’ ” So David came up close to Saul without being seen. He cut off a corner of Saul’s robe.<verse eid="1SA 24:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 24:5"/>Later, David felt sorry that he had cut off a corner of Saul’s robe. <verse eid="1SA 24:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 24:6"/>He said to his men, “May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> keep me from doing a thing like that again to my master. He is the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s anointed king. So I promise that I will never lay my hand on him. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has anointed him.” <verse eid="1SA 24:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 24:7"/>David said that to correct his men. He wanted them to know that they should never suggest harming the king. He didn’t allow them to attack Saul. So Saul left the cave and went on his way.<verse eid="1SA 24:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 24:8"/>Then David went out of the cave. He called out to Saul, “King Saul! My master!” When Saul looked behind him, David bowed down. He lay down flat with his face toward the ground. <verse eid="1SA 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 24:9"/>He said to Saul, “Why do you listen when men say, ‘David is trying to harm you’? <verse eid="1SA 24:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 24:10"/>This day you have seen with your own eyes how the <char style="nd">Lord</char> handed you over to me in the cave. Some of my men begged me to kill you. But I didn’t. I said, ‘I will never lay my hand on my master. He is the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s anointed king.’ <verse eid="1SA 24:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 24:11"/>Look, my father! Look at this piece of your robe in my hand! I cut off the corner of your robe. But I didn’t kill you. See, there is nothing in my hand that shows I am guilty of doing anything wrong. I haven’t turned against you. I haven’t done anything to harm you. But you are hunting me down. You want to kill me. <verse eid="1SA 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 24:12"/>May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> judge between you and me. And may the <char style="nd">Lord</char> pay you back because of the wrong things you have done to me. But I won’t do anything to hurt you. <verse eid="1SA 24:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 24:13"/>People say, ‘Evil acts come from those who do evil.’ So I won’t do anything to hurt you.<verse eid="1SA 24:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 24:14"/>“King Saul, who are you trying to catch? Who do you think you are chasing? I’m nothing but a dead dog or a flea! <verse eid="1SA 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 24:15"/>May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> be our judge. May he decide between us. May he consider my case and stand up for me. May he show that I’m not guilty of doing anything wrong. May he save me from you.”<verse eid="1SA 24:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 24:16"/>When David finished speaking, Saul asked him a question. He said, “My son David, is that your voice?” And Saul wept out loud. <verse eid="1SA 24:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 24:17"/>“You are a better person than I am,” he said. “You have treated me well. But I’ve treated you badly. <verse eid="1SA 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 24:18"/>You have just now told me about the good things you did to me. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> handed me over to you. But you didn’t kill me. <verse eid="1SA 24:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 24:19"/>Suppose a man finds his enemy. He doesn’t let him get away without harming him. May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> reward you with many good things. May he do it because of the way you treated me today. <verse eid="1SA 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 24:20"/>I know for sure that you will be king. I know that the kingdom of Israel will be made secure under your control. <verse eid="1SA 24:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 24:21"/>Now make a promise in the name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Promise me that you won’t kill the children of my family. Also promise me that you won’t wipe out my name from my family line.”<verse eid="1SA 24:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 24:22"/>So David made that promise to Saul. Then Saul returned home. But David and his men went up to his usual place of safety.<verse eid="1SA 24:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 24"/>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="1SA 25"/>
  <para style="s1">David, Nabal and Abigail</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 25:1"/>When Samuel died, the whole nation of Israel gathered together. They were filled with sorrow because he was dead. They buried him at his home in Ramah. Then David went down into the Desert of Paran.<verse eid="1SA 25:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 25:2"/>A certain man in Maon was very wealthy. He owned property there at Carmel. He had 1,000 goats and 3,000 sheep. He was clipping the wool off the sheep in Carmel. <verse eid="1SA 25:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 25:3"/>His name was Nabal. His wife’s name was Abigail. She was a wise and beautiful woman. But her husband was rude and mean in the way he treated others. He was from the family of Caleb.<verse eid="1SA 25:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 25:4"/>David was staying in the Desert of Paran. While he was there, he heard that Nabal was clipping the wool off his sheep. <verse eid="1SA 25:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 25:5"/>So he sent for ten young men. He said to them, “Go up to Nabal at Carmel. Greet him for me. <verse eid="1SA 25:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 25:6"/>Say to him, ‘May you live a long time! May everything go well with you and your family! And may things go well with everything that belongs to you!<verse eid="1SA 25:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 25:7"/>“ ‘I hear that you are clipping the wool off your sheep. When your shepherds were with us, we treated them well. The whole time they were at Carmel nothing that belonged to them was stolen. <verse eid="1SA 25:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 25:8"/>Ask your own servants. They’ll tell you. We’ve come to you now at a happy time of the year. Please be kind to my men. Please give me and my men anything you can find for us.’ ”<verse eid="1SA 25:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 25:9"/>When David’s men arrived, they gave Nabal the message from David. Then they waited.<verse eid="1SA 25:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 25:10"/>Nabal answered David’s servants, “Who is this David? Who is this son of Jesse? Many servants are running away from their masters these days. <verse eid="1SA 25:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 25:11"/>Why should I give away my bread and water? Why should I give away the meat I’ve prepared for those who clip the wool off my sheep? Why should I give food to men who come from who knows where?”<verse eid="1SA 25:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 25:12"/>So David’s men turned around and went back. When they arrived, they reported to David every word Nabal had spoken. <verse eid="1SA 25:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 25:13"/>David said to his men, “Each of you put on your swords!” So they did. David put his sword on too. About 400 men went up with David. Two hundred men stayed behind with the supplies.<verse eid="1SA 25:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 25:14"/>One of the servants warned Abigail, Nabal’s wife. He said, “David sent some messengers from the desert to give his greetings to our master. But Nabal shouted at them and was rude to them. <verse eid="1SA 25:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 25:15"/>David’s men had been very good to us. They treated us well. The whole time we were near them out in the fields, nothing was stolen. <verse eid="1SA 25:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 25:16"/>We were taking care of our sheep near them. During that time, they were like a wall around us night and day. They kept us safe. <verse eid="1SA 25:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 25:17"/>Now think it over. See what you can do. Horrible trouble will soon come to our master and his whole family. He’s such an evil man that no one can even talk to him.”<verse eid="1SA 25:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 25:18"/>Abigail didn’t waste any time. She got 200 loaves of bread and two bottles of wine. The bottles were made out of animal skins. She got five sheep that were ready to be cooked. She got a bushel of grain that had been cooked. She got 100 raisin cakes. And she got 200 cakes of pressed figs. She loaded all of it on the backs of donkeys. <verse eid="1SA 25:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 25:19"/>Then she told her servants, “Go on ahead. I’ll follow you.” But she didn’t tell her husband Nabal about it.<verse eid="1SA 25:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 25:20"/>Abigail rode her donkey into a mountain valley. There she saw David and his men. They were coming down toward her. <verse eid="1SA 25:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 25:21"/>David had just said, “Everything we’ve done hasn’t been worth a thing! I watched over that fellow’s property in the desert. I made sure none of it was stolen. But he has paid me back evil for good. <verse eid="1SA 25:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 25:22"/>I won’t leave even one of his men alive until morning. If I do, may God punish me greatly!”<verse eid="1SA 25:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 25:23"/>When Abigail saw David, she quickly got off her donkey. She bowed down in front of David with her face toward the ground. <verse eid="1SA 25:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 25:24"/>She fell at his feet. She said, “Pardon your servant, sir. Please let me speak to you. Listen to what I’m saying. Let me take the blame myself. <verse eid="1SA 25:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 25:25"/>Please don’t pay any attention to that evil man Nabal. His name means Foolish Person. And that’s exactly what he is. He’s always doing foolish things. I’m sorry I didn’t get a chance to see the men you sent. <verse eid="1SA 25:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 25:26"/>Sir, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has kept you from killing Nabal and his men. He has kept you from using your own hands to get even. So may what’s about to happen to Nabal happen to all your enemies. May it happen to everyone who wants to harm you. And may it happen just as surely as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God and you are alive. <verse eid="1SA 25:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 25:27"/>I’ve brought a gift for you. Give it to the men who follow you.<verse eid="1SA 25:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 25:28"/>“Please forgive me if I shouldn’t have done that. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will certainly give you and your family line a kingdom that will last. That’s because you fight the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s battles. You won’t do anything wrong as long as you live. <verse eid="1SA 25:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 25:29"/>Someone may chase you and try to kill you. But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will keep your life safe like a treasure hidden in a bag. And he’ll destroy your enemies. Their lives will be thrown away, just as a stone is thrown from a sling. <verse eid="1SA 25:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1SA 25:30"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will do for you every good thing he promised to do. He’ll appoint you ruler over Israel. <verse eid="1SA 25:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1SA 25:31"/>When that happens, you won’t have this heavy load on your mind. You won’t have to worry about how you killed people without any reason. You won’t have to worry about how you got even. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will give you success. When that happens, please remember me.”<verse eid="1SA 25:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1SA 25:32"/>David said to Abigail, “Give praise to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He is the God of Israel. He has sent you today to find me. <verse eid="1SA 25:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1SA 25:33"/>May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> bless you for what you have done. You have shown a lot of good sense. You have kept me from killing Nabal and his men this day. You have kept me from using my own hands to get even. <verse eid="1SA 25:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1SA 25:34"/>It’s a good thing you came quickly to meet me. If you hadn’t come, not one of Nabal’s men would have been left alive by sunrise. And that’s just as sure as the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, is alive. He has kept me from harming you.”<verse eid="1SA 25:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="1SA 25:35"/>Then David accepted from her what she had brought him. He said, “Go home in peace. I’ve heard your words. I’ll do what you have asked.”<verse eid="1SA 25:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="1SA 25:36"/>Abigail went back to Nabal. He was having a dinner party in the house. It was the kind of dinner a king would have. He had been drinking too much wine. He was very drunk. So she didn’t tell him anything at all until sunrise. <verse eid="1SA 25:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1SA 25:37"/>The next morning Nabal wasn’t drunk anymore. Then his wife told him everything. When she did, his heart grew weak. He became like a stone. <verse eid="1SA 25:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1SA 25:38"/>About ten days later, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> struck Nabal down. And he died.<verse eid="1SA 25:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="1SA 25:39"/>David heard that Nabal was dead. So he said, “Give praise to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Nabal was rude to me. But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> stood up for me. He has kept me from doing something wrong. He has paid Nabal back for the wrong things he did.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 25:39">Then David sent a message to Abigail. He asked her to become his wife. <verse eid="1SA 25:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1SA 25:40"/>His servants went to Carmel. They said to Abigail, “David has sent us to you. He wants you to come back with us and become his wife.”<verse eid="1SA 25:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="1SA 25:41"/>Abigail bowed down with her face toward the ground. She said, “I am your servant. I’m ready to serve him. I’m ready to wash the feet of his servants.” <verse eid="1SA 25:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1SA 25:42"/>Abigail quickly got on a donkey and went with David’s messengers. Her five female servants went with her. She became David’s wife. <verse eid="1SA 25:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1SA 25:43"/>David had also married Ahinoam from Jezreel. Both of them became his wives. <verse eid="1SA 25:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="1SA 25:44"/>But Saul had given his daughter Michal, David’s first wife, to Paltiel. Paltiel was from Gallim. He was the son of Laish.<verse eid="1SA 25:44"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 25"/>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="1SA 26"/>
  <para style="s1">Once Again David Doesn’t Kill Saul When He Has the Chance</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 26:1"/>Some people from Ziph went to Saul at Gibeah. They said, “David is hiding on the hill of Hakilah. It faces Jeshimon.”<verse eid="1SA 26:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 26:2"/>So Saul went down to the Desert of Ziph. He took 3,000 of the best soldiers in Israel with him. They went to the desert to look for David. <verse eid="1SA 26:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 26:3"/>Saul set up his camp beside the road. It was on the hill of Hakilah facing Jeshimon. But David stayed in the desert. He saw that Saul had followed him there. <verse eid="1SA 26:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 26:4"/>So he sent out scouts. From them he learned that Saul had arrived.<verse eid="1SA 26:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 26:5"/>Then David started out. He went to the place where Saul had camped. He saw where Saul and Abner were lying down. Saul was lying inside the camp. The army was camped all around him. Abner was commander of the army. He was the son of Ner.<verse eid="1SA 26:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 26:6"/>Then David spoke to Ahimelek, the Hittite. He also spoke to Joab’s brother Abishai, the son of Zeruiah. He asked them, “Who will go down with me into the camp to Saul?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 26:6">“I’ll go with you,” said Abishai.<verse eid="1SA 26:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 26:7"/>So that night David and Abishai went into the camp. They found Saul lying asleep inside the camp. His spear was stuck in the ground near his head. Abner and the soldiers were lying asleep around him.<verse eid="1SA 26:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 26:8"/>Abishai said to David, “Today God has handed your enemy over to you. So let me pin him to the ground. I can do it with one jab of the spear. I won’t even have to strike him twice.”<verse eid="1SA 26:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 26:9"/>But David said to Abishai, “Don’t destroy him! No one can do any harm to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s anointed king and not be guilty. <verse eid="1SA 26:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 26:10"/>You can be sure that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> lives,” he said. “And you can be just as sure that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> himself will strike Saul down. Perhaps he’ll die a natural death. Or perhaps he’ll go into battle and be killed. <verse eid="1SA 26:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 26:11"/>May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> keep me from doing anything to harm his anointed king. Now get the spear and water jug that are near his head. Then let’s leave.”<verse eid="1SA 26:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 26:12"/>So David took the spear and water jug that were near Saul’s head. Then he and Abishai left. No one saw them. No one knew about what they had done. In fact, no one even woke up. Everyone was sleeping. That’s because the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had put them into a deep sleep.<verse eid="1SA 26:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 26:13"/>David went across to the other side of the valley. He stood on top of a hill far away from Saul’s camp. There was a wide space between them. <verse eid="1SA 26:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 26:14"/>He called out to the army and to Abner, the son of Ner. He said, “Abner! Aren’t you going to answer me?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 26:14">Abner replied, “Who is calling out to the king?”<verse eid="1SA 26:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 26:15"/>David said, “You are a great soldier, aren’t you? There isn’t anyone else like you in Israel. So why didn’t you guard the king? He’s your master, isn’t he? Someone came into the camp to destroy him. <verse eid="1SA 26:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 26:16"/>You didn’t guard him. And that isn’t good. You can be sure that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> lives. And you can be just as sure that you and your men must die. That’s because you didn’t guard your master. He’s the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s anointed king. Look around you. Where are the king’s spear and water jug that were near his head?”<verse eid="1SA 26:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 26:17"/>Saul recognized David’s voice. He said, “My son David, is that your voice?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 26:17">David replied, “Yes it is, King Saul, my master.” <verse eid="1SA 26:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 26:18"/>He continued, “Why are you chasing me? What evil thing have I done? What am I guilty of? <verse eid="1SA 26:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 26:19"/>King Saul, please listen to what I’m saying. Was it the <char style="nd">Lord</char> who made you angry with me? If it was, may he accept my offering. Was it people who made you angry at me? If it was, may the <char style="nd">Lord</char> see them cursed. They have driven me today from my share of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s land. By doing that, they might as well have said, ‘Go and serve other gods.’ <verse eid="1SA 26:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 26:20"/>Don’t spill my blood on the ground far away from where the <char style="nd">Lord</char> lives. King Saul, you have come out to look for nothing but a flea. It’s as if you were hunting a partridge in the mountains.”<verse eid="1SA 26:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 26:21"/>Then Saul said, “I have sinned. My son David, come back. Today you thought my life was very special. So I won’t try to harm you again. I’ve really acted like a foolish person. I’ve made a huge mistake.”<verse eid="1SA 26:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 26:22"/>“Here’s your spear,” David answered. “Send one of your young men over to get it. <verse eid="1SA 26:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 26:23"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> rewards everyone for doing what is right and being faithful. He handed you over to me today. But I wouldn’t harm you. You are the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s anointed king. <verse eid="1SA 26:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 26:24"/>Today I thought your life had great value. In the same way, may the <char style="nd">Lord</char> think of my life as having great value. May he save me from all trouble.”<verse eid="1SA 26:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 26:25"/>Then Saul said to David, “May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> bless you, David my son. You will do great things. You will also have great success.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 26:25">So David went on his way. And Saul returned home.<verse eid="1SA 26:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 26"/>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="1SA 27"/>
  <para style="s1">David Among the Philistines</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 27:1"/>David thought, “Some day Saul will destroy me. So the best thing I can do is escape. I’ll go to the land of the Philistines. Then Saul will stop looking for me everywhere in Israel. His hand won’t be able to reach me.”<verse eid="1SA 27:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 27:2"/>So David and his 600 men left Israel. They went to Achish, the king of Gath. He was the son of Maok. <verse eid="1SA 27:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 27:3"/>David and his men made their homes in Gath near Achish. Each of David’s men had his family with him. David had his two wives with him. They were Ahinoam from Jezreel and Abigail from Carmel. Abigail was Nabal’s widow. <verse eid="1SA 27:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 27:4"/>Saul was told that David had run away to Gath. So he didn’t look for David anymore.<verse eid="1SA 27:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 27:5"/>David said to Achish, “If you are pleased with me, give me a place in one of your country towns. I can live there. I don’t really need to live near you in the royal city.”<verse eid="1SA 27:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 27:6"/>So on that day Achish gave David the town of Ziklag. It has belonged to the kings of Judah ever since that time. <verse eid="1SA 27:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 27:7"/>David lived in Philistine territory for a year and four months.<verse eid="1SA 27:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 27:8"/>Sometimes David and his men would go up and attack the Geshurites. At other times they would attack the Girzites or the Amalekites. All those people had lived in the land that reached all the way to Shur and Egypt. They had been there for a long time. <verse eid="1SA 27:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 27:9"/>When David would attack an area, he wouldn’t leave a man or woman alive. But he would take their sheep, cattle, donkeys, camels and clothes. Then he would return to Achish.<verse eid="1SA 27:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 27:10"/>Achish would ask, “Who did you attack today?” David would answer, “The people who live in the Negev Desert of Judah.” Or he would answer, “The people in the Negev Desert of Jerahmeel.” Or he would answer, “The people in the Negev Desert of the Kenites.” <verse eid="1SA 27:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 27:11"/>David wouldn’t leave a man or woman alive to be brought back to Gath. He thought, “They might tell on us. They might tell Achish who we really attacked.” That’s what David did as long as he lived in Philistine territory. <verse eid="1SA 27:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 27:12"/>Achish trusted David. He thought, “David’s own people, the Israelites, can’t stand him anymore. So he’ll be my servant for life.”<verse eid="1SA 27:12"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 27"/>
  <chapter number="28" style="c" sid="1SA 28"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 28:1"/>While David was living in Ziklag, the Philistines gathered their army together. They planned to fight against Israel. Achish said to David, “Here is what you must understand. You and your men must march out with me and my army.”<verse eid="1SA 28:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 28:2"/>David said, “I understand. You will see for yourself what I can do.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 28:2">Achish replied, “All right. I’ll make you my own personal guard for life.”<verse eid="1SA 28:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Saul and the Woman at Endor</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 28:3"/>Samuel had died. The whole nation of Israel was filled with sorrow because he was dead. They had buried him in his own town of Ramah. Saul had thrown out of the land people who get messages from those who have died. He had also thrown out people who talk to the spirits of the dead.<verse eid="1SA 28:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 28:4"/>The Philistines gathered together and set up camp at Shunem. At the same time, Saul gathered together all the Israelites. They set up camp at Gilboa. <verse eid="1SA 28:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 28:5"/>When Saul saw the Philistine army, he was afraid. Terror filled his heart. <verse eid="1SA 28:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 28:6"/>He asked the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for advice. But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> didn’t answer him through dreams or prophets. He didn’t answer him when Saul had the priest cast lots by using the Urim. <verse eid="1SA 28:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 28:7"/>Saul spoke to his attendants. He said, “Find me a woman who gets messages from those who have died. Then I can go and ask her some questions.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 28:7">“There’s a woman like that in Endor,” they said.<verse eid="1SA 28:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 28:8"/>Saul put on different clothes so people wouldn’t know who he was. At night he and two of his men went to see the woman. “I want you to talk to a spirit for me,” he said. “Bring up the spirit of the dead person I choose.”<verse eid="1SA 28:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 28:9"/>But the woman said to him, “By now you must know what Saul has done. He has removed everyone who gets messages from those who have died. He has also removed everyone who talks to the spirits of the dead. He has thrown all of them out of the land. Why are you trying to trap me? Why do you want to have me put to death?”<verse eid="1SA 28:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 28:10"/>Saul made a promise in the name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He said to the woman, “You can be sure that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> lives. And you can be just as sure that you won’t be punished for helping me.”<verse eid="1SA 28:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 28:11"/>Then the woman asked, “Whose spirit should I bring up for you?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 28:11">“Bring Samuel up,” he said.<verse eid="1SA 28:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 28:12"/>When the woman saw Samuel, she let out a loud scream. She said to Saul, “Why have you tricked me? You are King Saul!”<verse eid="1SA 28:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 28:13"/>He said to her, “Don’t be afraid. Tell me what you see.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 28:13">The woman said, “I see a ghostly figure. He’s coming up out of the earth.”<verse eid="1SA 28:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 28:14"/>“What does he look like?” Saul asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 28:14">“An old man wearing a robe is coming up,” she said.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 28:14">Then Saul knew it was Samuel. He bowed down. He lay down flat with his face toward the ground.<verse eid="1SA 28:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 28:15"/>Samuel said to Saul, “Why have you troubled me by bringing me up from the dead?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 28:15">“I’m having big problems,” Saul said. “The Philistines are fighting against me. God has left me. He doesn’t answer me anymore. He doesn’t speak to me through prophets or dreams. So I’ve called on you to tell me what to do.”<verse eid="1SA 28:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 28:16"/>Samuel said, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has left you. He has become your enemy. So why are you asking me what you should do? <verse eid="1SA 28:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 28:17"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has spoken through me and has done what he said he would do. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has torn the kingdom out of your hands. He has given it to one of your neighbors. He has given it to David. <verse eid="1SA 28:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 28:18"/>You didn’t obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. You didn’t show his great anger against the Amalekites by destroying them. So he’s punishing you today. <verse eid="1SA 28:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 28:19"/>He will hand both Israel and you over to the Philistines. Tomorrow you and your sons will be down here with me. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will also hand Israel’s army over to the Philistines.”<verse eid="1SA 28:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 28:20"/>Immediately Saul fell flat on the ground. What Samuel had said filled Saul with fear. His strength was gone. He hadn’t eaten anything all that day and all that night.<verse eid="1SA 28:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 28:21"/>The woman went over to Saul because she saw that he was very upset. She said, “Look, I’ve obeyed you. I put my own life in danger by doing what you told me to do. <verse eid="1SA 28:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 28:22"/>So please listen to me. Let me give you some food. Eat it. Then you will have the strength to go on your way.”<verse eid="1SA 28:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 28:23"/>But he refused. He said, “I don’t want anything to eat.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 28:23">Then his men joined the woman in begging him to eat. Finally, he paid attention to them. He got up from the ground and sat on a couch.<verse eid="1SA 28:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 28:24"/>The woman had a fat calf at her house. She killed it at once. She got some flour. She mixed it and baked some bread that didn’t have any yeast in it. <verse eid="1SA 28:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 28:25"/>Then she set the food in front of Saul and his men. They ate it. That same night they got up and left.<verse eid="1SA 28:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 28"/>
  <chapter number="29" style="c" sid="1SA 29"/>
  <para style="s1">Achish Sends David Back to Ziklag</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 29:1"/>The Philistines gathered their whole army together at Aphek. Israel’s army camped by the spring of water at Jezreel. <verse eid="1SA 29:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 29:2"/>The Philistine rulers marched out in groups of hundreds and thousands. David and his men were marching with Achish behind the others. <verse eid="1SA 29:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 29:3"/>The commanders of the Philistines asked, “Why are these Hebrews here?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 29:3">Achish replied, “That’s David, isn’t it? Wasn’t he an officer of Saul, the king of Israel? He has already been with me for more than a year. I haven’t found any fault in him. That’s been true from the day he left Saul until now.”<verse eid="1SA 29:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 29:4"/>But the Philistine commanders were angry with Achish. They said, “Send David back. Let him return to the town you gave him. He must not go with us into battle. If he does, he’ll turn against us during the fighting. In fact, he might even cut off the heads of our own men. What better way could he choose to win back his master’s favor? <verse eid="1SA 29:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 29:5"/>Isn’t David the one the Israelites sang about when they danced? They sang,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 29:5">“ ‘Saul has killed thousands of men.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 29:5">David has killed tens of thousands.’ ”<verse eid="1SA 29:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 29:6"/>So Achish called David over to him. He said, “You have been faithful to me. And that’s just as sure as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is alive. I would be pleased to have you serve with me in the army. I haven’t found any fault in you. That’s been true from the day you came to me until today. But the Philistine rulers aren’t pleased to have you come along. <verse eid="1SA 29:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 29:7"/>So now go back home in peace. Don’t do anything that wouldn’t please the Philistine rulers.”<verse eid="1SA 29:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 29:8"/>“But what have I done?” asked David. “What have you found against me from the day I came to you until now? Why can’t I go and fight against your enemies? After all, you are my king and master.”<verse eid="1SA 29:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 29:9"/>Achish answered, “You have been as pleasing to me as an angel of God. But the Philistine commanders have said, ‘We don’t want David to go up with us into battle.’ <verse eid="1SA 29:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 29:10"/>So get up early in the morning. Take with you the men who used to serve Saul. Leave as soon as the sun begins to come up.”<verse eid="1SA 29:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 29:11"/>So David and his men got up early in the morning. They went back to the land of the Philistines. And the Philistines went up to Jezreel.<verse eid="1SA 29:11"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 29"/>
  <chapter number="30" style="c" sid="1SA 30"/>
  <para style="s1">David Destroys the Amalekites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 30:1"/>On the third day David and his men arrived in Ziklag. The Amalekites had attacked the people of the Negev Desert. They had also attacked Ziklag and burned it. <verse eid="1SA 30:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 30:2"/>They had captured the women and everyone else in Ziklag. They had taken as prisoners young people and old people alike. But they didn’t kill any of them. Instead, they carried them off as they went on their way.<verse eid="1SA 30:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 30:3"/>David and his men reached Ziklag. They saw that it had been destroyed by fire. They found out that their wives and sons and daughters had been captured. <verse eid="1SA 30:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 30:4"/>So David and his men began to weep out loud. They wept until they couldn’t weep anymore. <verse eid="1SA 30:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 30:5"/>David’s two wives had been captured. Their names were Ahinoam from Jezreel and Abigail from Carmel. Abigail was Nabal’s widow. <verse eid="1SA 30:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 30:6"/>David was greatly troubled. His men were even talking about killing him by throwing stones at him. All of them were very bitter because their sons and daughters had been taken away. But David was made strong by the <char style="nd">Lord</char> his God.<verse eid="1SA 30:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 30:7"/>Then David spoke to Abiathar the priest, the son of Ahimelek. He said, “Bring me the linen apron.” Abiathar brought it to him. <verse eid="1SA 30:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 30:8"/>David asked the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for advice. He said, “Should I chase after the men who attacked Ziklag? If I do, will I catch up with them?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 30:8">“Chase after them,” the <char style="nd">Lord</char> answered. “You will certainly catch up with them. You will succeed in saving those who were captured.”<verse eid="1SA 30:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 30:9"/>David and his 600 men came to the Besor Valley. Some of them stayed behind there. <verse eid="1SA 30:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 30:10"/>That’s because 200 of them were too tired to go across the valley. But David and the other 400 continued the chase.<verse eid="1SA 30:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 30:11"/>David’s men found an Egyptian in a field. They brought him to David. They gave him water to drink and food to eat. <verse eid="1SA 30:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 30:12"/>They gave him part of a cake of pressed figs. They also gave him two raisin cakes. After he ate them, he felt as good as new. That’s because he hadn’t eaten any food for three days and three nights. He hadn’t drunk any water during that time either.<verse eid="1SA 30:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 30:13"/>David asked him, “Who do you belong to? Where do you come from?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 30:13">The man said, “I’m from Egypt. I’m the slave of an Amalekite. My master deserted me when I became ill three days ago. <verse eid="1SA 30:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 30:14"/>We attacked the people in the Negev Desert of the Kerethites. We attacked the territory that belongs to Judah. We attacked the people in the Negev Desert of Caleb. And we burned Ziklag.”<verse eid="1SA 30:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 30:15"/>David asked him, “Can you lead me down to the men who attacked Ziklag?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 30:15">He answered, “Make a promise to me in the name of God. Promise that you won’t kill me. Promise that you won’t hand me over to my master. Then I’ll take you down to them.”<verse eid="1SA 30:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 30:16"/>He led David down to where the men were. They were scattered all over the countryside. They were eating and drinking and dancing wildly. That’s because they had taken a large amount of goods from those they had attacked. They had taken it from the land of the Philistines and from the people of Judah. <verse eid="1SA 30:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 30:17"/>David fought against them from sunset until the evening of the next day. None of them escaped except 400 young men. They rode off on camels and got away. <verse eid="1SA 30:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 30:18"/>David got everything back that the Amalekites had taken. That included his two wives. <verse eid="1SA 30:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 30:19"/>Nothing was missing. Not one young person or old person or boy or girl was missing. None of the goods or anything else the Amalekites had taken was missing. David brought everything back. <verse eid="1SA 30:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 30:20"/>He brought back all the flocks and herds. His men drove them on ahead of the other livestock. They said, “Here’s what David has captured.”<verse eid="1SA 30:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 30:21"/>Then David came to the 200 men who had been too tired to follow him. They had been left behind in the Besor Valley. They came out to welcome David and the men with him. As David and his men approached, he asked them how they were. <verse eid="1SA 30:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 30:22"/>But some of the men who had gone out with David were evil. They wanted to stir up trouble. They said, “The 200 men didn’t go out into battle with us. So we won’t share with them the goods we brought back. But each man can take his wife and children and go home.”<verse eid="1SA 30:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 30:23"/>David replied, “No, my friends. You must not hold back their share of what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has given us. He has kept us safe. He has handed over to us the men who attacked us. <verse eid="1SA 30:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 30:24"/>So no one will pay any attention to what you are saying. Each man who stayed with the supplies will receive the same share as each man who went down to the battle. Everyone’s share will be the same.” <verse eid="1SA 30:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 30:25"/>David made that a law and a rule for Israel. It has been followed from that day until now.<verse eid="1SA 30:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 30:26"/>David reached Ziklag. He sent some of the goods to the elders of Judah. They were his friends. He said, “Here’s a gift for you. It’s part of the things we took from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s enemies.”<verse eid="1SA 30:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 30:27"/>David sent some goods to the elders in Bethel, Ramoth Negev and Jattir. <verse eid="1SA 30:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 30:28"/>He sent some to the elders in Aroer, Siphmoth, Eshtemoa <verse eid="1SA 30:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 30:29"/>and Rakal. He sent some to the elders in the towns of the Jerahmeelites and Kenites. <verse eid="1SA 30:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1SA 30:30"/>He sent some to the elders in Hormah, Bor Ashan, Athak <verse eid="1SA 30:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1SA 30:31"/>and Hebron. He also sent some to the elders in all the other places where he and his men had wandered around.<verse eid="1SA 30:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 30"/>
  <chapter number="31" style="c" sid="1SA 31"/>
  <para style="s1">Saul Takes His Own Life</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 31:1"/>The Philistines fought against the Israelites. The Israelites ran away from them. But many Israelites were killed on Mount Gilboa. <verse eid="1SA 31:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 31:2"/>The Philistines kept chasing Saul and his sons. They killed his sons Jonathan, Abinadab and Malki-Shua. <verse eid="1SA 31:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 31:3"/>The fighting was heavy around Saul. Men who were armed with bows and arrows caught up with him. They shot their arrows at him and wounded him badly.<verse eid="1SA 31:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 31:4"/>Saul spoke to the man carrying his armor. He said, “Pull out your sword. Stick it through me. If you don’t, these fellows who aren’t circumcised will come. They’ll stick their swords through me and hurt me badly.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 31:4">But the man was terrified. He wouldn’t do it. So Saul took his own sword and fell on it. <verse eid="1SA 31:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 31:5"/>The man saw that Saul was dead. So he fell on his own sword and died with him. <verse eid="1SA 31:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 31:6"/>Saul and his three sons died together that same day. The man who carried his armor also died with them that day. So did all of Saul’s men.<verse eid="1SA 31:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 31:7"/>The Israelites who lived along the valley saw that their army had run away. So did those who lived across the Jordan River. They saw that Saul and his sons were dead. So they left their towns and ran away. Then the Philistines came and made their homes in them.<verse eid="1SA 31:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 31:8"/>The day after the Philistines had won the battle, they came to take what they wanted from the dead bodies. They found Saul and his three sons dead on Mount Gilboa. <verse eid="1SA 31:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 31:9"/>So they cut off Saul’s head. They took his armor from his body. Then they sent messengers through the whole land of the Philistines. They announced the news in the temple where they had set up statues of their gods. They also announced it among their people. <verse eid="1SA 31:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 31:10"/>They put Saul’s armor in the temple where they had set up statues of female gods that were named Ashtoreth. They hung his body up on the wall of Beth Shan.<verse eid="1SA 31:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 31:11"/>The people of Jabesh Gilead heard about what the Philistines had done to Saul. <verse eid="1SA 31:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 31:12"/>So all their brave men marched through the night to Beth Shan. They took down the bodies of Saul and his sons from the wall of Beth Shan. They brought them to Jabesh. There they burned them. <verse eid="1SA 31:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 31:13"/>Then they got the bones of Saul and his sons and buried them under a tamarisk tree at Jabesh. They didn’t eat anything for seven days.<verse eid="1SA 31:13"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 31"/>
</usx>
