<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="2JN" style="id">- New International Readers Version 2014</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1995, 1996, 1998, 2014 by Biblica, Inc.</para>
  <para style="h">2 John</para>
  <para style="toc1">2 John</para>
  <para style="toc2">2 John</para>
  <para style="toc3">2Jn</para>
  <para style="mt1">2 John</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">The apostle John wrote a second letter. He identifies himself in the letter as a church leader. He does this by using the title of elder. In this letter John refers to the church as a lady. And he refers to the members of the church as her children. This is typical of the greetings used by early followers of Jesus. The same type of greeting is used at the end of Peter’s first letter.</para>
  <para style="ip">Some people from this church had just come to visit John. He was pleased to learn that they continued to believe the truth. But John wrote this letter to warn them about false teachers. He was concerned that the false teachers would spread their false ideas and practices. He warns the church not to support the false teachers in anyway.</para>
  <para style="ip">This brief letter presents all of the themes stated in 1 John. In 1 John, however, the themes are developed more completely.</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="2JN 1"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2JN 1:1"/>I, the elder, am writing this letter.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="2JN 1:1"/>
  <para style="p" vid="2JN 1:1">I am sending it to the lady chosen by God and to her children. I love all of you because of the truth. I’m not the only one who loves you. So does everyone who knows the truth. <verse eid="2JN 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2JN 1:2"/>I love you because of the truth that is alive in us. This truth will be with us forever.<verse eid="2JN 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2JN 1:3"/>God the Father and Jesus Christ his Son will give you grace, mercy and peace. These blessings will be with us because we love the truth.<verse eid="2JN 1:3"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2JN 1:4"/>It has given me great joy to find some of your children living by the truth. That’s just what the Father commanded us to do. <verse eid="2JN 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2JN 1:5"/>Dear lady, I’m not writing you a new command. I’m writing a command we’ve had from the beginning. I’m asking that we love one another. <verse eid="2JN 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2JN 1:6"/>The way we show our love is to obey God’s commands. He commands you to lead a life of love. That’s what you have heard from the beginning.<verse eid="2JN 1:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2JN 1:7"/>I say this because many people have tried to fool others. These people have gone out into the world. They don’t agree that Jesus Christ came in a human body. People like this try to trick others. These people are like the great enemy of Christ. <verse eid="2JN 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2JN 1:8"/>Watch out that you don’t lose what we have worked for. Make sure that you get your full reward. <verse eid="2JN 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2JN 1:9"/>Suppose someone thinks they know more than we do. So they don’t follow Christ’s teaching. Then that person doesn’t belong to God. But whoever follows Christ’s teaching belongs to the Father and the Son. <verse eid="2JN 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2JN 1:10"/>Suppose someone comes to you and doesn’t teach these truths. Then don’t take them into your house or welcome them. <verse eid="2JN 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2JN 1:11"/>Anyone who welcomes them shares in their evil work.<verse eid="2JN 1:11"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2JN 1:12"/>I have a lot to write to you. But I don’t want to use paper and ink. I hope I can visit you instead. Then I can talk with you face to face. That will make our joy complete.<verse eid="2JN 1:12"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2JN 1:13"/>The children of your sister, who is chosen by God, send their greetings.<verse eid="2JN 1:13"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2JN 1"/>
</usx>
