<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="2PE" style="id">- New International Readers Version 2014</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1995, 1996, 1998, 2014 by Biblica, Inc.</para>
  <para style="h">2 Peter</para>
  <para style="toc1">2 Peter</para>
  <para style="toc2">2 Peter</para>
  <para style="toc3">2Pe</para>
  <para style="mt1">2 Peter</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">The Roman emperor Nero put the apostle Peter in prison. And Peter realized he would soon be put to death. So Peter decided to write another letter to the believers he had written to before. Peter wanted these believers to be certain of the truth about Jesus. Peter wrote this letter with authority because he had been with Jesus during his entire ministry.</para>
  <para style="ip">False teachers had come into the churches. They were saying that Jesus really wasn’t going to come back. Some believers had accepted this false teaching. They didn’t expect Jesus to return or to bring justice. So, they started living very ungodly lives.</para>
  <para style="ip">Peter shows that the false teachers are wrong. He points out that he personally saw the glory and majesty of Jesus. He saw it when he was with Jesus on the sacred mountain. Peter states that everyone will see this glory when Jesus comes again. Peter states that the false teachers will lead some people astray. And then he provides a powerful example of the judgment waiting for them.</para>
  <para style="ip">In the final section of the letter, Peter states specifically that Jesus is coming again. But God has delayed when Jesus is coming so people will turn away from their sin. God wants people to live in a way that pleases him. And we are to wait with hope since we all look forward to a new heaven and a new earth.</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="2PE 1"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2PE 1:1"/>I, Simon Peter, am writing this letter. I serve Jesus Christ. I am his apostle.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="2PE 1:1"/>
  <para style="p" vid="2PE 1:1">I am sending this letter to you. You are those who have received a faith as valuable as ours. You received it because our God and Savior Jesus Christ does what is right.<verse eid="2PE 1:1"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2PE 1:2"/>May more and more grace and peace be given to you. May they come to you as you learn more about God and about Jesus our Lord.<verse eid="2PE 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="s1">Showing That God Has Chosen You</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2PE 1:3"/>God’s power has given us everything we need to lead a godly life. All of this has come to us because we know the God who chose us. He chose us because of his own glory and goodness. <verse eid="2PE 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2PE 1:4"/>He has also given us his very great and valuable promises. He did it so you could share in his nature. You can share in it because you’ve escaped from the evil in the world. This evil is caused by sinful desires.<verse eid="2PE 1:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2PE 1:5"/>So you should try very hard to add goodness to your faith. To goodness, add knowledge. <verse eid="2PE 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2PE 1:6"/>To knowledge, add the ability to control yourselves. To the ability to control yourselves, add the strength to keep going. To the strength to keep going, add godliness. <verse eid="2PE 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2PE 1:7"/>To godliness, add kindness for one another. And to kindness for one another, add love. <verse eid="2PE 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2PE 1:8"/>All these things should describe you more and more. They will make you useful and fruitful as you know our Lord Jesus Christ better. <verse eid="2PE 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2PE 1:9"/>But what if these things don’t describe someone at all? Then that person can’t see very well. In fact, they are blind. They have forgotten that their past sins have been washed away.<verse eid="2PE 1:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2PE 1:10"/>My brothers and sisters, try very hard to show that God has appointed you to be saved. Try hard to show that he has chosen you. If you do everything I have just said, you will never trip and fall. <verse eid="2PE 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2PE 1:11"/>You will receive a rich welcome into the kingdom that lasts forever. It is the kingdom of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.<verse eid="2PE 1:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Prophecy of Scripture Comes From God</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2PE 1:12"/>So I will always remind you of these things. I’ll do it even though you know them. I’ll do it even though you now have deep roots in the truth. <verse eid="2PE 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2PE 1:13"/>I think it is right for me to remind you. It is right as long as I live in this tent. I’m talking about my body. <verse eid="2PE 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2PE 1:14"/>I know my tent will soon be removed. Our Lord Jesus Christ has made that clear to me. <verse eid="2PE 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2PE 1:15"/>I hope that you will always be able to remember these things after I’m gone. I will try very hard to see that you do.<verse eid="2PE 1:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2PE 1:16"/>We told you about the time our Lord Jesus Christ came with power. But we didn’t make up clever stories when we told you about it. With our own eyes we saw him in all his majesty. <verse eid="2PE 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2PE 1:17"/>God the Father gave him honor and glory. The voice of the Majestic Glory came to him. It said, “This is my Son, and I love him. I am very pleased with him.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="MAT 17:5">Matthew 17:5</ref>; <ref loc="MRK 9:7">Mark 9:7</ref>; <ref loc="LUK 9:35">Luke 9:35</ref>)</char> <verse eid="2PE 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2PE 1:18"/>We ourselves heard this voice that came from heaven. We were with him on the sacred mountain.<verse eid="2PE 1:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2PE 1:19"/>We also have the message of the prophets. This message can be trusted completely. You must pay attention to it. The message is like a light shining in a dark place. It will shine until the day Jesus comes. Then the Morning Star will rise in your hearts. <verse eid="2PE 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2PE 1:20"/>Above all, here is what you must understand. No prophecy in Scripture ever came from a prophet’s own understanding of things. <verse eid="2PE 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2PE 1:21"/>Prophecy never came simply because a prophet wanted it to. Instead, the Holy Spirit guided the prophets as they spoke. So, although prophets are human, prophecy comes from God.<verse eid="2PE 1:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2PE 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="2PE 2"/>
  <para style="s1">False Teachers Will Be Destroyed</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2PE 2:1"/>But there were also false prophets among the people. In the same way there will be false teachers among you. In secret they will bring in teachings that will destroy you. They will even turn against the Lord and Master who died to pay for their sins. So they will quickly destroy themselves. <verse eid="2PE 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2PE 2:2"/>Many people will follow their lead. These people will do the same evil things the false teachers do. They will cause people to think badly about the way of truth. <verse eid="2PE 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2PE 2:3"/>These teachers are never satisfied. They want to get something out of you. So they make up stories to take advantage of you. They have been under a sentence of death for a long time. The God who will destroy them has not been sleeping.<verse eid="2PE 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2PE 2:4"/>God did not spare angels when they sinned. Instead, he sent them to hell. He chained them up in dark prisons. He will keep them there until he judges them. <verse eid="2PE 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2PE 2:5"/>God did not spare the world’s ungodly people long ago. He brought the flood on them. But Noah preached about the right way to live. God kept him safe. He also saved seven others. <verse eid="2PE 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2PE 2:6"/>God judged the cities of Sodom and Gomorrah. He burned them to ashes. He made them an example of what is going to happen to ungodly people. <verse eid="2PE 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2PE 2:7"/>God saved Lot, a man who did what was right. Lot was shocked by the evil conduct of people who didn’t obey God’s laws. <verse eid="2PE 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2PE 2:8"/>That good man lived among them day after day. He saw and heard the evil things they were doing. They were breaking God’s laws. And the godly spirit of Lot was deeply troubled. <verse eid="2PE 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2PE 2:9"/>Since all this is true, then the Lord knows how to save godly people. He knows how to keep them safe in times of testing. The Lord also knows how to keep ungodly people under guard. He will do so until the day they will be judged and punished. <verse eid="2PE 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2PE 2:10"/>Most of all, this is true of people who follow desires that come from sin’s power. These people hate to be under authority.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2PE 2:10">They are bold and proud. So they aren’t even afraid to speak evil things against heavenly beings. <verse eid="2PE 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2PE 2:11"/>Now angels are stronger and more powerful than these people. But even angels don’t speak evil things against heavenly beings. They don’t do this when they bring judgment on them from the Lord. <verse eid="2PE 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2PE 2:12"/>These people speak evil about things they don’t understand. They are like wild animals who can’t think. Instead, they do what comes naturally to them. They are born only to be caught and destroyed. Just like animals, these people too will die.<verse eid="2PE 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2PE 2:13"/>They will be paid back with harm for the harm they have done. Their idea of pleasure is to have wild parties in the middle of the day. They are like dirty spots and stains. They enjoy their sinful pleasures while they eat with you. <verse eid="2PE 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2PE 2:14"/>They stare at women who are not their wives. They want to sleep with them. They never stop sinning. They trap those who are not firm in their faith. They have mastered the art of getting what they want. God has placed them under his judgment. <verse eid="2PE 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2PE 2:15"/>They have left God’s way. They have wandered off. They follow the way of Balaam, son of Beor. He loved to get paid for doing his evil work. <verse eid="2PE 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2PE 2:16"/>But a donkey corrected him for the wrong he did. Animals don’t speak. But the donkey spoke with a human voice. It tried to stop the prophet from doing a very dumb thing.<verse eid="2PE 2:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2PE 2:17"/>These people are like springs without water. They are like mists driven by a storm. The blackest darkness is reserved for them. <verse eid="2PE 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2PE 2:18"/>They speak empty, bragging words. They make their appeal to the evil desires that come from sin’s power. They tempt new believers who are just escaping from the company of sinful people. <verse eid="2PE 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2PE 2:19"/>They promise to give freedom to these new believers. But they themselves are slaves to sinful living. That’s because “people are slaves to anything that controls them.” <verse eid="2PE 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2PE 2:20"/>They may have escaped the sin of the world. They may have come to know our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ. But what if they are once again caught up in sin? And what if it has become their master? Then they are worse off at the end than they were at the beginning. <verse eid="2PE 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2PE 2:21"/>Suppose they had not known the way of godliness. This would have been better than to know godliness and then turn away from it. The way of godliness is the sacred command passed on to them. <verse eid="2PE 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2PE 2:22"/>What the proverbs say about them is true. “A dog returns to where it has thrown up.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PRO 26:11">Proverbs 26:11</ref>)</char> And, “A pig that is washed goes back to rolling in the mud.”<verse eid="2PE 2:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2PE 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="2PE 3"/>
  <para style="s1">The Day of the Lord</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2PE 3:1"/>Dear friends, this is now my second letter to you. I have written both of them as reminders. I want to encourage you to think in a way that is pure. <verse eid="2PE 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2PE 3:2"/>I want you to remember the words the holy prophets spoke in the past. Remember the command our Lord and Savior gave through your apostles.<verse eid="2PE 3:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2PE 3:3"/>Most of all, here is what you must understand. In the last days people will make fun of the truth. They will laugh at it. They will follow their own evil desires. <verse eid="2PE 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2PE 3:4"/>They will say, “Where is this ‘return’ he promised? Everything goes on in the same way it has since our people of long ago died. In fact, it has continued this way since God first created everything.” <verse eid="2PE 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2PE 3:5"/>Long ago, God’s word brought the heavens into being. His word separated the earth from the waters. And the waters surrounded it. But these people forget things like that on purpose. <verse eid="2PE 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2PE 3:6"/>The waters also flooded the world of that time. And so they destroyed the world. <verse eid="2PE 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2PE 3:7"/>By God’s word the heavens and earth of today are being reserved for fire. They are being kept for the day when God will judge. Then ungodly people will be destroyed.<verse eid="2PE 3:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2PE 3:8"/>Dear friends, here is one thing you must not forget. With the Lord a day is like a thousand years. And a thousand years are like a day. <verse eid="2PE 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2PE 3:9"/>The Lord is not slow to keep his promise. He is not slow in the way some people understand it. Instead, he is patient with you. He doesn’t want anyone to be destroyed. Instead, he wants all people to turn away from their sins.<verse eid="2PE 3:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2PE 3:10"/>But the day of the Lord will come like a thief. The heavens will disappear with a roar. Fire will destroy everything in them. God will judge the earth and everything done in it.<verse eid="2PE 3:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2PE 3:11"/>So everything will be destroyed in this way. And what kind of people should you be? You should lead holy and godly lives. <verse eid="2PE 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2PE 3:12"/>Live like this as you look forward to the day of God. Living like this will make the day come more quickly. On that day fire will destroy the heavens. Its heat will melt everything in them. <verse eid="2PE 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2PE 3:13"/>But we are looking forward to a new heaven and a new earth. Godliness will live there. All this is in keeping with God’s promise.<verse eid="2PE 3:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2PE 3:14"/>Dear friends, I know you are looking forward to this. So try your best to be found pure and without blame. Be at peace with God. <verse eid="2PE 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2PE 3:15"/>Remember that while our Lord is waiting patiently to return, people are being saved. Our dear brother Paul also wrote to you about this. God made him wise to write as he did. <verse eid="2PE 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2PE 3:16"/>Paul writes the same way in all his letters. He speaks about what I have just told you. His letters include some things that are hard to understand. People who don’t know better and aren’t firm in the faith twist what he says. They twist the other Scriptures too. So they will be destroyed.<verse eid="2PE 3:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2PE 3:17"/>Dear friends, you have already been warned about this. So be on your guard. Then you won’t be led astray by people who don’t obey the law. Instead, you will remain safe. <verse eid="2PE 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2PE 3:18"/>Grow in the grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="2PE 3:18"/>
  <para style="b" vid="2PE 3:18"/>
  <para style="p" vid="2PE 3:18">Glory belongs to him both now and forever. Amen.<verse eid="2PE 3:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2PE 3"/>
</usx>
