<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="ACT" style="id">- New International Readers Version 2014</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1995, 1996, 1998, 2014 by Biblica, Inc.</para>
  <para style="h">Acts</para>
  <para style="toc1">Acts</para>
  <para style="toc2">Acts</para>
  <para style="toc3">Ac</para>
  <para style="mt1">Acts</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">Luke wrote the book of Acts as well as the book of Luke. Acts continues the story of the good news of life in Jesus Christ. In the book of Acts the story moves from Jerusalem to other nations. It tells about the Holy Spirit coming to the believers in Jerusalem. And it tells about the teaching and work of Peter and Paul. They were followers of Jesus and leaders of the new church. People from many nations became believers.</para>
  <para style="ip">The book of Acts has six main parts. Each part tells about a new step in the spread of the good news about Jesus. Each part is marked by words similar to “God’s word spread and grew.”</para>
  <para style="ip">First, the church is established in Jerusalem. For the first time the Greek language is used in the church. This allowed for the message of the good news to spread throughout the Roman Empire.</para>
  <para style="ip">Second, the message of the good news spread to Galilee and Samaria.</para>
  <para style="ip">Third, it became clear that the message about Jesus was also for people who were not Jews.</para>
  <para style="ip">Fourth, messengers of the good news went west into the Roman part of Asia.</para>
  <para style="ip">Fifth, the message went from Asia into Europe.</para>
  <para style="ip">Sixth, the last part of the book tells how the message of good news spread to Rome. Rome was the capital city of the Empire. The good news of God’s kingdom is reaching all nations.</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="ACT 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Is Taken Up Into Heaven</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 1:1"/>Theophilus, I wrote about Jesus in my earlier book. I wrote about all he did and taught <verse eid="ACT 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 1:2"/>until the day he was taken up to heaven. Before Jesus left, he gave orders to the apostles he had chosen. He did this through the Holy Spirit. <verse eid="ACT 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 1:3"/>After his suffering and death, he appeared to them. In many ways he proved that he was alive. He appeared to them over a period of 40 days. During that time he spoke about God’s kingdom. <verse eid="ACT 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 1:4"/>One day Jesus was eating with them. He gave them a command. “Do not leave Jerusalem,” he said. “Wait for the gift my Father promised. You have heard me talk about it. <verse eid="ACT 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 1:5"/>John baptized with water. But in a few days you will be baptized with the Holy Spirit.”<verse eid="ACT 1:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 1:6"/>Then the apostles gathered around Jesus and asked him a question. “Lord,” they said, “are you going to give the kingdom back to Israel now?”<verse eid="ACT 1:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 1:7"/>He said to them, “You should not be concerned about times or dates. The Father has set them by his own authority. <verse eid="ACT 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 1:8"/>But you will receive power when the Holy Spirit comes on you. Then you will tell people about me in Jerusalem, and in all Judea and Samaria. And you will even tell other people about me from one end of the earth to the other.”<verse eid="ACT 1:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 1:9"/>After Jesus said this, he was taken up to heaven. The apostles watched until a cloud hid him from their sight.<verse eid="ACT 1:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 1:10"/>While he was going up, they kept on looking at the sky. Suddenly two men dressed in white clothing stood beside them. <verse eid="ACT 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 1:11"/>“Men of Galilee,” they said, “why do you stand here looking at the sky? Jesus has been taken away from you into heaven. But he will come back in the same way you saw him go.”<verse eid="ACT 1:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Matthias Is Chosen to Take the Place of Judas Iscariot</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 1:12"/>The apostles returned to Jerusalem from the hill called the Mount of Olives. It is just over half a mile from the city. <verse eid="ACT 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 1:13"/>When they arrived, they went upstairs to the room where they were staying. Here is a list of those who were there.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ACT 1:13"/>
  <para style="li1" vid="ACT 1:13">Peter, John, James and Andrew,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="ACT 1:13">Philip and Thomas,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="ACT 1:13">Bartholomew and Matthew,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="ACT 1:13">James son of Alphaeus, Simon the Zealot and Judas son of James<verse eid="ACT 1:13"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 1:14"/>They all came together regularly to pray. The women joined them too. So did Jesus’ mother Mary and his brothers.<verse eid="ACT 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 1:15"/>In those days Peter stood up among the believers. About 120 of them were there. <verse eid="ACT 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 1:16"/>Peter said, “Brothers and sisters, a long time ago the Holy Spirit spoke through David. He spoke about Judas Iscariot. What the Scripture said would happen had to come true. Judas was the guide for the men who arrested Jesus. <verse eid="ACT 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 1:17"/>But Judas was one of us. He shared with us in our work for God.”<verse eid="ACT 1:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 1:18"/>Judas bought a field with the payment he received for the evil thing he had done. He fell down headfirst in the field. His body burst open. All his insides spilled out. <verse eid="ACT 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 1:19"/>Everyone in Jerusalem heard about this. So they called that field Akeldama. In their language, Akeldama means the Field of Blood.<verse eid="ACT 1:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 1:20"/>Peter said, “Here is what is written in the Book of Psalms. It says,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 1:20">“ ‘May his home be deserted.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 1:20">May no one live in it.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 69:25">Psalm 69:25</ref>)</char></para>
  <para style="m" vid="ACT 1:20">The Psalms also say,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 1:20">“ ‘Let someone else take his place as leader.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 109:8">Psalm 109:8</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 1:20"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 1:21"/>So we need to choose someone to take his place. It will have to be a man who was with us the whole time the Lord Jesus was living among us. <verse eid="ACT 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 1:22"/>That time began when John was baptizing. It ended when Jesus was taken up from us. The one we choose must join us in telling people that Jesus rose from the dead.”<verse eid="ACT 1:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 1:23"/>So they suggested the names of two men. One was Joseph, who was called Barsabbas. He was also called Justus. The other man was Matthias. <verse eid="ACT 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 1:24"/>Then the believers prayed. They said, “Lord, you know everyone’s heart. Show us which of these two you have chosen. <verse eid="ACT 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 1:25"/>Show us who should take the place of Judas as an apostle. He gave up being an apostle to go where he belongs.” <verse eid="ACT 1:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 1:26"/>Then they cast lots. Matthias was chosen. So he was added to the 11 apostles.<verse eid="ACT 1:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="ACT 2"/>
  <para style="s1">The Holy Spirit Comes at Pentecost</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 2:1"/>When the day of Pentecost came, all the believers gathered in one place. <verse eid="ACT 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 2:2"/>Suddenly a sound came from heaven. It was like a strong wind blowing. It filled the whole house where they were sitting. <verse eid="ACT 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 2:3"/>They saw something that looked like fire in the shape of tongues. The flames separated and came to rest on each of them. <verse eid="ACT 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 2:4"/>All of them were filled with the Holy Spirit. They began to speak in languages they had not known before. The Spirit gave them the ability to do this.<verse eid="ACT 2:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 2:5"/>Godly Jews from every country in the world were staying in Jerusalem. <verse eid="ACT 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 2:6"/>A crowd came together when they heard the sound. They were bewildered because each of them heard their own language being spoken. <verse eid="ACT 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 2:7"/>The crowd was really amazed. They asked, “Aren’t all these people who are speaking Galileans? <verse eid="ACT 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 2:8"/>Then why do we each hear them speaking in our own native language? <verse eid="ACT 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 2:9"/>We are Parthians, Medes and Elamites. We live in Mesopotamia, Judea and Cappadocia. We are from Pontus, Asia, <verse eid="ACT 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 2:10"/>Phrygia and Pamphylia. Others of us are from Egypt and the parts of Libya near Cyrene. Still others are visitors from Rome. <verse eid="ACT 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 2:11"/>Some of the visitors are Jews. Others have accepted the Jewish faith. Also, Cretans and Arabs are here. We hear all these people speaking about God’s wonders in our own languages!” <verse eid="ACT 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 2:12"/>They were amazed and bewildered. They asked one another, “What does this mean?”<verse eid="ACT 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 2:13"/>But some people in the crowd made fun of the believers. “They’ve had too much wine!” they said.<verse eid="ACT 2:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Peter Speaks to the Crowd</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 2:14"/>Then Peter stood up with the 11 apostles. In a loud voice he spoke to the crowd. “My fellow Jews,” he said, “let me explain this to you. All of you who live in Jerusalem, listen carefully to what I say. <verse eid="ACT 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 2:15"/>You think these people are drunk. But they aren’t. It’s only nine o’clock in the morning! <verse eid="ACT 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 2:16"/>No, here is what the prophet Joel meant. <verse eid="ACT 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 2:17"/>He said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 2:17">“ ‘In the last days, God says,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:17">I will pour out my Holy Spirit on all people.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 2:17">Your sons and daughters will prophesy.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:17">Your young men will see visions.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:17">Your old men will have dreams.<verse eid="ACT 2:17"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 2:18"/>In those days, I will pour out my Spirit on my servants.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:18">I will pour out my Spirit on both men and women.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:18">When I do, they will prophesy.<verse eid="ACT 2:18"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 2:19"/>I will show wonders in the heavens above.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:19">I will show signs on the earth below.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:19">There will be blood and fire and clouds of smoke.<verse eid="ACT 2:19"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 2:20"/>The sun will become dark.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:20">The moon will turn red like blood.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:20">This will happen before the coming of the great and glorious day of the Lord.<verse eid="ACT 2:20"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 2:21"/>Everyone who calls</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:21">on the name of the Lord will be saved.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="JOL 2:28-32">Joel 2:28–32</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 2:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 2:22"/>“Fellow Israelites, listen to this! Jesus of Nazareth was a man who had God’s approval. God did miracles, wonders and signs among you through Jesus. You yourselves know this. <verse eid="ACT 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 2:23"/>Long ago God planned that Jesus would be handed over to you. With the help of evil people, you put Jesus to death. You nailed him to the cross. <verse eid="ACT 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 2:24"/>But God raised him from the dead. He set him free from the suffering of death. It wasn’t possible for death to keep its hold on Jesus. <verse eid="ACT 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 2:25"/>David spoke about him. He said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 2:25">“ ‘I know that the Lord is always with me.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:25">Because he is at my right hand,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:25">I will always be secure.<verse eid="ACT 2:25"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 2:26"/>So my heart is glad and joy is on my tongue.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:26">My whole body will be full of hope.<verse eid="ACT 2:26"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 2:27"/>You will not leave me in the place of the dead.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:27">You will not let your holy one rot away.<verse eid="ACT 2:27"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 2:28"/>You always show me the path that leads to life.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:28">You will fill me with joy when I am with you.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 16:8-11">Psalm 16:8–11</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 2:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 2:29"/>“Fellow Israelites, you can be sure that King David died. He was buried. His tomb is still here today. <verse eid="ACT 2:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 2:30"/>But David was a prophet. He knew that God had made a promise to him. God had promised that he would make someone in David’s family line king after him. <verse eid="ACT 2:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 2:31"/>David saw what was coming. So he spoke about the Messiah rising from the dead. He said that the Messiah would not be left in the place of the dead. His body wouldn’t rot in the ground. <verse eid="ACT 2:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 2:32"/>God has raised this same Jesus back to life. We are all witnesses of this. <verse eid="ACT 2:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 2:33"/>Jesus has been given a place of honor at the right hand of God. He has received the Holy Spirit from the Father. This is what God had promised. It is Jesus who has poured out what you now see and hear. <verse eid="ACT 2:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 2:34"/>David did not go up to heaven. But he said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 2:34">“ ‘The Lord said to my Lord,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:34">“Sit at my right hand.<verse eid="ACT 2:34"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 2:35"/>I will put your enemies</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 2:35">under your control.” ’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 110:1">Psalm 110:1</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 2:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 2:36"/>“So be sure of this, all you people of Israel. You nailed Jesus to the cross. But God has made him both Lord and Messiah.”<verse eid="ACT 2:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 2:37"/>When the people heard this, it had a deep effect on them. They said to Peter and the other apostles, “Brothers, what should we do?”<verse eid="ACT 2:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 2:38"/>Peter replied, “All of you must turn away from your sins and be baptized in the name of Jesus Christ. Then your sins will be forgiven. You will receive the gift of the Holy Spirit. <verse eid="ACT 2:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 2:39"/>The promise is for you and your children. It is also for all who are far away. It is for all whom the Lord our God will choose.”<verse eid="ACT 2:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 2:40"/>Peter said many other things to warn them. He begged them, “Save yourselves from these evil people.” <verse eid="ACT 2:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 2:41"/>Those who accepted his message were baptized. About 3,000 people joined the believers that day.<verse eid="ACT 2:41"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Believers Share Their Lives Together</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="ACT 2:42"/>The believers studied what the apostles taught. They shared their lives together. They ate and prayed together. <verse eid="ACT 2:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="ACT 2:43"/>Everyone was amazed at what God was doing. They were amazed when the apostles performed many wonders and signs. <verse eid="ACT 2:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="ACT 2:44"/>All the believers were together. They shared everything they had. <verse eid="ACT 2:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="ACT 2:45"/>They sold property and other things they owned. They gave to anyone who needed something. <verse eid="ACT 2:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="ACT 2:46"/>Every day they met together in the temple courtyard. They ate meals together in their homes. Their hearts were glad and sincere. <verse eid="ACT 2:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="ACT 2:47"/>They praised God. They were respected by all the people. Every day the Lord added to their group those who were being saved.<verse eid="ACT 2:47"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="ACT 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Peter Heals a Beggar Who Can’t Walk</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 3:1"/>One day Peter and John were going up to the temple. It was three o’clock in the afternoon. It was the time for prayer. <verse eid="ACT 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 3:2"/>A man unable to walk was being carried to the temple gate called Beautiful. He had been that way since he was born. Every day someone put him near the gate. There he would beg from people going into the temple courtyards. <verse eid="ACT 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 3:3"/>He saw that Peter and John were about to enter. So he asked them for money. <verse eid="ACT 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 3:4"/>Peter looked straight at him, and so did John. Then Peter said, “Look at us!” <verse eid="ACT 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 3:5"/>So the man watched them closely. He expected to get something from them.<verse eid="ACT 3:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 3:6"/>Peter said, “I don’t have any silver or gold. But I’ll give you what I do have. In the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth, get up and walk.” <verse eid="ACT 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 3:7"/>Then Peter took him by the right hand and helped him up. At once the man’s feet and ankles became strong. <verse eid="ACT 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 3:8"/>He jumped to his feet and began to walk. He went with Peter and John into the temple courtyards. He walked and jumped and praised God. <verse eid="ACT 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 3:9"/>All the people saw him walking and praising God. <verse eid="ACT 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 3:10"/>They recognized him as the same man who used to sit and beg at the temple gate called Beautiful. They were filled with wonder. They were amazed at what had happened to him.<verse eid="ACT 3:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Peter Speaks to the People at the Temple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 3:11"/>The man was holding on to Peter and John. All the people were amazed. They came running to them at the place called Solomon’s Porch. <verse eid="ACT 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 3:12"/>When Peter saw this, he said, “Fellow Israelites, why does this surprise you? Why do you stare at us? It’s not as if we’ve made this man walk by our own power or godliness. <verse eid="ACT 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 3:13"/>The God of our fathers, Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, has done this. God has brought glory to Jesus, who serves him. But you handed Jesus over to be killed. Pilate had decided to let him go. But you spoke against Jesus when he was in Pilate’s court. <verse eid="ACT 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 3:14"/>You spoke against the Holy and Blameless One. You asked for a murderer to be set free instead. <verse eid="ACT 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 3:15"/>You killed the one who gives life. But God raised him from the dead. We are witnesses of this. <verse eid="ACT 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 3:16"/>This man whom you see and know was made strong because of faith in Jesus’ name. Faith in Jesus has healed him completely. You can see it with your own eyes.<verse eid="ACT 3:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 3:17"/>“My fellow Israelites, I know you didn’t realize what you were doing. Neither did your leaders. <verse eid="ACT 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 3:18"/>But God had given a promise through all the prophets. And this is how he has made his promise come true. He said that his Messiah would suffer. <verse eid="ACT 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 3:19"/>So turn away from your sins. Turn to God. Then your sins will be wiped away. The time will come when the Lord will make everything new. <verse eid="ACT 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 3:20"/>He will send the Messiah. Jesus has been appointed as the Messiah for you. <verse eid="ACT 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 3:21"/>Heaven must receive him until the time when God makes everything new. He promised this long ago through his holy prophets. <verse eid="ACT 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 3:22"/>Moses said, ‘The Lord your God will raise up for you a prophet like me. He will be one of your own people. You must listen to everything he tells you. <verse eid="ACT 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 3:23"/>Anyone who does not listen to him will be completely cut off from their people.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="DEU 18:15">Deuteronomy 18:15</ref>,<ref loc="DEU 18:18">18</ref>,<ref loc="DEU 18:19">19</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 3:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 3:24"/>“Beginning with Samuel, all the prophets spoke about this. They said these days would come. <verse eid="ACT 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 3:25"/>What the prophets said was meant for you. The covenant God made with your people long ago is yours also. He said to Abraham, ‘All nations on earth will be blessed through your children.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="GEN 22:18">Genesis 22:18</ref>; <ref loc="GEN 26:4">26:4</ref>)</char> <verse eid="ACT 3:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 3:26"/>God raised up Jesus, who serves him. God sent him first to you. He did it to bless you. He wanted to turn each of you from your evil ways.”<verse eid="ACT 3:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="ACT 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Peter and John Are Taken to the Sanhedrin</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 4:1"/>Peter and John were speaking to the people. The priests, the captain of the temple guard, and the Sadducees came up to the apostles. <verse eid="ACT 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 4:2"/>They were very upset by what the apostles were teaching the people. The apostles were saying that people can be raised from the dead. They said this can happen because Jesus rose from the dead. <verse eid="ACT 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 4:3"/>So the temple authorities arrested Peter and John. It was already evening, so they put them in prison until the next day. <verse eid="ACT 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 4:4"/>But many who heard the message believed. The number of men who believed grew to about 5,000.<verse eid="ACT 4:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 4:5"/>The next day the rulers, the elders and the teachers of the law met in Jerusalem. <verse eid="ACT 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 4:6"/>Annas, the high priest, was there. So were Caiaphas, John, Alexander and other people in the high priest’s family. <verse eid="ACT 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 4:7"/>They had Peter and John brought to them. They wanted to question them. “By what power did you do this?” they asked. “And through whose name?”<verse eid="ACT 4:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 4:8"/>Peter was filled with the Holy Spirit. He said to them, “Rulers and elders of the people! <verse eid="ACT 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 4:9"/>Are you asking us to explain our actions today? Do you want to know why we were kind to a man who couldn’t walk? Are you asking how he was healed? <verse eid="ACT 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 4:10"/>Then listen to this, you and all the people of Israel! You nailed Jesus Christ of Nazareth to the cross. But God raised him from the dead. It is through Jesus’ name that this man stands healed in front of you. <verse eid="ACT 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 4:11"/>Scripture says that Jesus is</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 4:11">“ ‘the stone you builders did not accept.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 4:11">But it has become the most important stone of all.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 118:22">Psalm 118:22</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 4:11"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 4:12"/>You can’t be saved by believing in anyone else. God has given people no other name under heaven that will save them.”<verse eid="ACT 4:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 4:13"/>The leaders saw how bold Peter and John were. They also realized that Peter and John were ordinary men with no training. This surprised the leaders. They realized that these men had been with Jesus. <verse eid="ACT 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 4:14"/>The leaders could see the man who had been healed. He was standing there with them. So there was nothing they could say. <verse eid="ACT 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 4:15"/>They ordered Peter and John to leave the Sanhedrin. Then they talked things over. <verse eid="ACT 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 4:16"/>“What can we do with these men?” they asked. “Everyone living in Jerusalem knows they have performed an unusual miracle. We can’t say it didn’t happen. <verse eid="ACT 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 4:17"/>We have to stop this thing. It must not spread any further among the people. We have to warn these men. They must never speak to anyone in Jesus’ name again.”<verse eid="ACT 4:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 4:18"/>Once again the leaders called in Peter and John. They commanded them not to speak or teach at all in Jesus’ name. <verse eid="ACT 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 4:19"/>But Peter and John replied, “Which is right from God’s point of view? Should we listen to you? Or should we listen to God? You be the judges! <verse eid="ACT 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 4:20"/>There’s nothing else we can do. We have to speak about the things we’ve seen and heard.”<verse eid="ACT 4:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 4:21"/>The leaders warned them again. Then they let them go. They couldn’t decide how to punish Peter and John. They knew that all the people were praising God for what had happened. <verse eid="ACT 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 4:22"/>The man who had been healed by the miracle was over 40 years old.<verse eid="ACT 4:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Believers Pray</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 4:23"/>Peter and John were allowed to leave. They went back to their own people. They reported everything the chief priests and the elders had said to them. <verse eid="ACT 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 4:24"/>The believers heard this. Then they raised their voices together in prayer to God. “Lord and King,” they said, “you made the heavens, the earth and the sea. You made everything in them. <verse eid="ACT 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 4:25"/>Long ago you spoke by the Holy Spirit. You spoke through the mouth of our father David, who served you. You said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 4:25">“ ‘Why are the nations angry?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 4:25">Why do the people make useless plans?<verse eid="ACT 4:25"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 4:26"/>The kings of the earth rise up.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 4:26">The rulers of the earth gather together</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 4:26">against the Lord</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 4:26">and against his anointed king.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 2:1">Psalm 2:1</ref>,<ref loc="PSA 2:2">2</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 4:26"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 4:27"/>In fact, Herod and Pontius Pilate met with the Gentiles in this city. They also met with the people of Israel. All of them made plans against your holy servant Jesus. He is the one you anointed. <verse eid="ACT 4:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 4:28"/>They did what your power and purpose had already decided should happen. <verse eid="ACT 4:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 4:29"/>Now, Lord, consider the bad things they say they are going to do. Help us to be very bold when we speak your word. <verse eid="ACT 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 4:30"/>Stretch out your hand to heal. Do signs and wonders through the name of your holy servant Jesus.”<verse eid="ACT 4:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 4:31"/>After they prayed, the place where they were meeting was shaken. They were all filled with the Holy Spirit. They were bold when they spoke God’s word.<verse eid="ACT 4:31"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Believers Share What They Own</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 4:32"/>All the believers were agreed in heart and mind. They didn’t claim that anything they had was their own. Instead, they shared everything they owned. <verse eid="ACT 4:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 4:33"/>With great power the apostles continued their teaching. They were telling people that the Lord Jesus had risen from the dead. And God’s grace was working powerfully in all of them. <verse eid="ACT 4:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 4:34"/>So there were no needy persons among them. From time to time, those who owned land or houses sold them. They brought the money from the sales. <verse eid="ACT 4:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 4:35"/>They put it down at the apostles’ feet. It was then given out to anyone who needed it.<verse eid="ACT 4:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 4:36"/>Joseph was a Levite from Cyprus. The apostles called him Barnabas. The name Barnabas means Son of Help. <verse eid="ACT 4:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 4:37"/>Barnabas sold a field he owned. He brought the money from the sale. He put it down at the apostles’ feet.<verse eid="ACT 4:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="ACT 5"/>
  <para style="s1">Ananias and Sapphira</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 5:1"/>A man named Ananias and his wife, Sapphira, also sold some land. <verse eid="ACT 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 5:2"/>He kept part of the money for himself. Sapphira knew he had kept it. He brought the rest of it and put it down at the apostles’ feet.<verse eid="ACT 5:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 5:3"/>Then Peter said, “Ananias, why did you let Satan fill your heart? He made you lie to the Holy Spirit. You have kept some of the money you received for the land. <verse eid="ACT 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 5:4"/>Didn’t the land belong to you before it was sold? After it was sold, you could have used the money as you wished. What made you think of doing such a thing? You haven’t lied just to people. You’ve also lied to God.”<verse eid="ACT 5:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 5:5"/>When Ananias heard this, he fell down and died. All who heard what had happened were filled with fear. <verse eid="ACT 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 5:6"/>Some young men came and wrapped up his body. They carried him out and buried him.<verse eid="ACT 5:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 5:7"/>About three hours later, the wife of Ananias came in. She didn’t know what had happened. <verse eid="ACT 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 5:8"/>Peter asked her, “Tell me. Is this the price you and Ananias sold the land for?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 5:8">“Yes,” she said. “That’s the price.”<verse eid="ACT 5:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 5:9"/>Peter asked her, “How could you agree to test the Spirit of the Lord? Listen! You can hear the steps of the men who buried your husband. They are at the door. They will carry you out also.”<verse eid="ACT 5:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 5:10"/>At that moment she fell down at Peter’s feet and died. Then the young men came in. They saw that Sapphira was dead. So they carried her out and buried her beside her husband. <verse eid="ACT 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 5:11"/>The whole church and all who heard about these things were filled with fear.<verse eid="ACT 5:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Apostles Heal Many People</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 5:12"/>The apostles did many signs and wonders among the people. All the believers used to meet together at Solomon’s Porch. <verse eid="ACT 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 5:13"/>No outsider dared to join them. But the people thought highly of them. <verse eid="ACT 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 5:14"/>More and more men and women believed in the Lord. They joined the other believers. <verse eid="ACT 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 5:15"/>So people brought those who were sick into the streets. They placed them on beds and mats. They hoped that at least Peter’s shadow might fall on some of them as he walked by. <verse eid="ACT 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 5:16"/>Crowds even gathered from the towns around Jerusalem. They brought their sick people. They also brought those who were suffering because of evil spirits. All of them were healed.<verse eid="ACT 5:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Apostles Are Treated Badly</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 5:17"/>The high priest and all his companions were Sadducees. They were very jealous of the apostles. <verse eid="ACT 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 5:18"/>So they arrested them and put them in the public jail. <verse eid="ACT 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 5:19"/>But during the night an angel of the Lord came. He opened the doors of the jail and brought the apostles out. <verse eid="ACT 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 5:20"/>“Go! Stand in the temple courtyard,” the angel said. “Tell the people all about this new life.”<verse eid="ACT 5:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 5:21"/>Early the next day they did as they had been told. They entered the temple courtyard. There they began to teach the people.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 5:21">The high priest and his companions arrived. They called the Sanhedrin together. The Sanhedrin was a gathering of all the elders of Israel. They sent for the apostles who were in jail. <verse eid="ACT 5:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 5:22"/>The officers arrived at the jail. But they didn’t find the apostles there. So they went back and reported it. <verse eid="ACT 5:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 5:23"/>“We found the jail locked up tight,” they said. “The guards were standing at the doors. But when we opened the doors, we didn’t find anyone inside.” <verse eid="ACT 5:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 5:24"/>When the captain of the temple guard and the chief priests heard this report, they were bewildered. They wondered what would happen next.<verse eid="ACT 5:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 5:25"/>Then someone came and said, “Look! The men you put in jail are standing in the temple courtyard. They are teaching the people.” <verse eid="ACT 5:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 5:26"/>So the captain went with his officers and brought the apostles back. But they didn’t use force. They were afraid the people would kill them by throwing stones at them.<verse eid="ACT 5:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 5:27"/>They brought the apostles to the Sanhedrin. The high priest questioned them. <verse eid="ACT 5:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 5:28"/>“We gave you clear orders not to teach in Jesus’ name,” he said. “But you have filled Jerusalem with your teaching. You want to make us guilty of this man’s death.”<verse eid="ACT 5:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 5:29"/>Peter and the other apostles replied, “We must obey God instead of people! <verse eid="ACT 5:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 5:30"/>You had Jesus killed by nailing him to a cross. But the God of our people raised Jesus from the dead. <verse eid="ACT 5:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 5:31"/>Now Jesus is Prince and Savior. God has proved this by giving Jesus a place of honor with him. He did it to turn Israel away from their sins and forgive them. <verse eid="ACT 5:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 5:32"/>We are telling people about these things. And so is the Holy Spirit. God has given the Spirit to those who obey him.”<verse eid="ACT 5:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 5:33"/>When the leaders heard this, they became very angry. They wanted to put the apostles to death. <verse eid="ACT 5:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 5:34"/>But a Pharisee named Gamaliel stood up in the Sanhedrin. He was a teacher of the law. He was honored by all the people. He ordered the apostles to be taken outside for a little while. <verse eid="ACT 5:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 5:35"/>Then Gamaliel spoke to the Sanhedrin. “Men of Israel,” he said, “think carefully about what you plan to do to these men. <verse eid="ACT 5:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 5:36"/>Some time ago Theudas appeared. He claimed he was really somebody. About 400 people followed him. But he was killed. All his followers were scattered. So they accomplished nothing. <verse eid="ACT 5:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 5:37"/>After this, Judas from Galilee came along. This was in the days when the Romans made a list of all the people. Judas led a gang of men against the Romans. He too was killed. All his followers were scattered. <verse eid="ACT 5:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 5:38"/>So let me give you some advice. Leave these men alone! Let them go! If their plans and actions only come from people, they will fail. <verse eid="ACT 5:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 5:39"/>But if their plans come from God, you won’t be able to stop these men. You will only find yourselves fighting against God.”<verse eid="ACT 5:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 5:40"/>His speech won the leaders over. They called the apostles in and had them whipped. The leaders ordered them not to speak in Jesus’ name. Then they let the apostles go.<verse eid="ACT 5:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 5:41"/>The apostles were full of joy as they left the Sanhedrin. They considered it an honor to suffer shame for the name of Jesus. <verse eid="ACT 5:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="ACT 5:42"/>Every day they taught in the temple courtyards and from house to house. They never stopped telling people the good news that Jesus is the Messiah.<verse eid="ACT 5:42"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="ACT 6"/>
  <para style="s1">Seven Leaders Are Chosen</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 6:1"/>In those days the number of believers was growing. The Greek Jews complained about the non-Greek Jews. They said that the widows of the Greek Jews were not being taken care of. They weren’t getting their fair share of food each day. <verse eid="ACT 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 6:2"/>So the 12 apostles gathered all the believers together. They said, “It wouldn’t be right for us to give up teaching God’s word. And we’d have to stop teaching to wait on tables. <verse eid="ACT 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 6:3"/>Brothers and sisters, choose seven of your men. They must be known as men who are wise and full of the Holy Spirit. We will turn this important work over to them. <verse eid="ACT 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 6:4"/>Then we can give our attention to prayer and to teaching God’s word.”<verse eid="ACT 6:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 6:5"/>This plan pleased the whole group. They chose Stephen. He was full of faith and of the Holy Spirit. Philip, Procorus, Nicanor, Timon and Parmenas were chosen too. The group also chose Nicolas from Antioch. He had accepted the Jewish faith. <verse eid="ACT 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 6:6"/>The group brought them to the apostles. Then the apostles prayed and placed their hands on them.<verse eid="ACT 6:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 6:7"/>So God’s word spread. The number of believers in Jerusalem grew quickly. Also, a large number of priests began to obey Jesus’ teachings.<verse eid="ACT 6:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Stephen Is Arrested</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 6:8"/>Stephen was full of God’s grace and power. He did great wonders and signs among the people. <verse eid="ACT 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 6:9"/>But members of the group called the Synagogue of the Freedmen began to oppose him. Some of them were Jews from Cyrene and Alexandria. Others were Jews from Cilicia and Asia Minor. They all began to argue with Stephen. <verse eid="ACT 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 6:10"/>But he was too wise for them. That’s because the Holy Spirit gave Stephen wisdom whenever he spoke.<verse eid="ACT 6:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 6:11"/>Then in secret they talked some men into lying about Stephen. They said, “We heard Stephen speak evil things against Moses and against God.”<verse eid="ACT 6:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 6:12"/>So the people were stirred up. The elders and the teachers of the law were stirred up too. They arrested Stephen and brought him to the Sanhedrin. <verse eid="ACT 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 6:13"/>They found witnesses who were willing to tell lies. These liars said, “This fellow never stops speaking against this holy place. He also speaks against the law. <verse eid="ACT 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 6:14"/>We have heard him say that this Jesus of Nazareth will destroy this place. He says Jesus will change the practices that Moses handed down to us.”<verse eid="ACT 6:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 6:15"/>All who were sitting in the Sanhedrin looked right at Stephen. They saw that his face was like the face of an angel.<verse eid="ACT 6:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="ACT 7"/>
  <para style="s1">Stephen Speaks to the Sanhedrin</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 7:1"/>Then the high priest questioned Stephen. “Is what these people are saying true?” he asked.<verse eid="ACT 7:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 7:2"/>“Brothers and fathers, listen to me!” Stephen replied. “The God of glory appeared to our father Abraham. At that time Abraham was still in Mesopotamia. He had not yet begun living in Harran. <verse eid="ACT 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 7:3"/>‘Leave your country and your people,’ God said. ‘Go to the land I will show you.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="GEN 12:1">Genesis 12:1</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 7:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 7:4"/>“So Abraham left the land of Babylonia. He settled in Harran. After his father died, God sent Abraham to this land where you are now living. <verse eid="ACT 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 7:5"/>God didn’t give him any property here. He didn’t even give him enough land to set his foot on. But God made a promise to him and to all his family after him. He said they would possess the land. The promise was made even though at that time Abraham had no child. <verse eid="ACT 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 7:6"/>Here is what God said to him. ‘For 400 years your family after you will be strangers in a country not their own. They will be slaves and will be treated badly. <verse eid="ACT 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 7:7"/>But I will punish the nation that makes them slaves,’ God said. ‘After that, they will leave that country and worship me here.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="GEN 15:13">Genesis 15:13</ref>,<ref loc="GEN 15:14">14</ref>)</char> <verse eid="ACT 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 7:8"/>Then God made a covenant with Abraham. God told him that circumcision would show who the members of the covenant were. Abraham became Isaac’s father. He circumcised Isaac eight days after he was born. Later, Isaac became Jacob’s father. Jacob had 12 sons. They became the founders of the 12 tribes of Israel.<verse eid="ACT 7:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 7:9"/>“Jacob’s sons were jealous of their brother Joseph. So they sold him as a slave. He was taken to Egypt. But God was with him. <verse eid="ACT 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 7:10"/>He saved Joseph from all his troubles. God made Joseph wise. He helped him to become the friend of Pharaoh, the king of Egypt. So Pharaoh made Joseph ruler over Egypt and his whole palace.<verse eid="ACT 7:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 7:11"/>“There was not enough food for all Egypt and Canaan. This brought great suffering. Jacob and his sons couldn’t find food. <verse eid="ACT 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 7:12"/>But Jacob heard that there was grain in Egypt. So he sent his sons on their first visit. <verse eid="ACT 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 7:13"/>On their second visit, Joseph told his brothers who he was. Pharaoh learned about Joseph’s family. <verse eid="ACT 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 7:14"/>After this, Joseph sent for his father Jacob and his whole family. The total number of people was 75. <verse eid="ACT 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 7:15"/>Then Jacob went down to Egypt. There he and his family died. <verse eid="ACT 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 7:16"/>Some of their bodies were brought back to Shechem. They were placed in a tomb Abraham had bought. He had purchased it from Hamor’s sons at Shechem. He had purchased it for a certain amount of money.<verse eid="ACT 7:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 7:17"/>“In Egypt the number of our people grew and grew. It was nearly time for God to make his promise to Abraham come true. <verse eid="ACT 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 7:18"/>Then ‘a new king came to power in Egypt. Joseph didn’t mean anything to him.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="EXO 1:8">Exodus 1:8</ref>)</char> <verse eid="ACT 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 7:19"/>The king was very evil and dishonest with our people. He treated them badly. He forced them to throw out their newborn babies to die.<verse eid="ACT 7:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 7:20"/>“At that time Moses was born. He was not an ordinary child. For three months he was taken care of by his family. <verse eid="ACT 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 7:21"/>Then he was placed outside. But Pharaoh’s daughter took him home. She brought him up as her own son. <verse eid="ACT 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 7:22"/>Moses was taught all the knowledge of the people of Egypt. He became a powerful speaker and a man of action.<verse eid="ACT 7:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 7:23"/>“When Moses was 40 years old, he decided to visit the people of Israel. They were his own people. <verse eid="ACT 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 7:24"/>He saw one of them being treated badly by an Egyptian. So he went to help him. He got even by killing the man. <verse eid="ACT 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 7:25"/>Moses thought his own people would realize that God was using him to save them. But they didn’t. <verse eid="ACT 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 7:26"/>The next day Moses saw two Israelites fighting. He tried to make peace between them. ‘Men, you are both Israelites,’ he said. ‘Why do you want to hurt each other?’<verse eid="ACT 7:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 7:27"/>“But the man who was treating the other one badly pushed Moses to one side. He said, ‘Who made you ruler and judge over us? <verse eid="ACT 7:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 7:28"/>Are you thinking of killing me as you killed the Egyptian yesterday?’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="EXO 2:14">Exodus 2:14</ref>)</char> <verse eid="ACT 7:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 7:29"/>When Moses heard this, he escaped to Midian. He lived there as an outsider. He became the father of two sons there.<verse eid="ACT 7:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 7:30"/>“Forty years passed. Then an angel appeared to Moses in the flames of a burning bush. This happened in the desert near Mount Sinai. <verse eid="ACT 7:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 7:31"/>When Moses saw the bush, he was amazed. He went over for a closer look. There he heard the Lord say, <verse eid="ACT 7:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 7:32"/>‘I am the God of your fathers. I am the God of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="EXO 3:6">Exodus 3:6</ref>)</char> Moses shook with fear. He didn’t dare to look.<verse eid="ACT 7:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 7:33"/>“Then the Lord said to him, ‘Take off your sandals. You must do this because the place where you are standing is holy ground. <verse eid="ACT 7:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 7:34"/>I have seen my people beaten down in Egypt. I have heard their groans. I have come down to set them free. Now come. I will send you back to Egypt.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="EXO 3:5">Exodus 3:5</ref>,<ref loc="EXO 3:7">7</ref>,<ref loc="EXO 3:8">8</ref>,<ref loc="EXO 3:10">10</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 7:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 7:35"/>“This is the same Moses the two men of Israel would not accept. They had said, ‘Who made you ruler and judge?’ But God himself sent Moses to rule the people of Israel and set them free. He spoke to Moses through an angel. The angel had appeared to him in the bush. <verse eid="ACT 7:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 7:36"/>So Moses led them out of Egypt. He did wonders and signs in Egypt, at the Red Sea, and for 40 years in the desert.<verse eid="ACT 7:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 7:37"/>“This is the same Moses who spoke to the Israelites. ‘God will send you a prophet,’ he said. ‘He will be like me. He will come from your own people.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="DEU 18:15">Deuteronomy 18:15</ref>)</char> <verse eid="ACT 7:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 7:38"/>Moses was with the Israelites in the desert. He was with the angel who spoke to him on Mount Sinai. Moses was with our people of long ago. He received living words to pass on to us.<verse eid="ACT 7:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 7:39"/>“But our people refused to obey Moses. They would not accept him. In their hearts, they wished they were back in Egypt. <verse eid="ACT 7:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 7:40"/>They told Aaron, ‘Make us a god who will lead us. This fellow Moses brought us up out of Egypt. But we don’t know what has happened to him!’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="EXO 32:1">Exodus 32:1</ref>)</char> <verse eid="ACT 7:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 7:41"/>That was the time they made a statue to be their god. It was shaped like a calf. They brought sacrifices to it. They even enjoyed what they had made with their own hands. <verse eid="ACT 7:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="ACT 7:42"/>But God turned away from them. He let them go on worshiping the sun, moon and stars. This agrees with what is written in the book of the prophets. There it says,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 7:42">“ ‘People of Israel, did you bring me sacrifices and offerings</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 7:42">for 40 years in the desert?<verse eid="ACT 7:42"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="ACT 7:43"/>You have taken with you the shrine of your false god Molek.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 7:43">You have taken with you the star of your false god Rephan.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 7:43">You made statues of those gods to worship.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 7:43">So I will send you away from your country.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="AMO 5:25-27">Amos 5:25–27</ref>)</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 7:43">God sent them to Babylon and even farther.<verse eid="ACT 7:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="ACT 7:44"/>“Long ago our people were in the desert. They had with them the holy tent. The tent was where the tablets of the covenant law were kept. Moses had made the holy tent as God had commanded him. Moses made it like the pattern he had seen. <verse eid="ACT 7:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="ACT 7:45"/>Our people received the tent from God. Then they brought it with them when they took the land of Canaan. God drove out the nations that were in their way. At that time Joshua was Israel’s leader. The tent remained in the land until David’s time. <verse eid="ACT 7:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="ACT 7:46"/>David was blessed by God. So David asked if he could build a house for the God of Jacob. <verse eid="ACT 7:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="ACT 7:47"/>But it was Solomon who built the temple for God.<verse eid="ACT 7:47"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="ACT 7:48"/>“But the Most High God does not live in houses made by human hands. As God says through the prophet,<verse eid="ACT 7:48"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="ACT 7:49"/>“ ‘Heaven is my throne.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 7:49">The earth is under my control.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 7:49">What kind of house will you build for me?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 7:49">says the Lord.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 7:49">Where will my resting place be?<verse eid="ACT 7:49"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="ACT 7:50"/>Didn’t my hand make all these things?’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 66:1">Isaiah 66:1</ref>,<ref loc="ISA 66:2">2</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 7:50"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="51" style="v" sid="ACT 7:51"/>“You stubborn people! You won’t obey! You won’t listen! You are just like your people of long ago! You always oppose the Holy Spirit! <verse eid="ACT 7:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="ACT 7:52"/>Was there ever a prophet your people didn’t try to hurt? They even killed those who told about the coming of the Blameless One. And now you have handed him over to his enemies. You have murdered him. <verse eid="ACT 7:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="ACT 7:53"/>The law you received was given by angels. But you haven’t obeyed it.”<verse eid="ACT 7:53"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Stephen Is Killed</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="ACT 7:54"/>When the members of the Sanhedrin heard this, they became very angry. They were so angry they ground their teeth at Stephen. <verse eid="ACT 7:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="ACT 7:55"/>But he was full of the Holy Spirit. He looked up to heaven and saw God’s glory. He saw Jesus standing at God’s right hand. <verse eid="ACT 7:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="ACT 7:56"/>“Look!” he said. “I see heaven open. The Son of Man is standing at God’s right hand.”<verse eid="ACT 7:56"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="57" style="v" sid="ACT 7:57"/>When the Sanhedrin heard this, they covered their ears. They yelled at the top of their voices. They all rushed at him. <verse eid="ACT 7:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="ACT 7:58"/>They dragged him out of the city. They began to throw stones at him to kill him. The people who had brought false charges against Stephen took off their coats. They placed them at the feet of a young man named Saul.<verse eid="ACT 7:58"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="59" style="v" sid="ACT 7:59"/>While the members of the Sanhedrin were throwing stones at Stephen, he prayed. “Lord Jesus, receive my spirit,” he said. <verse eid="ACT 7:59"/><verse number="60" style="v" sid="ACT 7:60"/>Then he fell on his knees. He cried out, “Lord! Don’t hold this sin against them!” When he had said this, he died.<verse eid="ACT 7:60"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="ACT 8"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 8:1"/>And Saul had agreed with the Sanhedrin that Stephen should die.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="ACT 8:1">The Church Is Treated Badly and Scattered</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 8:1">On that day the church in Jerusalem began to be attacked and treated badly. All except the apostles were scattered throughout Judea and Samaria. <verse eid="ACT 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 8:2"/>Godly Jews buried Stephen. They mourned deeply for him. <verse eid="ACT 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 8:3"/>But Saul began to destroy the church. He went from house to house. He dragged away men and women and put them in prison.<verse eid="ACT 8:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Philip Goes to Samaria</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 8:4"/>The believers who had been scattered preached the word everywhere they went. <verse eid="ACT 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 8:5"/>Philip went down to a city in Samaria. There he preached about the Messiah. <verse eid="ACT 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 8:6"/>The crowds listened to Philip and saw the signs he did. All of them paid close attention to what he said. <verse eid="ACT 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 8:7"/>Evil spirits screamed and came out of many people. Many people who were disabled or who couldn’t walk were healed. <verse eid="ACT 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 8:8"/>So there was great joy in that city.<verse eid="ACT 8:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Simon the Evil Magician</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 8:9"/>A man named Simon lived in the city. For quite a while he had practiced evil magic there. He amazed all the people of Samaria. He claimed to be someone great. <verse eid="ACT 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 8:10"/>And all the people listened to him, from the least important of them to the most important. They exclaimed, “It is right to call this man the Great Power of God!” <verse eid="ACT 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 8:11"/>He had amazed them for a long time with his evil magic. So they followed him. <verse eid="ACT 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 8:12"/>But Philip announced the good news of God’s kingdom and the name of Jesus Christ. So men and women believed and were baptized. <verse eid="ACT 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 8:13"/>Simon himself believed and was baptized. He followed Philip everywhere. He was amazed by the great signs and miracles he saw.<verse eid="ACT 8:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 8:14"/>The apostles in Jerusalem heard that people in Samaria had accepted God’s word. So they sent Peter and John to Samaria. <verse eid="ACT 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 8:15"/>When they arrived there, they prayed for the new believers. They prayed that they would receive the Holy Spirit. <verse eid="ACT 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 8:16"/>The Holy Spirit had not yet come on any of them. They had only been baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus. <verse eid="ACT 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 8:17"/>Then Peter and John placed their hands on them. And they received the Holy Spirit.<verse eid="ACT 8:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 8:18"/>Simon watched as the apostles placed their hands on them. He saw that the Spirit was given to them. So he offered money to Peter and John. <verse eid="ACT 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 8:19"/>He said, “Give me this power too. Then everyone I place my hands on will receive the Holy Spirit.”<verse eid="ACT 8:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 8:20"/>Peter answered, “May your money be destroyed with you! Do you think you can buy God’s gift with money? <verse eid="ACT 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 8:21"/>You have no part or share in this holy work. Your heart is not right with God. <verse eid="ACT 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 8:22"/>Turn away from this evil sin of yours. Pray to the Lord. Perhaps he will forgive you for having such a thought in your heart. <verse eid="ACT 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 8:23"/>I see that you are very bitter. You are a prisoner of sin.”<verse eid="ACT 8:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 8:24"/>Then Simon answered, “Pray to the Lord for me. Pray that nothing you have said will happen to me.”<verse eid="ACT 8:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 8:25"/>Peter and John continued to preach the word of the Lord and tell people about Jesus. Then they returned to Jerusalem. On the way they preached the good news in many villages in Samaria.<verse eid="ACT 8:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Philip and the Man From Ethiopia</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 8:26"/>An angel of the Lord spoke to Philip. “Go south to the desert road,” he said. “It’s the road that goes down from Jerusalem to Gaza.” <verse eid="ACT 8:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 8:27"/>So Philip started out. On his way he met an Ethiopian official. The man had an important position in charge of all the wealth of the Kandake. Kandake means queen of Ethiopia. This official had gone to Jerusalem to worship. <verse eid="ACT 8:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 8:28"/>On his way home he was sitting in his chariot. He was reading the Book of Isaiah the prophet. <verse eid="ACT 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 8:29"/>The Holy Spirit told Philip, “Go to that chariot. Stay near it.”<verse eid="ACT 8:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 8:30"/>So Philip ran up to the chariot. He heard the man reading Isaiah the prophet. “Do you understand what you’re reading?” Philip asked.<verse eid="ACT 8:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 8:31"/>“How can I?” he said. “I need someone to explain it to me.” So he invited Philip to come up and sit with him.<verse eid="ACT 8:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 8:32"/>Here is the part of Scripture the official was reading. It says,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 8:32">“He was led like a sheep to be killed.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 8:32">Just as lambs are silent while their wool is being cut off,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 8:32">he did not open his mouth.<verse eid="ACT 8:32"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 8:33"/>When he was treated badly, he was refused a fair trial.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 8:33">Who can say anything about his children?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 8:33">His life was cut off from the earth.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 53:7">Isaiah 53:7</ref>,<ref loc="ISA 53:8">8</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 8:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 8:34"/>The official said to Philip, “Tell me, please. Who is the prophet talking about? Himself, or someone else?” <verse eid="ACT 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 8:35"/>Then Philip began with that same part of Scripture. He told him the good news about Jesus.<verse eid="ACT 8:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36-37" style="v" sid="ACT 8:36-37"/>As they traveled along the road, they came to some water. The official said, “Look! Here is water! What can stop me from being baptized?” <verse eid="ACT 8:36-37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 8:38"/>He gave orders to stop the chariot. Then both Philip and the official went down into the water. Philip baptized him. <verse eid="ACT 8:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 8:39"/>When they came up out of the water, the Spirit of the Lord suddenly took Philip away. The official did not see him again. He went on his way full of joy. <verse eid="ACT 8:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 8:40"/>Philip was seen next at Azotus. From there he traveled all around. He preached the good news in all the towns. Finally he arrived in Caesarea.<verse eid="ACT 8:40"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="ACT 9"/>
  <para style="s1">Saul Becomes a Believer</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 9:1"/>Meanwhile, Saul continued to oppose the Lord’s followers. He said they would be put to death. He went to the high priest. <verse eid="ACT 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 9:2"/>He asked the priest for letters to the synagogues in Damascus. He wanted to find men and women who belonged to the Way of Jesus. The letters would allow him to take them as prisoners to Jerusalem. <verse eid="ACT 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 9:3"/>On his journey, Saul approached Damascus. Suddenly a light from heaven flashed around him. <verse eid="ACT 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 9:4"/>He fell to the ground. He heard a voice speak to him, “Saul! Saul! Why are you opposing me?”<verse eid="ACT 9:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 9:5"/>“Who are you, Lord?” Saul asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 9:5">“I am Jesus,” he replied. “I am the one you are opposing. <verse eid="ACT 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 9:6"/>Now get up and go into the city. There you will be told what you must do.”<verse eid="ACT 9:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 9:7"/>The men traveling with Saul stood there. They weren’t able to speak. They had heard the sound. But they didn’t see anyone. <verse eid="ACT 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 9:8"/>Saul got up from the ground. He opened his eyes, but he couldn’t see. So they led him by the hand into Damascus. <verse eid="ACT 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 9:9"/>For three days he was blind. He didn’t eat or drink anything.<verse eid="ACT 9:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 9:10"/>In Damascus there was a believer named Ananias. The Lord called out to him in a vision. “Ananias!” he said.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 9:10">“Yes, Lord,” he answered.<verse eid="ACT 9:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 9:11"/>The Lord told him, “Go to the house of Judas on Straight Street. Ask for a man from Tarsus named Saul. He is praying. <verse eid="ACT 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 9:12"/>In a vision Saul has seen a man come and place his hands on him. That man’s name is Ananias. In the vision, Ananias placed his hands on Saul so he could see again.”<verse eid="ACT 9:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 9:13"/>“Lord,” Ananias answered, “I’ve heard many reports about this man. They say he has done great harm to your holy people in Jerusalem. <verse eid="ACT 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 9:14"/>Now he has come here to arrest all those who worship you. The chief priests have given him authority to do this.”<verse eid="ACT 9:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 9:15"/>But the Lord said to Ananias, “Go! I have chosen this man to work for me. He will announce my name to the Gentiles and to their kings. He will also announce my name to the people of Israel. <verse eid="ACT 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 9:16"/>I will show him how much he must suffer for me.”<verse eid="ACT 9:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 9:17"/>Then Ananias went to the house and entered it. He placed his hands on Saul. “Brother Saul,” he said, “you saw the Lord Jesus. He appeared to you on the road as you were coming here. He has sent me so that you will be able to see again. You will be filled with the Holy Spirit.” <verse eid="ACT 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 9:18"/>Right away something like scales fell from Saul’s eyes. And he could see again. He got up and was baptized. <verse eid="ACT 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 9:19"/>After eating some food, he got his strength back.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="ACT 9:19">Saul in Damascus and Jerusalem</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 9:19">Saul spent several days with the believers in Damascus. <verse eid="ACT 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 9:20"/>Right away he began to preach in the synagogues. He taught that Jesus is the Son of God. <verse eid="ACT 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 9:21"/>All who heard him were amazed. They asked, “Isn’t he the man who caused great trouble in Jerusalem? Didn’t he make trouble for those who worship Jesus? Hasn’t he come here to take them as prisoners to the chief priests?” <verse eid="ACT 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 9:22"/>But Saul grew more and more powerful. The Jews living in Damascus couldn’t believe what was happening. Saul proved to them that Jesus is the Messiah.<verse eid="ACT 9:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 9:23"/>After many days, the Jews had a meeting. They planned to kill Saul. <verse eid="ACT 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 9:24"/>But he learned about their plan. Day and night they watched the city gates closely in order to kill him. <verse eid="ACT 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 9:25"/>But his followers helped him escape by night. They lowered him in a basket through an opening in the wall.<verse eid="ACT 9:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 9:26"/>When Saul came to Jerusalem, he tried to join the believers. But they were all afraid of him. They didn’t believe he was really one of Jesus’ followers. <verse eid="ACT 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 9:27"/>But Barnabas took him to the apostles. He told them about Saul’s journey. He said that Saul had seen the Lord. He told how the Lord had spoken to Saul. Barnabas also said that Saul had preached without fear in Jesus’ name in Damascus. <verse eid="ACT 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 9:28"/>So Saul stayed with the believers. He moved about freely in Jerusalem. He spoke boldly in the Lord’s name. <verse eid="ACT 9:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 9:29"/>He talked and argued with the Greek Jews. But they tried to kill him. <verse eid="ACT 9:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 9:30"/>The other believers heard about this. They took Saul down to Caesarea. From there they sent him off to Tarsus.<verse eid="ACT 9:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 9:31"/>Then the church throughout Judea, Galilee and Samaria enjoyed a time of peace. The church was strengthened and grew larger. That’s because they worshiped the Lord and the Holy Spirit helped them.<verse eid="ACT 9:31"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Peter Heals Aeneas and Dorcas</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 9:32"/>Peter traveled around the country. He went to visit the Lord’s people who lived in Lydda. <verse eid="ACT 9:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 9:33"/>There he found a disabled man named Aeneas. For eight years the man had spent most of his time in bed. <verse eid="ACT 9:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 9:34"/>“Aeneas,” Peter said to him, “Jesus Christ heals you. Get up! Roll up your mat!” So Aeneas got up right away. <verse eid="ACT 9:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 9:35"/>Everyone who lived in Lydda and Sharon saw him. They turned to the Lord.<verse eid="ACT 9:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 9:36"/>In Joppa there was a believer named Tabitha. Her name in the Greek language is Dorcas. She was always doing good and helping poor people. <verse eid="ACT 9:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 9:37"/>About that time she became sick and died. Her body was washed and placed in a room upstairs. <verse eid="ACT 9:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 9:38"/>Lydda was near Joppa. The believers heard that Peter was in Lydda. So they sent two men to him. They begged him, “Please come at once!”<verse eid="ACT 9:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 9:39"/>Peter went with them. When he arrived, he was taken upstairs to the room. All the widows stood around him crying. They showed him the robes and other clothes Dorcas had made before she died.<verse eid="ACT 9:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 9:40"/>Peter sent them all out of the room. Then he got down on his knees and prayed. He turned toward the dead woman. He said, “Tabitha, get up.” She opened her eyes. When she saw Peter, she sat up. <verse eid="ACT 9:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 9:41"/>He took her by the hand and helped her to her feet. Then he called the believers and especially the widows. He brought her to them. They saw that she was alive. <verse eid="ACT 9:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="ACT 9:42"/>This became known all over Joppa. Many people believed in the Lord. <verse eid="ACT 9:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="ACT 9:43"/>Peter stayed in Joppa for some time. He stayed with Simon, a man who worked with leather.<verse eid="ACT 9:43"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="ACT 10"/>
  <para style="s1">Cornelius Calls for Peter</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 10:1"/>A man named Cornelius lived in Caesarea. He was a Roman commander in the Italian Regiment. <verse eid="ACT 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 10:2"/>Cornelius and all his family were faithful and worshiped God. He gave freely to people who were in need. He prayed to God regularly. <verse eid="ACT 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 10:3"/>One day about three o’clock in the afternoon he had a vision. He saw clearly an angel of God. The angel came to him and said, “Cornelius!”<verse eid="ACT 10:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 10:4"/>Cornelius was afraid. He stared at the angel. “What is it, Lord?” he asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 10:4">The angel answered, “Your prayers and gifts to poor people are like an offering to God. So he has remembered you. <verse eid="ACT 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 10:5"/>Now send men to Joppa. Have them bring back a man named Simon. He is also called Peter. <verse eid="ACT 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 10:6"/>He is staying with another Simon, a man who works with leather. His house is by the sea.”<verse eid="ACT 10:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 10:7"/>The angel who spoke to him left. Then Cornelius called two of his servants. He also called a godly soldier who was one of his attendants. <verse eid="ACT 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 10:8"/>He told them everything that had happened. Then he sent them to Joppa.<verse eid="ACT 10:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Peter Has a Vision</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 10:9"/>It was about noon the next day. The men were on their journey and were approaching the city. Peter went up on the roof to pray. <verse eid="ACT 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 10:10"/>He became hungry. He wanted something to eat. While the meal was being prepared, Peter had a vision. <verse eid="ACT 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 10:11"/>He saw heaven open up. There he saw something that looked like a large sheet. It was being let down to earth by its four corners. <verse eid="ACT 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 10:12"/>It had all kinds of four-footed animals in it. It also had reptiles and birds in it. <verse eid="ACT 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 10:13"/>Then a voice told him, “Get up, Peter. Kill and eat.”<verse eid="ACT 10:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 10:14"/>“No, Lord! I will not!” Peter replied. “I have never eaten anything that is not pure and ‘clean.’ ”<verse eid="ACT 10:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 10:15"/>The voice spoke to him a second time. It said, “Do not say anything is not pure that God has made ‘clean.’ ”<verse eid="ACT 10:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 10:16"/>This happened three times. Right away the sheet was taken back up to heaven.<verse eid="ACT 10:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 10:17"/>Peter was wondering what the vision meant. At that very moment the men sent by Cornelius found Simon’s house. They stopped at the gate <verse eid="ACT 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 10:18"/>and called out. They asked if Simon Peter was staying there.<verse eid="ACT 10:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 10:19"/>Peter was still thinking about the vision. The Holy Spirit spoke to him. “Simon,” he said, “three men are looking for you. <verse eid="ACT 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 10:20"/>Get up and go downstairs. Don’t let anything keep you from going with them. I have sent them.”<verse eid="ACT 10:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 10:21"/>Peter went down and spoke to the men. “I’m the one you’re looking for,” he said. “Why have you come?”<verse eid="ACT 10:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 10:22"/>The men replied, “We have come from Cornelius, the Roman commander. He is a good man who worships God. All the Jewish people respect him. A holy angel told him to invite you to his house. Then Cornelius can hear what you have to say.” <verse eid="ACT 10:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 10:23"/>Then Peter invited the men into the house to be his guests.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="ACT 10:23">Peter Goes to the House of Cornelius</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 10:23">The next day Peter went with the three men. Some of the believers from Joppa went along. <verse eid="ACT 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 10:24"/>The following day he arrived in Caesarea. Cornelius was expecting them. He had called together his relatives and close friends. <verse eid="ACT 10:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 10:25"/>When Peter entered the house, Cornelius met him. As a sign of respect, he fell at Peter’s feet. <verse eid="ACT 10:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 10:26"/>But Peter made him get up. “Stand up,” he said. “I am only a man myself.”<verse eid="ACT 10:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 10:27"/>As he was talking with Cornelius, Peter went inside. There he found a large group of people. <verse eid="ACT 10:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 10:28"/>He said to them, “You know that it is against our law for a Jew to enter a Gentile home. A Jew shouldn’t have any close contact with a Gentile. But God has shown me that I should not say anyone is not pure and ‘clean.’ <verse eid="ACT 10:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 10:29"/>So when you sent for me, I came without asking any questions. May I ask why you sent for me?”<verse eid="ACT 10:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 10:30"/>Cornelius answered, “Three days ago at this very hour I was in my house praying. It was three o’clock in the afternoon. Suddenly a man in shining clothes stood in front of me. <verse eid="ACT 10:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 10:31"/>He said, ‘Cornelius, God has heard your prayer. He has remembered your gifts to poor people. <verse eid="ACT 10:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 10:32"/>Send someone to Joppa to get Simon Peter. He is a guest in the home of another Simon, who works with leather. He lives by the sea.’ <verse eid="ACT 10:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 10:33"/>So I sent for you right away. It was good of you to come. Now we are all here. And God is here with us. We are ready to listen to everything the Lord has commanded you to tell us.”<verse eid="ACT 10:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 10:34"/>Then Peter began to speak. “I now realize how true it is that God treats everyone the same,” he said. <verse eid="ACT 10:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 10:35"/>“He accepts people from every nation. He accepts anyone who has respect for him and does what is right. <verse eid="ACT 10:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 10:36"/>You know the message God sent to the people of Israel. It is the good news of peace through Jesus Christ. He is Lord of all. <verse eid="ACT 10:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 10:37"/>You know what has happened all through the area of Judea. It started in Galilee after John preached about baptism. <verse eid="ACT 10:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 10:38"/>You know how God anointed Jesus of Nazareth with the Holy Spirit and with power. Jesus went around doing good. He healed all who were under the devil’s power. God was with him.<verse eid="ACT 10:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 10:39"/>“We are witnesses of everything he did in the land of the Jews and in Jerusalem. They killed him by nailing him to a cross. <verse eid="ACT 10:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 10:40"/>But on the third day God raised him from the dead. God allowed Jesus to be seen. <verse eid="ACT 10:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 10:41"/>But he wasn’t seen by all the people. He was seen only by us. We are witnesses whom God had already chosen. We ate and drank with him after he rose from the dead. <verse eid="ACT 10:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="ACT 10:42"/>He commanded us to preach to the people. He told us to tell people that he is the one appointed by God to judge the living and the dead. <verse eid="ACT 10:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="ACT 10:43"/>All the prophets tell about him. They say that all who believe in him have their sins forgiven through his name.”<verse eid="ACT 10:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="ACT 10:44"/>While Peter was still speaking, the Holy Spirit came on all who heard the message. <verse eid="ACT 10:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="ACT 10:45"/>Some Jewish believers had come with Peter. They were amazed because the gift of the Holy Spirit had been poured out even on the Gentiles. <verse eid="ACT 10:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="ACT 10:46"/>They heard them speaking in languages they had not known before. They also heard them praising God.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 10:46">Then Peter said, <verse eid="ACT 10:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="ACT 10:47"/>“Surely no one can keep these people from being baptized with water. They have received the Holy Spirit just as we have.” <verse eid="ACT 10:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="ACT 10:48"/>So he ordered that they be baptized in the name of Jesus Christ. Then they asked Peter to stay with them for a few days.<verse eid="ACT 10:48"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="ACT 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Peter Explains His Actions</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 11:1"/>The apostles and the believers all through Judea heard that Gentiles had also received God’s word. <verse eid="ACT 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 11:2"/>Peter went up to Jerusalem. There the Jewish believers found fault with him. <verse eid="ACT 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 11:3"/>They said, “You went into the house of Gentiles. You ate with them.”<verse eid="ACT 11:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 11:4"/>Starting from the beginning, Peter told them the whole story. <verse eid="ACT 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 11:5"/>“I was in the city of Joppa praying,” he said. “There I had a vision. I saw something that looked like a large sheet. It was being let down from heaven by its four corners. It came down to where I was. <verse eid="ACT 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 11:6"/>I looked into it and saw four-footed animals of the earth. There were also wild animals, reptiles and birds. <verse eid="ACT 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 11:7"/>Then I heard a voice speaking to me. ‘Get up, Peter,’ the voice said. ‘Kill and eat.’<verse eid="ACT 11:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 11:8"/>“I replied, ‘No, Lord! I will not! Nothing that is not pure and “clean” has ever entered my mouth.’<verse eid="ACT 11:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 11:9"/>“A second time the voice spoke from heaven. The voice said, ‘Do not say anything is not pure that God has made “clean.” ’ <verse eid="ACT 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 11:10"/>This happened three times. Then the sheet was pulled up into heaven.<verse eid="ACT 11:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 11:11"/>“Just then three men stopped at the house where I was staying. They had been sent to me from Caesarea. <verse eid="ACT 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 11:12"/>The Holy Spirit told me not to let anything keep me from going with them. These six brothers here went with me. We entered the man’s house. <verse eid="ACT 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 11:13"/>He told us how he had seen an angel appear in his house. The angel said, ‘Send to Joppa for Simon Peter. <verse eid="ACT 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 11:14"/>He has a message to bring to you. You and your whole family will be saved through it.’<verse eid="ACT 11:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 11:15"/>“As I began to speak, the Holy Spirit came on them. He came just as he had come on us at the beginning. <verse eid="ACT 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 11:16"/>Then I remembered the Lord’s words. ‘John baptized with water,’ he had said. ‘But you will be baptized with the Holy Spirit.’ <verse eid="ACT 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 11:17"/>God gave them the same gift he gave those of us who believed in the Lord Jesus Christ. So who was I to think that I could stand in God’s way?”<verse eid="ACT 11:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 11:18"/>When they heard this, they didn’t object anymore. They praised God. They said, “So then, God has allowed even Gentiles to turn away from their sins. He did this so that they could live.”<verse eid="ACT 11:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Believers in Antioch</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 11:19"/>Some believers had been scattered by the suffering that unbelievers had caused them. They were scattered after Stephen was killed. Those believers traveled as far as Phoenicia, Cyprus and Antioch. But they spread the word only among Jews. <verse eid="ACT 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 11:20"/>Some believers from Cyprus and Cyrene went to Antioch. There they began to speak to Greeks also. They told them the good news about the Lord Jesus. <verse eid="ACT 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 11:21"/>The Lord’s power was with them. Large numbers of people believed and turned to the Lord.<verse eid="ACT 11:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 11:22"/>The church in Jerusalem heard about this. So they sent Barnabas to Antioch. <verse eid="ACT 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 11:23"/>When he arrived and saw what the grace of God had done, he was glad. He told them all to remain true to the Lord with all their hearts. <verse eid="ACT 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 11:24"/>Barnabas was a good man. He was full of the Holy Spirit and of faith. Large numbers of people came to know the Lord.<verse eid="ACT 11:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 11:25"/>Then Barnabas went to Tarsus to look for Saul. <verse eid="ACT 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 11:26"/>He found him there. Then he brought him to Antioch. For a whole year Barnabas and Saul met with the church. They taught large numbers of people. At Antioch the believers were called Christians for the first time.<verse eid="ACT 11:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 11:27"/>In those days some prophets came down from Jerusalem to Antioch. <verse eid="ACT 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 11:28"/>One of them was named Agabus. He stood up and spoke through the Spirit. He said there would not be nearly enough food anywhere in the Roman world. This happened while Claudius was the emperor. <verse eid="ACT 11:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 11:29"/>The believers decided to provide help for the brothers and sisters living in Judea. All of them helped as much as they could. <verse eid="ACT 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 11:30"/>They sent their gift to the elders through Barnabas and Saul.<verse eid="ACT 11:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="ACT 12"/>
  <para style="s1">An Angel Helps Peter Escape From Prison</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 12:1"/>About this time, King Herod arrested some people who belonged to the church. He planned to make them suffer greatly. <verse eid="ACT 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 12:2"/>He had James killed with a sword. James was John’s brother. <verse eid="ACT 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 12:3"/>Herod saw that the death of James pleased some Jews. So he arrested Peter also. This happened during the Feast of Unleavened Bread. <verse eid="ACT 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 12:4"/>After Herod arrested Peter, he put him in prison. Peter was placed under guard. He was watched by four groups of four soldiers each. Herod planned to put Peter on public trial. It would take place after the Passover Feast.<verse eid="ACT 12:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 12:5"/>So Peter was kept in prison. But the church prayed hard to God for him.<verse eid="ACT 12:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 12:6"/>It was the night before Herod was going to bring him to trial. Peter was sleeping between two soldiers. Two chains held him there. Lookouts stood guard at the entrance. <verse eid="ACT 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 12:7"/>Suddenly an angel of the Lord appeared. A light shone in the prison cell. The angel struck Peter on his side. Peter woke up. “Quick!” the angel said. “Get up!” The chains fell off Peter’s wrists.<verse eid="ACT 12:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 12:8"/>Then the angel said to him, “Put on your clothes and sandals.” Peter did so. “Put on your coat,” the angel told him. “Follow me.” <verse eid="ACT 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 12:9"/>Peter followed him out of the prison. But he had no idea that what the angel was doing was really happening. He thought he was seeing a vision. <verse eid="ACT 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 12:10"/>They passed the first and second guards. Then they came to the iron gate leading to the city. It opened for them by itself. They went through it. They walked the length of one street. Suddenly the angel left Peter.<verse eid="ACT 12:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 12:11"/>Then Peter realized what had happened. He said, “Now I know for sure that the Lord has sent his angel. He set me free from Herod’s power. He saved me from everything the Jewish people were hoping would happen.”<verse eid="ACT 12:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 12:12"/>When Peter understood what had happened, he went to Mary’s house. Mary was the mother of John Mark. Many people had gathered in her home. They were praying there. <verse eid="ACT 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 12:13"/>Peter knocked at the outer entrance. A servant named Rhoda came to answer the door. <verse eid="ACT 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 12:14"/>She recognized Peter’s voice. She was so excited that she ran back without opening the door. “Peter is at the door!” she exclaimed.<verse eid="ACT 12:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 12:15"/>“You’re out of your mind,” they said to her. But she kept telling them it was true. So they said, “It must be his angel.”<verse eid="ACT 12:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 12:16"/>Peter kept on knocking. When they opened the door and saw him, they were amazed. <verse eid="ACT 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 12:17"/>Peter motioned with his hand for them to be quiet. He explained how the Lord had brought him out of prison. “Tell James and the other brothers and sisters about this,” he said. Then he went to another place.<verse eid="ACT 12:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 12:18"/>In the morning the soldiers were bewildered. They couldn’t figure out what had happened to Peter. <verse eid="ACT 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 12:19"/>So Herod had them look everywhere for Peter. But they didn’t find him. Then Herod questioned the guards closely. He ordered that they be put to death.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="ACT 12:19">Herod Dies</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 12:19">Then Herod went from Judea to Caesarea and stayed there. <verse eid="ACT 12:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 12:20"/>He had been quarreling with the people of Tyre and Sidon. So they got together and asked for a meeting with him. This was because they depended on the king’s country to supply them with food. They gained the support of Blastus and then asked for peace. Blastus was a trusted personal servant of the king.<verse eid="ACT 12:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 12:21"/>The appointed day came. Herod was seated on his throne. He was wearing his royal robes. He made a speech to the people. <verse eid="ACT 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 12:22"/>Then they shouted, “This is the voice of a god. It’s not the voice of a man.” <verse eid="ACT 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 12:23"/>Right away an angel of the Lord struck Herod down. Herod had not given praise to God. So he was eaten by worms and died.<verse eid="ACT 12:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 12:24"/>But God’s word continued to spread and many people believed the message.<verse eid="ACT 12:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Barnabas and Saul Are Sent Off</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 12:25"/>Barnabas and Saul finished their task. Then they returned from Jerusalem. They took John Mark with them.<verse eid="ACT 12:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="ACT 13"/>
  <para style="nb">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 13:1"/>In the church at Antioch there were prophets and teachers. Among them were Barnabas, Simeon, and Lucius from Cyrene. Simeon was also called Niger. Another was Manaen. He had been brought up with Herod, the ruler of Galilee. Saul was among them too. <verse eid="ACT 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 13:2"/>While they were worshiping the Lord and fasting, the Holy Spirit spoke. “Set apart Barnabas and Saul for me,” he said. “I have appointed them to do special work.” <verse eid="ACT 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 13:3"/>The prophets and teachers fasted and prayed. They placed their hands on Barnabas and Saul. Then they sent them off.<verse eid="ACT 13:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Events on Cyprus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 13:4"/>Barnabas and Saul were sent on their way by the Holy Spirit. They went down to Seleucia. From there they sailed to Cyprus. <verse eid="ACT 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 13:5"/>They arrived at Salamis. There they preached God’s word in the Jewish synagogues. John was with them as their helper.<verse eid="ACT 13:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 13:6"/>They traveled all across the island until they came to Paphos. There they met a Jew named Bar-Jesus. He was an evil magician and a false prophet. <verse eid="ACT 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 13:7"/>He was an attendant of Sergius Paulus, the governor. Paulus was a man of understanding. He sent for Barnabas and Saul. He wanted to hear God’s word. <verse eid="ACT 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 13:8"/>But the evil magician named Elymas opposed them. The name Elymas means Magician. He tried to keep the governor from becoming a believer. <verse eid="ACT 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 13:9"/>Saul was also known as Paul. He was filled with the Holy Spirit. He looked straight at Elymas. He said to him, <verse eid="ACT 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 13:10"/>“You are a child of the devil! You are an enemy of everything that is right! You cheat people. You use all kinds of tricks. Won’t you ever stop twisting the right ways of the Lord? <verse eid="ACT 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 13:11"/>Now the Lord’s hand is against you. You are going to go blind. For a while you won’t even be able to see the light of the sun.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 13:11">Right away mist and darkness came over him. He tried to feel his way around. He wanted to find someone to lead him by the hand. <verse eid="ACT 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 13:12"/>When the governor saw what had happened, he believed. He was amazed at what Paul was teaching about the Lord.<verse eid="ACT 13:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Preaches in Pisidian Antioch</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 13:13"/>From Paphos, Paul and his companions sailed to Perga in Pamphylia. There John Mark left them and returned to Jerusalem. <verse eid="ACT 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 13:14"/>From Perga they went on to Pisidian Antioch. On the Sabbath day they entered the synagogue and sat down. <verse eid="ACT 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 13:15"/>The Law and the Prophets were read aloud. Then the leaders of the synagogue sent word to Paul and his companions. They said, “Brothers, do you have any words of instruction for the people? If you do, please speak.”<verse eid="ACT 13:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 13:16"/>Paul stood up and motioned with his hand. Then he said, “Fellow Israelites, and you Gentiles who worship God, listen to me! <verse eid="ACT 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 13:17"/>The God of Israel chose our people who lived long ago. He blessed them greatly while they were in Egypt. With his mighty power he led them out of that country. <verse eid="ACT 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 13:18"/>He put up with their behavior for about 40 years in the desert. <verse eid="ACT 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 13:19"/>And he destroyed seven nations in Canaan. Then he gave the land to his people as their rightful share. <verse eid="ACT 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 13:20"/>All this took about 450 years.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 13:20">“After this, God gave them judges until the time of Samuel the prophet. <verse eid="ACT 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 13:21"/>Then the people asked for a king. He gave them Saul, son of Kish. Saul was from the tribe of Benjamin. He ruled for 40 years. <verse eid="ACT 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 13:22"/>God removed him and made David their king. Here is God’s witness about him. ‘David, son of Jesse, is a man dear to my heart,’ he said. ‘David will do everything I want him to do.’<verse eid="ACT 13:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 13:23"/>“From this man’s family line God has brought to Israel the Savior Jesus. This is what he had promised. <verse eid="ACT 13:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 13:24"/>Before Jesus came, John preached that we should turn away from our sins and be baptized. He preached this to all Israel. <verse eid="ACT 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 13:25"/>John was coming to the end of his work. ‘Who do you suppose I am?’ he said. ‘I am not the one you are looking for. But there is someone coming after me. I am not good enough to untie his sandals.’<verse eid="ACT 13:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 13:26"/>“Listen, fellow children of Abraham! Listen, you Gentiles who worship God! This message of salvation has been sent to us. <verse eid="ACT 13:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 13:27"/>The people of Jerusalem and their rulers did not recognize Jesus. By finding him guilty, they made the prophets’ words come true. These are read every Sabbath day. <verse eid="ACT 13:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 13:28"/>The people and their rulers had no reason at all for sentencing Jesus to death. But they asked Pilate to have him killed. <verse eid="ACT 13:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 13:29"/>They did everything that had been written about Jesus. Then they took him down from the cross. They laid him in a tomb. <verse eid="ACT 13:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 13:30"/>But God raised him from the dead. <verse eid="ACT 13:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 13:31"/>For many days he was seen by those who had traveled with him from Galilee to Jerusalem. Now they are telling our people about Jesus.<verse eid="ACT 13:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 13:32"/>“We are telling you the good news. What God promised our people long ago <verse eid="ACT 13:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 13:33"/>he has done for us, their children. He has raised up Jesus. This is what is written in the second Psalm. It says,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 13:33">“ ‘You are my son.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 13:33">Today I have become your father.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 2:7">Psalm 2:7</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 13:33"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 13:34"/>God raised Jesus from the dead. He will never rot in the grave. As God has said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 13:34">“ ‘Holy and sure blessings were promised to David.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 13:34">I will give them to you.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 55:3">Isaiah 55:3</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 13:34"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 13:35"/>In another place it also says,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 13:35">“ ‘You will not let your holy one rot away.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 16:10">Psalm 16:10</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 13:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 13:36"/>“David carried out God’s purpose while he lived. Then he died. He was buried with his people. His body rotted away. <verse eid="ACT 13:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 13:37"/>But the one whom God raised from the dead did not rot away.<verse eid="ACT 13:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 13:38"/>“My friends, here is what I want you to know. I announce to you that your sins can be forgiven because of what Jesus has done. <verse eid="ACT 13:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 13:39"/>Through him everyone who believes is set free from every sin. Moses’ law could not make you right in God’s eyes. <verse eid="ACT 13:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 13:40"/>Be careful! Don’t let what the prophets spoke about happen to you. They said,<verse eid="ACT 13:40"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 13:41"/>“ ‘Look, you who make fun of the truth!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 13:41">Wonder and die!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 13:41">I am going to do something in your days</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 13:41">that you would never believe.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 13:41">You wouldn’t believe it even if someone told you.’ ” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="HAB 1:5">Habakkuk 1:5</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 13:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="ACT 13:42"/>Paul and Barnabas started to leave the synagogue. The people invited them to say more about these things on the next Sabbath day. <verse eid="ACT 13:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="ACT 13:43"/>The people were told they could leave the service. Many Jews followed Paul and Barnabas. Many Gentiles who faithfully worshiped the God of the Jews did the same. Paul and Barnabas talked with them. They tried to get them to keep living in God’s grace.<verse eid="ACT 13:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="ACT 13:44"/>On the next Sabbath day, almost the whole city gathered. They gathered to hear the word of the Lord. <verse eid="ACT 13:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="ACT 13:45"/>When the Jews saw the crowds, they became very jealous. They began to disagree with what Paul was saying. They said evil things against him.<verse eid="ACT 13:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="ACT 13:46"/>Then Paul and Barnabas answered them boldly. “We had to speak God’s word to you first,” they said. “But you don’t accept it. You don’t think you are good enough for eternal life. So now we are turning to the Gentiles. <verse eid="ACT 13:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="ACT 13:47"/>This is what the Lord has commanded us to do. He said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 13:47">“ ‘I have made you a light for the Gentiles.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 13:47">You will bring salvation to the whole earth.’ ” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 49:6">Isaiah 49:6</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 13:47"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="ACT 13:48"/>When the Gentiles heard this, they were glad. They honored the word of the Lord. All who were appointed for eternal life believed.<verse eid="ACT 13:48"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="ACT 13:49"/>The word of the Lord spread through the whole area. <verse eid="ACT 13:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="ACT 13:50"/>But the Jewish leaders stirred up the important women who worshiped God. They also stirred up the men who were leaders in the city. The Jewish leaders tried to get the women and men to attack Paul and Barnabas. They threw Paul and Barnabas out of that area. <verse eid="ACT 13:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="ACT 13:51"/>Paul and Barnabas shook the dust off their feet. This was a warning to the people who had opposed them. Then Paul and Barnabas went on to Iconium. <verse eid="ACT 13:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="ACT 13:52"/>The believers were filled with joy and with the Holy Spirit.<verse eid="ACT 13:52"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="ACT 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Paul and Barnabas Preach in Iconium</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 14:1"/>At Iconium, Paul and Barnabas went into the Jewish synagogue as usual. They spoke there with great power. Large numbers of Jews and Greeks became believers. <verse eid="ACT 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 14:2"/>But the Jews who refused to believe stirred up some of the Gentiles who were there. They turned them against the two men and the new believers. <verse eid="ACT 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 14:3"/>So Paul and Barnabas spent a lot of time there. They spoke boldly for the Lord. He gave them the ability to do signs and wonders. In this way the Lord showed that they were telling the truth about his grace. <verse eid="ACT 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 14:4"/>The people of the city did not agree with one another. Some were on the side of the Jews. Others were on the side of the apostles. <verse eid="ACT 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 14:5"/>Jews and Gentiles alike planned to treat Paul and Barnabas badly. Their leaders agreed. They planned to kill them by throwing stones at them. <verse eid="ACT 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 14:6"/>But Paul and Barnabas found out about the plan. They escaped to the Lycaonian cities of Lystra and Derbe and to the surrounding area. <verse eid="ACT 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 14:7"/>There they continued to preach the good news.<verse eid="ACT 14:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Preaches in Lystra</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 14:8"/>In Lystra there sat a man who couldn’t walk. He hadn’t been able to use his feet since the day he was born. <verse eid="ACT 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 14:9"/>He listened as Paul spoke. Paul looked right at him. He saw that the man had faith to be healed. <verse eid="ACT 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 14:10"/>So he called out, “Stand up on your feet!” Then the man jumped up and began to walk.<verse eid="ACT 14:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 14:11"/>The crowd saw what Paul had done. They shouted in the Lycaonian language. “The gods have come down to us in human form!” they exclaimed. <verse eid="ACT 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 14:12"/>They called Barnabas Zeus. Paul was the main speaker. So they called him Hermes. <verse eid="ACT 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 14:13"/>Just outside the city was the temple of the god Zeus. The priest of Zeus brought bulls and wreaths to the city gates. He and the crowd wanted to offer sacrifices to Paul and Barnabas.<verse eid="ACT 14:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 14:14"/>But the apostles Barnabas and Paul heard about this. So they tore their clothes. They rushed out into the crowd. They shouted, <verse eid="ACT 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 14:15"/>“Friends, why are you doing this? We are only human, just like you. We are bringing you good news. Turn away from these worthless things. Turn to the living God. He is the one who made the heavens and the earth and the sea. He made everything in them. <verse eid="ACT 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 14:16"/>In the past, he let all nations go their own way. <verse eid="ACT 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 14:17"/>But he has given proof of what he is like. He has shown kindness by giving you rain from heaven. He gives you crops in their seasons. He provides you with plenty of food. He fills your hearts with joy.” <verse eid="ACT 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 14:18"/>Paul and Barnabas told them all these things. But they had trouble keeping the crowd from offering sacrifices to them.<verse eid="ACT 14:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 14:19"/>Then some Jews came from Antioch and Iconium. They won the crowd over to their side. They threw stones at Paul. They thought he was dead, so they dragged him out of the city. <verse eid="ACT 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 14:20"/>The believers gathered around Paul. Then he got up and went back into the city. The next day he and Barnabas left for Derbe.<verse eid="ACT 14:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul and Barnabas Return to Antioch</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 14:21"/>Paul and Barnabas preached the good news in the city of Derbe. They won large numbers of followers. Then they returned to Lystra, Iconium and Antioch. <verse eid="ACT 14:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 14:22"/>There they helped the believers gain strength. They told them to remain faithful to what they had been taught. “We must go through many hard times to enter God’s kingdom,” they said. <verse eid="ACT 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 14:23"/>Paul and Barnabas appointed elders for them in each church. The elders had trusted in the Lord. Paul and Barnabas prayed and fasted. They placed the elders in the Lord’s care. <verse eid="ACT 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 14:24"/>After going through Pisidia, Paul and Barnabas came into Pamphylia. <verse eid="ACT 14:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 14:25"/>They preached the good news in Perga. Then they went down to Attalia.<verse eid="ACT 14:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 14:26"/>From Attalia they sailed back to Antioch. In Antioch they had been put in God’s care to preach the good news. They had now completed the work God had given them to do. <verse eid="ACT 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 14:27"/>When they arrived at Antioch, they gathered the church together. They reported all that God had done through them. They told how he had opened a way for the Gentiles to believe. <verse eid="ACT 14:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 14:28"/>And they stayed there a long time with the believers.<verse eid="ACT 14:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="ACT 15"/>
  <para style="s1">Church Leaders Meet in Jerusalem</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 15:1"/>Certain people came down from Judea to Antioch. Here is what they were teaching the believers. “Moses commanded you to be circumcised,” they said. “If you aren’t, you can’t be saved.” <verse eid="ACT 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 15:2"/>But Paul and Barnabas didn’t agree with this. They argued strongly with them. So Paul and Barnabas were appointed to go up to Jerusalem. Some other believers were chosen to go with them. They were told to ask the apostles and elders about this question. <verse eid="ACT 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 15:3"/>The church sent them on their way. They traveled through Phoenicia and Samaria. There they told how the Gentiles had turned to God. This news made all the believers very glad. <verse eid="ACT 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 15:4"/>When they arrived in Jerusalem, the church welcomed them. The apostles and elders welcomed them too. Then Paul and Barnabas reported everything God had done through them.<verse eid="ACT 15:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 15:5"/>Some of the believers were Pharisees. They stood up and said, “The Gentiles must be circumcised. They must obey the law of Moses.”<verse eid="ACT 15:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 15:6"/>The apostles and elders met to consider this question. <verse eid="ACT 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 15:7"/>After they had talked it over, Peter got up and spoke to them. “Brothers,” he said, “you know that some time ago God chose me. He appointed me to take the good news to the Gentiles. He wanted them to hear the good news and believe. <verse eid="ACT 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 15:8"/>God knows the human heart. By giving the Holy Spirit to the Gentiles, he showed that he accepted them. He did the same for them as he had done for us. <verse eid="ACT 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 15:9"/>God showed that there is no difference between us and them. That’s because he made their hearts pure because of their faith. <verse eid="ACT 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 15:10"/>Now then, why are you trying to test God? You test him when you put a heavy load on the shoulders of Gentiles. Our people of long ago couldn’t carry that load. We can’t either. <verse eid="ACT 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 15:11"/>No! We believe we are saved through the grace of our Lord Jesus. The Gentiles are saved in the same way.”<verse eid="ACT 15:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 15:12"/>Everyone became quiet as they listened to Barnabas and Paul. They were telling about the signs and wonders God had done through them among the Gentiles. <verse eid="ACT 15:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 15:13"/>When they finished, James spoke up. “Brothers,” he said, “listen to me. <verse eid="ACT 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 15:14"/>Simon Peter has explained to us what God has now done. He has chosen some of the Gentiles to be among his very own people. <verse eid="ACT 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 15:15"/>The prophets’ words agree with that. They say,<verse eid="ACT 15:15"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 15:16"/>“ ‘After this I will return</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 15:16">and set up again David’s fallen tent.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 15:16">I will rebuild what was destroyed.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 15:16">I will make it what it used to be.<verse eid="ACT 15:16"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 15:17"/>Then everyone else can look to the Lord.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 15:17">This includes all the Gentiles who belong to me, says the Lord.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 15:17">The Lord is the one who does these things.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="AMO 9:11">Amos 9:11</ref>,<ref loc="AMO 9:12">12</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 15:17"/></para>
  <para style="q2">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 15:18"/>The Lord does things that have been known from long ago.<verse eid="ACT 15:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 15:19"/>“Now here is my decision. We should not make it hard for the Gentiles who are turning to God. <verse eid="ACT 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 15:20"/>Here is what we should write to them. They must not eat food that has been made impure by being offered to statues of gods. They must not commit sexual sins. They must not eat the meat of animals that have been choked to death. And they must not drink blood. <verse eid="ACT 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 15:21"/>These laws of Moses have been preached in every city from the earliest times. They are read out loud in the synagogues every Sabbath day.”<verse eid="ACT 15:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">A Letter Is Written to Gentile Believers</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 15:22"/>Then the apostles, the elders and the whole church decided what to do. They would choose some of their own men who were leaders among the believers. They would send them to Antioch with Paul and Barnabas. So they chose Judas Barsabbas and Silas. They were leaders among the believers. <verse eid="ACT 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 15:23"/>Here is the letter they sent with them.</para>
  <para style="pmo" vid="ACT 15:23">The apostles and elders, your brothers, are writing this letter.</para>
  <para style="pmo" vid="ACT 15:23">We are sending it to the Gentile believers in Antioch, Syria and Cilicia.</para>
  <para style="pmo" vid="ACT 15:23">Greetings.<verse eid="ACT 15:23"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 15:24"/>We have heard that some of our people came to you and caused trouble. You were upset by what they said. But we had given them no authority to go. <verse eid="ACT 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 15:25"/>So we all agreed to send our dear friends Barnabas and Paul to you. We chose some other men to go with them. <verse eid="ACT 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 15:26"/>Barnabas and Paul have put their lives in danger. They did it for the name of our Lord Jesus Christ. <verse eid="ACT 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 15:27"/>So we are sending Judas and Silas with them. What they say will agree with this letter. <verse eid="ACT 15:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 15:28"/>Here is what seemed good to the Holy Spirit and to us. We will not give you a load that is too heavy. So here are a few basic rules. <verse eid="ACT 15:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 15:29"/>Don’t eat food that has been offered to statues of gods. Don’t drink blood. Don’t eat the meat of animals that have been choked to death. And don’t commit sexual sins. You will do well to keep away from these things.</para>
  <para style="pmc" vid="ACT 15:29">Farewell.<verse eid="ACT 15:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 15:30"/>So the men were sent down to Antioch. There they gathered the church together. They gave the letter to them. <verse eid="ACT 15:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 15:31"/>The people read it. They were glad for its message of hope. <verse eid="ACT 15:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 15:32"/>Judas and Silas were prophets. They said many things to give strength and hope to the believers. <verse eid="ACT 15:32"/><verse number="33-34" style="v" sid="ACT 15:33-34"/>Judas and Silas stayed there for some time. Then the believers sent them away with the blessing of peace. They sent them back to those who had sent them out. <verse eid="ACT 15:33-34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 15:35"/>Paul and Barnabas remained in Antioch. There they and many others taught and preached the word of the Lord.<verse eid="ACT 15:35"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul and Barnabas Do Not Agree</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 15:36"/>Some time later Paul spoke to Barnabas. “Let’s go back to all the towns where we preached the word of the Lord,” he said. “Let’s visit the believers and see how they are doing.” <verse eid="ACT 15:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 15:37"/>Barnabas wanted to take John Mark with them. <verse eid="ACT 15:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 15:38"/>But Paul didn’t think it was wise to take him. Mark had deserted them in Pamphylia. He hadn’t continued with them in their work. <verse eid="ACT 15:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 15:39"/>Barnabas and Paul strongly disagreed with each other. So they went their separate ways. Barnabas took Mark and sailed for Cyprus. <verse eid="ACT 15:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 15:40"/>But Paul chose Silas. The believers asked the Lord to give his grace to Paul and Silas as they went. <verse eid="ACT 15:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 15:41"/>Paul traveled through Syria and Cilicia. He gave strength to the churches there.<verse eid="ACT 15:41"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="ACT 16"/>
  <para style="s1">Timothy Joins Paul and Silas</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 16:1"/>Paul came to Derbe. Then he went on to Lystra. A believer named Timothy lived there. His mother was Jewish and a believer. His father was a Greek. <verse eid="ACT 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 16:2"/>The believers at Lystra and Iconium said good things about Timothy. <verse eid="ACT 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 16:3"/>Paul wanted to take him along on the journey. So he circumcised Timothy because of the Jews who lived in that area. They all knew that Timothy’s father was a Greek. <verse eid="ACT 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 16:4"/>Paul and his companions traveled from town to town. They reported what the apostles and elders in Jerusalem had decided. The people were supposed to obey what was in the report. <verse eid="ACT 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 16:5"/>So the churches were made strong in the faith. The number of believers grew every day.<verse eid="ACT 16:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul’s Vision of the Man From Macedonia</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 16:6"/>Paul and his companions traveled all through the area of Phrygia and Galatia. The Holy Spirit had kept them from preaching the word in Asia Minor. <verse eid="ACT 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 16:7"/>They came to the border of Mysia. From there they tried to enter Bithynia. But the Spirit of Jesus would not let them. <verse eid="ACT 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 16:8"/>So they passed by Mysia. Then they went down to Troas. <verse eid="ACT 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 16:9"/>During the night Paul had a vision. He saw a man from Macedonia standing and begging him. “Come over to Macedonia!” the man said. “Help us!” <verse eid="ACT 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 16:10"/>After Paul had seen the vision, we got ready at once to leave for Macedonia. We decided that God had called us to preach the good news there.<verse eid="ACT 16:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Lydia Becomes a Believer in Philippi</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 16:11"/>At Troas we got into a boat. We sailed straight for Samothrace. The next day we went on to Neapolis. <verse eid="ACT 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 16:12"/>From there we traveled to Philippi, a Roman colony. It is an important city in that part of Macedonia. We stayed there several days.<verse eid="ACT 16:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 16:13"/>On the Sabbath day we went outside the city gate. We walked down to the river. There we expected to find a place of prayer. We sat down and began to speak to the women who had gathered together. <verse eid="ACT 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 16:14"/>One of the women listening was from the city of Thyatira. Her name was Lydia, and her business was selling purple cloth. She was a worshiper of God. The Lord opened her heart to accept Paul’s message. <verse eid="ACT 16:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 16:15"/>She and her family were baptized. Then she invited us to her home. “Do you consider me a believer in the Lord?” she asked. “If you do, come and stay at my house.” She succeeded in getting us to go home with her.<verse eid="ACT 16:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul and Silas Are Thrown Into Prison</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 16:16"/>One day we were going to the place of prayer. On the way we were met by a female slave. She had a spirit that helped her tell people what was going to happen. She earned a lot of money for her owners by doing this. <verse eid="ACT 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 16:17"/>She followed Paul and the rest of us around. She shouted, “These men serve the Most High God. They are telling you how to be saved.” <verse eid="ACT 16:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 16:18"/>She kept this up for many days. Finally Paul became upset. Turning around, he spoke to the spirit that was in her. “In the name of Jesus Christ,” he said, “I command you to come out of her!” At that very moment the spirit left the woman.<verse eid="ACT 16:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 16:19"/>Her owners realized that their hope of making money was gone. So they grabbed Paul and Silas. They dragged them into the market place to face the authorities. <verse eid="ACT 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 16:20"/>They brought them to the judges. “These men are Jews,” her owners said. “They are making trouble in our city. <verse eid="ACT 16:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 16:21"/>They are suggesting practices that are against Roman law. These are practices we can’t accept or take part in.”<verse eid="ACT 16:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 16:22"/>The crowd joined the attack against Paul and Silas. The judges ordered that Paul and Silas be stripped and beaten with rods. <verse eid="ACT 16:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 16:23"/>They were whipped without mercy. Then they were thrown into prison. The jailer was commanded to guard them carefully. <verse eid="ACT 16:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 16:24"/>When he received these orders, he put Paul and Silas deep inside the prison. He fastened their feet so they couldn’t get away.<verse eid="ACT 16:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 16:25"/>About midnight Paul and Silas were praying. They were also singing hymns to God. The other prisoners were listening to them. <verse eid="ACT 16:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 16:26"/>Suddenly there was a powerful earthquake. It shook the prison from top to bottom. All at once the prison doors flew open. Everyone’s chains came loose. <verse eid="ACT 16:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 16:27"/>The jailer woke up. He saw that the prison doors were open. He pulled out his sword and was going to kill himself. He thought the prisoners had escaped. <verse eid="ACT 16:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 16:28"/>“Don’t harm yourself!” Paul shouted. “We are all here!”<verse eid="ACT 16:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 16:29"/>The jailer called out for some lights. He rushed in, shaking with fear. He fell down in front of Paul and Silas. <verse eid="ACT 16:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 16:30"/>Then he brought them out. He asked, “Sirs, what must I do to be saved?”<verse eid="ACT 16:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 16:31"/>They replied, “Believe in the Lord Jesus. Then you and everyone living in your house will be saved.” <verse eid="ACT 16:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 16:32"/>They spoke the word of the Lord to him. They also spoke to all the others in his house. <verse eid="ACT 16:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 16:33"/>At that hour of the night, the jailer took Paul and Silas and washed their wounds. Right away he and everyone who lived with him were baptized. <verse eid="ACT 16:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 16:34"/>The jailer brought them into his house. He set a meal in front of them. He and everyone who lived with him were filled with joy. They had become believers in God.<verse eid="ACT 16:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 16:35"/>Early in the morning the judges sent their officers to the jailer. They ordered him, “Let those men go.” <verse eid="ACT 16:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 16:36"/>The jailer told Paul, “The judges have ordered me to set you and Silas free. You can leave now. Go in peace.”<verse eid="ACT 16:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 16:37"/>But Paul replied to the officers. “They beat us in public,” he said. “We weren’t given a trial. And we are Roman citizens! They threw us into prison. And now do they want to get rid of us quietly? No! Let them come themselves and personally lead us out.”<verse eid="ACT 16:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 16:38"/>The officers reported this to the judges. When the judges heard that Paul and Silas were Roman citizens, they became afraid. <verse eid="ACT 16:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 16:39"/>So they came and said they were sorry. They led them out of the prison. Then they asked them to leave the city. <verse eid="ACT 16:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 16:40"/>After Paul and Silas came out of the prison, they went to Lydia’s house. There they met with the brothers and sisters. They told them to be brave. Then they left.<verse eid="ACT 16:40"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="ACT 17"/>
  <para style="s1">Paul and Silas Arrive in Thessalonica</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 17:1"/>Paul and those traveling with him passed through Amphipolis and Apollonia. They came to Thessalonica. A Jewish synagogue was there. <verse eid="ACT 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 17:2"/>Paul went into the synagogue as he usually did. For three Sabbath days in a row he talked with the Jews about the Scriptures. <verse eid="ACT 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 17:3"/>He explained and proved that the Messiah had to suffer and rise from the dead. “This Jesus I am telling you about is the Messiah!” he said. <verse eid="ACT 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 17:4"/>His words won over some of the Jews. They joined Paul and Silas. A large number of Greeks who worshiped God joined them too. So did quite a few important women.<verse eid="ACT 17:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 17:5"/>But other Jews were jealous. So they rounded up some evil people from the market place. Forming a crowd, they started all kinds of trouble in the city. The Jews rushed to Jason’s house. They were looking for Paul and Silas. They wanted to bring them out to the crowd. <verse eid="ACT 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 17:6"/>But they couldn’t find them. So they dragged Jason and some other believers to the city officials. “These men have caused trouble all over the world,” they shouted. “Now they have come here. <verse eid="ACT 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 17:7"/>Jason has welcomed them into his house. They are all disobeying Caesar’s commands. They say there is another king. He is called Jesus.” <verse eid="ACT 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 17:8"/>When the crowd and the city officials heard this, they became very upset. <verse eid="ACT 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 17:9"/>They made Jason and the others give them money. The officials did this to make sure they would return to the court. Then they let Jason and the others go.<verse eid="ACT 17:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul and Silas Are Sent to Berea</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 17:10"/>As soon as it was night, the believers sent Paul and Silas away to Berea. When they arrived, they went to the Jewish synagogue. <verse eid="ACT 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 17:11"/>The Berean Jews were very glad to receive Paul’s message. They studied the Scriptures carefully every day. They wanted to see if what Paul said was true. So they were more noble than the Thessalonian Jews. <verse eid="ACT 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 17:12"/>Because of this, many of the Berean Jews believed. A number of important Greek women also became believers. And so did many Greek men.<verse eid="ACT 17:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 17:13"/>But the Jews in Thessalonica found out that Paul was preaching God’s word in Berea. So some of them went there too. They stirred up the crowds and got them all worked up. <verse eid="ACT 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 17:14"/>Right away the believers sent Paul to the coast. But Silas and Timothy stayed in Berea. <verse eid="ACT 17:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 17:15"/>The believers who went with Paul took him to Athens. Then they returned with orders that Silas and Timothy were supposed to join him as soon as they could.<verse eid="ACT 17:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Preaches in Athens</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 17:16"/>Paul was waiting for Silas and Timothy in Athens. He was very upset to see that the city was full of statues of gods. <verse eid="ACT 17:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 17:17"/>So he went to the synagogue. There he talked both with Jews and with Greeks who worshiped God. Each day he spoke with anyone who happened to be in the market place. <verse eid="ACT 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 17:18"/>A group of Epicurean and Stoic thinkers began to argue with him. Some of them asked, “What is this fellow chattering about?” Others said, “He seems to be telling us about gods we’ve never heard of.” They said this because Paul was preaching the good news about Jesus. He was telling them that Jesus had risen from the dead. <verse eid="ACT 17:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 17:19"/>They took him to a meeting of the Areopagus. There they said to him, “What is this new teaching you’re giving us? <verse eid="ACT 17:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 17:20"/>You have some strange ideas we’ve never heard before. We would like to know what they mean.” <verse eid="ACT 17:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 17:21"/>All the people of Athens spent their time talking about and listening to the latest ideas. People from other lands who lived there did the same.<verse eid="ACT 17:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 17:22"/>Then Paul stood up in the meeting of the Areopagus. He said, “People of Athens! I see that you are very religious in every way. <verse eid="ACT 17:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 17:23"/>As I walked around, I looked carefully at the things you worship. I even found an altar with</para>
  <para style="pc" vid="ACT 17:23">To an Unknown God</para>
  <para style="m" vid="ACT 17:23">written on it. So you don’t know what you are worshiping. Now I am going to tell you about this ‘unknown god.’<verse eid="ACT 17:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 17:24"/>“He is the God who made the world. He also made everything in it. He is the Lord of heaven and earth. He doesn’t live in temples built by human hands. <verse eid="ACT 17:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 17:25"/>He is not served by human hands. He doesn’t need anything. Instead, he himself gives life and breath to all people. He also gives them everything else they have. <verse eid="ACT 17:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 17:26"/>From one man he made all the people of the world. Now they live all over the earth. He decided exactly when they should live. And he decided exactly where they should live. <verse eid="ACT 17:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 17:27"/>God did this so that people would seek him. And perhaps they would reach out for him and find him. They would find him even though he is not far from any of us. <verse eid="ACT 17:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 17:28"/>‘In him we live and move and exist.’ As some of your own poets have also said, ‘We are his children.’<verse eid="ACT 17:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 17:29"/>“Yes, we are God’s children. So we shouldn’t think that God is made out of gold or silver or stone. He isn’t a statue planned and made by clever people. <verse eid="ACT 17:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 17:30"/>In the past, God didn’t judge people for what they didn’t know. But now he commands all people everywhere to turn away from their sins. <verse eid="ACT 17:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 17:31"/>He has set a day when he will judge the world fairly. He has appointed a man to be its judge. God has proved this to everyone by raising that man from the dead.”<verse eid="ACT 17:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 17:32"/>They heard Paul talk about the dead being raised. Some of them made fun of this idea. But others said, “We want to hear you speak about this again.” <verse eid="ACT 17:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 17:33"/>So Paul left the meeting of the Areopagus. <verse eid="ACT 17:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 17:34"/>Some of the people became followers of Paul and believed in Jesus. Dionysius was one of them. He was a member of the Areopagus. A woman named Damaris also became a believer. And so did some others.<verse eid="ACT 17:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="ACT 18"/>
  <para style="s1">Paul Goes to Corinth</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 18:1"/>After this, Paul left Athens and went to Corinth. <verse eid="ACT 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 18:2"/>There he met a Jew named Aquila, who was a native of Pontus. Aquila had recently come from Italy with his wife Priscilla. The emperor Claudius had ordered all Jews to leave Rome. Paul went to see Aquila and Priscilla. <verse eid="ACT 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 18:3"/>They were tentmakers, just as he was. So he stayed and worked with them. <verse eid="ACT 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 18:4"/>Every Sabbath day he went to the synagogue. He was trying to get both Jews and Greeks to believe in the Lord.<verse eid="ACT 18:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 18:5"/>Silas and Timothy came from Macedonia. Then Paul spent all his time preaching. He was a witness to the Jews that Jesus was the Messiah. <verse eid="ACT 18:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 18:6"/>But they opposed Paul. They treated him badly. So he shook out his clothes in protest. Then he said to them, “God’s judgment against you will be your own fault! Don’t blame me for it! From now on I will go to the Gentiles.”<verse eid="ACT 18:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 18:7"/>Then Paul left the synagogue and went to the house next door. It was the house of Titius Justus, a man who worshiped God. <verse eid="ACT 18:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 18:8"/>Crispus was the synagogue leader. He and everyone living in his house came to believe in the Lord. Many others who lived in Corinth heard Paul. They too believed and were baptized.<verse eid="ACT 18:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 18:9"/>One night the Lord spoke to Paul in a vision. “Don’t be afraid,” he said. “Keep on speaking. Don’t be silent. <verse eid="ACT 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 18:10"/>I am with you. No one will attack you and harm you. I have many people in this city.” <verse eid="ACT 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 18:11"/>So Paul stayed in Corinth for a year and a half. He taught them God’s word.<verse eid="ACT 18:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 18:12"/>At that time Gallio was governor of Achaia. The Jews of Corinth got together and attacked Paul. They brought him into court. <verse eid="ACT 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 18:13"/>They made a charge against Paul. They said, “This man is talking people into worshiping God in wrong ways. Those ways are against the law.”<verse eid="ACT 18:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 18:14"/>Paul was about to give reasons for his actions. But just then Gallio spoke to them. He said, “You Jews don’t claim that Paul has committed a great or small crime. If you did, it would make sense for me to listen to you. <verse eid="ACT 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 18:15"/>But this is about your own law. It is a question of words and names. Settle the matter yourselves. I will not be a judge of such things.” <verse eid="ACT 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 18:16"/>So he made them leave. <verse eid="ACT 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 18:17"/>Then the crowd there turned against Sosthenes, the synagogue leader. They beat him up in front of the governor. But Gallio didn’t care at all.<verse eid="ACT 18:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Priscilla and Aquila Teach Apollos</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 18:18"/>Paul stayed in Corinth for some time. Then he left the brothers and sisters and sailed for Syria. Priscilla and Aquila went with him. Before he sailed, he had his hair cut off at Cenchreae. He did this because he had made a promise to God. <verse eid="ACT 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 18:19"/>They arrived at Ephesus. There Paul said goodbye to Priscilla and Aquila. He himself went into the synagogue and talked with the Jews. <verse eid="ACT 18:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 18:20"/>The Jews asked him to spend more time with them. But he said no. <verse eid="ACT 18:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 18:21"/>As he left, he made them a promise. “If God wants me to,” he said, “I will come back.” Then he sailed from Ephesus. <verse eid="ACT 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 18:22"/>When he landed at Caesarea, he went up to Jerusalem. There he greeted the church. He then went down to Antioch.<verse eid="ACT 18:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 18:23"/>Paul spent some time in Antioch. Then he left and traveled all over Galatia and Phrygia. He gave strength to all the believers there.<verse eid="ACT 18:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 18:24"/>At that time a Jew named Apollos came to Ephesus. He was an educated man from Alexandria. He knew the Scriptures very well. <verse eid="ACT 18:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 18:25"/>Apollos had been taught the way of the Lord. He spoke with great power. He taught the truth about Jesus. But he only knew about John’s baptism. <verse eid="ACT 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 18:26"/>He began to speak boldly in the synagogue. Priscilla and Aquila heard him. So they invited him to their home. There they gave him a better understanding of the way of God.<verse eid="ACT 18:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 18:27"/>Apollos wanted to go to Achaia. The brothers and sisters agreed with him. They wrote to the believers there. They asked them to welcome him. When he arrived, he was a great help to those who had become believers by God’s grace. <verse eid="ACT 18:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 18:28"/>In public meetings, he argued strongly against Jews who disagreed with him. He proved from the Scriptures that Jesus was the Messiah.<verse eid="ACT 18:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="ACT 19"/>
  <para style="s1">Paul Goes to Ephesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 19:1"/>While Apollos was at Corinth, Paul took the road to Ephesus. When he arrived, he found some believers there. <verse eid="ACT 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 19:2"/>He asked them, “Did you receive the Holy Spirit when you became believers?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 19:2">“No,” they answered. “We haven’t even heard that there is a Holy Spirit.”<verse eid="ACT 19:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 19:3"/>So Paul asked, “Then what baptism did you receive?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 19:3">“John’s baptism,” they replied.<verse eid="ACT 19:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 19:4"/>Paul said, “John baptized people, calling them to turn away from their sins. He told them to believe in the one who was coming after him. Jesus is that one.” <verse eid="ACT 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 19:5"/>After hearing this, they were baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus. <verse eid="ACT 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 19:6"/>Paul placed his hands on them. Then the Holy Spirit came on them. They spoke in languages they had not known before. They also prophesied. <verse eid="ACT 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 19:7"/>There were about 12 men in all.<verse eid="ACT 19:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 19:8"/>Paul entered the synagogue. There he spoke boldly for three months. He gave good reasons for believing the truth about God’s kingdom. <verse eid="ACT 19:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 19:9"/>But some of them wouldn’t listen. They refused to believe. In public they said evil things about the Way of Jesus. So Paul left them. He took the believers with him. Each day he talked with people in the lecture hall of Tyrannus. <verse eid="ACT 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 19:10"/>This went on for two years. So all the Jews and Greeks who lived in Asia Minor heard the word of the Lord.<verse eid="ACT 19:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 19:11"/>God did amazing miracles through Paul. <verse eid="ACT 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 19:12"/>Even handkerchiefs and aprons that had touched him were taken to those who were sick. When this happened, their sicknesses were healed and evil spirits left them.<verse eid="ACT 19:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 19:13"/>Some Jews went around driving out evil spirits. They tried to use the name of the Lord Jesus to set free those who were controlled by demons. They said, “In Jesus’ name I command you to come out. He is the Jesus that Paul is preaching about.” <verse eid="ACT 19:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 19:14"/>Seven sons of Sceva were doing this. Sceva was a Jewish chief priest. <verse eid="ACT 19:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 19:15"/>One day the evil spirit answered them, “I know Jesus. And I know about Paul. But who are you?” <verse eid="ACT 19:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 19:16"/>Then the man who had the evil spirit jumped on Sceva’s sons. He overpowered them all. He gave them a terrible beating. They ran out of the house naked and bleeding.<verse eid="ACT 19:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 19:17"/>The Jews and Greeks living in Ephesus heard about this. They were all overcome with fear. They held the name of the Lord Jesus in high honor. <verse eid="ACT 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 19:18"/>Many who believed now came and openly admitted what they had done. <verse eid="ACT 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 19:19"/>A number of those who had practiced evil magic brought their scrolls together. They set them on fire out in the open. They added up the value of the scrolls. The scrolls were worth more than someone could earn in two lifetimes. <verse eid="ACT 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 19:20"/>The word of the Lord spread everywhere. It became more and more powerful.<verse eid="ACT 19:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 19:21"/>After all this had happened, Paul decided to go to Jerusalem. He went through Macedonia and Achaia. “After I have been to Jerusalem,” he said, “I must visit Rome also.” <verse eid="ACT 19:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 19:22"/>He sent Timothy and Erastus, two of his helpers, to Macedonia. But he stayed a little longer in Asia Minor.<verse eid="ACT 19:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Trouble in Ephesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 19:23"/>At that time many people became very upset about the Way of Jesus. <verse eid="ACT 19:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 19:24"/>There was a man named Demetrius who made things out of silver. He made silver models of the temple of the goddess Artemis. He brought in a lot of business for the other skilled workers there. <verse eid="ACT 19:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 19:25"/>One day he called them together. He also called others who were in the same kind of business. “My friends,” he said, “you know that we make good money from our work. <verse eid="ACT 19:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 19:26"/>You have seen and heard what this fellow Paul is doing. He has talked to large numbers of people here in Ephesus. Almost everywhere in Asia Minor he has led people away from our gods. He says that the gods made by human hands are not gods at all. <verse eid="ACT 19:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 19:27"/>Our work is in danger of losing its good name. People’s faith in the temple of the great goddess Artemis will be weakened. Now she is worshiped all over Asia Minor and the whole world. But soon she will be robbed of her greatness.”<verse eid="ACT 19:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 19:28"/>When they heard this, they became very angry. They began shouting, “Great is Artemis of the Ephesians!” <verse eid="ACT 19:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 19:29"/>Soon people were making trouble in the whole city. They all rushed into the theater. They dragged Gaius and Aristarchus along with them. These two men had come with Paul from Macedonia. <verse eid="ACT 19:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 19:30"/>Paul wanted to appear in front of the crowd. But the believers wouldn’t let him. <verse eid="ACT 19:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 19:31"/>Some of the officials in Asia Minor were friends of Paul. They sent him a message, begging him not to go into the theater.<verse eid="ACT 19:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 19:32"/>The crowd didn’t know what was going on. Some were shouting one thing and some another. Most of the people didn’t even know why they were there. <verse eid="ACT 19:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 19:33"/>The Jews in the crowd pushed Alexander to the front. They tried to tell him what to say. But he motioned for them to be quiet. He was about to give the people reasons for his actions. <verse eid="ACT 19:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 19:34"/>But then they realized that he was a Jew. So they all shouted the same thing for about two hours. “Great is Artemis of the Ephesians!” they yelled.<verse eid="ACT 19:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 19:35"/>The city clerk quieted the crowd down. “People of Ephesus!” he said. “The city of Ephesus guards the temple of the great Artemis. The whole world knows this. They know that Ephesus guards her statue, which fell from heaven. <verse eid="ACT 19:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 19:36"/>These facts can’t be questioned. So calm down. Don’t do anything foolish. <verse eid="ACT 19:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 19:37"/>These men haven’t robbed any temples. They haven’t said evil things against our female god. But you have brought them here anyhow. <verse eid="ACT 19:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 19:38"/>Demetrius and the other skilled workers may feel they have been wronged by someone. Let them bring charges. The courts are open. We have our governors. <verse eid="ACT 19:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 19:39"/>Is there anything else you want to bring up? Settle it in a court of law. <verse eid="ACT 19:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 19:40"/>As it is, we are in danger of being charged with a crime. We could be charged with causing all this trouble today. There is no reason for it. So we wouldn’t be able to explain what has happened.” <verse eid="ACT 19:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 19:41"/>After he said this, he sent the people away.<verse eid="ACT 19:41"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="ACT 20"/>
  <para style="s1">Paul Travels Through Macedonia and Greece</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 20:1"/>All the trouble came to an end. Then Paul sent for the believers. After encouraging them, he said goodbye. He then left for Macedonia. <verse eid="ACT 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 20:2"/>He traveled through that area, speaking many words of hope to the people. Finally he arrived in Greece. <verse eid="ACT 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 20:3"/>There he stayed for three months. He was just about to sail for Syria. But some Jews were making plans against him. So he decided to go back through Macedonia. <verse eid="ACT 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 20:4"/>Sopater, son of Pyrrhus, from Berea went with him. Aristarchus and Secundus from Thessalonica, Gaius from Derbe, and Timothy went too. Tychicus and Trophimus from Asia Minor also went with him. <verse eid="ACT 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 20:5"/>These men went on ahead. They waited for us at Troas. <verse eid="ACT 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 20:6"/>But we sailed from Philippi after the Feast of Unleavened Bread. Five days later we joined the others at Troas. We stayed there for seven days.<verse eid="ACT 20:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Eutychus Is Raised From the Dead at Troas</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 20:7"/>On the first day of the week we met to break bread and eat together. Paul spoke to the people. He kept on talking until midnight because he planned to leave the next day. <verse eid="ACT 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 20:8"/>There were many lamps in the room upstairs where we were meeting. <verse eid="ACT 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 20:9"/>A young man named Eutychus was sitting in a window. He sank into a deep sleep as Paul talked on and on. Sound asleep, Eutychus fell from the third floor. When they picked him up from the ground, he was dead. <verse eid="ACT 20:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 20:10"/>Paul went down and threw himself on the young man. He put his arms around him. “Don’t be alarmed,” he told them. “He’s alive!” <verse eid="ACT 20:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 20:11"/>Then Paul went upstairs again. He broke bread and ate with them. He kept on talking until daylight. Then he left. <verse eid="ACT 20:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 20:12"/>The people took the young man home. They were greatly comforted because he was alive.<verse eid="ACT 20:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Says Goodbye to the Ephesian Elders</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 20:13"/>We went on ahead to the ship. We sailed for Assos. There we were going to take Paul on board. He had planned it this way because he wanted to go to Assos by land. <verse eid="ACT 20:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 20:14"/>So he met us there. We took him on board and went on to Mitylene. <verse eid="ACT 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 20:15"/>The next day we sailed from there. We arrived near Chios. The day after that we crossed over to Samos. We arrived at Miletus the next day. <verse eid="ACT 20:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 20:16"/>Paul had decided to sail past Ephesus. He didn’t want to spend time in Asia Minor. He was in a hurry to get to Jerusalem. If he could, he wanted to be there by the day of Pentecost.<verse eid="ACT 20:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 20:17"/>From Miletus, Paul sent for the elders of the church at Ephesus. <verse eid="ACT 20:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 20:18"/>When they arrived, he spoke to them. “You know how I lived the whole time I was with you,” he said. “From the first day I came into Asia Minor, <verse eid="ACT 20:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 20:19"/>I served the Lord with tears and without pride. I served him when I was greatly tested. I was tested by the evil plans of the Jews who disagreed with me. <verse eid="ACT 20:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 20:20"/>You know that nothing has kept me from preaching whatever would help you. I have taught you in public and from house to house. <verse eid="ACT 20:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 20:21"/>I have told both Jews and Greeks that they must turn away from their sins to God. They must have faith in our Lord Jesus.<verse eid="ACT 20:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 20:22"/>“Now I am going to Jerusalem. The Holy Spirit compels me. I don’t know what will happen to me there. <verse eid="ACT 20:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 20:23"/>I only know that in every city the Spirit warns me. He tells me that I will face prison and suffering. <verse eid="ACT 20:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 20:24"/>But my life means nothing to me. My only goal is to finish the race. I want to complete the work the Lord Jesus has given me. He wants me to tell others about the good news of God’s grace.<verse eid="ACT 20:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 20:25"/>“I have spent time with you preaching about the kingdom. I know that none of you will ever see me again. <verse eid="ACT 20:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 20:26"/>So I tell you today that I am not guilty if any of you don’t believe. <verse eid="ACT 20:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 20:27"/>I haven’t let anyone keep me from telling you everything God wants you to do. <verse eid="ACT 20:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 20:28"/>Keep watch over yourselves. Keep watch over all the believers. The Holy Spirit has made you leaders over them. Be shepherds of God’s church. He bought it with his own blood. <verse eid="ACT 20:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 20:29"/>I know that after I leave, wild wolves will come in among you. They won’t spare any of the sheep. <verse eid="ACT 20:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 20:30"/>Even men from your own people will rise up and twist the truth. They want to get the believers to follow them. <verse eid="ACT 20:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 20:31"/>So be on your guard! Remember that for three years I never stopped warning you. Night and day I warned each of you with tears.<verse eid="ACT 20:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 20:32"/>“Now I trust God to take care of you. I commit you to the message about his grace. It can build you up. Then you will share in what God plans to give all his people. <verse eid="ACT 20:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 20:33"/>I haven’t longed for anyone’s silver or gold or clothing. <verse eid="ACT 20:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 20:34"/>You yourselves know that I have used my own hands to meet my needs. I have also met the needs of my companions. <verse eid="ACT 20:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 20:35"/>In everything I did, I showed you that we must work hard and help the weak. We must remember the words of the Lord Jesus. He said, ‘It is more blessed to give than to receive.’ ”<verse eid="ACT 20:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 20:36"/>Paul finished speaking. Then he got down on his knees with all of them and prayed. <verse eid="ACT 20:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 20:37"/>They all wept as they hugged and kissed him. <verse eid="ACT 20:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 20:38"/>Paul had said that they would never see him again. That’s what hurt them the most. Then they went with him to the ship.<verse eid="ACT 20:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="ACT 21"/>
  <para style="s1">Paul Continues His Journey to Jerusalem</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 21:1"/>After we had torn ourselves away from the Ephesian elders, we headed out to sea. We sailed straight to Kos. The next day we went to Rhodes. From there we continued on to Patara. <verse eid="ACT 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 21:2"/>We found a ship crossing over to Phoenicia. So we went on board and headed out to sea. <verse eid="ACT 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 21:3"/>We came near Cyprus and passed to the south of it. Then we sailed on to Syria. We landed at Tyre. There our ship was supposed to unload. <verse eid="ACT 21:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 21:4"/>We looked for the believers there and stayed with them for seven days. The believers tried to keep Paul from going on to Jerusalem. They were led by the Holy Spirit to do this. <verse eid="ACT 21:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 21:5"/>When it was time to leave, we continued on our way. All the believers, including their whole families, went with us out of the city. There on the beach we got down on our knees to pray. <verse eid="ACT 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 21:6"/>We said goodbye to each other. Then we went on board the ship. And they returned home.<verse eid="ACT 21:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 21:7"/>Continuing on from Tyre, we landed at Ptolemais. There we greeted the brothers and sisters. We stayed with them for a day. <verse eid="ACT 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 21:8"/>The next day we left and arrived at Caesarea. We stayed at the house of Philip the evangelist. He was one of the seven deacons. <verse eid="ACT 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 21:9"/>He had four unmarried daughters who prophesied.<verse eid="ACT 21:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 21:10"/>We stayed there several days. Then a prophet named Agabus came down from Judea. <verse eid="ACT 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 21:11"/>He came over to us. Then he took Paul’s belt and tied his own hands and feet with it. He said, “The Holy Spirit says, ‘This is how the Jewish leaders in Jerusalem will tie up the owner of this belt. They will hand him over to the Gentiles.’ ”<verse eid="ACT 21:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 21:12"/>When we heard this, we all begged Paul not to go up to Jerusalem. <verse eid="ACT 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 21:13"/>He asked, “Why are you crying? Why are you breaking my heart? I’m ready to be put in prison. In fact, I’m ready to die in Jerusalem for the Lord Jesus.” <verse eid="ACT 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 21:14"/>We couldn’t change his mind. So we gave up. We said, “May what the Lord wants to happen be done.”<verse eid="ACT 21:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 21:15"/>After this, we started on our way to Jerusalem. <verse eid="ACT 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 21:16"/>Some of the believers from Caesarea went with us. They brought us to Mnason’s home. We were supposed to stay there. Mnason was from Cyprus. He was one of the first believers.<verse eid="ACT 21:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Arrives in Jerusalem</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 21:17"/>When we arrived in Jerusalem, the brothers and sisters gave us a warm welcome. <verse eid="ACT 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 21:18"/>The next day Paul and the rest of us went to see James. All the elders were there. <verse eid="ACT 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 21:19"/>Paul greeted them. Then he reported everything God had done among the Gentiles through his work.<verse eid="ACT 21:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 21:20"/>When they heard this, they praised God. Then they spoke to Paul. “Brother,” they said, “you see that thousands of Jews have become believers. All of them try very hard to obey the law. <verse eid="ACT 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 21:21"/>They have been told that you teach Jews to turn away from the Law of Moses. You teach this to the Jews who live among the Gentiles. They think that you teach those Jews not to circumcise their children. They think that you teach them to give up our Jewish ways. <verse eid="ACT 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 21:22"/>What should we do? They will certainly hear that you have come. <verse eid="ACT 21:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 21:23"/>So do what we tell you. There are four men with us who have made a promise to God. <verse eid="ACT 21:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 21:24"/>Take them with you. Join them in the Jewish practice that makes people pure and ‘clean.’ Pay their expenses so they can have their heads shaved. Then everyone will know that these reports about you are not true in any way. They will know that you yourself obey the law. <verse eid="ACT 21:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 21:25"/>We have already given written directions to the believers who are not Jews. They must not eat food that has been offered to statues of gods. They must not drink blood. They must not eat the meat of animals that have been choked to death. And they must not commit sexual sins.”<verse eid="ACT 21:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 21:26"/>The next day Paul took the men with him. They all made themselves pure and “clean” in the usual way. Then Paul went to the temple. There he reported the date when the days of cleansing would end. At that time the proper offering would be made for each of them.<verse eid="ACT 21:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Is Arrested</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 21:27"/>The seven days of cleansing were almost over. Some Jews from Asia Minor saw Paul at the temple. They stirred up the whole crowd and grabbed Paul. <verse eid="ACT 21:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 21:28"/>“Fellow Israelites, help us!” they shouted. “This is the man who teaches everyone in all places against our people. He speaks against our law and against this holy place. Besides, he has brought Greeks into the temple. He has made this holy place ‘unclean.’ ” <verse eid="ACT 21:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 21:29"/>They said this because they had seen Trophimus the Ephesian in the city with Paul. They thought Paul had brought him into the temple.<verse eid="ACT 21:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 21:30"/>The whole city was stirred up. People came running from all directions. They grabbed Paul and dragged him out of the temple. Right away the temple gates were shut. <verse eid="ACT 21:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 21:31"/>The people were trying to kill Paul. But news reached the commander of the Roman troops. He heard that people were making trouble in the whole city of Jerusalem. <verse eid="ACT 21:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 21:32"/>Right away he took some officers and soldiers with him. They ran down to the crowd. The people causing the trouble saw the commander and his soldiers. So they stopped beating Paul.<verse eid="ACT 21:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 21:33"/>The commander came up and arrested Paul. He ordered him to be held with two chains. Then he asked who Paul was and what he had done. <verse eid="ACT 21:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 21:34"/>Some in the crowd shouted one thing, some another. But the commander couldn’t get the facts because of all the noise. So he ordered that Paul be taken into the fort. <verse eid="ACT 21:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 21:35"/>Paul reached the steps. But then the mob became so wild that he had to be carried by the soldiers. <verse eid="ACT 21:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 21:36"/>The crowd that followed kept shouting, “Get rid of him!”<verse eid="ACT 21:36"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Speaks to the Crowd</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 21:37"/>The soldiers were about to take Paul into the fort. Then he asked the commander, “May I say something to you?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 21:37">“Do you speak Greek?” he replied. <verse eid="ACT 21:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 21:38"/>“Aren’t you the Egyptian who turned some of our people against their leaders? Didn’t you lead 4,000 terrorists out into the desert some time ago?”<verse eid="ACT 21:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 21:39"/>Paul answered, “I am a Jew from Tarsus in Cilicia. I am a citizen of an important city. Please let me speak to the people.”<verse eid="ACT 21:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 21:40"/>The commander told him he could. So Paul stood on the steps and motioned to the crowd. When all of them were quiet, he spoke to them in the Aramaic language.<verse eid="ACT 21:40"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="ACT 22"/>
  <para style="nb">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 22:1"/>“Brothers and fathers,” Paul began, “listen to me now. I want to give you reasons for my actions.”<verse eid="ACT 22:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 22:2"/>When they heard that he was speaking to them in Aramaic, they became very quiet.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 22:2">Then Paul said, <verse eid="ACT 22:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 22:3"/>“I am a Jew. I was born in Tarsus in Cilicia, but I grew up here in Jerusalem. I studied with Gamaliel. I was well trained by him in the law given to our people long ago. I wanted to serve God as much as any of you do today. <verse eid="ACT 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 22:4"/>I hurt the followers of the Way of Jesus. I sent many of them to their death. I arrested men and women. I threw them into prison. <verse eid="ACT 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 22:5"/>The high priest and the whole Council can be witnesses of this themselves. I even had some official letters they had written to their friends in Damascus. So I went there to bring these people as prisoners to Jerusalem to be punished.<verse eid="ACT 22:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 22:6"/>“I had almost reached Damascus. About noon a bright light from heaven suddenly flashed around me. <verse eid="ACT 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 22:7"/>I fell to the ground and heard a voice speak to me. ‘Saul! Saul!’ it said. ‘Why are you opposing me?’<verse eid="ACT 22:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 22:8"/>“ ‘Who are you, Lord?’ I asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 22:8">“ ‘I am Jesus of Nazareth,’ he replied. ‘I am the one you are opposing.’ <verse eid="ACT 22:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 22:9"/>The light was seen by my companions. But they didn’t understand the voice of the one speaking to me.<verse eid="ACT 22:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 22:10"/>“ ‘What should I do, Lord?’ I asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 22:10">“ ‘Get up,’ the Lord said. ‘Go into Damascus. There you will be told everything you have been given to do.’ <verse eid="ACT 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 22:11"/>The brightness of the light had blinded me. So my companions led me by the hand into Damascus.<verse eid="ACT 22:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 22:12"/>“A man named Ananias came to see me. He was a godly Jew who obeyed the law. All the Jews living there respected him very much. <verse eid="ACT 22:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 22:13"/>He stood beside me and said, ‘Brother Saul, receive your sight!’ At that very moment I was able to see him.<verse eid="ACT 22:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 22:14"/>“Then he said, ‘The God of our people has chosen you. He wanted to tell you his plans for you. You have seen the Blameless One. You have heard words from his mouth. <verse eid="ACT 22:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 22:15"/>Now you will tell everyone about what you have seen and heard. <verse eid="ACT 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 22:16"/>So what are you waiting for? Get up and call on his name. Be baptized. Have your sins washed away.’<verse eid="ACT 22:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 22:17"/>“I returned to Jerusalem and was praying at the temple. Then it seemed to me that I was dreaming. <verse eid="ACT 22:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 22:18"/>I saw the Lord speaking to me. ‘Quick!’ he said. ‘Leave Jerusalem at once. The people here will not accept what you tell them about me.’<verse eid="ACT 22:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 22:19"/>“ ‘Lord,’ I replied, ‘these people know what I used to do. I went from one synagogue to another and put believers in prison. I also beat them. <verse eid="ACT 22:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 22:20"/>Stephen was a man who told other people about you. I stood there when he was killed. I had agreed that he should die. I even guarded the coats of those who were killing him.’<verse eid="ACT 22:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 22:21"/>“Then the Lord said to me, ‘Go. I will send you far away to people who are not Jews.’ ”<verse eid="ACT 22:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul the Roman Citizen</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 22:22"/>The crowd listened to Paul until he said this. Then they shouted, “Kill him! He isn’t fit to live!”<verse eid="ACT 22:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 22:23"/>They shouted and threw off their coats. They threw dust into the air. <verse eid="ACT 22:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 22:24"/>So the commanding officer ordered that Paul be taken into the fort. He gave orders for Paul to be whipped and questioned. He wanted to find out why the people were shouting at him like this. <verse eid="ACT 22:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 22:25"/>A commander was standing there as they stretched Paul out to be whipped. Paul said to him, “Does the law allow you to whip a Roman citizen who hasn’t even been found guilty?”<verse eid="ACT 22:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 22:26"/>When the commander heard this, he went to the commanding officer and reported it. “What are you going to do?” the commander asked. “This man is a Roman citizen.”<verse eid="ACT 22:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 22:27"/>So the commanding officer went to Paul. “Tell me,” he asked. “Are you a Roman citizen?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 22:27">“Yes, I am,” Paul answered.<verse eid="ACT 22:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 22:28"/>Then the officer said, “I had to pay a lot of money to become a citizen.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 22:28">“But I was born a citizen,” Paul replied.<verse eid="ACT 22:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 22:29"/>Right away those who were about to question him left. Even the officer was alarmed. He realized that he had put Paul, a Roman citizen, in chains.<verse eid="ACT 22:29"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Is Taken to the Sanhedrin</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 22:30"/>The commanding officer wanted to find out exactly what the Jews had against Paul. So the next day he let Paul out of prison. He ordered a meeting of the chief priests and all the members of the Sanhedrin. Then he brought Paul and had him stand in front of them.<verse eid="ACT 22:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="ACT 23"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 23:1"/>Paul looked straight at the Sanhedrin. “My brothers,” he said, “I have always done my duty to God. To this day I feel that I have done nothing wrong.” <verse eid="ACT 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 23:2"/>Ananias the high priest heard this. So he ordered the men standing near Paul to hit him on the mouth. <verse eid="ACT 23:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 23:3"/>Then Paul said to him, “You pretender! God will hit you! You sit there and judge me by the law. But you yourself broke the law when you commanded them to hit me!”<verse eid="ACT 23:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 23:4"/>Those who were standing near Paul spoke to him. They said, “How dare you talk like that to God’s high priest!”<verse eid="ACT 23:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 23:5"/>Paul replied, “Brothers, I didn’t realize he was the high priest. It is written, ‘Do not speak evil about the ruler of your people.’ ” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="EXO 22:28">Exodus 22:28</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 23:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 23:6"/>Paul knew that some of them were Sadducees and the others were Pharisees. So he called out to the members of the Sanhedrin. “My brothers,” he said, “I am a Pharisee. I come from a family of Pharisees. I believe that people will rise from the dead. That’s why I am on trial.” <verse eid="ACT 23:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 23:7"/>When he said this, the Pharisees and the Sadducees started to argue. They began to take sides. <verse eid="ACT 23:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 23:8"/>The Sadducees say that people will not rise from the dead. They don’t believe there are angels or spirits either. But the Pharisees believe all these things.<verse eid="ACT 23:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 23:9"/>People were causing trouble and making a lot of noise. Some of the teachers of the law who were Pharisees stood up. They argued strongly. “We find nothing wrong with this man,” they said. “What if a spirit or an angel has spoken to him?” <verse eid="ACT 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 23:10"/>The people arguing were getting out of control. The commanding officer was afraid that Paul would be torn to pieces by them. So he ordered the soldiers to go down and take him away from them by force. The officer had told them to bring Paul into the fort.<verse eid="ACT 23:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 23:11"/>The next night the Lord stood near Paul. He said, “Be brave! You have told people about me in Jerusalem. You must do the same in Rome.”<verse eid="ACT 23:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Plan to Kill Paul</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 23:12"/>The next morning some Jews gathered secretly to make plans against Paul. They made a promise to themselves. They promised that they would not eat or drink anything until they killed him. <verse eid="ACT 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 23:13"/>More than 40 men took part in this plan. <verse eid="ACT 23:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 23:14"/>They went to the chief priests and the elders. They said, “We have made a special promise to God. We will not eat anything until we have killed Paul. <verse eid="ACT 23:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 23:15"/>Now then, you and the Sanhedrin must make an appeal to the commanding officer. Ask him to bring Paul to you. Pretend you want more facts about his case. We are ready to kill him before he gets here.”<verse eid="ACT 23:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 23:16"/>But Paul’s nephew heard about this plan. So he went into the fort and told Paul.<verse eid="ACT 23:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 23:17"/>Then Paul called one of the commanders. He said to him, “Take this young man to the commanding officer. He has something to tell him.” <verse eid="ACT 23:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 23:18"/>So the commander took Paul’s nephew to the officer.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 23:18">The commander said, “Paul, the prisoner, sent for me. He asked me to bring this young man to you. The young man has something to tell you.”<verse eid="ACT 23:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 23:19"/>The commanding officer took the young man by the hand. He spoke to him in private. “What do you want to tell me?” the officer asked.<verse eid="ACT 23:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 23:20"/>He said, “Some Jews have agreed to ask you to bring Paul to the Sanhedrin tomorrow. They will pretend they want more facts about him. <verse eid="ACT 23:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 23:21"/>Don’t give in to them. More than 40 of them are waiting in hiding to attack him. They have promised that they will not eat or drink anything until they have killed him. They are ready now. All they need is for you to bring Paul to the Sanhedrin.”<verse eid="ACT 23:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 23:22"/>The commanding officer let the young man go. But he gave him a warning. “Don’t tell anyone you have reported this to me,” he said.<verse eid="ACT 23:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Is Taken to Caesarea</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 23:23"/>Then the commanding officer called for two of his commanders. He ordered them, “Gather a company of 200 soldiers, 70 horsemen and 200 men armed with spears. Get them ready to go to Caesarea at nine o’clock tonight. <verse eid="ACT 23:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 23:24"/>Provide horses for Paul so that he may be taken safely to Governor Felix.”<verse eid="ACT 23:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 23:25"/>Here is the letter the officer wrote.<verse eid="ACT 23:25"/></para>
  <para style="pmo">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 23:26"/>I, Claudius Lysias, am writing this letter.</para>
  <para style="pmo" vid="ACT 23:26">I am sending it to His Excellency, Governor Felix.</para>
  <para style="pmo" vid="ACT 23:26">Greetings.<verse eid="ACT 23:26"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 23:27"/>The Jews grabbed Paul. They were about to kill him. But I came with my soldiers and saved him. I had learned that he is a Roman citizen. <verse eid="ACT 23:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 23:28"/>I wanted to know why they were bringing charges against him. So I brought him to their Sanhedrin. <verse eid="ACT 23:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 23:29"/>I found out that the charge against him was based on questions about their law. But there was no charge against him worthy of death or prison. <verse eid="ACT 23:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 23:30"/>Then I was told about a plan against the man. So I sent him to you at once. I also ordered those bringing charges against him to present their case to you.<verse eid="ACT 23:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 23:31"/>The soldiers followed their orders. During the night they took Paul with them. They brought him as far as Antipatris. <verse eid="ACT 23:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 23:32"/>The next day they let the horsemen go on with him. The soldiers returned to the fort. <verse eid="ACT 23:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 23:33"/>The horsemen arrived in Caesarea. They gave the letter to the governor. Then they handed Paul over to him. <verse eid="ACT 23:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 23:34"/>The governor read the letter. He asked Paul where he was from. He learned that Paul was from Cilicia. <verse eid="ACT 23:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 23:35"/>So he said, “I will hear your case when those bringing charges against you get here.” Then he ordered that Paul be kept under guard in Herod’s palace.<verse eid="ACT 23:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="ACT 24"/>
  <para style="s1">Paul’s Trial in Front of Felix</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 24:1"/>Five days later Ananias the high priest went down to Caesarea. Some elders and a lawyer named Tertullus went with him. They brought their charges against Paul to the governor. <verse eid="ACT 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 24:2"/>So Paul was called in. Tertullus began to bring the charges against Paul. He said to Felix, “We have enjoyed a long time of peace while you have been ruling. You are a wise leader. You have made this a better nation. <verse eid="ACT 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 24:3"/>Most excellent Felix, we gladly admit this everywhere and in every way. And we are very thankful. <verse eid="ACT 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 24:4"/>I don’t want to bother you. But would you be kind enough to listen to us for a short time?<verse eid="ACT 24:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 24:5"/>“We have found that Paul is a troublemaker. This man stirs up trouble among Jews all over the world. He is a leader of those who follow Jesus of Nazareth. <verse eid="ACT 24:5"/><verse number="6-7" style="v" sid="ACT 24:6-7"/>He even tried to make our temple impure. So we arrested him. <verse eid="ACT 24:6-7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 24:8"/>Question him yourself. Then you will learn the truth about all these charges we are bringing against him.”<verse eid="ACT 24:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 24:9"/>The other Jews said the same thing. They agreed that the charges were true.<verse eid="ACT 24:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 24:10"/>The governor motioned for Paul to speak. Paul said, “I know that you have been a judge over this nation for quite a few years. So I am glad to explain my actions to you. <verse eid="ACT 24:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 24:11"/>About 12 days ago I went up to Jerusalem to worship. You can easily check on this. <verse eid="ACT 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 24:12"/>Those bringing charges against me did not find me arguing with anyone at the temple. I wasn’t stirring up a crowd in the synagogues or anywhere else in the city. <verse eid="ACT 24:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 24:13"/>They can’t prove to you any of the charges they are making against me. <verse eid="ACT 24:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 24:14"/>It is true that I worship the God of our people. I am a follower of the Way of Jesus. Those bringing charges against me call it a cult. I believe everything that is in keeping with the Law. I believe everything that is in keeping with what is written in the Prophets. <verse eid="ACT 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 24:15"/>I have the same hope in God that these men themselves have. I believe that both the godly and the ungodly will rise from the dead. <verse eid="ACT 24:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 24:16"/>So I always try not to do anything wrong in the eyes of God or in the eyes of people.<verse eid="ACT 24:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 24:17"/>“I was away for several years. Then I came to Jerusalem to bring my people gifts for those who were poor. I also came to offer sacrifices. <verse eid="ACT 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 24:18"/>They found me doing this in the temple courtyard. I had already been made pure and ‘clean’ in the usual way. There was no crowd with me. I didn’t stir up any trouble. <verse eid="ACT 24:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 24:19"/>But there are some other Jews who should be here in front of you. They are from Asia Minor. They should bring charges if they have anything against me. <verse eid="ACT 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 24:20"/>Let the Jews who are here tell you what crime I am guilty of. After all, I was put on trial by the Sanhedrin. <verse eid="ACT 24:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 24:21"/>Perhaps they blame me for what I said when I was on trial. I shouted, ‘I believe that people will rise from the dead. That is why I am on trial here today.’ ”<verse eid="ACT 24:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 24:22"/>Felix knew all about the Way of Jesus. So he put off the trial for the time being. “Lysias the commanding officer will come,” he said. “Then I will decide your case.” <verse eid="ACT 24:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 24:23"/>He ordered the commander to keep Paul under guard. He told him to give Paul some freedom. He also told him to allow Paul’s friends to take care of his needs.<verse eid="ACT 24:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 24:24"/>Several days later Felix came with his wife Drusilla. She was a Jew. Felix sent for Paul and listened to him speak about faith in Christ Jesus. <verse eid="ACT 24:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 24:25"/>Paul talked about how to live a godly life. He talked about how people should control themselves. He also talked about the time when God will judge everyone. Then Felix became afraid. “That’s enough for now!” he said. “You may leave. When I find the time, I will send for you.” <verse eid="ACT 24:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 24:26"/>He was hoping that Paul would offer him some money to let him go. So he often sent for Paul and talked with him.<verse eid="ACT 24:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 24:27"/>Two years passed. Porcius Festus took the place of Felix. But Felix wanted to do the Jews a favor. So he left Paul in prison.<verse eid="ACT 24:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 24"/>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="ACT 25"/>
  <para style="s1">Paul’s Trial in Front of Festus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 25:1"/>Three days after Festus arrived, he went up from Caesarea to Jerusalem. <verse eid="ACT 25:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 25:2"/>There the chief priests and the Jewish leaders came to Festus. They brought their charges against Paul. <verse eid="ACT 25:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 25:3"/>They tried very hard to get Festus to have Paul taken to Jerusalem. They asked for this as a favor. They were planning to hide and attack Paul along the way. They wanted to kill him. <verse eid="ACT 25:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 25:4"/>Festus answered, “Paul is being held at Caesarea. Soon I’ll be going there myself. <verse eid="ACT 25:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 25:5"/>Let some of your leaders come with me. If the man has done anything wrong, they can bring charges against him there.”<verse eid="ACT 25:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 25:6"/>Festus spent eight or ten days in Jerusalem with them. Then he went down to Caesarea. The next day he called the court together. He ordered Paul to be brought to him. <verse eid="ACT 25:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 25:7"/>When Paul arrived, the Jews who had come down from Jerusalem stood around him. They brought many strong charges against him. But they couldn’t prove that these charges were true.<verse eid="ACT 25:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 25:8"/>Then Paul spoke up for himself. He said, “I’ve done nothing wrong against the law of the Jews or against the temple. I’ve done nothing wrong against Caesar.”<verse eid="ACT 25:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 25:9"/>But Festus wanted to do the Jews a favor. So he said to Paul, “Are you willing to go up to Jerusalem? Are you willing to go on trial there? Are you willing to face these charges in my court?”<verse eid="ACT 25:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 25:10"/>Paul answered, “I’m already standing in Caesar’s court. This is where I should go on trial. I haven’t done anything wrong to the Jews. You yourself know that very well. <verse eid="ACT 25:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 25:11"/>If I am guilty of anything worthy of death, I’m willing to die. But the charges brought against me by these Jews are not true. No one has the right to hand me over to them. I make my appeal to Caesar!”<verse eid="ACT 25:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 25:12"/>Festus talked it over with the members of his court. Then he said, “You have made an appeal to Caesar. To Caesar you will go!”<verse eid="ACT 25:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Festus Talks With King Agrippa</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 25:13"/>A few days later King Agrippa and Bernice arrived in Caesarea. They came to pay a visit to Festus. <verse eid="ACT 25:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 25:14"/>They were spending many days there. So Festus talked with the king about Paul’s case. He said, “There’s a man here that Felix left as a prisoner. <verse eid="ACT 25:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 25:15"/>When I went to Jerusalem, the Jewish chief priests and the elders brought charges against the man. They wanted him to be found guilty.<verse eid="ACT 25:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 25:16"/>“I told them that this is not the way Romans do things. We don’t judge people before they have faced those bringing charges against them. They must have a chance to argue against the charges for themselves. <verse eid="ACT 25:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 25:17"/>When the Jewish leaders came back with me, I didn’t waste any time. I called the court together the next day. I ordered the man to be brought in. <verse eid="ACT 25:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 25:18"/>Those bringing charges against him got up to speak. But they didn’t charge him with any of the crimes I had expected. <verse eid="ACT 25:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 25:19"/>Instead, they argued with him about their own beliefs. They didn’t agree about a man named Jesus. They said Jesus was dead, but Paul claimed Jesus was alive. <verse eid="ACT 25:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 25:20"/>I had no idea how to look into such matters. So I asked Paul if he would be willing to go to Jerusalem. There he could be tried on these charges. <verse eid="ACT 25:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 25:21"/>But Paul made an appeal to have the Emperor decide his case. So I ordered him to be held until I could send him to Caesar.”<verse eid="ACT 25:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 25:22"/>Then Agrippa said to Festus, “I would like to hear this man myself.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 25:22">Festus replied, “Tomorrow you will hear him.”<verse eid="ACT 25:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul in Front of Agrippa</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 25:23"/>The next day Agrippa and Bernice arrived. They were treated like very important people. They entered the courtroom. The most important military officers and the leading men of the city came with them. When Festus gave the command, Paul was brought in. <verse eid="ACT 25:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 25:24"/>Festus said, “King Agrippa, and everyone else here, take a good look at this man! A large number of Jews have come to me about him. They came to me in Jerusalem and also here in Caesarea. They keep shouting that he shouldn’t live any longer. <verse eid="ACT 25:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 25:25"/>I have found that he hasn’t done anything worthy of death. But he made his appeal to the Emperor. So I decided to send him to Rome. <verse eid="ACT 25:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 25:26"/>I don’t have anything certain to write about him to His Majesty. So I have brought him here today. Now all of you will be able to hear him. King Agrippa, it will also be very good for you to hear him. As a result of this hearing, I will have something to write. <verse eid="ACT 25:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 25:27"/>It doesn’t make sense to send a prisoner on to Rome without listing the charges against him.”<verse eid="ACT 25:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 25"/>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="ACT 26"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 26:1"/>Agrippa said to Paul, “You may now present your case.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 26:1">So Paul motioned with his hand. Then he began to present his case. <verse eid="ACT 26:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 26:2"/>“King Agrippa,” he said, “I am happy to be able to stand here today. I will answer all the charges brought against me by the Jews. <verse eid="ACT 26:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 26:3"/>I am very pleased that you are familiar with Jewish ways. You know the kinds of things they argue about. So I beg you to be patient as you listen to me.<verse eid="ACT 26:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 26:4"/>“The Jewish people all know how I have lived ever since I was a child. They know all about me from the beginning of my life. They know how I lived in my own country and in Jerusalem. <verse eid="ACT 26:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 26:5"/>They have known me for a long time. So if they wanted to, they could tell you how I have lived. I have lived by the rules of the Pharisees. Those rules are harder to obey than those of any other Jewish group. <verse eid="ACT 26:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 26:6"/>Today I am on trial because of the hope I have. I believe in what God promised our people of long ago. <verse eid="ACT 26:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 26:7"/>It is the promise that our 12 tribes are hoping to see come true. Because of this hope they serve God with faithful and honest hearts day and night. King Agrippa, it is also because of this hope that these Jews are bringing charges against me. <verse eid="ACT 26:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 26:8"/>Why should any of you think it is impossible for God to raise the dead?<verse eid="ACT 26:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 26:9"/>“I believed that I should oppose the name of Jesus of Nazareth. So I did everything I could to oppose his name. <verse eid="ACT 26:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 26:10"/>That’s just what I was doing in Jerusalem. On the authority of the chief priests, I put many of the Lord’s people in prison. I agreed that they should die. <verse eid="ACT 26:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 26:11"/>I often went from one synagogue to another to have them punished. I tried to force them to speak evil things against Jesus. All I wanted to do was hurt them. I even went looking for them in the cities of other lands.<verse eid="ACT 26:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 26:12"/>“On one of these journeys I was on my way to Damascus. I had the authority and commission of the chief priests. <verse eid="ACT 26:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 26:13"/>About noon, King Agrippa, I was on the road. I saw a light coming from heaven. It was brighter than the sun. It was shining around me and my companions. <verse eid="ACT 26:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 26:14"/>We all fell to the ground. I heard a voice speak to me in the Aramaic language. ‘Saul! Saul!’ it said. ‘Why are you opposing me? It is hard for you to go against what you know is right.’<verse eid="ACT 26:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 26:15"/>“Then I asked, ‘Who are you, Lord?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ACT 26:15">“ ‘I am Jesus,’ the Lord replied. ‘I am the one you are opposing. <verse eid="ACT 26:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 26:16"/>Now get up. Stand on your feet. I have appeared to you to appoint you to serve me. And you must tell other people about me. You must tell others that you have seen me today. You must also tell them that I will show myself to you again. <verse eid="ACT 26:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 26:17"/>I will save you from your own people and from the Gentiles. I am sending you to them <verse eid="ACT 26:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 26:18"/>to open their eyes. I want you to turn them from darkness to light. I want you to turn them from Satan’s power to God. I want their sins to be forgiven. They will be forgiven when they believe in me. They will have their place among God’s people.’<verse eid="ACT 26:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 26:19"/>“So then, King Agrippa, I obeyed the vision that appeared from heaven. <verse eid="ACT 26:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 26:20"/>First I preached to people in Damascus. Then I preached in Jerusalem and in all Judea. And then I preached to the Gentiles. I told them to turn away from their sins to God. The way they live must show that they have turned away from their sins. <verse eid="ACT 26:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 26:21"/>That’s why some Jews grabbed me in the temple courtyard and tried to kill me. <verse eid="ACT 26:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 26:22"/>But God has helped me to this day. So I stand here and tell you what is true. I tell it to everyone, both small and great. I have been saying nothing different from what the prophets and Moses said would happen. <verse eid="ACT 26:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 26:23"/>They said the Messiah would suffer. He would be the first to rise from the dead. He would bring the message of God’s light. He would bring it to his own people and to the Gentiles.”<verse eid="ACT 26:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 26:24"/>While Paul was still presenting his case, Festus interrupted. “You are out of your mind, Paul!” he shouted. “Your great learning is driving you crazy!”<verse eid="ACT 26:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 26:25"/>“I am not crazy, most excellent Festus,” Paul replied. “What I am saying is true and reasonable. <verse eid="ACT 26:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 26:26"/>The king is familiar with these things. So I can speak openly to him. I am certain he knows everything that has been going on. After all, it was not done in secret. <verse eid="ACT 26:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 26:27"/>King Agrippa, do you believe the prophets? I know you do.”<verse eid="ACT 26:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 26:28"/>Then Agrippa spoke to Paul. “Are you trying to talk me into becoming a Christian?” he said. “Do you think you can do that in such a short time?”<verse eid="ACT 26:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 26:29"/>Paul replied, “I don’t care if it takes a short time or a long time. I pray to God for you and all who are listening to me today. I pray that you may become like me, except for these chains.”<verse eid="ACT 26:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 26:30"/>The king stood up. The governor and Bernice and those sitting with them stood up too. <verse eid="ACT 26:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 26:31"/>They left the room and began to talk with one another. “Why should this man die or be put in prison?” they said. “He has done nothing worthy of that!”<verse eid="ACT 26:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 26:32"/>Agrippa said to Festus, “This man could have been set free. But he has made an appeal to Caesar.”<verse eid="ACT 26:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 26"/>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="ACT 27"/>
  <para style="s1">Paul Sails for Rome</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 27:1"/>It was decided that we would sail for Italy. Paul and some other prisoners were handed over to a Roman commander named Julius. He belonged to the Imperial Guard. <verse eid="ACT 27:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 27:2"/>We boarded a ship from Adramyttium. It was about to sail for ports along the coast of Asia Minor. We headed out to sea. Aristarchus was with us. He was a Macedonian from Thessalonica.<verse eid="ACT 27:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 27:3"/>The next day we landed at Sidon. There Julius was kind to Paul. He let Paul visit his friends so they could give him what he needed. <verse eid="ACT 27:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 27:4"/>From there we headed out to sea again. We passed the calmer side of Cyprus because the winds were against us. <verse eid="ACT 27:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 27:5"/>We sailed across the open sea off the coast of Cilicia and Pamphylia. Then we landed at Myra in Lycia. <verse eid="ACT 27:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 27:6"/>There the commander found a ship from Alexandria sailing for Italy. He put us on board. <verse eid="ACT 27:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 27:7"/>We moved along slowly for many days. We had trouble getting to Cnidus. The wind did not let us stay on course. So we passed the calmer side of Crete, opposite Salmone. <verse eid="ACT 27:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 27:8"/>It was not easy to sail along the coast. Then we came to a place called Fair Havens. It was near the town of Lasea.<verse eid="ACT 27:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 27:9"/>A lot of time had passed. Sailing had already become dangerous. By now it was after the Day of Atonement, a day of fasting. So Paul gave them a warning. <verse eid="ACT 27:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 27:10"/>“Men,” he said, “I can see that our trip is going to be dangerous. The ship and everything in it will be lost. Our own lives will be in danger also.” <verse eid="ACT 27:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 27:11"/>But the commander didn’t listen to what Paul said. Instead, he followed the advice of the pilot and the ship’s owner. <verse eid="ACT 27:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 27:12"/>The harbor wasn’t a good place for ships to stay during winter. So most of the people decided we should sail on. They hoped we would reach Phoenix. They wanted to spend the winter there. Phoenix was a harbor in Crete. It faced both southwest and northwest.<verse eid="ACT 27:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Storm</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 27:13"/>A gentle south wind began to blow. The ship’s crew thought they saw their chance to leave safely. So they pulled up the anchor and sailed along the shore of Crete. <verse eid="ACT 27:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 27:14"/>Before very long, a wind blew down from the island. It had the force of a hurricane. It was called the Northeaster. <verse eid="ACT 27:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 27:15"/>The ship was caught by the storm. We could not keep it sailing into the wind. So we gave up and were driven along by the wind. <verse eid="ACT 27:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 27:16"/>We passed the calmer side of a small island called Cauda. We almost lost the lifeboat that was tied to the side of the ship. <verse eid="ACT 27:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 27:17"/>So the men lifted the lifeboat on board. Then they tied ropes under the ship itself to hold it together. They were afraid it would get stuck on the sandbars of Syrtis. So they lowered the sea anchor and let the ship be driven along. <verse eid="ACT 27:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 27:18"/>We took a very bad beating from the storm. The next day the crew began to throw the ship’s contents overboard. <verse eid="ACT 27:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 27:19"/>On the third day, they even threw the ship’s tools and supplies overboard with their own hands. <verse eid="ACT 27:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 27:20"/>The sun and stars didn’t appear for many days. The storm was terrible. So we gave up all hope of being saved.<verse eid="ACT 27:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 27:21"/>The men had not eaten for a long time. Paul stood up in front of them. “Men,” he said, “you should have taken my advice not to sail from Crete. Then you would have avoided this harm and loss. <verse eid="ACT 27:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 27:22"/>Now I beg you to be brave. Not one of you will die. Only the ship will be destroyed. <verse eid="ACT 27:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 27:23"/>I belong to God and serve him. Last night his angel stood beside me. <verse eid="ACT 27:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 27:24"/>The angel said, ‘Do not be afraid, Paul. You must go on trial in front of Caesar. God has shown his grace by sparing the lives of all those sailing with you.’ <verse eid="ACT 27:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 27:25"/>Men, continue to be brave. I have faith in God. It will happen just as he told me. <verse eid="ACT 27:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 27:26"/>But we must run the ship onto the beach of some island.”<verse eid="ACT 27:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Ship Is Destroyed</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 27:27"/>On the 14th night the wind was still pushing us across the Adriatic Sea. About midnight the sailors had a feeling that they were approaching land. <verse eid="ACT 27:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 27:28"/>They measured how deep the water was. They found that it was 120 feet deep. A short time later they measured the water again. This time it was 90 feet deep. <verse eid="ACT 27:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 27:29"/>They were afraid we would crash against the rocks. So they dropped four anchors from the back of the ship. They prayed that daylight would come. <verse eid="ACT 27:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 27:30"/>The sailors wanted to escape from the ship. So they let the lifeboat down into the sea. They pretended they were going to lower some anchors from the front of the ship. <verse eid="ACT 27:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 27:31"/>But Paul spoke to the commander and the soldiers. “These men must stay with the ship,” he said. “If they don’t, you can’t be saved.” <verse eid="ACT 27:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 27:32"/>So the soldiers cut the ropes that held the lifeboat. They let it drift away.<verse eid="ACT 27:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 27:33"/>Just before dawn Paul tried to get them all to eat. “For the last 14 days,” he said, “you have wondered what would happen. You have gone without food. You haven’t eaten anything. <verse eid="ACT 27:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 27:34"/>Now I am asking you to eat some food. You need it to live. Not one of you will lose a single hair from your head.” <verse eid="ACT 27:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 27:35"/>After Paul said this, he took some bread and gave thanks to God. He did this where they all could see him. Then he broke it and began to eat. <verse eid="ACT 27:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 27:36"/>All of them were filled with hope. So they ate some food. <verse eid="ACT 27:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 27:37"/>There were 276 of us on board. <verse eid="ACT 27:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 27:38"/>They ate as much as they wanted. They needed to make the ship lighter. So they threw the rest of the grain into the sea.<verse eid="ACT 27:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 27:39"/>When daylight came, they saw a bay with a sandy beach. They didn’t recognize the place. But they decided to run the ship onto the beach if they could. <verse eid="ACT 27:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 27:40"/>So they cut the anchors loose and left them in the sea. At the same time, they untied the ropes that held the rudders. They lifted the sail at the front of the ship to the wind. Then they headed for the beach. <verse eid="ACT 27:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 27:41"/>But the ship hit a sandbar. So the front of it got stuck and wouldn’t move. The back of the ship was broken to pieces by the pounding of the waves.<verse eid="ACT 27:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="ACT 27:42"/>The soldiers planned to kill the prisoners. They wanted to keep them from swimming away and escaping. <verse eid="ACT 27:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="ACT 27:43"/>But the commander wanted to save Paul’s life. So he kept the soldiers from carrying out their plan. He ordered those who could swim to jump overboard first and swim to land. <verse eid="ACT 27:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="ACT 27:44"/>The rest were supposed to get there on boards or other pieces of the ship. That is how everyone reached land safely.<verse eid="ACT 27:44"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 27"/>
  <chapter number="28" style="c" sid="ACT 28"/>
  <para style="s1">On Shore at Malta</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 28:1"/>When we were safe on shore, we found out that the island was called Malta. <verse eid="ACT 28:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 28:2"/>The people of the island were unusually kind. It was raining and cold. So they built a fire and welcomed all of us. <verse eid="ACT 28:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 28:3"/>Paul gathered some sticks and put them on the fire. A poisonous snake was driven out by the heat. It fastened itself on Paul’s hand. <verse eid="ACT 28:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 28:4"/>The people of the island saw the snake hanging from his hand. They said to one another, “This man must be a murderer. He escaped from the sea. But the female god Justice won’t let him live.” <verse eid="ACT 28:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 28:5"/>Paul shook the snake off into the fire. He was not harmed. <verse eid="ACT 28:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 28:6"/>The people expected him to swell up. They thought he would suddenly fall dead. They waited for a long time. But they didn’t see anything unusual happen to him. So they changed their minds. They said he was a god.<verse eid="ACT 28:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 28:7"/>Publius owned property nearby. He was the chief official on the island. He welcomed us to his home. For three days he took care of us. He treated us with kindness. <verse eid="ACT 28:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 28:8"/>His father was sick in bed. The man suffered from fever and dysentery. So Paul went in to see him. Paul prayed for him. He placed his hands on him and healed him. <verse eid="ACT 28:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 28:9"/>Then the rest of the sick people on the island came. They too were healed. <verse eid="ACT 28:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 28:10"/>The people of the island honored us in many ways. When we were ready to sail, they gave us the supplies we needed.<verse eid="ACT 28:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Arrives in Rome</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 28:11"/>After three months we headed out to sea. We sailed in a ship from Alexandria that had stayed at the island during the winter. On the front of the ship the figures of twin gods were carved. Their names were Castor and Pollux. <verse eid="ACT 28:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 28:12"/>We landed at Syracuse and stayed there for three days. <verse eid="ACT 28:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 28:13"/>From there we sailed to Rhegium. The next day the south wind came up. The day after that, we reached Puteoli. <verse eid="ACT 28:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 28:14"/>There we found some believers. They invited us to spend a week with them. At last we came to Rome. <verse eid="ACT 28:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 28:15"/>The believers there had heard we were coming. They traveled as far as the Forum of Appius and the Three Taverns to meet us. When Paul saw these people, he thanked God for them and was encouraged by them. <verse eid="ACT 28:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 28:16"/>When we got to Rome, Paul was allowed to live by himself. But a soldier guarded him.<verse eid="ACT 28:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Preaches in Rome</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 28:17"/>Three days later Paul called a meeting of the local Jewish leaders. When they came, Paul spoke to them. He said, “My brothers, I have done nothing against our people. I have also done nothing against what our people of long ago practiced. But I was arrested in Jerusalem. I was handed over to the Romans. <verse eid="ACT 28:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 28:18"/>They questioned me. And they wanted to let me go. They saw I wasn’t guilty of any crime worthy of death. <verse eid="ACT 28:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 28:19"/>But the Jews objected, so I had to make an appeal to Caesar. I certainly did not mean to bring any charge against my own people. <verse eid="ACT 28:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 28:20"/>I share Israel’s hope. That is why I am held with this chain. So I have asked to see you and talk with you.”<verse eid="ACT 28:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 28:21"/>They replied, “We have not received any letters from Judea about you. None of our people here from Judea has reported or said anything bad about you. <verse eid="ACT 28:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 28:22"/>But we want to hear what your ideas are. We know that people everywhere are talking against those who believe as you do.”<verse eid="ACT 28:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 28:23"/>They decided to meet Paul on a certain day. At that time even more people came to the place where he was staying. From morning until evening, he told them about God’s kingdom. Using the Law of Moses and the Prophets, he tried to get them to believe in Jesus. <verse eid="ACT 28:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 28:24"/>Some believed what he said, and others did not. <verse eid="ACT 28:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 28:25"/>They didn’t agree with one another. They began to leave after Paul had made a final statement. He said, “The Holy Spirit was right when he spoke to your people long ago. Through Isaiah the prophet the Spirit said,<verse eid="ACT 28:25"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 28:26"/>“ ‘Go to your people. Say to them,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 28:26">“You will hear but never understand.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 28:26">You will see but never know what you are seeing.”<verse eid="ACT 28:26"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 28:27"/>These people’s hearts have become stubborn.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 28:27">They can barely hear with their ears.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 28:27">They have closed their eyes.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 28:27">Otherwise they might see with their eyes.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 28:27">They might hear with their ears.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ACT 28:27">They might understand with their hearts.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ACT 28:27">They might turn, and then I would heal them.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 6:9">Isaiah 6:9</ref>,<ref loc="ISA 6:10">10</ref>)</char><verse eid="ACT 28:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28-29" style="v" sid="ACT 28:28-29"/>“Here is what I want you to know. God has sent his salvation to the Gentiles. And they will listen!”<verse eid="ACT 28:28-29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 28:30"/>For two whole years Paul stayed there in a house he rented. He welcomed all who came to see him. <verse eid="ACT 28:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 28:31"/>He preached boldly about God’s kingdom. He taught people about the Lord Jesus Christ. And no one could keep him from teaching and preaching about these things.<verse eid="ACT 28:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 28"/>
</usx>
