<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="DEU" style="id">- New International Readers Version 2014</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1995, 1996, 1998, 2014 by Biblica, Inc.</para>
  <para style="h">Deuteronomy</para>
  <para style="toc1">Deuteronomy</para>
  <para style="toc2">Deuteronomy</para>
  <para style="toc3">Dt</para>
  <para style="mt1">Deuteronomy</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">The book of Deuteronomy records the great speeches Moses gives just before he died. Moses talks to the Israelites who had grown up while wandering in the desert. He speaks to them as they prepare to enter the land of Canaan. God wants them to know what renewed life with his blessings will be like.</para>
  <para style="ip">Deuteronomy tells about God’s special promise to the Israelites. That promise is presented in the form of an agreement. This type of agreement was used by rulers of those times. These rulers made agreements with the people they ruled. The usual form of the agreement had these five parts. The book of Deuteronomy follows the pattern of these five parts very closely.</para>
  <para style="ili1">1. The God of Israel is the great king. Moses speaks God’s words to the people.</para>
  <para style="ili1">2. The mighty acts that God did for the Israelites are stated. This will help the people remember.</para>
  <para style="ili1">3. The rules, laws and commands that God gave are listed. Moses asks the people to promise that they will obey these rules, laws and commands.</para>
  <para style="ili1">4. The blessings for keeping God’s laws and commands are stated. And the bad things that will happen for not keeping them are also stated.</para>
  <para style="ili1">5. Moses chooses Joshua to be the next leader of the Israelites.</para>
  <para style="ip">Deuteronomy ends with Moses and the Israelites. Moses climbs the mountain and sees the land promised to Israelites. There Moses dies. The Israelites stand ready to take the land God promised to them. And in that promise they see a new life before them.</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="DEU 1"/>
  <para style="s1">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> Commands Israel to Leave Mount Horeb</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 1:1"/>These are the words Moses spoke to all the Israelites. At that time, they were in the desert east of the Jordan River. It’s in the Arabah Valley across from Suph. The people were between Paran and Tophel, Laban, Hazeroth and Dizahab. <verse eid="DEU 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 1:2"/>It takes 11 days to go from Mount Horeb to Kadesh Barnea if you travel on the Mount Seir road.<verse eid="DEU 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 1:3"/>It was the 40th year since the Israelites had left Egypt. On the first day of the 11th month, Moses spoke to them. He told them everything the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded him to tell them. <verse eid="DEU 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 1:4"/>They had already won the battle over Sihon. Sihon was the king of the Amorites. He had ruled in Heshbon. Israel had also won the battle over Og at Edrei. Og was the king of Bashan. He had ruled in Ashtaroth.<verse eid="DEU 1:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 1:5"/>The people were east of the Jordan River in the territory of Moab. There Moses began to explain the law. Here is what he said.<verse eid="DEU 1:5"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 1:6"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God spoke to us at Mount Horeb. He said, “You have stayed long enough at this mountain. <verse eid="DEU 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 1:7"/>Take your tents down. Go into the hill country of the Amorites. Go to all the people who are their neighbors. Go to the people who live in the Arabah Valley. Travel to the mountains and the western hills. Go to the people in the Negev Desert and along the coast. Travel to the land of Canaan and to Lebanon. Go as far as the great Euphrates River. <verse eid="DEU 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 1:8"/>I have given you all this land. Go in and take it as your own. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> promised he would give the land to your fathers. He promised it to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. He also said he would give it to their children after them.”<verse eid="DEU 1:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Some Officials Are Chosen to Help Moses</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 1:9"/>At that time I spoke to you. I said, “You are too heavy a load for me to carry alone. <verse eid="DEU 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 1:10"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has caused there to be many of you. Today you are as many as the stars in the sky. <verse eid="DEU 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 1:11"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is the God of your people. May he cause there to be a thousand times more of you. May he bless you, just as he promised he would. <verse eid="DEU 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 1:12"/>But I can’t handle your problems and troubles all by myself. I can’t settle your arguments. <verse eid="DEU 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 1:13"/>So choose some wise men from each of your tribes. They must understand how to give good advice. The people must have respect for them. I will appoint those men to have authority over you.”<verse eid="DEU 1:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 1:14"/>You answered me, “Your suggestion is good.”<verse eid="DEU 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 1:15"/>So I chose the leading men of your tribes who were wise and respected. I appointed them to have authority over you. I made them commanders of thousands, hundreds, fifties and tens. I appointed them to be officials over the tribes. <verse eid="DEU 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 1:16"/>Here is what I commanded your judges at that time. I said, “Listen to your people’s cases when they argue with one another. Judge them fairly. It doesn’t matter whether the case is between two Israelites or between an Israelite and an outsider living among you. <verse eid="DEU 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 1:17"/>When you judge them, treat everyone the same. Listen to those who are important and those who are not. Don’t be afraid of anyone. God is the highest judge. Bring me any case that is too hard for you. I’ll listen to it.” <verse eid="DEU 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 1:18"/>At that time I told you everything you should do.<verse eid="DEU 1:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Twelve Men Check Out the Land of Canaan</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 1:19"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God commanded us to start out from Mount Horeb. So we did. We went toward the hill country of the Amorites. We traveled all through the huge and terrible desert you saw. Finally, we reached Kadesh Barnea. <verse eid="DEU 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 1:20"/>Then I said to you, “You have reached the hill country of the Amorites. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God is giving it to us. <verse eid="DEU 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 1:21"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has given you the land. Go up and take it. Do what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> says. He’s the God of your people. Don’t be afraid. Don’t lose hope.”<verse eid="DEU 1:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 1:22"/>Then all of you came to me. You said, “Let’s send some men ahead of us. They can check out the land for us and bring back a report. They can suggest to us which way to go. They can tell us about the towns we’ll come to.”<verse eid="DEU 1:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 1:23"/>That seemed like a good idea to me. So I chose 12 of you. I picked one man from each tribe. <verse eid="DEU 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 1:24"/>They left and went up into the hill country. There they came to the Valley of Eshkol. They checked it out. <verse eid="DEU 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 1:25"/>They got some of the fruit of that land. Then they brought it down to us and gave us their report. They said, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God is giving us a good land.”<verse eid="DEU 1:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Israel Refuses to Obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 1:26"/>But you wouldn’t go up. You refused to obey the command of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="DEU 1:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 1:27"/>You spoke against him in your tents. You said, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> hates us. That’s why he brought us out of Egypt to hand us over to the Amorites. He wanted to destroy us. <verse eid="DEU 1:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 1:28"/>Where can we go? The men who checked out the land have made us afraid. They say, ‘The people are stronger and taller than we are. The cities are large. They have walls that reach up to the sky. We even saw the Anakites there.’ ”<verse eid="DEU 1:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 1:29"/>Then I said to you, “Don’t be terrified. Don’t be afraid of them. <verse eid="DEU 1:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 1:30"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will go ahead of you. He will fight for you. With your own eyes you saw how he fought for you in Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 1:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 1:31"/>You also saw how the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God brought you through the desert. He carried you everywhere you went, just as a father carries his son. And now you have arrived here.”<verse eid="DEU 1:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 1:32"/>In spite of that, you didn’t trust in the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="DEU 1:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 1:33"/>He went ahead of you on your journey. He was in the fire at night and in the cloud during the day. He found places for you to camp. He showed you the way you should go.<verse eid="DEU 1:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 1:34"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> heard what you said. So he became angry. He made a promise. He said, <verse eid="DEU 1:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 1:35"/>“I promised to give this good land to your people of long ago. But no one alive today will see it. <verse eid="DEU 1:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 1:36"/>Only Caleb will see the land. He is the son of Jephunneh. I will give him and his children after him the land he walked on. He followed me with his whole heart.”<verse eid="DEU 1:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 1:37"/>Because of you, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> became angry with me also. He said, “You will not enter the land either. <verse eid="DEU 1:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="DEU 1:38"/>But Joshua, the son of Nun, is your helper. Joshua will enter the land. Help him to be brave. Give him hope. He will lead Israel to take the land as their own. <verse eid="DEU 1:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="DEU 1:39"/>You said your little ones would be taken prisoner. But they will enter the land. They do not yet know right from wrong. But I will give them the land. They will take it as their own. <verse eid="DEU 1:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="DEU 1:40"/>As for you, turn around. Start out toward the desert. Go along the road that leads to the Red Sea.”<verse eid="DEU 1:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="DEU 1:41"/>Then you replied, “We have sinned against the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. We will go up and fight. We’ll do just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God has commanded us.” So all of you got your swords and put them on. You thought it would be easy to go up into the hill country.<verse eid="DEU 1:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="DEU 1:42"/>But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to me. He said, “Tell them, ‘Do not go up and fight. I will not be with you. Your enemies will win the battle over you.’ ”<verse eid="DEU 1:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="DEU 1:43"/>So I told you what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said. But you wouldn’t listen. You refused to obey his command. You were so filled with pride that you marched up into the hill country. <verse eid="DEU 1:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="DEU 1:44"/>The Amorites who lived in those hills came out and attacked you. Like large numbers of bees they chased you. They beat you down from Seir all the way to Hormah. <verse eid="DEU 1:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="DEU 1:45"/>You came back and wept in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. But he didn’t pay any attention to your weeping. He wouldn’t listen to you. <verse eid="DEU 1:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="DEU 1:46"/>So you stayed in Kadesh for many years. You spent a long time in that area.<verse eid="DEU 1:46"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="DEU 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Israel Wanders in the Desert</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 2:1"/>We turned back and started out toward the desert. We went along the road that leads to the Red Sea. That’s how the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had directed me. For a long time we made our way around the hill country of Seir.<verse eid="DEU 2:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 2:2"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to me. He said, <verse eid="DEU 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 2:3"/>“You have made your way around this hill country long enough. So now turn north. <verse eid="DEU 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 2:4"/>Here are the orders I want you to give the people. Tell them, ‘You are about to pass through the territory of your relatives. They are from the family line of Esau. They live in Seir. They will be afraid of you. But be very careful. <verse eid="DEU 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 2:5"/>Do not make them angry. If you do, they will go to war against you. I will not give you any of their land. You will not have even enough to put your foot on. I have given Esau’s people the hill country of Seir as their own. <verse eid="DEU 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 2:6"/>Pay them with silver for the food you eat and the water you drink.’ ”<verse eid="DEU 2:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 2:7"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has blessed you in everything your hands have done. He watched over you when you traveled through that huge desert. For these 40 years the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has been with you. So you have had everything you need.<verse eid="DEU 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 2:8"/>We went on past our relatives. They are from the family line of Esau. They live in Seir. We turned away from the Arabah Valley road. It comes up from Elath and Ezion Geber. We traveled along the desert road of Moab.<verse eid="DEU 2:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 2:9"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to me, “Do not attack the Moabites. Do not even make them angry. If you do, they will go to war against you. I will not give you any part of their land. I have given Moab to the people in the family line of Lot. I have given it to them as their own.”<verse eid="DEU 2:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 2:10"/>The Emites used to live there. They were strong people. There were large numbers of them. They were as tall as the Anakites. <verse eid="DEU 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 2:11"/>Like the Anakites, they too were thought of as Rephaites. But the Moabites called them Emites. <verse eid="DEU 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 2:12"/>The Horites used to live in Seir. But the people of Esau drove them out. They destroyed the Horites to make room for themselves. Then they settled in their territory. They did just as Israel has done in the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave them as their own.<verse eid="DEU 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 2:13"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said, “Now get up. Go across the Zered Valley.” So we went across it.<verse eid="DEU 2:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 2:14"/>Between the time we left Kadesh Barnea and the time we went across the Zered Valley, 38 years had passed. By then, all the fighting men who had been in our camp from the beginning had died. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> had warned them that it would happen. <verse eid="DEU 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 2:15"/>He used his power against them until he had gotten rid of all of them. Not one was left in the camp.<verse eid="DEU 2:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 2:16"/>Finally, the last of the fighting men among the people died. <verse eid="DEU 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 2:17"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to me, <verse eid="DEU 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 2:18"/>“Today you must pass near the border of Moab. Moab is also called Ar. <verse eid="DEU 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 2:19"/>When you come to the Ammonites, do not attack them. Do not make them angry. If you do, they will go to war against you. I will not give you any of their land as your own. I have given it to the people in the family line of Lot. I have given it to them as their own.”<verse eid="DEU 2:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 2:20"/>That land was also thought of as a land of the Rephaites. They used to live there. But the Ammonites called them Zamzummites. <verse eid="DEU 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 2:21"/>The Rephaites were strong people. There were large numbers of them. They were as tall as the Anakites. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> destroyed the Rephaites to make room for the Ammonites. So the Ammonites drove them out. Then they settled in the territory of the Rephaites. <verse eid="DEU 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 2:22"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> had done the same thing for the people of Esau. They lived in Seir. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> destroyed the Horites to make room for Esau’s people. They drove the Horites out. So the people of Esau have lived in Seir in the territory of the Horites to this very day. <verse eid="DEU 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 2:23"/>The Avvites lived in villages as far away as Gaza. But people came from Crete and destroyed the Avvites. Then the people of Crete made their home in the territory of the Avvites.<verse eid="DEU 2:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Israel Wins the Battle Over Sihon</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 2:24"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said, “Start out and go across the valley of the Arnon River. I have handed Sihon over to you. He is the Amorite king of Heshbon. I have also given you his country. Begin to take it as your own. Go to war against him. <verse eid="DEU 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 2:25"/>This very day I will bring fear and terror on all the nations because of you. They will hear about you. They will tremble with fear. Pain and suffering will grip them because of you.”<verse eid="DEU 2:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 2:26"/>I sent messengers from the Desert of Kedemoth. I told them to go to Sihon, the king of Heshbon. They offered him peace. They said, <verse eid="DEU 2:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 2:27"/>“Let us pass through your country. We’ll stay on the main road. We won’t turn off it to one side or the other. <verse eid="DEU 2:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 2:28"/>We’ll pay you the right amount of silver for food to eat and water to drink. Just let us walk through your country. <verse eid="DEU 2:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 2:29"/>The people of Esau, who live in Seir, allowed us to do that. The people of Moab, who live in Ar, also allowed us to do it. So let us walk through until we go across the Jordan River. Then we’ll be able to go into the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God is giving us.” <verse eid="DEU 2:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 2:30"/>But Sihon, the king of Heshbon, refused to let us walk through. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God had made him stubborn in his heart and spirit. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> wanted to hand him over to you. And that’s exactly what he has done.<verse eid="DEU 2:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 2:31"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to me, “I have begun to hand Sihon and his country over to you. So begin the battle to take his land as your own.”<verse eid="DEU 2:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 2:32"/>Sihon and his whole army came out to fight against us at Jahaz. <verse eid="DEU 2:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 2:33"/>But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God handed him over to us. We struck him down together with his sons and his whole army. <verse eid="DEU 2:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 2:34"/>At that time we took all his towns. We completely destroyed them. We killed all the men, women and children. We didn’t leave any of them alive. <verse eid="DEU 2:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 2:35"/>But we took for ourselves the livestock and everything else from the towns we had captured. <verse eid="DEU 2:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 2:36"/>Not a single town was too strong for us. That includes all the towns from Aroer on the rim of the Arnon River valley all the way to Gilead. It also includes the town in the valley. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God gave us all of them. <verse eid="DEU 2:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 2:37"/>And you obeyed the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s command. You didn’t go near any part of the land of the Ammonites. That includes the land along the Jabbok River. It also includes the land around the towns in the hills.<verse eid="DEU 2:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="DEU 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Israel Wins the Battle Over Og</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 3:1"/>Next, we turned and went up along the road toward Bashan. Og marched out with his whole army. They fought against us at Edrei. Og was the king of Bashan. <verse eid="DEU 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 3:2"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to me, “Do not be afraid of Og. I have handed him over to you. I have also handed over his whole army and his land. Do to him what you did to Sihon. Sihon was the Amorite king who ruled in Heshbon.”<verse eid="DEU 3:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 3:3"/>So the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God also handed Og, the king of Bashan, and his whole army over to us. We struck them down. We didn’t leave any of them alive. <verse eid="DEU 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 3:4"/>At that time we took all his cities. There were 60 of them. We took the whole area of Argob. That was Og’s kingdom in Bashan. <verse eid="DEU 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 3:5"/>All those cities had high walls around them. The city gates were made secure with heavy metal bars. There were also large numbers of villages that didn’t have walls. <verse eid="DEU 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 3:6"/>We completely destroyed them. We did to them just as we had done to Sihon, the king of Heshbon. We destroyed all their cities. We destroyed the men, women and children. <verse eid="DEU 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 3:7"/>But we kept for ourselves the livestock and everything else we took from their cities.<verse eid="DEU 3:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 3:8"/>So at that time we took the territory east of the Jordan River. We captured it from those two Amorite kings. The territory goes all the way from the Arnon River valley to Mount Hermon. <verse eid="DEU 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 3:9"/>Hermon is called Sirion by the people of Sidon. The Amorites call it Senir. <verse eid="DEU 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 3:10"/>We captured all the towns on the high plains. We took the whole land of Gilead. And we captured the whole land of Bashan as far away as Salekah and Edrei. Those were towns that belonged to Og’s kingdom in Bashan. <verse eid="DEU 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 3:11"/>Og, the king of Bashan, was the only Rephaite left. His bed was decorated with iron. It was more than 13 feet long and six feet wide. It is still in the Ammonite city of Rabbah.<verse eid="DEU 3:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Moses Divides Up the Land</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 3:12"/>I divided up the land we took over at that time. I gave the tribes of Reuben and Gad the territory north of Aroer by the Arnon River valley. It includes half of the hill country of Gilead together with its towns. <verse eid="DEU 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 3:13"/>I gave the rest of Gilead to half of the tribe of Manasseh. I also gave them the whole land of Bashan, the kingdom of Og. The whole area of Argob in Bashan used to be known as a land of the Rephaites. <verse eid="DEU 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 3:14"/>Jair took the whole area of Argob. He was from the family line of Manasseh. Argob goes all the way to the border of the people of Geshur and Maakah. It was named after Jair. So Bashan is called Havvoth Jair to this very day. <verse eid="DEU 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 3:15"/>I gave Gilead to Makir. <verse eid="DEU 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 3:16"/>But I gave to the tribes of Reuben and Gad the territory that reaches from Gilead down to the Arnon River valley. It goes all the way to the Jabbok River. The Jabbok is the northern border of Ammon. The middle of the Arnon River valley is its southern border. <verse eid="DEU 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 3:17"/>The western border of Reuben and Gad is the Jordan River in the Arabah Valley. It reaches from the Sea of Galilee to the Dead Sea. It runs below the slopes of Pisgah.<verse eid="DEU 3:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 3:18"/>Here is the command I gave at that time to the tribes of Reuben and Gad and half of the tribe of Manasseh. I said, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has given you this land as your very own. But all your strong men must be prepared for battle. They must cross over ahead of the rest of the Israelites. <verse eid="DEU 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 3:19"/>But your wives and children can stay in the towns I’ve given you. You can keep your livestock there too. I know you have a lot of livestock. <verse eid="DEU 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 3:20"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has given you peace and rest. Then let your families and livestock stay in those towns until the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gives peace and rest to the other tribes. And let your families stay until the other tribes have taken over the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving them. That land is across the Jordan River. After that, each of you may go back to the land I’ve given you as your very own.”<verse eid="DEU 3:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> Will Not Allow Moses to Cross the Jordan River</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 3:21"/>At that time I gave Joshua a command. I said, “Your own eyes have seen everything the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has done to Sihon and Og. He will do the same thing to all the kingdoms in the land where you are going. <verse eid="DEU 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 3:22"/>Don’t be afraid of them. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God himself will fight for you.”<verse eid="DEU 3:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 3:23"/>At that time I made my appeal to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. I said, <verse eid="DEU 3:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 3:24"/>“<char style="nd">Lord</char> and King, you have begun to show me how great you are. You have shown me how strong your hand is. You do great works and mighty acts. There isn’t any god in heaven or on earth who can do what you do. <verse eid="DEU 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 3:25"/>Let me go across the Jordan River. Let me see the good land beyond it. I want to see that fine hill country and Lebanon.”<verse eid="DEU 3:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 3:26"/>But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> was angry with me because of what you did. He wouldn’t listen to me. “That is enough!” the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said. “Do not speak to me anymore about this matter. <verse eid="DEU 3:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 3:27"/>Go up to the highest slopes of Pisgah. Look west and north and south and east. Look at the land with your own eyes. But you are not going to go across this Jordan River. <verse eid="DEU 3:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 3:28"/>So appoint Joshua as the new leader. Help him to be brave. Give him hope and strength. He will take these people across the Jordan. You will see the land. But he will lead them into it to take it as their own.” <verse eid="DEU 3:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 3:29"/>So we stayed in the valley near Beth Peor.<verse eid="DEU 3:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="DEU 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 4:1"/>Now, Israel, listen to the rules and laws I’m going to teach you. Obey them and you will live. You will go in and take over the land. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> was the God of your people of long ago. He’s giving you the land. <verse eid="DEU 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 4:2"/>Don’t add to what I’m commanding you. Don’t subtract from it either. Instead, obey the commands of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God that I’m giving you.<verse eid="DEU 4:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 4:3"/>Your own eyes saw what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God did at Baal Peor. He destroyed every one of your people who worshiped the Baal that was worshiped at Peor. <verse eid="DEU 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 4:4"/>But all of you who remained true to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God are still alive today.<verse eid="DEU 4:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 4:5"/>I have taught you rules and laws, just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> my God commanded me. Obey them in the land you are entering to take as your very own. <verse eid="DEU 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 4:6"/>Be careful to keep them. That will show the nations how wise and understanding you are. They will hear about all these rules. They’ll say, “That great nation certainly has wise and understanding people.” <verse eid="DEU 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 4:7"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God is near us every time we pray to him. What other nation is great enough to have its gods that close to them? <verse eid="DEU 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 4:8"/>I’m giving you the laws of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> today. What other nation is great enough to have rules and laws as fair as these?<verse eid="DEU 4:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 4:9"/>Don’t be careless. Instead, be very careful. Don’t forget the things your eyes have seen. As long as you live, don’t let them slip from your mind. Teach them to your children and their children after them. <verse eid="DEU 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 4:10"/>Remember the day you stood at Mount Horeb. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God was there. He said to me, “Bring the people to me to hear my words. I want them to learn to have respect for me as long as they live in the land. I want them to teach my words to their children.” <verse eid="DEU 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 4:11"/>You came near and stood at the foot of the mountain. It blazed with fire that reached as high as the very heavens. There were black clouds and deep darkness. <verse eid="DEU 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 4:12"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to you out of the fire. You heard the sound of his words. But you didn’t see any shape or form. You only heard a voice. <verse eid="DEU 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 4:13"/>He announced his covenant to you. That covenant is the Ten Commandments. He commanded you to obey them. Then he wrote them down on two stone tablets. <verse eid="DEU 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 4:14"/>At that time the <char style="nd">Lord</char> directed me to teach you his rules and laws. You must obey them in the land you are crossing the Jordan River to take as your own.<verse eid="DEU 4:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Don’t Make or Worship Statues of Gods</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 4:15"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to you at Mount Horeb out of the fire. But you didn’t see any shape or form that day. So be very careful. <verse eid="DEU 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 4:16"/>Make sure you don’t commit a horrible sin. Don’t make for yourselves a statue of a god. Don’t make a god that looks like a man or woman or anything else. <verse eid="DEU 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 4:17"/>Don’t make one that looks like any animal on earth or any bird that flies in the sky. <verse eid="DEU 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 4:18"/>Don’t make a statue that looks like any creature that moves along the ground or any fish that swims in the water. <verse eid="DEU 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 4:19"/>When you look up at the heavens, you will see the sun and moon. And you will see huge numbers of stars. Don’t let anyone tempt you to bow down to the sun, moon or stars. Don’t worship things the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has provided for all the nations on earth. <verse eid="DEU 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 4:20"/>Egypt was like a furnace that melts iron down and makes it pure. But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> took you and brought you out of Egypt. He wanted you to be his very own people. And that’s exactly what you are.<verse eid="DEU 4:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 4:21"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> was angry with me because of what you did. He promised that he would never let me go across the Jordan River. He promised that I would never enter that good land. It’s the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you as your own. <verse eid="DEU 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 4:22"/>I’ll die here in this land. I won’t go across the Jordan. But you are about to cross over it. You will take that good land as your own. <verse eid="DEU 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 4:23"/>Be careful. Don’t forget the covenant the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God made with you. Don’t make for yourselves a statue of any god at all. He has told you not to. So don’t do it. <verse eid="DEU 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 4:24"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is like a fire that burns everything up. He wants you to worship only him.<verse eid="DEU 4:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 4:25"/>So don’t make a statue of a god. Don’t commit that horrible sin. Don’t do it even after you have had children and grandchildren. Don’t do it even after you have lived in the land a long time. If you do, that will be an evil thing in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. You will make him angry. <verse eid="DEU 4:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 4:26"/>Today I’m calling out to the heavens and the earth to be witnesses against you. Suppose you do these things. Then you will quickly die in the land you are going across the Jordan River to take over. You won’t live there very long. You will certainly be destroyed. <verse eid="DEU 4:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 4:27"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will drive you out of your land. He will scatter you among the nations. Only a few of you will remain alive there. <verse eid="DEU 4:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 4:28"/>There you will worship gods that men have made out of wood and stone. Those gods can’t see, hear, eat or smell. <verse eid="DEU 4:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 4:29"/>Perhaps while you are there, you will seek the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. You will find him if you seek him with all your heart and with all your soul. <verse eid="DEU 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 4:30"/>All the things I’ve told you about might happen to you. And you will be in trouble. But later you will return to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. You will obey him. <verse eid="DEU 4:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 4:31"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is tender and loving. He won’t leave you or destroy you. He won’t forget the covenant he made with your people of long ago. He gave his word when he made it.<verse eid="DEU 4:31"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> Is God</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 4:32"/>Ask now about the days of long ago. Find out what happened long before your time. Ask about what has happened since the time God created human beings on the earth. Ask from one end of the world to the other. Has anything as great as this ever happened? Has anything like it ever been heard of? <verse eid="DEU 4:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 4:33"/>You heard the voice of God speaking out of fire. And you lived! Has that happened to any other people? <verse eid="DEU 4:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 4:34"/>Has any god ever tried to take one nation out of another to be his own? Has any god done it by testing his people? Has any god done it with signs and amazing deeds or with war? Has any god reached out his mighty hand and powerful arm? Or has any god shown his people his great and wonderful acts? The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God did all those things for you in Egypt. With your very own eyes you saw him do them.<verse eid="DEU 4:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 4:35"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> showed you those things so that you might know he is God. There is no other God except him. <verse eid="DEU 4:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 4:36"/>From heaven he made you hear his voice. He wanted to teach you. On earth he showed you his great fire. You heard his words coming out of the fire. <verse eid="DEU 4:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 4:37"/>He loved your people of long ago. He chose their children after them. So he brought you out of Egypt. He used his great strength to do it. <verse eid="DEU 4:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="DEU 4:38"/>He drove out nations to make room for you. They were greater and stronger than you are. He will bring you into their land. He wants to give it to you as your very own. The whole land is as good as yours right now.<verse eid="DEU 4:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="DEU 4:39"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is God in heaven above and on the earth below. Today you must agree with that and take it to heart. There is no other God. <verse eid="DEU 4:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="DEU 4:40"/>I’m giving you his rules and commands today. Obey them. Then things will go well with you and your children after you. You will live a long time in the land. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you the land for all time to come.<verse eid="DEU 4:40"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Cities to Run to for Safety</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="DEU 4:41"/>Then Moses set apart three cities east of the Jordan River. <verse eid="DEU 4:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="DEU 4:42"/>Suppose someone killed a person they didn’t hate and without meaning to do it. That person could run to one of those cities and stay alive. <verse eid="DEU 4:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="DEU 4:43"/>Here are the names of the cities. Bezer was for the people of Reuben. It was in the high plains in the desert. Ramoth was for the people of Gad. It was in Gilead. Golan was for the people of Manasseh. It was in Bashan.<verse eid="DEU 4:43"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Moses Gives the Law to Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="DEU 4:44"/>Here is the law Moses gave the Israelites. <verse eid="DEU 4:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="DEU 4:45"/>Here are its terms, rules and laws. Moses gave them to the people when they came out of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 4:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="DEU 4:46"/>They were now east of the Jordan River in the valley near Beth Peor. They were in the land of Sihon, the king of the Amorites. He ruled in Heshbon. But Moses and the Israelites won the battle over him after we came out of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 4:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="DEU 4:47"/>They captured his land and made it their own. They also took the land of Og, the king of Bashan. Sihon and Og were the two Amorite kings east of the Jordan River. <verse eid="DEU 4:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="DEU 4:48"/>Their land reached from Aroer on the rim of the Arnon River valley to Mount Hermon. <verse eid="DEU 4:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="DEU 4:49"/>It included the whole Arabah Valley east of the Jordan. It included land all the way to the Dead Sea below the slopes of Pisgah.<verse eid="DEU 4:49"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="DEU 5"/>
  <para style="s1">The Ten Commandments</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 5:1"/>Moses sent for all the Israelites. Here is what he said to them.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="DEU 5:1">Israel, listen to me. Here are the rules and laws I’m announcing to you today. Learn them well. Be sure to obey them. <verse eid="DEU 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 5:2"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God made a covenant with us at Mount Horeb. <verse eid="DEU 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 5:3"/>He didn’t make it only with our people of long ago. He also made it with us. In fact, he made it with all of us who are alive here today. <verse eid="DEU 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 5:4"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to you face to face. His voice came out of the fire on the mountain. <verse eid="DEU 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 5:5"/>At that time I stood between the <char style="nd">Lord</char> and you. I announced to you the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s message. I did it because you were afraid of the fire. You didn’t go up the mountain.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="DEU 5:5">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said,<verse eid="DEU 5:5"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 5:6"/>“I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. I brought you out of Egypt. That is the land where you were slaves.<verse eid="DEU 5:6"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 5:7"/>“Do not put any other gods in place of me.<verse eid="DEU 5:7"/></para>
  <para style="li">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 5:8"/>“Do not make statues of gods that look like anything in the sky or on the earth or in the waters. <verse eid="DEU 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 5:9"/>Do not bow down to them or worship them. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. I want you to worship only me. I cause the sins of the parents to affect their children. I will cause the sins of those who hate me to affect even their grandchildren and great-grandchildren. <verse eid="DEU 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 5:10"/>But for all time to come I show love to all those who love me and keep my commandments.<verse eid="DEU 5:10"/></para>
  <para style="li">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 5:11"/>“Do not misuse the name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will find guilty anyone who misuses his name.<verse eid="DEU 5:11"/></para>
  <para style="li">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 5:12"/>“Keep the Sabbath day holy. Do this just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has commanded you. <verse eid="DEU 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 5:13"/>Do all your work in six days. <verse eid="DEU 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 5:14"/>But the seventh day is a sabbath to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Do not do any work on that day. The same command applies to your sons and daughters, your male and female servants, your oxen, your donkeys and your other animals. It also applies to any outsiders who live in your towns. I want your male and female servants to rest, just as you do. <verse eid="DEU 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 5:15"/>Remember that you were slaves in Egypt. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God reached out his mighty hand and powerful arm and brought you out of there. So the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has commanded you to keep the Sabbath day holy.<verse eid="DEU 5:15"/></para>
  <para style="li">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 5:16"/>“Honor your father and mother, just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has commanded you. Then you will live a long time in the land he is giving you. And things will go well with you there.<verse eid="DEU 5:16"/></para>
  <para style="li">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 5:17"/>“Do not murder.<verse eid="DEU 5:17"/></para>
  <para style="li">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 5:18"/>“Do not commit adultery.<verse eid="DEU 5:18"/></para>
  <para style="li">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 5:19"/>“Do not steal.<verse eid="DEU 5:19"/></para>
  <para style="li">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 5:20"/>“Do not be a false witness against your neighbor.<verse eid="DEU 5:20"/></para>
  <para style="li">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 5:21"/>“Do not want to have your neighbor’s wife. Do not desire anything your neighbor owns. Do not desire to have your neighbor’s house or land, male or female servant, ox or donkey.”<verse eid="DEU 5:21"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 5:22"/>These are the commandments the <char style="nd">Lord</char> announced in a loud voice to your whole community. He gave them to you there on the mountain. He spoke out of the fire, cloud and deep darkness. He didn’t add anything else. Then he wrote the commandments on two stone tablets. And he gave them to me.<verse eid="DEU 5:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 5:23"/>The mountain was blazing with fire. You heard the voice coming out of the darkness. So your elders and all the leaders of your tribes came to me. <verse eid="DEU 5:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 5:24"/>You said, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God has shown us his glory and majesty. We have heard his voice coming out of the fire. Today we have seen that a person can still stay alive even if God speaks with them. <verse eid="DEU 5:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 5:25"/>But why should we die? This great fire will burn us up. We’ll die if we hear the voice of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God again. <verse eid="DEU 5:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 5:26"/>We have heard the voice of the living God. We’ve heard him speaking out of the fire. Has any other human being ever heard him speak like that and stayed alive? <verse eid="DEU 5:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 5:27"/>Go near and listen to everything the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God says. Then tell us what he tells you. We will listen and obey.”<verse eid="DEU 5:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 5:28"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> heard you when you spoke to me. He said to me, “I have heard what these people said to you. Everything they said was good. <verse eid="DEU 5:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 5:29"/>But I wish they would always have respect for me in their hearts. I wish they would always obey all my commands. Then things would go well with them and their children forever.<verse eid="DEU 5:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 5:30"/>“Go and tell them to return to their tents. <verse eid="DEU 5:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 5:31"/>But you stay here with me. Then I will give you all my commands, rules and laws. You must teach the people to obey them in the land I am giving them as their very own.”<verse eid="DEU 5:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 5:32"/>So be careful to do what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has commanded you. Don’t turn away from his commands to the right or the left. <verse eid="DEU 5:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 5:33"/>Live exactly as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has commanded you to live. Then you will enjoy life in the land you will soon own. Things will go well with you there. You will live there for a long time.<verse eid="DEU 5:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="DEU 6"/>
  <para style="s1">Love the <char style="nd">Lord</char> Your God</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 6:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has directed me to teach you his commands, rules and laws. Obey them in the land you will take over when you go across the Jordan River. <verse eid="DEU 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 6:2"/>Then you, your children and their children after them will honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God as long as you live. Obey all his rules and commands I’m giving you. If you do, you will enjoy long life. <verse eid="DEU 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 6:3"/>Israel, listen to me. Make sure you obey me. Then things will go well with you. The number of your people will increase greatly in a land that has plenty of milk and honey. That’s what the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, the God of your parents, promised you.<verse eid="DEU 6:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 6:4"/>Israel, listen to me. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is our God. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is the one and only God. <verse eid="DEU 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 6:5"/>Love the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God with all your heart and with all your soul. Love him with all your strength. <verse eid="DEU 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 6:6"/>The commandments I give you today must be in your hearts. <verse eid="DEU 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 6:7"/>Make sure your children learn them. Talk about them when you are at home. Talk about them when you walk along the road. Speak about them when you go to bed. And speak about them when you get up. <verse eid="DEU 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 6:8"/>Write them down and tie them on your hands as a reminder. Also tie them on your foreheads. <verse eid="DEU 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 6:9"/>Write them on the doorframes of your houses. Also write them on your gates.<verse eid="DEU 6:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 6:10"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will bring you into the land of Canaan. He gave his word. He promised he would give the land to your fathers, to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. The land has large, wealthy cities you didn’t build. <verse eid="DEU 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 6:11"/>It has houses filled with all kinds of good things you didn’t provide. The land has wells you didn’t dig. And it has vineyards and groves of olive trees you didn’t plant. You will have plenty to eat. <verse eid="DEU 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 6:12"/>But be careful that you don’t forget the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Remember that he brought you out of Egypt. That’s the land where you were slaves.<verse eid="DEU 6:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 6:13"/>Worship the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. He is the only one you should serve. When you make promises, do so in his name. <verse eid="DEU 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 6:14"/>Don’t serve the gods of the nations around you. <verse eid="DEU 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 6:15"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is among you. He wants you to worship only him. If you worship other gods, God will be very angry with you. And he will destroy you from the face of the land. <verse eid="DEU 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 6:16"/>Don’t test the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God as you did at Massah. <verse eid="DEU 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 6:17"/>Be sure to obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s commands. Obey the terms and rules he has given you. <verse eid="DEU 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 6:18"/>Do what is right and good in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s eyes. Then things will go well with you. You will go in and take over the land. It’s the good land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> promised to your people of long ago. <verse eid="DEU 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 6:19"/>You will drive out all your enemies to make room for you. That’s what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said would happen.<verse eid="DEU 6:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 6:20"/>Later on, your child might ask you, “What is the meaning of the terms, rules and laws the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God has commanded you to obey?” <verse eid="DEU 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 6:21"/>If they do ask you, tell them, “We were Pharaoh’s slaves in Egypt. But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> used his mighty hand to bring us out of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 6:22"/>With our own eyes we saw the <char style="nd">Lord</char> send amazing signs. They were great and terrible. He sent them on Egypt and Pharaoh and everyone in his house. <verse eid="DEU 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 6:23"/>But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> brought us out of Egypt. He planned to bring us into the land of Canaan and give it to us. It’s the land he promised to our people of long ago. <verse eid="DEU 6:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 6:24"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God commanded us to obey all his rules. He commanded us to honor him. If we do, we will always succeed and be kept alive. That’s what is happening today. <verse eid="DEU 6:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 6:25"/>We must make sure we obey the whole law in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God. That’s what he has commanded us to do. If we obey his law, we’ll be doing what he requires of us.”<verse eid="DEU 6:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="DEU 7"/>
  <para style="s1">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> Will Drive Out Many Nations</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 7:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will bring you into the land. You are going to enter it and take it as your own. He’ll drive out many nations to make room for you. He’ll drive out the Hittites, Girgashites, Amorites, Canaanites, Perizzites, Hivites and Jebusites. Those seven nations are larger and stronger than you are. <verse eid="DEU 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 7:2"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will hand them over to you. You will win the battle over them. You must completely destroy them. Don’t make a peace treaty with them. Don’t show them any mercy. <verse eid="DEU 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 7:3"/>Don’t marry any of their people. Don’t give your daughters to their sons. And don’t take their daughters for your sons. <verse eid="DEU 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 7:4"/>If you do, those people will turn your children away from serving the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Then your children will serve other gods. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will be very angry with you. He will quickly destroy you. <verse eid="DEU 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 7:5"/>So here is what you must do to those people. Break down their altars. Smash their sacred stones. Cut down the poles they use to worship the female god named Asherah. Burn the statues of their gods in the fire. <verse eid="DEU 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 7:6"/>You are a holy nation. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has set you apart for himself. He has chosen you to be his special treasure. He chose you out of all the nations on the face of the earth to be his people.<verse eid="DEU 7:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 7:7"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> chose you because he loved you very much. He didn’t choose you because you had more people than other nations. In fact, you had the smallest number of all. <verse eid="DEU 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 7:8"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> chose you because he loved you. He wanted to keep the promise he had made to your people of long ago. That’s why he used his mighty hand to bring you out of Egypt. He bought you back from the land where you were slaves. He set you free from the power of Pharaoh, the king of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 7:9"/>So I want you to realize that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is God. He is the faithful God. He keeps his covenant for all time to come. He keeps it with those who love him and obey his commandments. He shows them his love. <verse eid="DEU 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 7:10"/>But he will pay back those who hate him. He’ll destroy them. He’ll quickly pay back those who hate him. <verse eid="DEU 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 7:11"/>So be careful to obey the commands, rules and laws I’m giving you today.<verse eid="DEU 7:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 7:12"/>Pay attention to the laws of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Be careful to obey them. Then he will keep his covenant of love with you. That’s what he promised to your people of long ago. <verse eid="DEU 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 7:13"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will love you and bless you. He’ll cause there to be many of you. He’ll give you many children. He’ll bless the crops of your land. He’ll give you plenty of grain, olive oil and fresh wine. He’ll bless your herds with many calves. He’ll give your flocks many lambs. He’ll do all these things for you in the land of Canaan. It’s the land he promised your people of long ago that he would give you. <verse eid="DEU 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 7:14"/>He will bless you more than any other nation. All your men and women will have children. All your livestock will have little ones. <verse eid="DEU 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 7:15"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will keep you from getting sick. He won’t send on you any of the horrible sicknesses you saw all around you in Egypt. But he’ll send them on everyone who hates you. <verse eid="DEU 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 7:16"/>You must destroy all the nations the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God hands over to you. Don’t feel sorry for them. Don’t serve their gods. If you do, they will be a trap for you.<verse eid="DEU 7:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 7:17"/>You might say to yourselves, “These nations are stronger than we are. How can we drive them out?” <verse eid="DEU 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 7:18"/>But don’t be afraid of them. Be sure to remember what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God did to Pharaoh and all the Egyptians. <verse eid="DEU 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 7:19"/>With your own eyes you saw what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> did to them. You saw the signs and amazing things he did. He reached out his mighty hand and powerful arm. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God used all those things to bring you out. You are now afraid of the nations that are in the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> promised you. But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will do to them the same things he did to Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 7:20"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will also send hornets among those nations. Some of the people left alive will hide from you. But even they will die. <verse eid="DEU 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 7:21"/>So don’t be terrified by them. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is with you. He is a great and wonderful God. <verse eid="DEU 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 7:22"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will drive out those nations to make room for you. But he will do it little by little. You won’t be allowed to get rid of them all at once. If you did, wild animals would multiply all around you. <verse eid="DEU 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 7:23"/>But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will hand those nations over to you. He will throw them into a panic until they are destroyed. <verse eid="DEU 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 7:24"/>He will hand their kings over to you. You will wipe out their names from the earth. No one will be able to stand up against you. You will destroy them. <verse eid="DEU 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 7:25"/>Burn the statues of their gods in the fire. Don’t wish for the silver and gold on those statues. Don’t take it for yourselves. If you do, it will be a trap for you. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God hates it. <verse eid="DEU 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 7:26"/>Don’t bring anything he hates into your house. If you do, you will be completely destroyed along with it. So hate it with all your heart. It is set apart to be destroyed.<verse eid="DEU 7:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="DEU 8"/>
  <para style="s1">Remember What the <char style="nd">Lord</char> Has Done</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 8:1"/>Make sure you obey every command I’m giving you today. Then you will live, and there will be many of you. You will enter the land and take it as your own. It’s the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> promised to your people of long ago. <verse eid="DEU 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 8:2"/>Remember how the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God led you all the way. He guided you in the desert for these 40 years. He wanted to take your pride away. He wanted to test you to know what was in your hearts. He wanted to see whether you would obey his commands. <verse eid="DEU 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 8:3"/>He took your pride away. He let you go hungry. Then he gave you manna to eat. You and your parents had never even known anything about manna before. He tested you to teach you that man doesn’t live only on bread. He also lives on every word that comes from the mouth of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="DEU 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 8:4"/>Your clothes didn’t wear out during these 40 years. Your feet didn’t swell. <verse eid="DEU 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 8:5"/>Here is what I want you to know in your hearts. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God guides you, just as parents guide their children.<verse eid="DEU 8:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 8:6"/>Obey the commands of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Live as he wants you to live. Have respect for him. <verse eid="DEU 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 8:7"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is bringing you into a good land. It has brooks, streams and deep springs of water. Those springs flow in its valleys and hills. <verse eid="DEU 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 8:8"/>It has wheat, barley, vines, fig trees, pomegranates, olive oil and honey. <verse eid="DEU 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 8:9"/>There is plenty of food in that land. You will have everything you need. Its rocks have iron in them. And you can dig copper out of its hills.<verse eid="DEU 8:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 8:10"/>When you have eaten and are satisfied, praise the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Praise him for the good land he has given you. <verse eid="DEU 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 8:11"/>Make sure you don’t forget the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Don’t fail to obey his commands, laws and rules. I’m giving them to you today. <verse eid="DEU 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 8:12"/>But suppose you don’t obey his commands. And suppose you have plenty to eat. You build fine houses and live in them. <verse eid="DEU 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 8:13"/>The number of your herds and flocks increases. You also get more and more silver and gold. And everything you have multiplies. <verse eid="DEU 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 8:14"/>Then your hearts will become proud. And you will forget the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> brought you out of Egypt. That’s the land where you were slaves. <verse eid="DEU 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 8:15"/>He led you through that huge and terrible desert. It was a dry land. It didn’t have any water. It had poisonous snakes and scorpions. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave you water out of solid rock. <verse eid="DEU 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 8:16"/>He gave you manna to eat in the desert. Your people had never even known anything about manna before. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> took your pride away. He tested you. He did it so that things would go well with you in the end. <verse eid="DEU 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 8:17"/>You might say to yourself, “My power and my strong hands have made me rich.” <verse eid="DEU 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 8:18"/>But remember the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. He gives you the ability to produce wealth. That shows he stands by the terms of the covenant he made with you. He promised it to your people of long ago. And he’s still faithful to his covenant today.<verse eid="DEU 8:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 8:19"/>Don’t forget the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Don’t serve other gods. Don’t worship them and bow down to them. I am a witness against you today that if you do, you will certainly be destroyed. <verse eid="DEU 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 8:20"/>You will be destroyed just like the nations the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is destroying to make room for you. That’s what will happen if you don’t obey him.<verse eid="DEU 8:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="DEU 9"/>
  <para style="s1">Why the <char style="nd">Lord</char> Gave Canaan to Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 9:1"/>Israel, listen to me. You are now about to go across the Jordan River. You will take over the land of the nations that live there. Those nations are greater and stronger than you are. Their large cities have walls that reach up to the sky. <verse eid="DEU 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 9:2"/>The people who live there are Anakites. They are strong and tall. You know all about them. You have heard people say, “Who can stand up against the Anakites?” <verse eid="DEU 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 9:3"/>But today you can be sure the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will go over there ahead of you. He is like a fire that will burn them up. He’ll destroy them. He’ll bring them under your control. You will drive them out. You will put an end to them quickly, just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has promised you.<verse eid="DEU 9:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 9:4"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will drive them out to make room for you. When he does, don’t say to yourself, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has done it because I am godly. That’s why he brought me here to take over this land.” That isn’t true. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is going to drive out those nations to make room for you because they are very evil. <verse eid="DEU 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 9:5"/>You are not going in to take over their land because you have done what is right or honest. It’s because those nations are so evil. That’s why the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will drive them out to make room for you. He will do what he said he would do. He made a promise to your fathers, to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. <verse eid="DEU 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 9:6"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you this good land to take as your own. But you must understand that it isn’t because you are a godly nation. In fact, you are stubborn.<verse eid="DEU 9:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Israel Worshiped the Golden Calf</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 9:7"/>Here is something you must remember. Never forget it. You made the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God angry in the desert. You refused to obey him from the day you left Egypt until you arrived here. <verse eid="DEU 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 9:8"/>At Mount Horeb you made the <char style="nd">Lord</char> angry enough to destroy you. <verse eid="DEU 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 9:9"/>I went up the mountain. I went there to receive the tablets of the covenant law. They were made out of stone. It was the covenant the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had made with you. I stayed on the mountain for 40 days and 40 nights. I didn’t eat any food or drink any water. <verse eid="DEU 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 9:10"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave me two stone tablets. The words on them were written by the finger of God. All the commandments the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave you were written on the tablets. He announced them to you out of the fire on the mountain. He wrote them on the day you gathered together there.<verse eid="DEU 9:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 9:11"/>The 40 days and 40 nights came to an end. Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave me the two stone tablets. They were the tablets of the covenant law. <verse eid="DEU 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 9:12"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> told me, “Go down from here right away. The people you brought out of Egypt have become very sinful. They have quickly turned away from what I commanded them. They have made a statue of a god for themselves.”<verse eid="DEU 9:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 9:13"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> also said to me, “I have seen these people. They are so stubborn! <verse eid="DEU 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 9:14"/>Do not try to stop me. I am going to destroy them. I will wipe them out from the earth. Then I will make you into a great nation. Your people will be stronger than they were. There will be more of you than there were of them.”<verse eid="DEU 9:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 9:15"/>So I turned and went down the mountain. It was blazing with fire. I was carrying the two tablets of the covenant law. <verse eid="DEU 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 9:16"/>When I looked, I saw that you had sinned against the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. You had made for yourselves a metal statue of a god. It looked like a calf. You had quickly turned away from the path the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded you to follow. <verse eid="DEU 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 9:17"/>So I threw the two tablets out of my hands. You watched them break into pieces.<verse eid="DEU 9:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 9:18"/>Then once again I fell down flat in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> with my face toward the ground. I lay there for 40 days and 40 nights. I didn’t eat any food or drink any water. You had committed a terrible sin. You had done an evil thing in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s sight. You had made him angry. <verse eid="DEU 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 9:19"/>I was afraid of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s great anger. He was so angry with you he wanted to destroy you. But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> listened to me again. <verse eid="DEU 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 9:20"/>And he was so angry with Aaron he wanted to destroy him too. But at that time I prayed for Aaron. <verse eid="DEU 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 9:21"/>I also got that sinful calf you had made. I burned it in the fire. I crushed it and ground it into fine powder. Then I threw the powder into a stream that was flowing down the mountain.<verse eid="DEU 9:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 9:22"/>You also made the <char style="nd">Lord</char> angry at Taberah, Massah and Kibroth Hattaavah.<verse eid="DEU 9:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 9:23"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> sent you out from Kadesh Barnea. He said, “Go up and take over the land I have given you.” But you refused to do what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God had commanded you to do. You didn’t trust him or obey him. <verse eid="DEU 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 9:24"/>You have been refusing to obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as long as I’ve known you.<verse eid="DEU 9:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 9:25"/>I lay down in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> with my face toward the ground for 40 days and 40 nights. I did it because the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had said he would destroy you. <verse eid="DEU 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 9:26"/>I prayed to him. “<char style="nd">Lord</char> and King,” I said, “don’t destroy your people. They belong to you. You set them free by your great power. You used your mighty hand to bring them out of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 9:27"/>Remember your servants Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. Forgive the Israelites for being so stubborn. Don’t judge them for the evil and sinful things they’ve done. <verse eid="DEU 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 9:28"/>If you do, the Egyptians will say, ‘The <char style="nd">Lord</char> wasn’t able to take them into the land he had promised to give them. He hated them. So he brought them out of Egypt to put them to death in the desert.’ <verse eid="DEU 9:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 9:29"/>But they are your people. They belong to you. You used your great power to bring them out of Egypt. You reached out your mighty arm and saved them.”<verse eid="DEU 9:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="DEU 10"/>
  <para style="s1">The New Stone Tablets</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 10:1"/>At that time the <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to me. He said, “Carve out two stone tablets, just like the first ones. Then come up to me on the mountain. Also make a wooden ark. <verse eid="DEU 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 10:2"/>I will write on the tablets the words that were on the first tablets, which you broke. Then you must put the tablets in the ark.”<verse eid="DEU 10:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 10:3"/>So I made the ark out of acacia wood. I carved out two stone tablets that were just like the first ones. I went up the mountain. I carried the two tablets in my hands. <verse eid="DEU 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 10:4"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> wrote on the tablets what he had written before. It was the Ten Commandments. He had announced them to you out of the fire on the mountain. It was on the day you had gathered together there. So the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave the tablets to me. <verse eid="DEU 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 10:5"/>Then I came back down the mountain. I put the tablets in the ark I had made, just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded me. And that’s where they are now.<verse eid="DEU 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 10:6"/>Remember how the Israelites traveled from the wells of Bene Jaakan to Moserah. That’s where Aaron died. And his body was buried there. His son Eleazar became the next priest after him. <verse eid="DEU 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 10:7"/>From Moserah the people traveled to Gudgodah. Then they went on to Jotbathah. That land has streams of water. <verse eid="DEU 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 10:8"/>At that time the <char style="nd">Lord</char> set the tribe of Levi apart. He appointed them to carry the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He wanted them to serve him. He told them to bless the people in his name. And they still do it today. <verse eid="DEU 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 10:9"/>That’s why the Levites don’t have any part of the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave the other tribes in Israel. They don’t have any share among them. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> himself is their share. That’s what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God told them.<verse eid="DEU 10:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 10:10"/>I had stayed on the mountain for 40 days and 40 nights, just as I did the first time. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> listened to me that time also. He didn’t want to destroy you. <verse eid="DEU 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 10:11"/>“Go,” the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to me. “Lead the people on their way. Then they can enter the land and take it over. I have given my word. I promised I would give the land to their fathers, to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob.”<verse eid="DEU 10:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 10:12"/>And now, Israel, what is the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God asking you to do? Honor him. Live exactly as he wants you to live. Love him. Serve him with all your heart and with all your soul. <verse eid="DEU 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 10:13"/>Obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s commands and rules. I’m giving them to you today for your own good.<verse eid="DEU 10:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 10:14"/>The heavens belong to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Even the highest heavens belong to him. He owns the earth and everything in it. <verse eid="DEU 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 10:15"/>But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> loved your people of long ago very much. You are their children. And he chose you above all the other nations. His love and his promise remain with you to this very day. <verse eid="DEU 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 10:16"/>So don’t be stubborn anymore. Obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="DEU 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 10:17"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is the greatest God of all. He is the greatest <char style="nd">Lord</char> of all. He is the great God. He is mighty and wonderful. He treats everyone the same. He doesn’t accept any money from those who want special favors. <verse eid="DEU 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 10:18"/>He stands up for widows and for children whose fathers have died. He loves outsiders living among you. He gives them food and clothes. <verse eid="DEU 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 10:19"/>So you also must love outsiders. Remember that you yourselves were outsiders in Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 10:20"/>Honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Serve him. Remain true to him. When you make promises, do so in his name. <verse eid="DEU 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 10:21"/>He is the one you should praise. He’s your God. With your own eyes you saw the great and amazing things he did for you. <verse eid="DEU 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 10:22"/>Long ago, your people went down into Egypt. The total number of them was 70. And now the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has made you as many as the stars in the sky.<verse eid="DEU 10:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="DEU 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Love and Obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 11:1"/>Love the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Do what he requires. Always obey his rules, laws and commands. <verse eid="DEU 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 11:2"/>Remember today that your children weren’t the ones the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God guided and corrected. They didn’t see his majesty. They weren’t in Egypt when he reached out his mighty hand and powerful arm. <verse eid="DEU 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 11:3"/>They didn’t see the signs and the other things he did in Egypt. They didn’t see what he did to Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, and to his whole country. <verse eid="DEU 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 11:4"/>They weren’t there when the <char style="nd">Lord</char> destroyed the army of Egypt and its horses and chariots. He swept the waters of the Red Sea over the Egyptians while they were chasing you. He wiped them out forever. <verse eid="DEU 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 11:5"/>Your children didn’t see what he did for you in the desert before you arrived here. <verse eid="DEU 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 11:6"/>They didn’t see what he did to Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab. Eliab was from the tribe of Reuben. The earth opened its mouth right in the middle of the Israelite camp. It swallowed up Dathan and Abiram. It swallowed them up together with their families, tents and every living thing that belonged to them. <verse eid="DEU 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 11:7"/>But with your own eyes you saw all the great things the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has done.<verse eid="DEU 11:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 11:8"/>So obey all the commands I’m giving you today. Then you will be strong enough to go in and take over the land. You will go across the Jordan River and take the land as your own. <verse eid="DEU 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 11:9"/>You will live there for a long time. It’s the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> promised to give to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob and their children after them. He gave his word when he made that promise. The land has plenty of milk and honey. <verse eid="DEU 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 11:10"/>You will enter it and take it over. It isn’t like the land of Egypt. That’s where you came from. You planted your seeds there. You had to water them, just as you have to water a vegetable garden. <verse eid="DEU 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 11:11"/>But you will soon go across the Jordan River. The land you are going to take over has mountains and valleys in it. It drinks rain from heaven. <verse eid="DEU 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 11:12"/>It’s a land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God takes care of. His eyes always look on it with favor. He watches over it from the beginning of the year to its end.<verse eid="DEU 11:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 11:13"/>So be faithful. Obey the commands the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you today. Love him. Serve him with all your heart and with all your soul. <verse eid="DEU 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 11:14"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will send rain on your land at the right time. He’ll send rain in the fall and in the spring. You will be able to gather your grain. You will also be able to make olive oil and fresh wine. <verse eid="DEU 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 11:15"/>He’ll provide grass in the fields for your cattle. You will have plenty to eat.<verse eid="DEU 11:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 11:16"/>But be careful. Don’t let anyone tempt you to do something wrong. Don’t turn away and worship other gods. Don’t bow down to them. <verse eid="DEU 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 11:17"/>If you do, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will be very angry with you. He’ll close up the sky. It won’t rain. The ground won’t produce its crops. Soon you will die. You won’t live to enjoy the good land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is giving you. <verse eid="DEU 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 11:18"/>So keep my words in your hearts and minds. Write them down and tie them on your hands as a reminder. Also tie them on your foreheads. <verse eid="DEU 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 11:19"/>Teach them to your children. Talk about them when you are at home. Talk about them when you walk along the road. Speak about them when you go to bed. And speak about them when you get up. <verse eid="DEU 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 11:20"/>Write them on the doorframes of your houses. Also write them on your gates. <verse eid="DEU 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 11:21"/>Then you and your children will live for a long time in the land. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> promised to give the land to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. Your family line will continue as long as the heavens remain above the earth.<verse eid="DEU 11:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 11:22"/>So be careful. Obey all the commands I’m giving you to follow. Love the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Live exactly as he wants you to live. Remain true to him. <verse eid="DEU 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 11:23"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will drive out all the nations to make room for you. They are larger and stronger than you are. But you will take their land. <verse eid="DEU 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 11:24"/>Every place you walk on will belong to you. Your territory will go all the way from the desert to Lebanon. It will go from the Euphrates River to the Mediterranean Sea. <verse eid="DEU 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 11:25"/>No one will be able to stand up against you. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will throw the whole land into a panic because of you. He’ll do it everywhere you go, just as he promised you.<verse eid="DEU 11:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 11:26"/>Listen to me. I’m setting a blessing and a curse in front of you today. <verse eid="DEU 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 11:27"/>I’m giving you the commands of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God today. You will be blessed if you obey them. <verse eid="DEU 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 11:28"/>But you will be cursed if you don’t obey them. So don’t turn away from the path I’m now commanding you to take. Don’t turn away by worshiping other gods you didn’t know before. <verse eid="DEU 11:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 11:29"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will bring you into the land to take it over. When he does, you must announce the blessings from Mount Gerizim. You must announce the curses from Mount Ebal. <verse eid="DEU 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 11:30"/>As you know, those mountains are across the Jordan River. They are on the west side of the Jordan toward the setting sun. They are near the large trees of Moreh. The mountains are in the territory of the Canaanites, who live in the Arabah Valley near Gilgal. <verse eid="DEU 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 11:31"/>You are about to go across the Jordan River. You will enter the land and take it over. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving it to you. You will take it over and live there. <verse eid="DEU 11:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 11:32"/>When you do, make sure you obey all the rules and laws I’m giving you today.<verse eid="DEU 11:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="DEU 12"/>
  <para style="s1">Worship Only Where the <char style="nd">Lord</char> Wants You To</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 12:1"/>Here are the rules and laws you must obey. Be careful to obey them in the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has given you to take as your own. He’s the God of your people who lived long ago. Obey these rules and laws as long as you live in the land. <verse eid="DEU 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 12:2"/>You will soon drive the nations out of it. Completely destroy all the places where they worship their gods. Destroy them on the high mountains, on the hills and under every green tree. <verse eid="DEU 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 12:3"/>Break down their altars. Smash their sacred stones. Burn up the poles they use to worship the female god named Asherah. Cut down the statues of their gods. Wipe out the names of their gods from those places.<verse eid="DEU 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 12:4"/>You must not worship the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God the way those nations worship their gods. <verse eid="DEU 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 12:5"/>Instead, go to the special place he will choose from among all your tribes. He will put his Name there. That’s where you must go. <verse eid="DEU 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 12:6"/>Take your burnt offerings and sacrifices to that place. Bring your special gifts and a tenth of everything you produce. Take with you what you have promised to give. Bring any other offerings you choose to give. And bring the male animals among your livestock that were born first to their mothers. <verse eid="DEU 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 12:7"/>You and your families will eat at the place the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will choose. He will be with you there. You will find joy in everything you have done. That’s because he has blessed you.<verse eid="DEU 12:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 12:8"/>You must not do as we’re doing here today. All of us are doing only what we think is right. <verse eid="DEU 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 12:9"/>That’s because you haven’t yet reached the place the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is giving you. Your God will give you peace and rest there. <verse eid="DEU 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 12:10"/>But first you will go across the Jordan River. You will settle in the land he’s giving you. It will belong to you as your share. He will give you peace and rest from all your enemies around you. You will live in safety. <verse eid="DEU 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 12:11"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will choose a special place. He will put his Name there. That’s where you must bring everything I command you to bring. That includes your burnt offerings and sacrifices. It includes your special gifts and a tenth of everything you produce. It also includes all the things of value that you promised to give to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="DEU 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 12:12"/>Be filled with joy there in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Your children should also be joyful. So should your male and female servants. And so should the Levites from your towns. The Levites won’t receive any part of the land as their share. <verse eid="DEU 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 12:13"/>Be careful not to sacrifice your burnt offerings anywhere you want to. <verse eid="DEU 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 12:14"/>Offer them only at the place the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will choose in one of your tribes. There you must obey everything I command you.<verse eid="DEU 12:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 12:15"/>But you can kill your animals in any of your towns. You can eat as much of the meat as you want to. You can eat it as if it were antelope or deer meat. That is part of the blessing the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you. Those who are “clean” and those who are not can eat it. <verse eid="DEU 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 12:16"/>But you must not eat meat that still has blood in it. Pour the blood out on the ground like water. <verse eid="DEU 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 12:17"/>Here are the things you must not eat in your own towns. You must not eat the tenth part of your grain, olive oil and fresh wine. It belongs to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. You must not eat the male animals among your livestock that were born first to their mothers. Don’t eat anything you have promised to give. Don’t eat any offerings you have chosen to give. And you must not eat any of your special gifts. <verse eid="DEU 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 12:18"/>Instead, you must eat all those things in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Do it at the place he will choose. You, your children, your male and female servants and the Levites from your towns can eat them. Be filled with joy in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Be joyful in everything you do. <verse eid="DEU 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 12:19"/>Don’t forget to take care of the Levites as long as you live in your land.<verse eid="DEU 12:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 12:20"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will increase your territory, just as he has promised you. When he does, you might get hungry for meat. You might say, “I’d really like some meat.” Then you can eat as much of it as you want to. <verse eid="DEU 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 12:21"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will choose a special place. He will put his Name there. But suppose that place is too far away from you. Then you can kill animals from the herds and flocks the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has given you. Do it just as I have commanded you. In your own towns you can eat as much of the meat as you want to. <verse eid="DEU 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 12:22"/>Eat it as you would eat antelope or deer meat. Those who are “clean” and those who are not can eat it. <verse eid="DEU 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 12:23"/>But be sure you don’t eat meat that still has blood in it. The blood is the animal’s life. So you must not eat the life along with the meat. <verse eid="DEU 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 12:24"/>You must not eat the blood. Pour it out on the ground like water. <verse eid="DEU 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 12:25"/>Don’t eat it. Then things will go well with you and your children after you. You will be doing what is right in the eyes of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="DEU 12:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 12:26"/>But go to the place the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will choose. Take with you the things you have set apart for him. Bring what you have promised to give him. <verse eid="DEU 12:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 12:27"/>Sacrifice your burnt offerings on the altar of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Offer the meat and the blood there. The blood of your sacrifices must be poured out beside his altar. But you can eat the meat. <verse eid="DEU 12:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 12:28"/>Make sure you obey all the rules I’m giving you. Then things will always go well with you and your children after you. That’s because you will be doing what is good and right in the eyes of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="DEU 12:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 12:29"/>You are about to attack the land and take it over as your own. When you do, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will destroy the nations who live there. He will do it to make room for you. You will drive them out. You will settle in their land. <verse eid="DEU 12:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 12:30"/>They will be destroyed to make room for you. But when they are destroyed, be careful. Don’t be trapped. Don’t ask questions about their gods. Don’t say, “How do these nations serve their gods? We’ll do it in the same way.” <verse eid="DEU 12:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 12:31"/>You must not worship the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God the way they worship their gods. When they worship, they do all kinds of evil things the <char style="nd">Lord</char> hates. They even burn up their children in the fire as sacrifices to their gods.<verse eid="DEU 12:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 12:32"/>Be sure you do everything I am commanding you to do. Do not add anything to my commands. And do not take anything away from them.<verse eid="DEU 12:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="DEU 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Do Not Worship Other Gods</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 13:1"/>Suppose a prophet appears among you. Or someone comes who uses dreams to tell what’s going to happen. He tells you that a sign or something amazing is going to take place. <verse eid="DEU 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 13:2"/>The sign or amazing thing he has spoken about might really take place. And then the prophet might say, “Let’s serve other gods. Let’s worship them.” But you haven’t known anything about those gods before. <verse eid="DEU 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 13:3"/>So you must not listen to what that prophet or dreamer has said. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is testing you. He wants to know whether you love him with all your heart and with all your soul. <verse eid="DEU 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 13:4"/>You must worship him. You must honor him. Keep his commands. Obey him. Serve him. Remain true to him. <verse eid="DEU 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 13:5"/>That prophet or dreamer must be put to death. He told you not to obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> brought you out of Egypt. He set you free from the land where you were slaves. He commanded you to live the way he wants you to. But that prophet or dreamer has tried to get you to be unfaithful to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Get rid of that evil person.<verse eid="DEU 13:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 13:6"/>Suppose your very own brother or sister secretly tempts you to do something wrong. Or your child or the wife you love tempts you. Or your closest friend does it. Suppose one of them says, “Let’s go and worship other gods.” But you and your people of long ago hadn’t known anything about those gods before. <verse eid="DEU 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 13:7"/>They are the gods of the nations around you. Those nations might be near or far away. In fact, they might reach from one end of the land to the other. <verse eid="DEU 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 13:8"/>Don’t give in to those who are tempting you. Don’t listen to them. Don’t feel sorry for them. Don’t spare them or save them. <verse eid="DEU 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 13:9"/>You must certainly put them to death. You must be the first to throw stones at them. Then all the people must do the same thing. <verse eid="DEU 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 13:10"/>Put them to death by throwing stones at them. They tried to turn you away from the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. He brought you out of Egypt. That’s the land where you were slaves. <verse eid="DEU 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 13:11"/>After you kill those who tempted you, all the Israelites will hear about it. And they will be too scared to do an evil thing like that again.<verse eid="DEU 13:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 13:12"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you towns to live in. But suppose you hear something bad about one of those towns. <verse eid="DEU 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 13:13"/>You hear that people who cause trouble have appeared among you. They’ve tried to get the people of their town to do something wrong. They’ve said, “Let’s go and worship other gods.” But you haven’t known anything about those gods before. <verse eid="DEU 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 13:14"/>So you must ask people some questions. You must check out the matter carefully. If it’s true, an evil thing has really happened among you. It’s something the <char style="nd">Lord</char> hates. <verse eid="DEU 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 13:15"/>Then you must certainly kill with your swords everyone who lives in that town. You must destroy it completely. You must wipe out its people and livestock. <verse eid="DEU 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 13:16"/>You must gather all the goods of that town into the middle of the main street. You must burn the town completely. You must burn up everything in it. It’s a whole burnt offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. The town must remain a pile of stones forever. It must never be built again. <verse eid="DEU 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 13:17"/>Don’t keep anything that should be destroyed. Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will turn away from his great anger. He will show you mercy. He’ll have deep concern for you. He’ll cause there to be many of you. That’s what he promised your people of long ago. He gave his word when he made the promise. <verse eid="DEU 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 13:18"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will do those things if you obey him. I’m giving you his commands today. And you must obey all of them. You must do what is right in his eyes.<verse eid="DEU 13:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="DEU 14"/>
  <para style="s1">“Clean” and “Unclean” Food</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 14:1"/>You are the children of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Don’t cut yourselves to honor the dead. Don’t shave the front of your heads to honor the dead. <verse eid="DEU 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 14:2"/>You are a holy nation. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has set you apart for himself. He has chosen you to be his special treasure. He chose you out of all the nations on the face of the earth.<verse eid="DEU 14:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 14:3"/>Don’t eat anything the <char style="nd">Lord</char> hates. <verse eid="DEU 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 14:4"/>Here are the only animals you can eat. You can eat oxen, sheep, goats, <verse eid="DEU 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 14:5"/>deer, gazelles, roe deer, wild goats, ibexes, antelope and mountain sheep. <verse eid="DEU 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 14:6"/>You can eat any animal that has a divided hoof. But it must also chew the cud. <verse eid="DEU 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 14:7"/>Some animals only chew the cud. Others only have a divided hoof. The camel, rabbit and rock badger chew the cud, but they don’t have a divided hoof. So you can’t eat them. They are not “clean” for you. <verse eid="DEU 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 14:8"/>Pigs aren’t “clean” for you either. They have a divided hoof, but they don’t chew the cud. So don’t eat their meat. And don’t touch their dead bodies.<verse eid="DEU 14:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 14:9"/>Many creatures live in water. You can eat all the ones that have fins and scales. <verse eid="DEU 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 14:10"/>But don’t eat anything that doesn’t have fins and scales. It isn’t “clean” for you.<verse eid="DEU 14:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 14:11"/>You can eat any “clean” bird. <verse eid="DEU 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 14:12"/>But there are many birds you can’t eat. They include eagles, vultures, and black vultures. <verse eid="DEU 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 14:13"/>They include red kites, black kites and all kinds of falcons. <verse eid="DEU 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 14:14"/>They include all kinds of ravens. <verse eid="DEU 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 14:15"/>They include horned owls, screech owls, gulls and all kinds of hawks. <verse eid="DEU 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 14:16"/>They include little owls, great owls, white owls <verse eid="DEU 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 14:17"/>and desert owls. They include ospreys and cormorants. <verse eid="DEU 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 14:18"/>They include storks and all kinds of herons. They also include hoopoes and bats.<verse eid="DEU 14:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 14:19"/>All flying insects are “unclean” for you. So don’t eat them. <verse eid="DEU 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 14:20"/>But you can eat any creature that has wings and is “clean.”<verse eid="DEU 14:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 14:21"/>If you find something that’s already dead, don’t eat it. You can give it to an outsider living in any of your towns. They may eat it. Or you can sell it to someone from another country. But you are a holy nation. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has set you apart for himself.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="DEU 14:21">Don’t cook a young goat in its mother’s milk.<verse eid="DEU 14:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Give a Tenth of What You Produce</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 14:22"/>Be sure to set apart a tenth of everything your fields produce each year. <verse eid="DEU 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 14:23"/>Here are the things you should eat in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. You should eat a tenth part of your grain, olive oil and fresh wine. You should also eat the male animals among your livestock that were born first to their mothers. Eat all these things at the special place the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will choose. He will put his Name there. You will learn to honor him always. <verse eid="DEU 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 14:24"/>But suppose the place the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will choose for his Name is too far away from you. And suppose your God has blessed you. And your tenth part is too heavy for you to carry. <verse eid="DEU 14:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 14:25"/>Then sell it for silver. Take the silver with you. Go to the place the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will choose. <verse eid="DEU 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 14:26"/>Use the silver to buy anything you like. It can be cattle or sheep. It can be any kind of wine. In fact, it can be anything else you wish. Then you and your family can eat there in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. You can be filled with joy. <verse eid="DEU 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 14:27"/>Don’t forget to take care of the Levites who will live in your towns. They won’t receive any part of the land as their share.<verse eid="DEU 14:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 14:28"/>At the end of every three years, bring a tenth of everything you produce that year. Store it in your towns. <verse eid="DEU 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 14:29"/>Then the Levites can come and eat. That’s because they won’t receive any part of the land as their share. The outsiders and widows who live in your towns can come. So can the children whose fathers have died. Everyone can have plenty to eat. Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will bless you in everything you do.<verse eid="DEU 14:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="DEU 15"/>
  <para style="s1">The Year for Forgiving People What They Owe</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 15:1"/>At the end of every seven years you must forgive people what they owe you. <verse eid="DEU 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 15:2"/>Have you made a loan to one of your own people? Then forgive what is owed to you. You can’t require that person to pay you back. The <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s time to forgive what is owed has been announced. <verse eid="DEU 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 15:3"/>You can require someone from another nation to pay you back. But you must forgive what any of your own people owes you. <verse eid="DEU 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 15:4"/>There shouldn’t be any poor people among you. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will greatly bless you in the land he is giving you. You will take it over as your own. <verse eid="DEU 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 15:5"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will bless you if you obey him completely. Be careful to follow all the commands I’m giving you today. <verse eid="DEU 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 15:6"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will bless you, just as he has promised. You will lend money to many nations. But you won’t have to borrow from any of them. You will rule over many nations. But none of them will rule over you.<verse eid="DEU 15:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 15:7"/>Suppose someone is poor among you. And suppose they live in one of the towns in the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you. Then don’t be mean to them. They are poor. So don’t hold back money from them. <verse eid="DEU 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 15:8"/>Instead, open your hands and lend them what they need. Do it freely. <verse eid="DEU 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 15:9"/>Be careful not to have an evil thought in your mind. Don’t say to yourself, “The seventh year will soon be here. It’s the year for forgiving people what they owe.” If you think like that, you might treat the needy people among you badly. You might not give them anything. Then they might make their appeal to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> against you. And he will find you guilty of sin. <verse eid="DEU 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 15:10"/>So give freely to needy people. Let your heart be tender toward them. Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will bless you in all your work. He will bless you in everything you do. <verse eid="DEU 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 15:11"/>There will always be poor people in the land. So I’m commanding you to give freely to those who are poor and needy in your land. Open your hands to them.<verse eid="DEU 15:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Set Your Hebrew Servants Free</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 15:12"/>Suppose any Hebrew men or women sell themselves to you. If they do, they will serve you for six years. Then in the seventh year you must let them go free. <verse eid="DEU 15:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 15:13"/>But when you set them free, don’t send them away without anything to show for all their work. <verse eid="DEU 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 15:14"/>Freely give them some animals from your flock. Also give them some of your grain and wine. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has blessed you richly. Give to them as he has given to you. <verse eid="DEU 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 15:15"/>Remember that you were slaves in Egypt. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God set you free. That’s why I’m giving you this command today.<verse eid="DEU 15:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 15:16"/>But suppose your servant says to you, “I don’t want to leave you.” He loves you and your family. And you are taking good care of him. <verse eid="DEU 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 15:17"/>Then take him to the door of your house. Poke a hole through his earlobe into the doorpost. And he will become your servant for life. Do the same with your female servant.<verse eid="DEU 15:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 15:18"/>Don’t think you are being cheated when you set your servants free. After all, they have served you for six years. The service of each of them has been worth twice as much as the service of a hired worker. And the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will bless you in everything you do.<verse eid="DEU 15:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Male Animals Born First to Their Mothers</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 15:19"/>Set apart every male animal among your livestock that was born first to its mother. Set it apart to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Don’t put a firstborn cow to work. Don’t clip the wool from a firstborn sheep. <verse eid="DEU 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 15:20"/>Each year you and your family must eat them. Do it in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God at the place he will choose. <verse eid="DEU 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 15:21"/>Suppose an animal has something wrong with it. It might not be able to see or walk. Or it might have a bad flaw. Then you must not sacrifice it to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="DEU 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 15:22"/>You must eat it in your own towns. Those who are “clean” and those who are “unclean” can eat it. Eat it as if it were antelope or deer meat. <verse eid="DEU 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 15:23"/>But you must not eat meat that still has blood in it. Pour the blood out on the ground like water.<verse eid="DEU 15:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="DEU 16"/>
  <para style="s1">The Passover Feast</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 16:1"/>Celebrate the Passover Feast of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God in the month of Aviv. In that month he brought you out of Egypt at night. <verse eid="DEU 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 16:2"/>Sacrifice an animal from your flock or herd. It is the Passover sacrifice to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Sacrifice it at the special place the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will choose. He will put his Name there. <verse eid="DEU 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 16:3"/>Don’t eat the animal along with bread made with yeast. Instead, for seven days eat bread made without yeast. It’s the bread that reminds you of how much you suffered. Remember that you left Egypt in a hurry. Remember it all the days of your life. Don’t forget the day you left Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 16:4"/>Don’t keep any yeast anywhere in your land for seven days. You will sacrifice the Passover animal on the evening of the first day. Do not let any of its meat be left over until the next morning.<verse eid="DEU 16:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 16:5"/>You must not sacrifice the Passover animal in just any town the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you. <verse eid="DEU 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 16:6"/>Sacrifice it only in the special place he will choose for his Name. Sacrifice it there in the evening when the sun goes down. Do it on the same day every year. Be sure it’s the day you left Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 16:7"/>Cook the animal and eat it. Do it at the place the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will choose. Then in the morning return to your tents. <verse eid="DEU 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 16:8"/>For six days eat bread made without yeast. On the seventh day come together for a service to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Don’t do any work on that day.<verse eid="DEU 16:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Feast of Weeks</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 16:9"/>Count off seven weeks from the time you begin to cut your grain in the field. <verse eid="DEU 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 16:10"/>Then celebrate the Feast of Weeks to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Give to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> anything you choose to give as an offering. Give, just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has given to you. <verse eid="DEU 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 16:11"/>Be filled with joy in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Be joyful at the special place he will choose for his Name. You, your children, and your male and female servants should be joyful. So should the Levites living in your towns. So should the outsiders and widows living among you. And so should the children whose fathers have died. <verse eid="DEU 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 16:12"/>Remember that you were slaves in Egypt. Be careful to obey the rules I’m giving you.<verse eid="DEU 16:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Feast of Booths</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 16:13"/>Gather the grain from your threshing floors. Take the fresh wine from your winepresses. Then celebrate the Feast of Booths for seven days. <verse eid="DEU 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 16:14"/>Be filled with joy at your feast. You, your children, and your male and female servants should be joyful. So should the Levites, the outsiders, and the widows living in your towns. And so should the children whose fathers have died. <verse eid="DEU 16:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 16:15"/>For seven days celebrate the feast to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Do it at the place he will choose. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will bless you when you gather all your crops. He’ll bless you in everything you do. And you will be full of joy. <verse eid="DEU 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 16:16"/>All your men must appear in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God at the holy tent. They must go to the place he will choose. They must do it three times a year. They must go there to celebrate the Feast of Unleavened Bread, the Feast of Weeks and the Feast of Booths. None of your men should appear in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> without bringing something with him. <verse eid="DEU 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 16:17"/>Each of you must bring a gift. Give to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God, just as he has given to you.<verse eid="DEU 16:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Appoint Judges and Officials</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 16:18"/>Appoint judges and officials for each of your tribes. Do it in every town the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you. They must judge the people fairly. <verse eid="DEU 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 16:19"/>Do what is right. Treat everyone the same. Don’t take money from people who want special favors. It makes those who are wise close their eyes to the truth. It twists the words of those who have done nothing wrong. <verse eid="DEU 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 16:20"/>Do only what is right. Then you will live. You will take over the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you.<verse eid="DEU 16:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Don’t Worship Other Gods</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 16:21"/>Don’t set up a wooden pole used to worship the female god named Asherah. Don’t set it up beside the altar you build to worship the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="DEU 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 16:22"/>Don’t set up a sacred stone to honor another god. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God hates Asherah poles and sacred stones.<verse eid="DEU 16:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="DEU 17"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 17:1"/>Suppose an ox or sheep has anything at all wrong with it. Then don’t sacrifice it to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. He hates it.<verse eid="DEU 17:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 17:2"/>Someone living among you might do what is evil in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. It might happen in one of the towns the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is giving you. That person is breaking the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s covenant. <verse eid="DEU 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 17:3"/>The person might have worshiped or bowed down to other gods. That person might have bowed down to the sun or moon or stars in the sky. I have commanded you not to do these things. <verse eid="DEU 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 17:4"/>When you hear that people have done something like that, check the matter out carefully. If it’s true, an evil thing has been done in Israel. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> hates that. <verse eid="DEU 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 17:5"/>So take the person who has done that evil thing to your city gate. Put that person to death by throwing stones at them. <verse eid="DEU 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 17:6"/>Two or three witnesses are required to put someone to death. No one can be put to death because of what only one witness says. Two or three witnesses are required. <verse eid="DEU 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 17:7"/>The witnesses must throw the first stones. Then the rest of the people must also throw stones. Get rid of that evil person.<verse eid="DEU 17:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Law Courts</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 17:8"/>People will bring their cases to your courts. But some cases will be too hard for you to judge. They might be about murders, attacks or other crimes. Then take those hard cases to the place the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will choose. <verse eid="DEU 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 17:9"/>Go to a priest, who is a Levite. And go to the judge who is in office at that time. Ask them for their decision. They will give it to you. <verse eid="DEU 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 17:10"/>They’ll hand down their decisions at the place the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will choose. You must do what they decide. Be careful to do everything they tell you to do. <verse eid="DEU 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 17:11"/>Act according to whatever they teach you. Accept the decisions they give you. Don’t turn away from what they tell you. Don’t turn to the right or the left. <verse eid="DEU 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 17:12"/>Someone might show that they don’t respect the judge. Or they will show that they don’t respect the priest. The priest will serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God at the place God will choose. If anyone doesn’t show respect for these people, that person must be put to death. Remove that evil person from Israel. <verse eid="DEU 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 17:13"/>All the Israelites will hear about it. And they will be afraid to disrespect a judge or priest again.<verse eid="DEU 17:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Appoint the King the <char style="nd">Lord</char> Chooses</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 17:14"/>You will enter the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you. You will take it as your own. You will make your homes in it. When you do, you will say, “Let’s appoint a king over us, just like all the nations around us.” <verse eid="DEU 17:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 17:15"/>When that happens, make sure you appoint over yourselves a king the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God chooses. He must be from among your own people. Don’t appoint over yourselves someone from another country. Don’t choose anyone who isn’t from one of the tribes of Israel. <verse eid="DEU 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 17:16"/>The king must not get large numbers of horses for himself. He must not make the people return to Egypt to get more horses. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has told you, “You must not go back there again.” <verse eid="DEU 17:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 17:17"/>The king must not have many wives. If he does, they will lead him astray. He must not store up large amounts of silver and gold.<verse eid="DEU 17:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 17:18"/>When he sits on the throne of his kingdom, he must make for himself a copy of the law. He must write on a scroll the law that I am teaching you. He must copy it from the scroll of a priest, who is a Levite. <verse eid="DEU 17:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 17:19"/>The king must keep the scroll close to him at all times. He must read it all the days of his life. Then he can learn to have respect for the <char style="nd">Lord</char> his God. He can carefully obey all the words of this law and these rules. <verse eid="DEU 17:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 17:20"/>He won’t think of himself as being better than his people are. He won’t turn away from the law. He won’t turn to the right or the left. Then he and his sons after him will rule over his kingdom in Israel for a long time.<verse eid="DEU 17:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="DEU 18"/>
  <para style="s1">Offerings for Priests and Levites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 18:1"/>The priests, who are Levites, won’t receive any part of the land of Israel. That also applies to the whole tribe of Levi. They will eat the food offerings presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. That will be their share. <verse eid="DEU 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 18:2"/>They won’t have any part of the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave the other tribes in Israel. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> himself is their share, just as he promised them.<verse eid="DEU 18:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 18:3"/>Anyone who sacrifices a bull or a sheep owes a share of it to the priests. Their share is the shoulder, the inside parts and the meat from the head. <verse eid="DEU 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 18:4"/>You must give the priests the first share of the harvest of your grain, olive oil and fresh wine. You must also give them the first wool you clip from your sheep. <verse eid="DEU 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 18:5"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has chosen the Levites and their sons after them to serve him in his name always. He hasn’t chosen priests from any of your other tribes.<verse eid="DEU 18:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 18:6"/>Sometimes a Levite will move from the town in Israel where he’s living. And he will come to the place the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will choose. He’ll do it because he really wants to. <verse eid="DEU 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 18:7"/>Then he can serve in the name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> his God. He’ll be like all the other Levites who serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char> there. <verse eid="DEU 18:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 18:8"/>He must have an equal share of the good things they have. That applies even if he has already received money by selling things his family owned.<verse eid="DEU 18:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Practices the <char style="nd">Lord</char> Hates</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 18:9"/>You will enter the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you. When you do, don’t copy the practices of the nations there. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> hates those practices. <verse eid="DEU 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 18:10"/>Here are things you must not do. Don’t sacrifice your children in the fire to other gods. Don’t practice any kind of evil magic at all. Don’t use magic to try to explain the meaning of warnings in the sky or of any other signs. Don’t take part in worshiping evil powers. <verse eid="DEU 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 18:11"/>Don’t put a spell on anyone. Don’t get messages from those who have died. Don’t talk to the spirits of the dead. Don’t get advice from the dead. <verse eid="DEU 18:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 18:12"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God hates it when anyone does these things. The nations in the land he’s giving you do these things he hates. So he will drive out those nations to make room for you. <verse eid="DEU 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 18:13"/>You must be without blame in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="DEU 18:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Prophet of the <char style="nd">Lord</char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 18:14"/>You will take over the nations that are in the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is giving you. They listen to those who practice all kinds of evil magic. But you belong to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. He says you must not do these things. <verse eid="DEU 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 18:15"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will raise up for you a prophet like me. He will be one of your own people. You must listen to him. <verse eid="DEU 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 18:16"/>At Mount Horeb you asked the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God for a prophet. You asked him on the day you gathered together. You said, “We don’t want to hear the voice of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God. We don’t want to see this great fire anymore. If we do, we’ll die.”<verse eid="DEU 18:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 18:17"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to me, “What they are saying is good. <verse eid="DEU 18:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 18:18"/>I will raise up for them a prophet like you. He will be one of their own people. I will put my words in his mouth. He will tell them everything I command him to say. <verse eid="DEU 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 18:19"/>The prophet will speak in my name. But someone might not listen to what I say through the prophet. I will hold that person responsible for not listening. <verse eid="DEU 18:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 18:20"/>But suppose a prophet dares to speak in my name something I have not commanded. Or he speaks in the name of other gods. Then that prophet must be put to death.”<verse eid="DEU 18:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 18:21"/>You will say to yourselves, “How can we know when a message hasn’t been spoken by the <char style="nd">Lord</char>?” <verse eid="DEU 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 18:22"/>Sometimes a prophet will announce something in the name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. And it won’t take place or come true. Then that’s a message the <char style="nd">Lord</char> hasn’t told him to speak. That prophet has dared to speak on his own authority. So don’t be afraid of what he says.<verse eid="DEU 18:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="DEU 19"/>
  <para style="s1">Cities to Run to for Safety</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 19:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will destroy the nations whose land he is giving you. You will drive them out. And you will make your homes in their towns and their houses. <verse eid="DEU 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 19:2"/>When you do, set apart for yourselves three cities in the land. It’s the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you to take as your own. <verse eid="DEU 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 19:3"/>Figure out the distances and then separate the land into three parts. Then anyone who kills another person can run to one of these cities for safety. They are in the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you as your own.<verse eid="DEU 19:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 19:4"/>Here is the rule about a person who kills someone. That person can run to one of those cities for safety. The rule applies to anyone who kills a neighbor they didn’t hate and didn’t mean to kill. <verse eid="DEU 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 19:5"/>For example, suppose a man goes into a forest with his neighbor to cut wood. When he swings his ax to chop down a tree, the head of the ax flies off. And it hits his neighbor and kills him. Then that man can run to one of those cities and save his life. <verse eid="DEU 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 19:6"/>If he doesn’t go to one of those cities, the dead man’s nearest male relative might become very angry. He might chase the man. If the city is too far away, he might catch him and kill him. But the man running to the city isn’t worthy of death, because he didn’t hate his neighbor. <verse eid="DEU 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 19:7"/>That’s why I command you to set apart for yourselves three cities.<verse eid="DEU 19:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 19:8"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will increase the size of your territory. He promised your people of long ago that he would do it. He will give you the whole land he promised them. <verse eid="DEU 19:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 19:9"/>But he’ll do it only if you are careful to obey all the laws I’m commanding you today. I command you to love the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. You must always live as he wants you to live. Suppose you are careful to obey, and the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God gives you more land. Then you must set apart three more cities. <verse eid="DEU 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 19:10"/>Do it to protect those not guilty of murder. Then you won’t spill their blood in your land. It’s the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you as your own.<verse eid="DEU 19:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 19:11"/>But suppose a man hates his neighbor. So he hides and waits for him. Then he attacks him and kills him. And he runs to one of those cities for safety. <verse eid="DEU 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 19:12"/>If he does, the elders of his own town must send for him. He must be brought back from the city. He must be handed over to the dead man’s nearest male relative. Then the relative will kill him. <verse eid="DEU 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 19:13"/>Don’t feel sorry for him. He has killed someone who hadn’t done anything wrong. Crimes like that must be punished in Israel. Then things will go well with you.<verse eid="DEU 19:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 19:14"/>Don’t move your neighbor’s boundary stone. It was set up by people who lived there before you. It marks the border of a field in the land you will receive as your own. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you that land. You will take it over.<verse eid="DEU 19:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Witnesses</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 19:15"/>Suppose someone is charged with committing a crime of any kind. Then one witness won’t be enough to prove that person is guilty. Every matter must be proved by the words of two or three witnesses.<verse eid="DEU 19:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 19:16"/>Suppose a witness who tells lies goes to court and brings charges against someone. The witness says someone committed a crime. <verse eid="DEU 19:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 19:17"/>Then the two people in the case must stand in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They must stand in front of the priests and the judges who are in office at that time. <verse eid="DEU 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 19:18"/>The judges must check out the matter carefully. And suppose the witness is proved to be lying. Then he has said something false in court against another Israelite. <verse eid="DEU 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 19:19"/>So do to the lying witness what he tried to do to the other person. Get rid of that evil witness. <verse eid="DEU 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 19:20"/>The rest of the people will hear about it. And they will be afraid. They won’t allow such an evil thing to be done among them again. <verse eid="DEU 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 19:21"/>Don’t feel sorry for that evil person. A life must be taken for a life. An eye must be put out for an eye. A tooth must be knocked out for a tooth. A hand must be cut off for a hand and a foot for a foot.<verse eid="DEU 19:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="DEU 20"/>
  <para style="s1">Going to War</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 20:1"/>When you go to war against your enemies, you might see that they have horses and chariots. They might even have an army stronger than yours. But don’t be afraid of them. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will be with you. After all, he brought you up out of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 20:2"/>Just before you go into battle, the priest will come forward. He’ll speak to the army. <verse eid="DEU 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 20:3"/>He’ll say, “Men of Israel, listen to me. Today you are going into battle against your enemies. Don’t be scared. Don’t be afraid. Don’t panic or be terrified by them. <verse eid="DEU 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 20:4"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is going with you. He’ll fight for you. He’ll help you win the battle over your enemies.”<verse eid="DEU 20:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 20:5"/>The officers will speak to the army. They will say, “Has anyone built a new house and not started to live in it? Let him go home. If he doesn’t, he might die in battle. Then someone else will live in his house. <verse eid="DEU 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 20:6"/>Has anyone planted a vineyard and not started to enjoy it? Let him go home. If he doesn’t, he might die in battle. Then someone else will enjoy his vineyard. <verse eid="DEU 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 20:7"/>Has anyone promised to be married to a woman but hasn’t done it yet? Let him go home. If he doesn’t, he might die in battle. Then someone else will marry her.” <verse eid="DEU 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 20:8"/>The officers will continue, “Is anyone afraid or scared? Let him go home. Then the other soldiers won’t lose hope too.” <verse eid="DEU 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 20:9"/>The officers will finish speaking to the army. When they do, they’ll appoint commanders over it.<verse eid="DEU 20:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 20:10"/>Suppose you march up to attack a city. Before you attack it, offer to make peace with its people. <verse eid="DEU 20:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 20:11"/>Suppose they accept your offer and open their gates. Then force all the people in the city to be your slaves. They will have to work for you. <verse eid="DEU 20:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 20:12"/>But suppose they refuse your offer of peace and prepare for battle. Then surround that city. Get ready to attack it. <verse eid="DEU 20:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 20:13"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will hand it over to you. When he does, kill all the men with your swords. <verse eid="DEU 20:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 20:14"/>But you can take the women and children for yourselves. You can also take the livestock and everything else in the city. What you have captured from your enemies you can use for yourselves. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has given it to you. <verse eid="DEU 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 20:15"/>That’s how you must treat all the cities far away from you. Those cities don’t belong to the nations that are nearby.<verse eid="DEU 20:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 20:16"/>But what about the cities the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you as your own? Kill everything that breathes in those cities. <verse eid="DEU 20:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 20:17"/>Completely destroy them. Wipe out the Hittites, Amorites, Canaanites, Perizzites, Hivites and Jebusites. That’s what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God commanded you to do. <verse eid="DEU 20:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 20:18"/>If you don’t destroy them, they’ll teach you to do all the things the <char style="nd">Lord</char> hates. He hates the way they worship their gods. If you do those things, you will sin against the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="DEU 20:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 20:19"/>Suppose you surround a city and get ready to attack it. And suppose you fight against it for a long time in order to capture it. Then don’t chop down its trees and destroy them. You can eat their fruit. So don’t cut them down. Are the trees people? So why should you attack them? <verse eid="DEU 20:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 20:20"/>But you can cut down trees that you know aren’t fruit trees. You can build war machines out of their wood. You can use them until you capture the city you are fighting against.<verse eid="DEU 20:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="DEU 21"/>
  <para style="s1">What to Do When You Don’t Know Who Killed Someone</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 21:1"/>Suppose you find someone who has been killed. The body is lying in a field in the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you as your own. But no one knows who the killer was. <verse eid="DEU 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 21:2"/>Then your elders and judges will go out to the field. They will measure the distance from the body to the nearby towns. <verse eid="DEU 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 21:3"/>The elders from the town that is nearest to the body will get a young cow. It must never have been used for work. It must never have pulled a load. <verse eid="DEU 21:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 21:4"/>The elders must lead it down into a valley. The valley must not have been farmed. There must be a stream flowing through it. There in the valley the elders must break the cow’s neck. <verse eid="DEU 21:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 21:5"/>The priests, who are sons of Levi, will step forward. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has chosen them to serve him. He wants them to bless the people in his name. He wants them to decide all cases that have to do with people arguing and attacking others. <verse eid="DEU 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 21:6"/>Then all the elders from the town that is nearest to the body will wash their hands. They will wash them over the young cow whose neck they broke in the valley. <verse eid="DEU 21:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 21:7"/>They’ll say to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, “We didn’t kill that person. We didn’t see it happen. <verse eid="DEU 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 21:8"/>Accept this payment for the sin of your people Israel. <char style="nd">Lord</char>, you have set your people free. Don’t hold them guilty for spilling the blood of someone who hasn’t done anything wrong.” That will pay for the death of that person. <verse eid="DEU 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 21:9"/>So you will get rid of the guilt of killing someone who didn’t do anything wrong. That’s because you have done what is right in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s eyes.<verse eid="DEU 21:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Marrying a Woman Who Is Your Prisoner</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 21:10"/>Suppose you go to war against your enemies. And the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God hands them over to you and you take them as prisoners. <verse eid="DEU 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 21:11"/>Then you notice a beautiful woman among them. If you like her, you may marry her. <verse eid="DEU 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 21:12"/>Bring her home. Have her shave her head and cut her nails. <verse eid="DEU 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 21:13"/>Have her throw away the clothes she was wearing when she was captured. Let her live in your house and mourn the loss of her parents for a full month. Then you can go to her and be her husband. And she will be your wife. <verse eid="DEU 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 21:14"/>But suppose you aren’t pleased with her. Then let her go where she wants to. You must not sell her. You must not treat her as a slave. You have already brought shame on her.<verse eid="DEU 21:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Rights of the Oldest Son</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 21:15"/>Suppose a man has two wives. He loves one but not the other. And both of them have sons by him. But the oldest son is the son of the wife the man doesn’t love. <verse eid="DEU 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 21:16"/>Someday he’ll leave his property to his sons. When he does, he must not give the rights of the oldest son to the son of the wife he loves. He must give those rights to his oldest son. He must do it even though his oldest son is the son of the wife he doesn’t love. <verse eid="DEU 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 21:17"/>He must recognize the full rights of the oldest son. He must do it, even though that son is the son of the wife he doesn’t love. He must give that son a double share of everything he has. That son is the first sign of his father’s strength. So the rights of the oldest son belong to him.<verse eid="DEU 21:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">A Stubborn Son</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 21:18"/>Suppose someone has a very stubborn son. He doesn’t obey his father and mother. And he won’t listen to them when they try to correct him. <verse eid="DEU 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 21:19"/>Then his parents will take hold of him and bring him to the elders at the gate of his town. <verse eid="DEU 21:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 21:20"/>They will say to the elders, “This son of ours is very stubborn. He won’t obey us. He eats too much. He’s always getting drunk.” <verse eid="DEU 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 21:21"/>Then all the people in his town will put him to death by throwing stones at him. Get rid of that evil person. All the Israelites will hear about it. And they will be afraid to disobey their parents.<verse eid="DEU 21:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Several Other Laws</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 21:22"/>Suppose someone is put to death for a crime worthy of death. And a pole is stuck through their body and set up where people can see it. <verse eid="DEU 21:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 21:23"/>Then you must not leave the body on the pole all night. Make sure you bury it that same day. Everyone who is hung on a pole is under God’s curse. You must not make the land “unclean.” The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving it to you as your own.<verse eid="DEU 21:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="DEU 22"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 22:1"/>Suppose you see your neighbor’s ox or sheep wandering away. Then don’t act as if you didn’t see it. Instead, make sure you take it back to its owner. <verse eid="DEU 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 22:2"/>Its owner might not live near you. Or you might not know who owns it. So take the animal home with you. Keep it until the owner comes looking for it. Then give it back to them. <verse eid="DEU 22:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 22:3"/>Do the same thing if you find their donkey, coat or anything they have lost. Don’t act as if you didn’t see it.<verse eid="DEU 22:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 22:4"/>Suppose you see your neighbor’s donkey or ox that has fallen down on the road. Then don’t act as if you didn’t see it. Help the owner get it up on its feet again.<verse eid="DEU 22:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 22:5"/>A woman must not wear men’s clothes. And a man must not wear women’s clothes. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God hates it when anyone does this.<verse eid="DEU 22:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 22:6"/>Suppose you happen to find a bird’s nest beside the road. It might be in a tree or on the ground. And suppose the mother bird is sitting on her little birds or on the eggs. Then don’t take the mother along with the little ones. <verse eid="DEU 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 22:7"/>You can take the little ones. But make sure you let the mother go. Then things will go well with you. You will live for a long time.<verse eid="DEU 22:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 22:8"/>If you build a new house, put a low wall around the edge of your roof. Then you won’t be responsible if someone falls off your roof and dies.<verse eid="DEU 22:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 22:9"/>Don’t plant two kinds of seeds in your vineyard. If you do, the crops you grow there will be impure. Your grapes will also be impure.<verse eid="DEU 22:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 22:10"/>Don’t let an ox and a donkey pull the same plow together.<verse eid="DEU 22:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 22:11"/>Don’t wear clothes made out of wool and linen woven together.<verse eid="DEU 22:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 22:12"/>Make tassels on the four corners of the coat you wear.<verse eid="DEU 22:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Breaking Marriage Laws</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 22:13"/>Suppose a man marries a woman and sleeps with her. But then he doesn’t like her. <verse eid="DEU 22:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 22:14"/>So he tells lies about her and says she’s a bad woman. He says, “I married this woman. But when I slept with her, I discovered she wasn’t a virgin.” <verse eid="DEU 22:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 22:15"/>Then the young woman’s parents must bring proof that she was a virgin. They must give the proof to the elders at the gate of the town. <verse eid="DEU 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 22:16"/>Her father will speak to the elders. He’ll say, “I gave my daughter to this man to be his wife. But he doesn’t like her. <verse eid="DEU 22:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 22:17"/>So now he has told lies about her. He has said, ‘I discovered that your daughter wasn’t a virgin.’ But here’s the proof that my daughter was a virgin.” Then her parents will show the elders of the town the cloth that has her blood on it. <verse eid="DEU 22:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 22:18"/>The elders will punish the man. <verse eid="DEU 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 22:19"/>They’ll make him weigh out two and a half pounds of silver. They’ll give it to the young woman’s father. That’s because the man has said an Israelite virgin is a bad woman. She will continue to be his wife. He must not divorce her as long as he lives.<verse eid="DEU 22:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 22:20"/>But suppose the charge is true. And there isn’t any proof that the young woman was a virgin. <verse eid="DEU 22:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 22:21"/>Then she must be brought to the door of her father’s house. There the people of her town will put her to death by throwing stones at her. She has done a very terrible thing in Israel. She has slept with a man before she was married. Get rid of that evil person.<verse eid="DEU 22:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 22:22"/>Suppose a man is seen sleeping with another man’s wife. Then the man and the woman must both die. Get rid of those evil people.<verse eid="DEU 22:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 22:23"/>Suppose a man happens to see a virgin in a town. And she has promised to marry another man. But the man who happens to see her sleeps with her. <verse eid="DEU 22:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 22:24"/>Then you must take both of them to the gate of that town. You must put them to death by throwing stones at them. You must kill the young woman because she was in a town and didn’t scream for help. And you must kill the man because he slept with another man’s wife. Get rid of those evil people.<verse eid="DEU 22:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 22:25"/>But suppose a man happens to see a young woman out in the country. And she has promised to marry another man. But the man who happens to see her rapes her. Then only the man who has done that will die. <verse eid="DEU 22:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 22:26"/>Don’t do anything to the woman. She hasn’t committed a sin worthy of death. That case is like the case of someone who attacks and murders a neighbor. <verse eid="DEU 22:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 22:27"/>The man found the young woman out in the country. And she screamed for help. But there wasn’t anyone around who could save her.<verse eid="DEU 22:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 22:28"/>Suppose a man happens to see a virgin who hasn’t promised to marry another man. And the man who happens to see her rapes her. But someone discovers them. <verse eid="DEU 22:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 22:29"/>Then the man must weigh out 20 ounces of silver. He must give it to her father. The man must marry the young woman, because he raped her. And he can never divorce her as long as he lives.<verse eid="DEU 22:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 22:30"/>A man must not marry his stepmother. He must not bring shame on his father by sleeping with her.<verse eid="DEU 22:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="DEU 23"/>
  <para style="s1">Who Can Join in Worship With the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s People?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 23:1"/>No man whose sex organs have been crushed or cut can join in worship with the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s people.<verse eid="DEU 23:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 23:2"/>No one born to an unmarried woman can join in worship with the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s people. That also applies to the person’s children for all time to come.<verse eid="DEU 23:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 23:3"/>The people of Ammon and Moab can’t join in worship with the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s people. That also applies to their children after them for all time to come. <verse eid="DEU 23:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 23:4"/>The Ammonites and Moabites didn’t come to meet you with food and water on your way out of Egypt. They even hired Balaam from Pethor in Aram Naharaim to put a curse on you. Balaam was the son of Beor. <verse eid="DEU 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 23:5"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God wouldn’t listen to Balaam. Instead, he turned the curse into a blessing for you. He did it because he loves you. <verse eid="DEU 23:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 23:6"/>So don’t make a peace treaty with the Ammonites and Moabites as long as you live.<verse eid="DEU 23:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 23:7"/>Don’t hate the people of Edom. They are your relatives. Don’t hate the people of Egypt. After all, you lived as outsiders in their country. <verse eid="DEU 23:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 23:8"/>The great-grandchildren of the Edomites and Egyptians can join in worship with the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s people.<verse eid="DEU 23:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Keep the Camp of the Soldiers Pure and “Clean”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 23:9"/>There will be times when you are at war with your enemies. And your soldiers will be in camp. Then keep away from anything that isn’t pure and “clean.” <verse eid="DEU 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 23:10"/>Suppose semen flows from the body of one of your soldiers during the night. Then that will make him “unclean.” He must go outside the camp and stay there. <verse eid="DEU 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 23:11"/>But as evening approaches, he must wash himself. When the sun goes down, he can return to the camp.<verse eid="DEU 23:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 23:12"/>Choose a place outside the camp where you can go to the toilet. <verse eid="DEU 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 23:13"/>Keep a shovel among your tools. When you go to the toilet, dig a hole. Then cover up your waste. <verse eid="DEU 23:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 23:14"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God walks around in your camp. He’s there to keep you safe. He’s also there to hand your enemies over to you. So your camp must be holy. Then he won’t see anything among you that is shameful. He won’t turn away from you.<verse eid="DEU 23:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Several Other Laws</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 23:15"/>If a slave comes to you for safety, don’t hand them over to their master. <verse eid="DEU 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 23:16"/>Let them live among you anywhere they want to. Let them live in any town they choose. Don’t treat them badly.<verse eid="DEU 23:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 23:17"/>A man or woman in Israel must not become a temple prostitute. <verse eid="DEU 23:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 23:18"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God hates the money that men and women get for being prostitutes. So don’t take that money into the house of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> to pay what you promised to give.<verse eid="DEU 23:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 23:19"/>Don’t charge your own people any interest. Don’t charge them when they borrow money, food or anything else. <verse eid="DEU 23:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 23:20"/>You can charge interest to people from another country. But don’t charge your own people. Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will bless you in everything you do. He will bless you in the land you are entering to take as your own.<verse eid="DEU 23:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 23:21"/>Don’t put off giving to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God everything you promise him. He will certainly require it from you. And you will be guilty of committing a sin. <verse eid="DEU 23:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 23:22"/>But if you don’t make a promise, you won’t be guilty. <verse eid="DEU 23:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 23:23"/>Make sure you do what you promised to do. With your own mouth you made the promise to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. No one forced you to do it.<verse eid="DEU 23:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 23:24"/>When you enter your neighbor’s vineyard, you can eat all the grapes you want. But don’t put any of them in your basket. <verse eid="DEU 23:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 23:25"/>When you enter your neighbor’s field, you can pick heads of grain. But don’t cut down their standing grain.<verse eid="DEU 23:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="DEU 24"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 24:1"/>Suppose a man marries a woman. But later he decides he doesn’t like her. He finds something shameful about her. So he gives her a letter of divorce and sends her away from his house. <verse eid="DEU 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 24:2"/>Then after she leaves his house she becomes another man’s wife. <verse eid="DEU 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 24:3"/>But her second husband doesn’t like her either. So he gives her a letter of divorce and sends her away from his house. Or perhaps he dies. <verse eid="DEU 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 24:4"/>Then her first husband isn’t allowed to marry her again. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> would hate that. When her first husband divorced her, she became “unclean.” Don’t bring sin on the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you as your own.<verse eid="DEU 24:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 24:5"/>Suppose a man has just married his wife. Then don’t send him into battle. Don’t give him any other duty either. He’s free to stay home for one year. He needs time to make his new wife happy.<verse eid="DEU 24:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 24:6"/>Someone might borrow money from you and give you two millstones to keep until you are paid back. Don’t keep them. Don’t even keep the upper one. That person needs both millstones to make a living.<verse eid="DEU 24:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 24:7"/>Suppose someone is caught kidnapping another Israelite. And they sell or treat that person as a slave. Then the kidnapper must die. Get rid of that evil person.<verse eid="DEU 24:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 24:8"/>What about skin diseases? Be very careful to do exactly what the priests, who are Levites, tell you to do. You must be careful to obey the commands I’ve given them. <verse eid="DEU 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 24:9"/>Remember what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God did to Miriam on your way out of Egypt.<verse eid="DEU 24:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 24:10"/>Suppose your neighbor borrows something from you. And he offers you something to keep until you get paid back. Then don’t go into their house to get it. <verse eid="DEU 24:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 24:11"/>Stay outside. Let the neighbor bring it out to you. <verse eid="DEU 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 24:12"/>The neighbor might be poor. You might be given their coat to keep until you get paid back. Don’t go to sleep while you still have it. <verse eid="DEU 24:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 24:13"/>Return it before the sun goes down. They need it to sleep in and will thank you for returning it. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will see it and know that you have done the right thing.<verse eid="DEU 24:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 24:14"/>Don’t take advantage of any hired worker who is poor and needy. That applies to your own people. It also applies to outsiders living in one of your towns. <verse eid="DEU 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 24:15"/>Give them their pay every day. They are poor and are counting on it. If you don’t pay them, they might cry out to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> against you. Then you will be guilty of committing a sin.<verse eid="DEU 24:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 24:16"/>Parents must not be put to death because of what their children do. And children must not be put to death because of what their parents do. People must die because of their own sins.<verse eid="DEU 24:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 24:17"/>Do what is right and fair for outsiders and for children whose fathers have died. Suppose a widow borrows something from you. And she offers to give you her coat until she pays you back. Don’t take it. <verse eid="DEU 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 24:18"/>Remember that you were slaves in Egypt. Remember that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God set you free from there. That’s why I’m commanding you to do those things.<verse eid="DEU 24:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 24:19"/>When you are gathering crops in your field, you might leave some grain behind by mistake. Don’t go back to get it. Leave it behind for outsiders and widows. Leave it for children whose fathers have died. Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will bless you in everything you do. <verse eid="DEU 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 24:20"/>When you knock olives off your trees, don’t go back over the branches a second time. Leave what remains for outsiders and widows. Leave it for children whose fathers have died. <verse eid="DEU 24:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 24:21"/>When you pick grapes in your vineyard, don’t go back over the vines a second time. Leave what remains for outsiders and widows. Leave it for children whose fathers have died. <verse eid="DEU 24:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 24:22"/>Remember that you were slaves in Egypt. That’s why I’m commanding you to do these things.<verse eid="DEU 24:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 24"/>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="DEU 25"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 25:1"/>Suppose two people don’t agree about something. Then they must take their case to court. The judges will decide the case. They will let the one who isn’t guilty go free. And they will punish the one who is guilty. <verse eid="DEU 25:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 25:2"/>The guilty one might have done something that’s worthy of a beating. Then the judge will make them lie down and be beaten with a whip right there in court. The number of strokes should fit the crime. <verse eid="DEU 25:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 25:3"/>But the judge must not give the guilty person more than 40 strokes. If more than that are used, you will have disrespected your Israelite neighbor.<verse eid="DEU 25:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 25:4"/>Don’t stop an ox from eating while you use it to separate grain from straw.<verse eid="DEU 25:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 25:5"/>Suppose two brothers are living near each other. And one of them dies without having a son. Then his widow must not marry anyone outside the family. Her husband’s brother should marry her. That’s what a brother-in-law is supposed to do. <verse eid="DEU 25:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 25:6"/>Her first baby boy will be named after her first husband. Then the dead man’s name will continue in Israel.<verse eid="DEU 25:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 25:7"/>But suppose the man doesn’t want to marry his brother’s wife. Then she will go to the elders at the gate of the town. She will say, “My husband’s brother refuses to keep his brother’s name alive in Israel. He won’t do for me what a brother-in-law is supposed to do.” <verse eid="DEU 25:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 25:8"/>Then the elders in his town will send for him. They will talk to him. But he still might say, “I don’t want to marry her.” <verse eid="DEU 25:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 25:9"/>Then his brother’s widow will go up to him in front of the elders. She’ll pull one of his sandals off his foot. She’ll spit in his face. And she’ll say, “That’s what we do to a man who won’t build up his brother’s family line.” <verse eid="DEU 25:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 25:10"/>That man’s family line will be known in Israel as The Family of the Man Whose Sandal Was Pulled Off.<verse eid="DEU 25:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 25:11"/>Suppose two men are fighting. And the wife of one of them comes to save her husband from his attacker. So she reaches out and grabs hold of his attacker’s private parts. <verse eid="DEU 25:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 25:12"/>Then you must cut off her hand. Don’t feel sorry for her.<verse eid="DEU 25:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 25:13"/>Don’t have two different scales. Don’t have scales that cause things to seem heavier or lighter than they really are. <verse eid="DEU 25:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 25:14"/>And don’t have two different sets of measures. Don’t have measures that cause things to seem larger or smaller than they really are. <verse eid="DEU 25:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 25:15"/>You must use weights and measures that are honest and exact. Then you will live a long time in the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you. <verse eid="DEU 25:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 25:16"/>He hates anyone who cheats.<verse eid="DEU 25:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 25:17"/>Remember what the Amalekites did to you on your way out of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 25:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 25:18"/>You were tired and worn out. They met up with you on your journey. They attacked everyone who was lagging behind. They didn’t have any respect for God. <verse eid="DEU 25:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 25:19"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will give you peace and rest from all the enemies around you. He’ll do this in the land he’s giving you to take over as your very own. No one on earth will mention the Amalekites ever again because you will destroy them. Do not forget!<verse eid="DEU 25:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 25"/>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="DEU 26"/>
  <para style="s1">Give the <char style="nd">Lord</char> His Share</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 26:1"/>You will enter the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you as your own. You will take it over. You will make your homes in the land. <verse eid="DEU 26:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 26:2"/>When you do, get some of the first share of everything your soil produces. Put it in a basket. It’s from the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you. Take your gifts and go to the special place he will choose. He will put his Name there. <verse eid="DEU 26:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 26:3"/>Speak to the priest in office at that time. Tell him, “I announce today to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God that I have come to this land. It’s the land he promised to give us. He promised it to our people of long ago.” <verse eid="DEU 26:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 26:4"/>The priest will receive the basket from you. He’ll set it down in front of the altar of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="DEU 26:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 26:5"/>Then you will speak while the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is listening. You will say, “My father Jacob was a wanderer from the land of Aram. He went down into Egypt with a few people. He lived there and became the father of a great nation. It had huge numbers of people. <verse eid="DEU 26:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 26:6"/>But the people of Egypt treated us badly. They made us suffer. They made us work very hard. <verse eid="DEU 26:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 26:7"/>Then we cried out to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He is the God of our people who lived long ago. He heard our voice. He saw how much we were suffering. The Egyptians were treating us badly. They were making us work very hard. <verse eid="DEU 26:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 26:8"/>So the <char style="nd">Lord</char> used his mighty hand and powerful arm to bring us out of Egypt. He did great and terrifying things. He did signs and amazing things. <verse eid="DEU 26:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 26:9"/>He brought us to this place. He gave us this land. It’s a land that has plenty of milk and honey. <verse eid="DEU 26:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 26:10"/>Now, <char style="nd">Lord</char>, I’m bringing you the first share of crops from the soil. After all, you have given them to me.” Place the basket in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Bow down to him. <verse eid="DEU 26:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 26:11"/>Then you and the Levites and the outsiders among you will be full of joy. You will enjoy all the good things the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has given to you and your family.<verse eid="DEU 26:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 26:12"/>You will set apart a tenth of everything you produce in the third year. That’s the year for giving the tenth to people who have greater needs. You will give it to the Levites, outsiders and widows. You will also give it to children whose fathers have died. Then all of them will have plenty to eat in your towns. <verse eid="DEU 26:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 26:13"/>Speak to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Say to him, “I have taken your sacred share from my house. I have given it to the Levites, outsiders and widows. I have also given it to children whose fathers have died. I’ve done everything you commanded me to do. I haven’t stopped obeying your commands. I haven’t forgotten any of them. <verse eid="DEU 26:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 26:14"/>I haven’t eaten any part of your sacred share while I mourned over someone who had died. I haven’t taken any of it from my house while I was ‘unclean.’ And I haven’t offered any of it to the dead. <char style="nd">Lord</char> my God, I’ve obeyed you. I’ve done everything you commanded me to do. <verse eid="DEU 26:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 26:15"/>Look down from the holy place where you live in heaven. Bless your people Israel. Bless the land you have given us. It’s the land you promised to give to our people of long ago. It’s a land that has plenty of milk and honey.”<verse eid="DEU 26:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s Commands</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 26:16"/>This day the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God commands you to obey all these rules and laws. Be careful to obey them with all your heart and with all your soul. <verse eid="DEU 26:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 26:17"/>Today you have announced that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is your God. You have said you would live exactly as he wants you to live. You have agreed to keep his rules, commands and laws. And you have said you would listen to him. <verse eid="DEU 26:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 26:18"/>Today the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has announced that you are his people. He has said that you are his special treasure. He promised that you would be. He has told you to keep all his commands. <verse eid="DEU 26:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 26:19"/>He has announced that he will make you famous. He’ll give you more praise and honor than all the other nations he has made. And he has said that you will be a holy nation. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has set you apart for himself. That’s exactly what he promised to do.<verse eid="DEU 26:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 26"/>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="DEU 27"/>
  <para style="s1">The Altar on Mount Ebal</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 27:1"/>Moses and the elders of Israel gave commands to the people. They said, “Obey all the commands we’re giving you today. <verse eid="DEU 27:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 27:2"/>You will go across the Jordan River. You will enter the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you. When you do, set up some large stones. Put a coat of plaster on them. <verse eid="DEU 27:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 27:3"/>Write all the words of this law on them. Do it when you have crossed over into the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you. It’s a land that has plenty of milk and honey. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is the God of your people of long ago. He promised you that you would enter the land. <verse eid="DEU 27:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 27:4"/>After you have gone across the Jordan, set up those stones on Mount Ebal. Put a coat of plaster on them. We’re commanding you today to do that. <verse eid="DEU 27:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 27:5"/>Build an altar there to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Make it out of stones. Don’t use any iron tool on them. <verse eid="DEU 27:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 27:6"/>Use stones you find in the fields to build his altar. Then offer burnt offerings on it to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="DEU 27:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 27:7"/>Sacrifice friendship offerings there. Eat them and be filled with joy in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="DEU 27:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 27:8"/>You must write all the words of this law on the stones you have set up. Write the words very clearly.”<verse eid="DEU 27:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Curses for Not Obeying the <char style="nd">Lord</char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 27:9"/>Then Moses and the priests, who are Levites, spoke to all the Israelites. They said, “Israel, be quiet! Listen! You have now become the people of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="DEU 27:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 27:10"/>Obey him. Obey his commands and rules that we’re giving you today.”<verse eid="DEU 27:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 27:11"/>Here are the commands Moses gave the people that same day.<verse eid="DEU 27:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 27:12"/>You will go across the Jordan River. When you do, six tribes will stand on Mount Gerizim to bless the people. Those tribes are Simeon, Levi, Judah, Issachar, Joseph and Benjamin. <verse eid="DEU 27:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 27:13"/>The other six tribes will stand on Mount Ebal to announce some curses. Those tribes are Reuben, Gad, Asher, Zebulun, Dan and Naphtali.<verse eid="DEU 27:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 27:14"/>The Levites will speak to all the Israelites in a loud voice. The Levites will say,<verse eid="DEU 27:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 27:15"/>“May anyone who makes a statue of a god and sets it up in secret be under the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s curse. That statue is made by a skilled worker. And the <char style="nd">Lord</char> hates it.”</para>
  <para style="pr" vid="DEU 27:15">Then all the people will say, “Amen!”<verse eid="DEU 27:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 27:16"/>“May anyone who brings shame on their father or mother be under the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s curse.”</para>
  <para style="pr" vid="DEU 27:16">Then all the people will say, “Amen!”<verse eid="DEU 27:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 27:17"/>“May anyone who moves their neighbor’s boundary stone be under the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s curse.”</para>
  <para style="pr" vid="DEU 27:17">Then all the people will say, “Amen!”<verse eid="DEU 27:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 27:18"/>“May anyone who leads blind people down the wrong road be under the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s curse.”</para>
  <para style="pr" vid="DEU 27:18">Then all the people will say, “Amen!”<verse eid="DEU 27:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 27:19"/>“May anyone who treats unfairly outsiders, widows, and children whose fathers have died be under the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s curse.”</para>
  <para style="pr" vid="DEU 27:19">Then all the people will say, “Amen!”<verse eid="DEU 27:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 27:20"/>“May anyone who sleeps with his stepmother be under the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s curse. That man brings shame on his father by doing that.”</para>
  <para style="pr" vid="DEU 27:20">Then all the people will say, “Amen!”<verse eid="DEU 27:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 27:21"/>“May anyone who has sex with animals be under the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s curse.”</para>
  <para style="pr" vid="DEU 27:21">Then all the people will say, “Amen!”<verse eid="DEU 27:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 27:22"/>“May anyone who sleeps with his sister be under the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s curse. It doesn’t matter whether she is his full sister or his half sister.”</para>
  <para style="pr" vid="DEU 27:22">Then all the people will say, “Amen!”<verse eid="DEU 27:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 27:23"/>“May anyone who sleeps with his mother-in-law be under the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s curse.”</para>
  <para style="pr" vid="DEU 27:23">Then all the people will say, “Amen!”<verse eid="DEU 27:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 27:24"/>“May anyone who kills their neighbor secretly be under the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s curse.”</para>
  <para style="pr" vid="DEU 27:24">Then all the people will say, “Amen!”<verse eid="DEU 27:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 27:25"/>“May anyone who accepts money to kill someone who isn’t guilty of doing anything wrong be under the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s curse.”</para>
  <para style="pr" vid="DEU 27:25">Then all the people will say, “Amen!”<verse eid="DEU 27:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 27:26"/>“May anyone who doesn’t honor the words of this law by obeying them be under the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s curse.”</para>
  <para style="pr" vid="DEU 27:26">Then all the people will say, “Amen!”<verse eid="DEU 27:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 27"/>
  <chapter number="28" style="c" sid="DEU 28"/>
  <para style="s1">Blessings for Obeying the <char style="nd">Lord</char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 28:1"/>Make sure you obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God completely. Be careful to obey all his commands. I’m giving them to you today. If you do these things, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will honor you more than all the other nations on earth. <verse eid="DEU 28:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 28:2"/>If you obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God, here are the blessings that will come to you and remain with you.<verse eid="DEU 28:2"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 28:3"/>You will be blessed in the cities. You will be blessed out in the country.<verse eid="DEU 28:3"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 28:4"/>Your children will be blessed. Your crops will be blessed. The young animals among your livestock will be blessed. That includes your calves and lambs.<verse eid="DEU 28:4"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 28:5"/>Your baskets and bread pans will be blessed.<verse eid="DEU 28:5"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 28:6"/>You will be blessed no matter where you go.<verse eid="DEU 28:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 28:7"/>Enemies will rise up against you. But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will help you win the battle over them. They will come at you from one direction. But they’ll run away from you in every direction.<verse eid="DEU 28:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 28:8"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will bless your barns with plenty of grain and other food. He will bless everything you do. He’ll bless you in the land he’s giving you.<verse eid="DEU 28:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 28:9"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will make you his holy people. He will set you apart for himself. He promised to do this. He promised to do it if you would keep his commands and live exactly as he wants you to live. <verse eid="DEU 28:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 28:10"/>All the nations on earth will see that you belong to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. And they will be afraid of you. <verse eid="DEU 28:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 28:11"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will give you more than you need. You will have many children. Your livestock will have many little ones. Your crops will do very well. All of that will happen in the land he promised to give you. He promised this to your people of long ago.<verse eid="DEU 28:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 28:12"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will open up the heavens. That’s where he stores his riches. He will send rain on your land at just the right time. He’ll bless everything you do. You will lend money to many nations. But you won’t have to borrow from any of them. <verse eid="DEU 28:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 28:13"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will make you leaders, not followers. Pay attention to his commands that I’m giving you today. Be careful to obey them. Then you will always be on top. You will never be on the bottom. <verse eid="DEU 28:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 28:14"/>Don’t turn away from any of the commands I’m giving you today. Don’t turn to the right or the left. Don’t follow other gods. Don’t worship them.<verse eid="DEU 28:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Curses for Not Obeying the <char style="nd">Lord</char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 28:15"/>But suppose you don’t obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. And you aren’t careful to obey all his commands and rules I’m giving you today. Then he will send curses on you. They’ll catch up with you. Here are those curses.<verse eid="DEU 28:15"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 28:16"/>You will be cursed in the cities. You will be cursed out in the country.<verse eid="DEU 28:16"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 28:17"/>Your baskets and bread pans will be cursed.<verse eid="DEU 28:17"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 28:18"/>Your children will be cursed. Your crops will be cursed. Your calves and lambs will be cursed.<verse eid="DEU 28:18"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 28:19"/>You will be cursed no matter where you go.<verse eid="DEU 28:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 28:20"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will send curses on you. You won’t know what’s going on. In everything you do, he will be angry with you. You will be destroyed suddenly and completely. This will happen because you did an evil thing when you deserted the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="DEU 28:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 28:21"/>He will send all kinds of sicknesses on you. He’ll send them until he has destroyed you. He’ll remove you from the land you are entering to take as your own. <verse eid="DEU 28:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 28:22"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will make you sick and very weak. He will strike you with fever and swelling. He’ll send burning heat. There won’t be any rain. The hot winds will completely dry up your crops. All those things will happen until you die. <verse eid="DEU 28:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 28:23"/>The sky above you will be like bronze. The ground beneath you will be like iron. <verse eid="DEU 28:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 28:24"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will turn the rain of your country into dust and powder. It will come down from the skies until you are destroyed.<verse eid="DEU 28:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 28:25"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will help your enemies win the battle over you. You will come at them from one direction. But you will run away from them in every direction. All the kingdoms on earth will be completely shocked when they see you. <verse eid="DEU 28:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 28:26"/>Birds and wild animals will eat up your dead bodies. There won’t be anyone left to scare them away. <verse eid="DEU 28:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 28:27"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will send boils on you, just like the ones he sent on the Egyptians. You will have growths in your bodies and boils on your skin. You will itch all over. No one will be able to heal you. <verse eid="DEU 28:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 28:28"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will make you lose your mind. He will make you blind. You won’t know what’s going on. <verse eid="DEU 28:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 28:29"/>Even at noon you will have to feel your way around like a blind person in the dark. You won’t have success in anything you do. Day after day you will be robbed and treated badly. No one will be able to save you.<verse eid="DEU 28:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 28:30"/>You and a woman will promise to marry each other. But another man will take her and rape her. You will build a house. But you won’t live in it. You will plant a vineyard. But you won’t eat a single grape from it. <verse eid="DEU 28:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 28:31"/>Your ox will be killed right in front of your eyes. But you won’t eat any of it. Your donkey will be taken away from you by force. And you will never get it back. Your sheep will be given to your enemies. No one will be able to save them. <verse eid="DEU 28:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 28:32"/>Your children will be given to another nation. Day after day you will watch for them to come back. But you will only wear out your eyes. You won’t be able to help your children. <verse eid="DEU 28:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 28:33"/>A nation you don’t know anything about will eat what you work to produce on your land. You will only be treated badly as long as you live. <verse eid="DEU 28:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 28:34"/>The things you see will make you lose your mind. <verse eid="DEU 28:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 28:35"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will send painful boils on your knees and legs. No one will be able to heal them. They will cover you from head to toe.<verse eid="DEU 28:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 28:36"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will drive you out of the land. And he will drive out the king you place over yourselves. All of you will go to another nation. You and your people of long ago didn’t know anything about them. There you will worship other gods. They will be made out of wood and stone. <verse eid="DEU 28:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 28:37"/>You will look very bad to all the nations where the <char style="nd">Lord</char> sends you. They will be completely shocked when they see you. They will mock you and make fun of you.<verse eid="DEU 28:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="DEU 28:38"/>You will plant many seeds in your field. But you will gather very little food. Locusts will eat it up. <verse eid="DEU 28:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="DEU 28:39"/>You will plant vineyards and take care of them. But you won’t drink the wine. You won’t gather the grapes. Worms will eat them up. <verse eid="DEU 28:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="DEU 28:40"/>You will have olive trees through your whole country. But you won’t use the oil. The olives will drop off the trees. <verse eid="DEU 28:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="DEU 28:41"/>You will have children. But you won’t be able to keep them. They’ll be taken away as prisoners. <verse eid="DEU 28:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="DEU 28:42"/>Large numbers of locusts will eat up the leaves on all your trees. They will also eat up the crops on your land.<verse eid="DEU 28:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="DEU 28:43"/>Outsiders who live among you will become your leaders. They will rise higher and higher. But you will sink lower and lower. <verse eid="DEU 28:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="DEU 28:44"/>They will lend money to you. But you won’t be able to lend money to them. They will be the leaders. But you will be the followers.<verse eid="DEU 28:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="DEU 28:45"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will send all these curses on you. They will follow you everywhere. They’ll catch up with you. You will be under the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s curse until you are destroyed. That’s because you didn’t obey him. You didn’t keep the commands and rules he gave you. <verse eid="DEU 28:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="DEU 28:46"/>These curses will remain as signs and awful judgments against you and your children after you forever. <verse eid="DEU 28:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="DEU 28:47"/>You didn’t serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God with joy and gladness when times were good. <verse eid="DEU 28:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="DEU 28:48"/>So he will send enemies against you. You will have to serve them. You will be hungry and thirsty. You will be naked and poor. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will put the iron chains of slavery around your necks until he has destroyed you.<verse eid="DEU 28:48"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="DEU 28:49"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will bring a nation against you from far away. It will come from the ends of the earth. It will dive down on you like an eagle. You won’t understand that nation’s language. <verse eid="DEU 28:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="DEU 28:50"/>Its people will look mean. They won’t have any respect for old people. They won’t show any kindness to young people. <verse eid="DEU 28:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="DEU 28:51"/>They will eat up the young animals among your livestock. They’ll eat up the crops on your land. They’ll destroy you. They won’t leave you any grain, olive oil or fresh wine. They won’t leave you any calves or lambs. They’ll destroy you. <verse eid="DEU 28:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="DEU 28:52"/>They’ll surround all the cities throughout your whole land. They’ll attack those cities until the high, strong walls you trust in fall down. That’s what will happen to the cities in the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you.<verse eid="DEU 28:52"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="53" style="v" sid="DEU 28:53"/>Your enemies will surround you and attack you. They will make you suffer greatly. So you will eat your own children. You will eat the dead bodies of the sons and daughters the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has given you. <verse eid="DEU 28:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="DEU 28:54"/>There may be a gentle and caring man among you. But he will treat his own brother badly. He’ll be just as mean to the wife he loves and to any of his children who are still alive. <verse eid="DEU 28:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="DEU 28:55"/>He won’t give to a single one of them any part of the dead bodies of his children that he’s eating. It will be all he has left to eat. That’s how much your enemies will make you suffer when they surround all your cities and attack them. <verse eid="DEU 28:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="DEU 28:56"/>There may be a gentle and caring woman among you. She wouldn’t even touch the ground with her feet without first putting her sandals on. But she will not share anything with the husband she loves. She won’t share with her own children either. <verse eid="DEU 28:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="DEU 28:57"/>She will eat what comes out of her body after she has a baby. Then she’ll even eat her baby. She won’t share it with anyone in her family. In her great hunger she’ll plan to eat it in secret. There won’t be anything else for her to eat because the city she lives in will be surrounded. That’s an example of how much your enemies will make you suffer when they are attacking your cities.<verse eid="DEU 28:57"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="58" style="v" sid="DEU 28:58"/>Be careful to follow all the words of this law. They are written in this scroll. Have respect for the glorious and wonderful name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. If you don’t, <verse eid="DEU 28:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="DEU 28:59"/>he will send terrible plagues on you and your children after you. He’ll send horrible and lasting troubles. He’ll make you very sick for a long time. <verse eid="DEU 28:59"/><verse number="60" style="v" sid="DEU 28:60"/>He’ll bring on you all the sicknesses you were afraid of getting when you were in Egypt. You won’t be able to get rid of them. <verse eid="DEU 28:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="DEU 28:61"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will also bring on you all other kinds of sickness and trouble. I haven’t even written those down in this Book of the Law. You will be destroyed. <verse eid="DEU 28:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="DEU 28:62"/>At one time you were as many as the stars in the sky. But there will only be a few of you left. That’s because you didn’t obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="DEU 28:62"/><verse number="63" style="v" sid="DEU 28:63"/>It pleased the <char style="nd">Lord</char> to give you success and to cause there to be many of you. But it will please him just as much to wipe you out and destroy you. You will be removed from the land you are entering to take as your own.<verse eid="DEU 28:63"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="64" style="v" sid="DEU 28:64"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will scatter you among all the nations. He’ll spread you around from one end of the earth to the other. There you will worship statues of gods made out of wood and stone. You and your people of long ago hadn’t known anything about those gods. <verse eid="DEU 28:64"/><verse number="65" style="v" sid="DEU 28:65"/>Among those nations you won’t find any peace. There won’t be any place where you can make your home and rest your feet. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will give you minds filled with worry. He’ll give you eyes worn out from looking for help. You won’t have any hope in your hearts. <verse eid="DEU 28:65"/><verse number="66" style="v" sid="DEU 28:66"/>Your lives will always be in danger. You will be filled with fear night and day. You will never be sure you are safe. <verse eid="DEU 28:66"/><verse number="67" style="v" sid="DEU 28:67"/>In the morning you will say, “We wish it were evening!” In the evening you will say, “We wish it were morning!” Your hearts will be filled with fear. The things you see will terrify you. <verse eid="DEU 28:67"/><verse number="68" style="v" sid="DEU 28:68"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will send you back to Egypt in ships. He’ll send you on a journey I said you should never have to make again. You will offer to sell yourselves to your enemies as slaves in Egypt. But no one will buy you.<verse eid="DEU 28:68"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 28"/>
  <chapter number="29" style="c" sid="DEU 29"/>
  <para style="s1">Obey the Terms of the Covenant</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 29:1"/>Here are the terms of the covenant the <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded Moses to make with the Israelites in Moab. The terms were added to the covenant he had made with them at Mount Horeb.<verse eid="DEU 29:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 29:2"/>Moses sent for all the Israelites. Here is what he said to them.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="DEU 29:2"/>
  <para style="p" vid="DEU 29:2">With your own eyes you have seen everything the <char style="nd">Lord</char> did in Egypt to Pharaoh. You have seen what he did to all Pharaoh’s officials and to his whole land. <verse eid="DEU 29:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 29:3"/>With your own eyes you saw how the <char style="nd">Lord</char> really made them suffer. You saw the signs and amazing things he did. <verse eid="DEU 29:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 29:4"/>But to this day the <char style="nd">Lord</char> hasn’t given you a mind that understands. He hasn’t given you eyes that see. He hasn’t given you ears that hear. <verse eid="DEU 29:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 29:5"/>Yet the <char style="nd">Lord</char> says, “I led you through the desert for 40 years. During that time your clothes didn’t wear out. The sandals on your feet didn’t wear out either. <verse eid="DEU 29:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 29:6"/>You didn’t eat any bread. You didn’t drink any kind of wine. I did all these things because I wanted you to know that I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.”<verse eid="DEU 29:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 29:7"/>When you got here, Sihon and Og came out to fight against us. Sihon was the king of Heshbon. And Og was the king of Bashan. But we won the battle over them. <verse eid="DEU 29:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 29:8"/>We took their land. We gave it to the tribes of Reuben and Gad and half of the tribe of Manasseh as their share.<verse eid="DEU 29:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 29:9"/>Be careful to obey the terms of this covenant. Then you will have success in everything you do. <verse eid="DEU 29:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 29:10"/>Today all of you are standing here in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Your leaders and chief men are here. Your elders and officials are here. So are all the other men of Israel. <verse eid="DEU 29:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 29:11"/>Your children and wives are here with you too. So are the outsiders living in your camps. They chop your wood and carry your water. <verse eid="DEU 29:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 29:12"/>All of you are standing here in order to enter into a covenant with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. He is making the covenant with you today. He’s giving you his word. <verse eid="DEU 29:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 29:13"/>Today he wants to show you that you are his people and that he is your God. That’s what he promised to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. <verse eid="DEU 29:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 29:14"/>I’m making this covenant and the promise that goes along with it. I’m making this covenant with you. <verse eid="DEU 29:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 29:15"/>You are standing here with us today in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God. And I’m also making this covenant with those who aren’t here today.<verse eid="DEU 29:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 29:16"/>You yourselves know how we lived in Egypt. You also know how we passed through other countries on the way here. <verse eid="DEU 29:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 29:17"/>You saw the statues of their gods made out of wood, stone, silver and gold. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> hates those statues. <verse eid="DEU 29:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 29:18"/>Make sure there isn’t a man or woman among your families or tribes who turns away from the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God. No one must worship the gods of those nations. Make sure that kind of worship doesn’t spread like bitter poison through your whole community.<verse eid="DEU 29:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 29:19"/>Some people who worship those gods will hear the promise that seals the covenant I’m making. They think they can escape trouble by what they’re saying. They say, “We’ll be safe, even though we’re stubborn and go our own way.” But they will bring trouble on the whole land. <verse eid="DEU 29:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 29:20"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will never be willing to forgive those people. His great anger will blaze out against them. All the curses I’ve written down in this book will fall on them. And the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will erase any mention of them from the earth. <verse eid="DEU 29:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 29:21"/>He will find those people in all the tribes of Israel and give them nothing but trouble. That will agree with all the curses of the covenant. They are written down in this Book of the Law.<verse eid="DEU 29:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 29:22"/>Even your children’s children will see the troubles that have fallen on the land. They’ll see the sicknesses the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has brought on it. People who come from countries far away will also see those things. <verse eid="DEU 29:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 29:23"/>The whole land will be burned up. Nothing but salt and sulfur will be left. Nothing will be planted there. Nothing will grow there. In fact, nothing will even start to grow there. The land will be like Sodom, Gomorrah, Admah and Zeboyim after they were destroyed. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> wiped out those cities because he was very angry. <verse eid="DEU 29:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 29:24"/>All the nations will ask, “Why has the <char style="nd">Lord</char> done this to the land? What could have made him so very angry?”<verse eid="DEU 29:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 29:25"/>And they will hear the answer, “It’s because the people living there have broken the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He’s the God of their people of long ago. He made that covenant with them when he brought them out of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 29:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 29:26"/>They went off and worshiped other gods. They bowed down to them. They hadn’t known anything about those gods before. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> hadn’t given those gods to them. <verse eid="DEU 29:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 29:27"/>So the <char style="nd">Lord</char> became very angry with this land. He brought on it all the curses written down in this book. <verse eid="DEU 29:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 29:28"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s anger blazed out against his people. So he pulled them up out of their land. He threw them into another land. And that’s where they are now.”<verse eid="DEU 29:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 29:29"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God keeps certain things hidden. But he makes other things known to us and to our children forever. He does it so we can obey all the words of this law.<verse eid="DEU 29:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 29"/>
  <chapter number="30" style="c" sid="DEU 30"/>
  <para style="s1">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> Will Bless His People</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 30:1"/>I have told you about all these blessings and curses. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will bring them on you. Then you will think carefully about the blessings and curses. You will think about them everywhere the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God scatters you among the nations. <verse eid="DEU 30:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 30:2"/>You and your children will return to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. You will obey him with all your heart and with all your soul. That will be according to everything I’m commanding you today. <verse eid="DEU 30:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 30:3"/>When all that happens, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will bless you with great success again. He will be very kind to you. He’ll bring you back from all the nations where he scattered you. <verse eid="DEU 30:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 30:4"/>Suppose you have been forced to go away to the farthest land on earth. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will bring you back even from there. <verse eid="DEU 30:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 30:5"/>He will bring you to the land that belonged to your people of long ago. You will take it over. He’ll make you better off than your people were. He’ll cause there to be more of you than there were of them. <verse eid="DEU 30:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 30:6"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will keep you from being stubborn. He’ll do the same thing for your children and their children. Then you will love him with all your heart and with all your soul. And you will live. <verse eid="DEU 30:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 30:7"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will put all these curses on your enemies. They hated you and hunted you down. <verse eid="DEU 30:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 30:8"/>You will obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char> again. You will obey all his commands that I’m giving you today. <verse eid="DEU 30:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 30:9"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will give you great success in everything you do. You will have many children. Your livestock will have many little ones. Your crops will do very well. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will take delight in you again. He’ll give you success. That’s what he did for your people of long ago. <verse eid="DEU 30:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 30:10"/>But you must obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. You must keep his commands and rules. They are written in this Book of the Law. You must turn to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God with all your heart and with all your soul.<verse eid="DEU 30:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Choose Life, Not Death</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 30:11"/>What I’m commanding you today is not too hard for you. It isn’t beyond your reach. <verse eid="DEU 30:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 30:12"/>It isn’t up in heaven. So you don’t have to ask, “Who will go up into heaven to get it? Who will announce it to us so we can obey it?” <verse eid="DEU 30:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 30:13"/>And it isn’t beyond the ocean. So you don’t have to ask, “Who will go across the ocean to get it? Who will announce it to us so we can obey it?” <verse eid="DEU 30:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 30:14"/>No, the message isn’t far away at all. In fact, it’s really near you. It’s in your mouth and in your heart so that you can obey it.<verse eid="DEU 30:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 30:15"/>Today I’m giving you a choice. You can have life and success. Or you can have death and harm. <verse eid="DEU 30:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 30:16"/>I’m commanding you today to love the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. I’m commanding you to live exactly as he wants you to live. You must obey his commands, rules and laws. Then you will live. There will be many of you. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will bless you in the land you are entering to take as your own.<verse eid="DEU 30:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 30:17"/>Don’t let your hearts turn away from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Instead, obey him. Don’t let yourselves be drawn away to other gods. And don’t bow down to them and worship them. <verse eid="DEU 30:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 30:18"/>If you do, I announce to you this day that you will certainly be destroyed. You are about to go across the Jordan River and take over the land. But you won’t live there very long.<verse eid="DEU 30:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 30:19"/>I’m calling for the heavens and the earth to be witnesses against you this very day. I’m offering you the choice of life or death. You can choose either blessings or curses. But I want you to choose life. Then you and your children will live. <verse eid="DEU 30:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 30:20"/>And you will love the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. You will obey him. You will remain true to him. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is your very life. He will give you many years in the land. He promised to give that land to your fathers, to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob.<verse eid="DEU 30:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 30"/>
  <chapter number="31" style="c" sid="DEU 31"/>
  <para style="s1">Joshua Becomes the New Leader</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 31:1"/>Here are the words Moses spoke to all the Israelites. <verse eid="DEU 31:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 31:2"/>He said, “I am now 120 years old. I’m not able to lead you anymore. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has said to me, ‘You will not go across the Jordan River.’ <verse eid="DEU 31:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 31:3"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God himself will go across ahead of you. He’ll destroy the nations there in order to make room for you. You will take over their land. Joshua will also go across ahead of you, just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said he would. <verse eid="DEU 31:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 31:4"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will do to those nations what he did to Sihon and Og. He destroyed those Amorite kings along with their land. <verse eid="DEU 31:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 31:5"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will hand those nations over to you. Then you must do to them everything I’ve commanded you to do. <verse eid="DEU 31:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 31:6"/>Be strong and brave. Don’t be afraid of them. Don’t be terrified because of them. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will go with you. He will never leave you. He’ll never desert you.”<verse eid="DEU 31:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 31:7"/>Then Moses sent for Joshua. Moses spoke to him in front of all the Israelites. He said, “Be strong and brave. You must go with these people. They are going into the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> promised to give to their people of long ago. You must divide it up among them. They will each receive their share. <verse eid="DEU 31:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 31:8"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> himself will go ahead of you. He will be with you. He will never leave you. He’ll never desert you. So don’t be afraid. Don’t lose hope.”<verse eid="DEU 31:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Law Must Be Read to the People</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 31:9"/>Moses wrote down this law. He gave it to the priests, who are sons of Levi. They carried the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He also gave the law to all the elders of Israel. <verse eid="DEU 31:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 31:10"/>Then Moses commanded them, “You must read this law at the end of every seven years. Do it in the year when you forgive people what they owe. Read it during the Feast of Booths. <verse eid="DEU 31:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 31:11"/>That’s when all the Israelites come to appear in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God at the holy tent. It will be at the place he will choose. You must read this law to them. <verse eid="DEU 31:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 31:12"/>Gather the people together. Gather the men, women and children. Also bring together the outsiders living in your towns. Then they can listen and learn to have respect for the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. And they’ll be careful to obey all the words of this law. <verse eid="DEU 31:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 31:13"/>Their children must hear it read too. They don’t know this law yet. They too must learn to have respect for the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. They must honor him as long as you live in the land. You are about to go across the Jordan River and take that land as your very own.”<verse eid="DEU 31:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Israelites Will Refuse to Obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 31:14"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Moses, “The day when you will die is near. Have Joshua go to the tent of meeting. Join him there. That is where I will appoint him as the new leader.” So Joshua and Moses went to the tent of meeting.<verse eid="DEU 31:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 31:15"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> appeared at the tent in a pillar of cloud. It stood over the entrance to the tent. <verse eid="DEU 31:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 31:16"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, “You are going to join the members of your family who have already died. The Israelites will not be faithful to me. They will soon join themselves to the false gods that are worshiped in the land they are entering. The people will desert me. They will break the covenant I made with them. <verse eid="DEU 31:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 31:17"/>In that day I will become angry with them. I will desert them. I will turn my face away from them. And they will be destroyed. Many horrible troubles and hard times will come on them. On that day they will say, ‘Trouble has come on us. Our God isn’t with us!’ <verse eid="DEU 31:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 31:18"/>I will certainly turn away from them on that day. I will do it because they did a very evil thing when they turned to other gods.<verse eid="DEU 31:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 31:19"/>“I want you to write down a song and teach it to the Israelites. Have them sing it. It will be my witness against them. <verse eid="DEU 31:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 31:20"/>I will bring them into a land that has plenty of milk and honey. I promised the land to their people of long ago. In that land they will eat until they have had enough. They will get fat. When they do, they will turn to other gods and worship them. They will turn their backs on me. They will break my covenant. <verse eid="DEU 31:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 31:21"/>Many horrible troubles and hard times will come on them. Then the song I am giving you will be a witness against them. That is because the song will not be forgotten by their children and their children’s children. I know what they are likely to do. I know it even before I bring them into the land I promised them.” <verse eid="DEU 31:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 31:22"/>So that day Moses wrote the song down. And Moses taught it to the Israelites.<verse eid="DEU 31:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 31:23"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave a command to Joshua, the son of Nun. He said, “Be strong and brave. You will bring the Israelites into the land I promised them. I myself will be with you.”<verse eid="DEU 31:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 31:24"/>Moses finished writing the words of this law in a book. He wrote them down from beginning to end. <verse eid="DEU 31:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 31:25"/>Then he gave a command to the Levites who carried the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Moses said, <verse eid="DEU 31:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 31:26"/>“Take this Book of the Law. Place it beside the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. It will remain there as a witness against you. <verse eid="DEU 31:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 31:27"/>I know how you refuse to obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. I know how stubborn you are. You have refused to obey him while I’ve been living among you. So you will certainly refuse to obey him after I’m dead! <verse eid="DEU 31:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 31:28"/>Gather together all the elders of your tribes and all your officials. Bring them to me. Then I can speak these words to them. I can call for the heavens and the earth to be witnesses against them. <verse eid="DEU 31:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 31:29"/>I know that after I’m dead you will certainly become very sinful. You will turn away from the path I’ve commanded you to take. In days to come, trouble will fall on you. That’s because you will do what is evil in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. You will make him very angry because of the statues of gods your hands have made.”<verse eid="DEU 31:29"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Song of Moses</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 31:30"/>Moses spoke the words of this song from beginning to end. The whole community of Israel heard them. Here is what he said.<verse eid="DEU 31:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 31"/>
  <chapter number="32" style="c" sid="DEU 32"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 32:1"/>Heavens, listen to me. Then I will speak.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:1">Earth, hear the words of my mouth.<verse eid="DEU 32:1"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 32:2"/>Let my teaching fall like rain.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:2">Let my words come down like dew.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:2">Let them be like raindrops on new grass.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:2">Let them be like rain on tender plants.<verse eid="DEU 32:2"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 32:3"/>I will make known the name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:3">Praise God! How great he is!<verse eid="DEU 32:3"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 32:4"/>He is the Rock. His works are perfect.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:4">All his ways are right.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:4">He is faithful. He doesn’t do anything wrong.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:4">He is honest and fair.<verse eid="DEU 32:4"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 32:5"/>Israel, you have sinned against him very much.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:5">It’s too bad for you that you aren’t his children anymore.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:5">You have become a twisted and evil nation.<verse eid="DEU 32:5"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 32:6"/>Is that how you thank the <char style="nd">Lord</char>?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:6">You aren’t wise. You are foolish.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:6">Remember, he’s your Father. He’s your Creator.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:6">He made you. He formed you.<verse eid="DEU 32:6"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 32:7"/>Remember the days of long ago.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:7">Think about what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> did through those many years.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:7">Ask your father. He will tell you.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:7">Ask your elders. They’ll explain it to you.<verse eid="DEU 32:7"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 32:8"/>The Most High God gave the nations their lands.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:8">He divided up the human race.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:8">He set up borders for the nations.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:8">He did it based on the number of the angels in his heavenly court.<verse eid="DEU 32:8"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 32:9"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s people are his share.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:9">Jacob is the nation he has received.<verse eid="DEU 32:9"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 32:10"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> found Israel in a desert.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:10">He found them in an empty and windy land.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:10">He took care of them and kept them safe.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:10">He guarded them as he would guard his own eyes.<verse eid="DEU 32:10"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 32:11"/>He was like an eagle that stirs up its nest.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:11">It hovers over its little ones.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:11">It spreads out its wings to catch them.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:11">It carries them up in the air on its feathers.<verse eid="DEU 32:11"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 32:12"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> was the only one who led Israel.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:12">No other god was with them.<verse eid="DEU 32:12"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 32:13"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> made them ride on the highest places in the land.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:13">He fed them what grew in the fields.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:13">He gave them the sweetest honey.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:13">He fed them olive oil from a rocky hillside.<verse eid="DEU 32:13"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 32:14"/>He gave them butter and milk from the herds and flocks.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:14">He fed them the fattest lambs and goats.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:14">He gave them the best of Bashan’s rams.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:14">He fed them the finest wheat.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:14">They drank the bubbling red juice of grapes.<verse eid="DEU 32:14"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 32:15"/>When Israel grew fat, they became stubborn.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:15">When they were filled with food, they became fat and heavy.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:15">They left the God who made them.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:15">They turned away from the Rock who saved them.<verse eid="DEU 32:15"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 32:16"/>They made him jealous by serving false gods.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:16">They made him angry by worshiping statues of gods.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:16">He hated those gods.<verse eid="DEU 32:16"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 32:17"/>The people sacrificed to those false gods, not to God.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:17">They hadn’t known anything about those false gods.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:17">Those gods were new to them.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:17">Their people of long ago didn’t worship them.<verse eid="DEU 32:17"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 32:18"/>But then they deserted the Rock. He was their Father.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:18">They forgot the God who created them.<verse eid="DEU 32:18"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 32:19"/>When the <char style="nd">Lord</char> saw this, he turned away from them.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:19">His sons and daughters made him angry.<verse eid="DEU 32:19"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 32:20"/>“I will turn my face away from them,” he said.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:20">“I will see what will happen to them in the end.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:20">They are sinful people.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:20">They are unfaithful children.<verse eid="DEU 32:20"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 32:21"/>They made me jealous by serving what is not even a god.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:21">They made me angry by worshiping worthless statues of gods.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:21">I will use people who are not a nation to make them jealous.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:21">A nation that has no understanding will make them angry.<verse eid="DEU 32:21"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 32:22"/>My anger will start a fire.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:22">It will burn all the way down to the kingdom of the dead.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:22">It will eat up the earth and its crops.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:22">It will set the base of the mountains on fire.<verse eid="DEU 32:22"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 32:23"/>“I will pile troubles on my people.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:23">I will shoot all my arrows at them.<verse eid="DEU 32:23"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 32:24"/>I will send them hunger. It will make them weak.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:24">I will send terrible sickness. I will send deadly plagues.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:24">I will send wild animals that will tear them apart.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:24">Snakes that glide through the dust will bite them.<verse eid="DEU 32:24"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 32:25"/>In the streets their children will be killed by swords.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:25">Their homes will be filled with terror.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:25">The young men and women will die.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:25">The babies and old people will die.<verse eid="DEU 32:25"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 32:26"/>I said I would scatter them.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:26">I said I would erase their name from human memory.<verse eid="DEU 32:26"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 32:27"/>But I was afraid their enemies would make fun of that.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:27">I was afraid their attackers would not understand.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:27">I was sure they would say, ‘We’re the ones who’ve beaten them!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:27">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> isn’t the one who did it.’ ”<verse eid="DEU 32:27"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 32:28"/>Israel is a nation that doesn’t have any sense.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:28">They can’t understand anything.<verse eid="DEU 32:28"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 32:29"/>I wish they were wise. Then they would understand what’s coming.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:29">They’d realize what would happen to them in the end.<verse eid="DEU 32:29"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 32:30"/>How could one person chase a thousand?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:30">How could two make ten thousand run away?</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:30">It couldn’t happen unless their Rock had deserted them.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:30">It couldn’t take place unless the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had given them up.<verse eid="DEU 32:30"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 32:31"/>Their rock is not like our Rock.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:31">Even our enemies know that.<verse eid="DEU 32:31"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 32:32"/>Their vine comes from the vines of Sodom.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:32">It comes from the vineyards of Gomorrah.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:32">Their grapes are filled with poison.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:32">Their bunches of grapes taste bitter.<verse eid="DEU 32:32"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 32:33"/>Their wine is like the poison of snakes.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:33">It’s like the deadly poison of cobras.<verse eid="DEU 32:33"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 32:34"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> says, “I have kept all those terrible things stored away.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:34">I have kept them sealed up in my strongbox.<verse eid="DEU 32:34"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 32:35"/>I punish people. I will pay them back.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:35">The time will come when their feet will slip.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:35">Their day of trouble is near.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:35">Very soon they will be destroyed.”<verse eid="DEU 32:35"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 32:36"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will come to the aid of his people.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:36">He’ll show tender love to those who serve him.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:36">He will know when their strength is gone.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:36">He’ll see that no one at all is left.<verse eid="DEU 32:36"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 32:37"/>He’ll say, “Where are their gods now?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:37">Where is the rock they went to for safety?<verse eid="DEU 32:37"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="DEU 32:38"/>Where are the gods who ate the fat of their sacrifices?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:38">Where are the gods who drank the wine of their drink offerings?</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:38">Let those gods rise up to help you!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:38">Let them keep you safe!<verse eid="DEU 32:38"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="DEU 32:39"/>“Look! I am the One!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:39">There is no other God except me.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:39">I put some people to death. I bring others to life.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:39">I have wounded, and I will heal.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:39">No one can save you from my power.<verse eid="DEU 32:39"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="DEU 32:40"/>I raise my hand to heaven. Here is the promise I make.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:40">You can be sure that I live forever.<verse eid="DEU 32:40"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="DEU 32:41"/>And you can be just as sure</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:41">that I will sharpen my flashing sword.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:41">My hand will hold it when I judge.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:41">I will get even with my enemies.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:41">I will pay back those who hate me.<verse eid="DEU 32:41"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="DEU 32:42"/>I will make my arrows drip with blood.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:42">My sword will destroy people.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:42">It will kill some. It will even kill prisoners.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:42">It will cut off the heads of enemy leaders.”<verse eid="DEU 32:42"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="DEU 32:43"/>You nations, be full of joy. Be joyful together with God’s people.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:43">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will get even with his enemies.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:43">He will pay them back for killing those who serve him.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:43">He will wipe away the sin of his land and people.<verse eid="DEU 32:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="DEU 32:44"/>Moses spoke all the words of this song to the people. Joshua, the son of Nun, was with him. <verse eid="DEU 32:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="DEU 32:45"/>Moses finished speaking all these words to all the Israelites. <verse eid="DEU 32:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="DEU 32:46"/>Then he said to them, “Think carefully about all the words I have announced to you today. I want you to command your children to be careful to obey all the words of this law. <verse eid="DEU 32:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="DEU 32:47"/>They aren’t just useless words for you. They are your very life. If you obey them, you will live in the land for a long time. It’s the land you are going across the Jordan River to take as your own.”<verse eid="DEU 32:47"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Moses Will Die on Mount Nebo</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="DEU 32:48"/>On that same day the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Moses, <verse eid="DEU 32:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="DEU 32:49"/>“Go up into the Abarim mountains. Go to Mount Nebo in Moab. It is across from Jericho. From there look out over Canaan. It is the land I am giving the Israelites to take as their own. <verse eid="DEU 32:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="DEU 32:50"/>You will die there on the mountain you have climbed. You will join the members of your family who have already died. In the same way, your brother Aaron died on Mount Hor. He joined the members of his family who had already died. <verse eid="DEU 32:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="DEU 32:51"/>You and Aaron disobeyed me in front of the Israelites. It happened at the waters of Meribah Kadesh in the Desert of Zin. You did not honor me among the Israelites as the holy God. <verse eid="DEU 32:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="DEU 32:52"/>So you will see the land, but only from far away. You will not enter the land I am giving to the Israelites.”<verse eid="DEU 32:52"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 32"/>
  <chapter number="33" style="c" sid="DEU 33"/>
  <para style="s1">Moses Blesses the Tribes</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 33:1"/>Here is the blessing that Moses, the man of God, gave to the Israelites before he died. <verse eid="DEU 33:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 33:2"/>He said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:2">“The <char style="nd">Lord</char> came from Mount Sinai.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:2">Like the rising sun, he shone on his people from Mount Seir.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:2">He shone on them from Mount Paran.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:2">He came with large numbers of angels.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:2">He came from his mountain slopes in the south.<verse eid="DEU 33:2"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 33:3"/>
    <char style="nd">Lord</char>, I’m sure you love your people.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:3">All the holy ones are in your hands.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:3">At your feet all of them bow down.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:3">And you teach them.<verse eid="DEU 33:3"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 33:4"/>They learn the law Moses gave us.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:4">It belongs to the community of the people of Jacob.<verse eid="DEU 33:4"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 33:5"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> was king over Israel</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:5">when the leaders of the people came together.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:5">The tribes of Israel were also there.”<verse eid="DEU 33:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 33:6"/>Here’s what Moses said about Reuben.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:6">“Let Reuben live. Don’t let him die.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:6">And do not let his people be few.”<verse eid="DEU 33:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 33:7"/>Here’s what Moses said about Judah.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:7">“<char style="nd">Lord</char>, listen to Judah cry out.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:7">Bring him to his people.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:7">By his own power he stands up for himself.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:7">
    <char style="nd">Lord</char>, help him fight against his enemies!”<verse eid="DEU 33:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 33:8"/>Here’s what Moses said about Levi.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:8">“Your Thummim and Urim belong to your faithful servant.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:8">You tested him at Massah.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:8">You argued with him at the waters of Meribah.<verse eid="DEU 33:8"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 33:9"/>Levi didn’t show special favor to anyone.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:9">He did not spare his father and mother.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:9">He didn’t excuse his relatives or his children.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:9">But he watched over your word.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:9">He guarded your covenant.<verse eid="DEU 33:9"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 33:10"/>He teaches your rules to the people of Jacob.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:10">He teaches your law to Israel.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:10">He offers incense to you.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:10">He sacrifices whole burnt offerings on your altar.<verse eid="DEU 33:10"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 33:11"/>
    <char style="nd">Lord</char>, bless all his skills.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:11">Be pleased with everything he does.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:11">Destroy those who rise up against him.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:11">Strike down his enemies until they can’t get up.”<verse eid="DEU 33:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 33:12"/>Here’s what Moses said about Benjamin.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:12">“Let the one the <char style="nd">Lord</char> loves rest safely in him.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:12">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> guards him all day long.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:12">The one the <char style="nd">Lord</char> loves rests in his arms.”<verse eid="DEU 33:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 33:13"/>Here’s what Moses said about Joseph.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:13">“May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> bless Joseph’s land.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:13">May he bless it with dew from the highest heavens.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:13">May he bless it with water from the deepest oceans.<verse eid="DEU 33:13"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 33:14"/>May he bless it with the best crops the sun can produce.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:14">May he bless it with the finest crops the moon can give.<verse eid="DEU 33:14"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 33:15"/>May he bless it with the best products of the age-old mountains.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:15">May he bless it with the many crops of the ancient hills.<verse eid="DEU 33:15"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 33:16"/>May he bless it with the best gifts that fill the earth.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:16">May he bless it with the favor of the God who spoke out of the burning bush.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:16">Let all these blessings rest on the head of Joseph.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:16">Let them rest on the head of the one who is prince among his brothers.<verse eid="DEU 33:16"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 33:17"/>His glory is like the glory of a bull born first to its mother.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:17">His horns are like the horns of a wild ox.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:17">He will use them to destroy the nations.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:17">He’ll wipe out the nations that are very far away.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:17">The ten thousands of men in Ephraim’s army are like the bull and the ox.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:17">So are the thousands in the army of Manasseh.”<verse eid="DEU 33:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 33:18"/>Here’s what Moses said about Zebulun and Issachar.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:18">“Zebulun, be filled with joy when you go out.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:18">Issachar, be joyful in your tents.<verse eid="DEU 33:18"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 33:19"/>You will call for other people to go to the mountain.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:19">There you will offer the sacrifices of those who do what is right.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:19">You will enjoy the many good things your ships bring you.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:19">You will enjoy treasures that are hidden in the sand.”<verse eid="DEU 33:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 33:20"/>Here’s what Moses said about Gad.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:20">“May the God who gives Gad more land be praised!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:20">Gad lives there like a lion</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:20">that tears off arms and heads.<verse eid="DEU 33:20"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 33:21"/>He chose the best land for his livestock.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:21">The leader’s share was kept for him.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:21">The leaders of the people came together.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:21">Then Gad carried out the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s holy plan.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:21">He carried out the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s decisions for Israel.”<verse eid="DEU 33:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 33:22"/>Here’s what Moses said about Dan.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:22">“Dan is like a lion’s cub</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:22">that charges out of the land of Bashan.”<verse eid="DEU 33:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 33:23"/>Here’s what Moses said about Naphtali.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:23">“The <char style="nd">Lord</char> greatly favors Naphtali.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:23">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> fills him with his blessing.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:23">Naphtali’s land will reach south to the Sea of Galilee.”<verse eid="DEU 33:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 33:24"/>Here’s what Moses said about Asher.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:24">“Asher is the most blessed of sons.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:24">Let his brothers be kind to him.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:24">Let Asher wash his feet with olive oil.<verse eid="DEU 33:24"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 33:25"/>The bars of his gates will be made out of iron and bronze.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:25">His strength will last as long as he lives.<verse eid="DEU 33:25"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 33:26"/>“There is no one like the God of Israel.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:26">He rides across the heavens to help you.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:26">He rides on the clouds in his glory.<verse eid="DEU 33:26"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 33:27"/>God lives forever! You can run to him for safety.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:27">His powerful arms are always there to carry you.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:27">He will drive out your enemies to make room for you.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:27">He’ll say to you, ‘Destroy them!’<verse eid="DEU 33:27"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 33:28"/>So Israel will live in safety.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:28">Jacob will live secure</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:28">in a land that has grain and fresh wine.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:28">There the heavens drop their dew.<verse eid="DEU 33:28"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 33:29"/>Israel, how blessed you are!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:29">Who is like you?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:29">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has saved you.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:29">He keeps you safe. He helps you.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:29">He’s like a glorious sword to you.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:29">Your enemies will bow down to you in fear.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:29">You will walk on the highest places of their lands.”<verse eid="DEU 33:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 33"/>
  <chapter number="34" style="c" sid="DEU 34"/>
  <para style="s1">Moses Dies</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 34:1"/>Moses climbed Mount Nebo. He went up from the plains of Moab to the highest slopes of Pisgah. It’s across from Jericho. At Pisgah the <char style="nd">Lord</char> showed him the whole land from Gilead all the way to Dan. <verse eid="DEU 34:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 34:2"/>Moses saw the whole land of Naphtali. He saw the territory of Ephraim and Manasseh. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> showed him the whole land of Judah all the way to the Mediterranean Sea. <verse eid="DEU 34:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 34:3"/>Moses saw the Negev Desert. He saw the whole area from the Valley of Jericho all the way to Zoar. Jericho was also known as The City of Palm Trees. <verse eid="DEU 34:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 34:4"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, “This is the land I promised to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. I told them, ‘I will give this land to your children and their children.’ Moses, I have let you see it with your own eyes. But you will not go across the Jordan River to enter it.”<verse eid="DEU 34:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 34:5"/>Moses, the servant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, died there in Moab. It happened just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had said. <verse eid="DEU 34:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 34:6"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> buried the body of Moses in Moab. His grave is in the valley across from Beth Peor. But to this day no one knows where his grave is. <verse eid="DEU 34:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 34:7"/>Moses was 120 years old when he died. But his eyesight was still good. He was still very strong. <verse eid="DEU 34:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 34:8"/>The Israelites mourned over Moses on the plains of Moab for 30 days. They did it until their time for weeping and crying was over.<verse eid="DEU 34:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 34:9"/>Joshua, the son of Nun, was filled with wisdom. That’s because Moses had placed his hands on him. So the Israelites listened to Joshua. They did what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded Moses.<verse eid="DEU 34:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 34:10"/>Since then, Israel has never had a prophet like Moses. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> knew him face to face. <verse eid="DEU 34:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 34:11"/>Moses did many signs and amazing things. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> had sent him to do them in Egypt. Moses did them against Pharaoh, against all his officials and against his whole land. <verse eid="DEU 34:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 34:12"/>No one has ever had the mighty power Moses had. No one has ever done the wonderful acts he did in the sight of all the Israelites.<verse eid="DEU 34:12"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 34"/>
</usx>
