<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="EPH" style="id">- New International Readers Version 2014</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1995, 1996, 1998, 2014 by Biblica, Inc.</para>
  <para style="h">Ephesians</para>
  <para style="toc1">Ephesians</para>
  <para style="toc2">Ephesians</para>
  <para style="toc3">Eph</para>
  <para style="mt1">Ephesians</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">Paul wrote the letter that we call Ephesians. Paul spent at least two years in Ephesus, but this letter seems to be written to people he doesn’t know. Paul uses a pattern in writing this book. First, he explains the new identity believers have in Jesus the Messiah. After that, Paul explains what this new way of life means in practice.</para>
  <para style="ip">Paul begins by explaining that God has brought everything together under the rule of Jesus the Messiah. Jesus is above all things. Paul quotes from Psalm 8, which talks about the job that humans have. That task was to properly rule over all creation. Jesus has fulfilled the original task given to human beings. Paul also writes that Jews and Gentiles have been brought together into one family. Jesus is the head of this family. Through the renewing work of Jesus, God is making one new people. He is gathering people together from all over the world.</para>
  <para style="ip">Paul then tells these believers how to live. They must give up their old way of living. They are to live a way of life that is truly good and holy. They are to live a life of love and peace with their neighbors. God expects all the believers to serve each other. They are to respect each other just as they have respect for the Lord.</para>
  <para style="ip">Paul reminds these believers that they must remain strong against evil things. They must use everything God has provided to remain strong. And they must do that until the Lord returns. Then God will “bring together all things in heaven and on earth under Christ.”</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="EPH 1"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EPH 1:1"/>I, Paul, am writing this letter. I am an apostle of Christ Jesus just as God planned.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="EPH 1:1"/>
  <para style="p" vid="EPH 1:1">I am sending this letter to you, God’s holy people in Ephesus. Because you belong to Christ Jesus, you are faithful.<verse eid="EPH 1:1"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="EPH 1:2"/>May God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ give you grace and peace.<verse eid="EPH 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="s1">Praise God for His Spiritual Blessings in Christ</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="EPH 1:3"/>Give praise to the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ. He has blessed us with every spiritual blessing. Those blessings come from the heavenly world. They belong to us because we belong to Christ. <verse eid="EPH 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EPH 1:4"/>God chose us to belong to Christ before the world was created. He chose us to be holy and without blame in his eyes. He loved us. <verse eid="EPH 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EPH 1:5"/>So he decided long ago to adopt us. He adopted us as his children with all the rights children have. He did it because of what Jesus Christ has done. It pleased God to do it. <verse eid="EPH 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EPH 1:6"/>All those things bring praise to his glorious grace. God freely gave us his grace because of the One he loves. <verse eid="EPH 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EPH 1:7"/>We have been set free because of what Christ has done. Because he bled and died our sins have been forgiven. We have been set free because God’s grace is so rich. <verse eid="EPH 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EPH 1:8"/>He poured his grace on us. By giving us great wisdom and understanding, <verse eid="EPH 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EPH 1:9"/>he showed us the mystery of his plan. It was in keeping with what he wanted to do. It was what he had planned through Christ. <verse eid="EPH 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EPH 1:10"/>It will all come about when history has been completed. God will then bring together all things in heaven and on earth under Christ.<verse eid="EPH 1:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="EPH 1:11"/>We were also chosen to belong to him. God decided to choose us long ago in keeping with his plan. He works out everything to fit his plan and purpose. <verse eid="EPH 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EPH 1:12"/>We were the first to put our hope in Christ. We were chosen to bring praise to his glory. <verse eid="EPH 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EPH 1:13"/>You also became believers in Christ. That happened when you heard the message of truth. It was the good news about how you could be saved. When you believed, he stamped you with an official mark. That official mark is the Holy Spirit that he promised. <verse eid="EPH 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EPH 1:14"/>The Spirit marks us as God’s own. We can now be sure that someday we will receive all that God has promised. That will happen after God sets all his people completely free. All these things will bring praise to his glory.<verse eid="EPH 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Prays and Gives Thanks</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="EPH 1:15"/>I have heard about your faith in the Lord Jesus. I have also heard about your love for all God’s people. That is why <verse eid="EPH 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EPH 1:16"/>I have not stopped thanking God for you. I always remember you in my prayers. <verse eid="EPH 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EPH 1:17"/>I pray to the God of our Lord Jesus Christ. God is the glorious Father. I keep asking him to give you the wisdom and understanding that come from the Holy Spirit. I want you to know God better. <verse eid="EPH 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EPH 1:18"/>I pray that you may understand more clearly. Then you will know the hope God has chosen you to receive. You will know that what God will give his holy people is rich and glorious. <verse eid="EPH 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EPH 1:19"/>And you will know God’s great power. It can’t be compared with anything else. His power works for us who believe. It is the same mighty strength <verse eid="EPH 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EPH 1:20"/>God showed. He showed this when he raised Christ from the dead. God seated him at his right hand in his heavenly kingdom. <verse eid="EPH 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EPH 1:21"/>There Christ sits far above all who rule and have authority. He also sits far above all powers and kings. He is above every name that is appealed to in this world and in the world to come. <verse eid="EPH 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EPH 1:22"/>God placed all things under Christ’s rule. He appointed him to be ruler over everything for the church. <verse eid="EPH 1:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EPH 1:23"/>The church is Christ’s body and is filled by Christ. He fills everything in every way.<verse eid="EPH 1:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EPH 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="EPH 2"/>
  <para style="s1">God Has Given Us New Life Through Christ</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EPH 2:1"/>You were living in your sins and lawless ways. But in fact you were dead. <verse eid="EPH 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EPH 2:2"/>You used to live as sinners when you followed the ways of this world. You served the one who rules over the spiritual forces of evil. He is the spirit who is now at work in those who don’t obey God. <verse eid="EPH 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EPH 2:3"/>At one time we all lived among them. Our desires were controlled by sin. We tried to satisfy what they wanted us to do. We followed our desires and thoughts. God was angry with us like he was with everyone else. That’s because of the kind of people we all were. <verse eid="EPH 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EPH 2:4"/>But God loves us deeply. He is full of mercy. <verse eid="EPH 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EPH 2:5"/>So he gave us new life because of what Christ has done. He gave us life even when we were dead in sin. God’s grace has saved you. <verse eid="EPH 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EPH 2:6"/>God raised us up with Christ. He has seated us with him in his heavenly kingdom. That’s because we belong to Christ Jesus. <verse eid="EPH 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EPH 2:7"/>He has done it to show the riches of his grace for all time to come. His grace can’t be compared with anything else. He has shown it by being kind to us. He was kind to us because of what Christ Jesus has done. <verse eid="EPH 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EPH 2:8"/>God’s grace has saved you because of your faith in Christ. Your salvation doesn’t come from anything you do. It is God’s gift. <verse eid="EPH 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EPH 2:9"/>It is not based on anything you have done. No one can brag about earning it. <verse eid="EPH 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EPH 2:10"/>We are God’s creation. He created us to belong to Christ Jesus. Now we can do good works. Long ago God prepared these works for us to do.<verse eid="EPH 2:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God’s New Family of Jews and Gentiles</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="EPH 2:11"/>You who are not Jews by birth, here is what I want you to remember. You are called “uncircumcised” by those who call themselves “circumcised.” But they have only been circumcised in their bodies by human hands. <verse eid="EPH 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EPH 2:12"/>Before you believed in Christ, you were separated from him. You were not considered to be citizens of Israel. You were not included in what the covenants promised. You were without hope and without God in the world. <verse eid="EPH 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EPH 2:13"/>At one time you were far away from God. But now you belong to Christ Jesus. He spilled his blood for you. This has brought you near to God.<verse eid="EPH 2:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="EPH 2:14"/>Christ himself is our peace. He has made Jews and Gentiles into one group of people. He has destroyed the hatred that was like a wall between us. <verse eid="EPH 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EPH 2:15"/>Through his body on the cross, Christ set aside the law with all its commands and rules. He planned to create one new people out of Jews and Gentiles. He wanted to make peace between them. <verse eid="EPH 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EPH 2:16"/>He planned to bring both Jews and Gentiles back to God as one body. He planned to do this through the cross. On that cross, Christ put to death their hatred toward one another. <verse eid="EPH 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EPH 2:17"/>He came and preached peace to you who were far away. He also preached peace to those who were near. <verse eid="EPH 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EPH 2:18"/>Through Christ we both come to the Father by the power of one Holy Spirit.<verse eid="EPH 2:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="EPH 2:19"/>So you are no longer outsiders and strangers. You are citizens together with God’s people. You are also members of God’s family. <verse eid="EPH 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EPH 2:20"/>You are a building that is built on the apostles and prophets. They are the foundation. Christ Jesus himself is the most important stone in the building. <verse eid="EPH 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EPH 2:21"/>The whole building is held together by him. It rises to become a holy temple because it belongs to the Lord. <verse eid="EPH 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EPH 2:22"/>And because you belong to him, you too are being built together. You are being made into a house where God lives through his Spirit.<verse eid="EPH 2:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EPH 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="EPH 3"/>
  <para style="s1">God’s Wonderful Plan for the Gentiles</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EPH 3:1"/>I, Paul, am a prisoner because of Christ Jesus. I am in prison because of my work among you who are Gentiles.<verse eid="EPH 3:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="EPH 3:2"/>I am sure you have heard that God appointed me to share his grace with you. <verse eid="EPH 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EPH 3:3"/>I’m talking about the mystery God showed me. I have already written a little about it. <verse eid="EPH 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EPH 3:4"/>By reading about this mystery, you will be able to understand what I know. You will know about the mystery of Christ. <verse eid="EPH 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EPH 3:5"/>The mystery was not made known to people of other times. But now the Holy Spirit has made this mystery known to God’s holy apostles and prophets. <verse eid="EPH 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EPH 3:6"/>Here is the mystery. Because of the good news, God’s promises are for Gentiles as well as for Jews. Both groups are parts of one body. They share in the promise. It belongs to them because they belong to Christ Jesus.<verse eid="EPH 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="EPH 3:7"/>I now serve the good news because God gave me his grace. His power is at work in me. <verse eid="EPH 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EPH 3:8"/>I am by far the least important of all the Lord’s holy people. But he gave me the grace to preach to the Gentiles about the unlimited riches that Christ gives. <verse eid="EPH 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EPH 3:9"/>God told me to make clear to everyone how the mystery came about. In times past it was kept hidden in the mind of God, who created all things. <verse eid="EPH 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EPH 3:10"/>He wanted the rulers and authorities in the heavenly world to come to know his great wisdom. The church would make it known to them. <verse eid="EPH 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EPH 3:11"/>That was God’s plan from the beginning. He has fulfilled his plan through Christ Jesus our Lord. <verse eid="EPH 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EPH 3:12"/>Through him and through faith in him we can approach God. We can come to him freely. We can come without fear. <verse eid="EPH 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EPH 3:13"/>So here is what I’m asking you to do. Don’t lose hope because I am suffering for you. It will lead to the time when God will give you his glory.<verse eid="EPH 3:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Prays for the Ephesians</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="EPH 3:14"/>I bow in prayer to the Father because of my work among you. <verse eid="EPH 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EPH 3:15"/>From the Father every family in heaven and on earth gets its name. <verse eid="EPH 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EPH 3:16"/>I pray that he will use his glorious riches to make you strong. May his Holy Spirit give you his power deep down inside you. <verse eid="EPH 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EPH 3:17"/>Then Christ will live in your hearts because you believe in him. And I pray that your love will have deep roots. I pray that it will have a strong foundation. <verse eid="EPH 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EPH 3:18"/>May you have power together with all the Lord’s holy people to understand Christ’s love. May you know how wide and long and high and deep it is. <verse eid="EPH 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EPH 3:19"/>And may you know his love, even though it can’t be known completely. Then you will be filled with everything God has for you.<verse eid="EPH 3:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="EPH 3:20"/>God is able to do far more than we could ever ask for or imagine. He does everything by his power that is working in us. <verse eid="EPH 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EPH 3:21"/>Give him glory in the church and in Christ Jesus. Give him glory through all time and for ever and ever. Amen.<verse eid="EPH 3:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EPH 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="EPH 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Growing Up Together in the Body of Christ</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EPH 4:1"/>I am a prisoner because of the Lord. So I am asking you to live a life worthy of what God chose you for. <verse eid="EPH 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EPH 4:2"/>Don’t be proud at all. Be completely gentle. Be patient. Put up with one another in love. <verse eid="EPH 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EPH 4:3"/>The Holy Spirit makes you one in every way. So try your best to remain as one. Let peace keep you together. <verse eid="EPH 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EPH 4:4"/>There is one body and one Spirit. You were appointed to one hope when you were chosen. <verse eid="EPH 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EPH 4:5"/>There is one Lord, one faith and one baptism. <verse eid="EPH 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EPH 4:6"/>There is one God and Father of all. He is over everything. He is through everything. He is in everything.<verse eid="EPH 4:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="EPH 4:7"/>But each one of us has received a gift of grace. These gifts are given to us by Christ. <verse eid="EPH 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EPH 4:8"/>That is why Scripture says,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="EPH 4:8">“When he went up to his place on high,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="EPH 4:8">he took many prisoners.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="EPH 4:8">He gave gifts to his people.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 68:18">Psalm 68:18</ref>)</char><verse eid="EPH 4:8"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="EPH 4:9"/>What does “he went up” mean? It can only mean that he also came down to the lower, earthly places. <verse eid="EPH 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EPH 4:10"/>The one who came down is the same one who went up. He went up higher than all the heavens. He did it in order to fill all creation. <verse eid="EPH 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EPH 4:11"/>So Christ himself gave the gift of the apostles to the church. He gave the prophets and those who preach the good news. And he also gave the pastors and teachers as a gift to the church. <verse eid="EPH 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EPH 4:12"/>He gave all these people so that they might prepare God’s people to serve. Then the body of Christ will be built up. <verse eid="EPH 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EPH 4:13"/>That will continue until we all become one in the faith. We will also become one in the knowledge of God’s Son. Then we will be grown up in the faith. We will receive everything that Christ has for us.<verse eid="EPH 4:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="EPH 4:14"/>We will no longer be babies in the faith. We won’t be like ships tossed around by the waves. We won’t be blown here and there by every new teaching. We won’t be blown around by cleverness and tricks. Certain people use them to hide their evil plans. <verse eid="EPH 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EPH 4:15"/>Instead, we will speak the truth in love. So we will grow up in every way to become the body of Christ. Christ is the head of the body. <verse eid="EPH 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EPH 4:16"/>He makes the whole body grow and build itself up in love. Under the control of Christ, each part of the body does its work. It supports the other parts. In that way, the body is joined and held together.<verse eid="EPH 4:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Teachings for Living as Christians</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="EPH 4:17"/>Here is what I’m telling you. I am speaking for the Lord as I warn you. You must no longer live as the Gentiles do. Their thoughts don’t have any purpose. <verse eid="EPH 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EPH 4:18"/>They can’t understand the truth. They are separated from the life of God. That’s because they don’t know him. And they don’t know him because their hearts are stubborn. <verse eid="EPH 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EPH 4:19"/>They have lost all feeling for what is right. So they have given themselves over to all kinds of evil pleasures. They take part in every kind of unclean act. And they are full of greed.<verse eid="EPH 4:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="EPH 4:20"/>But that is not the way of life in Christ that you learned about. <verse eid="EPH 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EPH 4:21"/>You heard about Christ and were taught about life in him. What you learned was the truth about Jesus. <verse eid="EPH 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EPH 4:22"/>You were taught not to live the way you used to. You must get rid of your old way of life. That’s because it has been made impure by the desire for things that lead you astray. <verse eid="EPH 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EPH 4:23"/>You were taught to be made new in your thinking. <verse eid="EPH 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EPH 4:24"/>You were taught to start living a new life. It is created to be truly good and holy, just as God is.<verse eid="EPH 4:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="EPH 4:25"/>So each of you must get rid of your lying. Speak the truth to your neighbor. We are all parts of one body. <verse eid="EPH 4:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EPH 4:26"/>Scripture says, “When you are angry, do not sin.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 4:4">Psalm 4:4</ref>)</char> Do not let the sun go down while you are still angry. <verse eid="EPH 4:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EPH 4:27"/>Don’t give the devil a chance. <verse eid="EPH 4:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EPH 4:28"/>Anyone who has been stealing must never steal again. Instead, they must work. They must do something useful with their own hands. Then they will have something to give to people in need.<verse eid="EPH 4:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="EPH 4:29"/>Don’t let any evil talk come out of your mouths. Say only what will help to build others up and meet their needs. Then what you say will help those who listen. <verse eid="EPH 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EPH 4:30"/>Do not make God’s Holy Spirit mourn. The Holy Spirit is the proof that you belong to God. And the Spirit is the proof that God will set you completely free. <verse eid="EPH 4:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EPH 4:31"/>Get rid of all hard feelings, anger and rage. Stop all fighting and lying. Don’t have anything to do with any kind of hatred. <verse eid="EPH 4:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EPH 4:32"/>Be kind and tender to one another. Forgive one another, just as God forgave you because of what Christ has done.<verse eid="EPH 4:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EPH 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="EPH 5"/>
  <para style="nb">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EPH 5:1"/>You are the children that God dearly loves. So follow his example. <verse eid="EPH 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EPH 5:2"/>Lead a life of love, just as Christ did. He loved us. He gave himself up for us. He was a sweet-smelling offering and sacrifice to God.<verse eid="EPH 5:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="EPH 5:3"/>There should not be even a hint of sexual sin among you. Don’t do anything impure. And do not always want more and more. These are not the things God’s holy people should do. <verse eid="EPH 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EPH 5:4"/>There must not be any bad language or foolish talk or dirty jokes. They are out of place. Instead, you should give thanks. <verse eid="EPH 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EPH 5:5"/>Here is what you can be sure of. Those who give themselves over to sexual sins are lost. So are people whose lives are impure. The same is true of those who always want more and more. People who do these things might as well worship statues of gods. No one who does them will receive a share in the kingdom of Christ and of God. <verse eid="EPH 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EPH 5:6"/>Don’t let anyone fool you with worthless words. People who say things like that aren’t obeying God. He is angry with them. <verse eid="EPH 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EPH 5:7"/>So don’t go along with people like that.<verse eid="EPH 5:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="EPH 5:8"/>At one time you were in the dark. But now you are in the light because of what the Lord has done. Live like children of the light. <verse eid="EPH 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EPH 5:9"/>The light produces what is completely good, right and true. <verse eid="EPH 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EPH 5:10"/>Find out what pleases the Lord. <verse eid="EPH 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EPH 5:11"/>Have nothing to do with the acts of darkness. They don’t produce anything good. Show what they are really like. <verse eid="EPH 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EPH 5:12"/>It is shameful even to talk about what people who don’t obey do in secret. <verse eid="EPH 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EPH 5:13"/>But everything the light shines on can be seen. And everything that the light shines on becomes a light. <verse eid="EPH 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EPH 5:14"/>That is why it is said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="EPH 5:14">“Wake up, sleeper.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="EPH 5:14">Rise from the dead.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="EPH 5:14">Then Christ will shine on you.”<verse eid="EPH 5:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="EPH 5:15"/>So be very careful how you live. Do not live like people who aren’t wise. Live like people who are wise. <verse eid="EPH 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EPH 5:16"/>Make the most of every opportunity. The days are evil. <verse eid="EPH 5:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EPH 5:17"/>So don’t be foolish. Instead, understand what the Lord wants. <verse eid="EPH 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EPH 5:18"/>Don’t fill yourself up with wine. Getting drunk will lead to wild living. Instead, be filled with the Holy Spirit. <verse eid="EPH 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EPH 5:19"/>Speak to one another with psalms, hymns and songs from the Spirit. Sing and make music from your heart to the Lord. <verse eid="EPH 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EPH 5:20"/>Always give thanks to God the Father for everything. Give thanks to him in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ.<verse eid="EPH 5:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Teachings for Christian Families</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="EPH 5:21"/>Follow the lead of one another because of your respect for Christ.<verse eid="EPH 5:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="EPH 5:22"/>Wives, follow the lead of your own husbands as you follow the Lord. <verse eid="EPH 5:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EPH 5:23"/>The husband is the head of the wife, just as Christ is the head of the church. The church is Christ’s body. He is its Savior. <verse eid="EPH 5:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EPH 5:24"/>The church follows the lead of Christ. In the same way, wives should follow the lead of their husbands in everything.<verse eid="EPH 5:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="EPH 5:25"/>Husbands, love your wives. Love them just as Christ loved the church. He gave himself up for her. <verse eid="EPH 5:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EPH 5:26"/>He did it to make her holy. He made her clean by washing her with water and the word. <verse eid="EPH 5:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EPH 5:27"/>He did it to bring her to himself as a brightly shining church. He wants a church that has no stain or wrinkle or any other flaw. He wants a church that is holy and without blame. <verse eid="EPH 5:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EPH 5:28"/>In the same way, husbands should love their wives. They should love them as they love their own bodies. Any man who loves his wife loves himself. <verse eid="EPH 5:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="EPH 5:29"/>After all, no one ever hated their own body. Instead, they feed and care for their body. And this is what Christ does for the church. <verse eid="EPH 5:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EPH 5:30"/>We are parts of his body. <verse eid="EPH 5:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EPH 5:31"/>Scripture says, “That’s why a man will leave his father and mother and be joined to his wife. The two will become one.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="GEN 2:24">Genesis 2:24</ref>)</char> <verse eid="EPH 5:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EPH 5:32"/>That is a deep mystery. But I’m talking about Christ and the church. <verse eid="EPH 5:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="EPH 5:33"/>A husband also must love his wife. He must love her just as he loves himself. And a wife must respect her husband.<verse eid="EPH 5:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EPH 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="EPH 6"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EPH 6:1"/>Children, obey your parents as believers in the Lord. Obey them because it’s the right thing to do. <verse eid="EPH 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EPH 6:2"/>Scripture says, “Honor your father and mother.” That is the first commandment that has a promise. <verse eid="EPH 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EPH 6:3"/>“Then things will go well with you. You will live a long time on the earth.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="DEU 5:16">Deuteronomy 5:16</ref>)</char><verse eid="EPH 6:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="EPH 6:4"/>Fathers, don’t make your children angry. Instead, instruct them and teach them the ways of the Lord as you raise them.<verse eid="EPH 6:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="EPH 6:5"/>Slaves, obey your masters here on earth. Respect them and honor them with a heart that is true. Obey them just as you would obey Christ. <verse eid="EPH 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EPH 6:6"/>Don’t obey them only to please them when they are watching. Do it because you are slaves of Christ. Be sure your heart does what God wants. <verse eid="EPH 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EPH 6:7"/>Serve your masters with all your heart. Work as serving the Lord and not as serving people. <verse eid="EPH 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EPH 6:8"/>You know that the Lord will give each person a reward. He will give it to them in keeping with the good they do. It doesn’t matter whether they are a slave or not.<verse eid="EPH 6:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="EPH 6:9"/>Masters, treat your slaves in the same way. When you warn them, don’t be too hard on them. You know that the God who is their Master and yours is in heaven. And he treats everyone the same.<verse eid="EPH 6:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God’s Armor for Believers</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="EPH 6:10"/>Finally, let the Lord make you strong. Depend on his mighty power. <verse eid="EPH 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EPH 6:11"/>Put on all of God’s armor. Then you can remain strong against the devil’s evil plans. <verse eid="EPH 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EPH 6:12"/>Our fight is not against human beings. It is against the rulers, the authorities and the powers of this dark world. It is against the spiritual forces of evil in the heavenly world. <verse eid="EPH 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EPH 6:13"/>So put on all of God’s armor. Evil days will come. But you will be able to stand up to anything. And after you have done everything you can, you will still be standing. <verse eid="EPH 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EPH 6:14"/>So remain strong in the faith. Put the belt of truth around your waist. Put the armor of godliness on your chest. <verse eid="EPH 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EPH 6:15"/>Wear on your feet what will prepare you to tell the good news of peace. <verse eid="EPH 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EPH 6:16"/>Also, pick up the shield of faith. With it you can put out all the flaming arrows of the evil one. <verse eid="EPH 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EPH 6:17"/>Put on the helmet of salvation. And take the sword of the Holy Spirit. The sword is God’s word.<verse eid="EPH 6:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="EPH 6:18"/>At all times, pray by the power of the Spirit. Pray all kinds of prayers. Be watchful, so that you can pray. Always keep on praying for all the Lord’s people. <verse eid="EPH 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="EPH 6:19"/>Pray also for me. Pray that whenever I speak, the right words will be given to me. Then I can be bold as I tell the mystery of the good news. <verse eid="EPH 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EPH 6:20"/>Because of the good news, I am being held by chains as the Lord’s messenger. So pray that I will be bold as I preach the good news. That’s what I should do.<verse eid="EPH 6:20"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="s1">Final Greetings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="EPH 6:21"/>Tychicus is a dear brother. He is faithful in serving the Lord. He will tell you everything about me. Then you will know how I am and what I am doing. <verse eid="EPH 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EPH 6:22"/>That’s why I am sending him to you. I want you to know how we are. And I want him to encourage you.<verse eid="EPH 6:22"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="EPH 6:23"/>May God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ give peace to the brothers and sisters. May they also give the believers love and faith.<verse eid="EPH 6:23"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="EPH 6:24"/>May grace be given to everyone who loves our Lord Jesus Christ with a love that will never die.<verse eid="EPH 6:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EPH 6"/>
</usx>
