<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="EST" style="id">- New International Readers Version 2014</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1995, 1996, 1998, 2014 by Biblica, Inc.</para>
  <para style="h">Esther</para>
  <para style="toc1">Esther</para>
  <para style="toc2">Esther</para>
  <para style="toc3">Est</para>
  <para style="mt1">Esther</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">The story told in the book of Esther occurs during the time when Xerxes was king of Persia. The time of the story was about 450 years before Jesus Christ was born. During this time the people of Israel were prisoners and slaves living in Persia. The Israelites living there were also known as Jews.</para>
  <para style="ip">The book of Esther explains why these Jews began celebrating a new feast. Before this time, the Jews celebrated the feasts of Passover and Tabernacles. These feasts were described in the commands God gave Moses. These feasts reminded the Israelites of the mighty acts God used to rescue them. And so in the story of Esther, God once again saves the Jews. This great rescue is celebrated in the new feast called Purim.</para>
  <para style="ip">Esther and her cousin Mordecai are the key people in this story. They uncover an evil plan to destroy all the Jews. The story tells of Esther and Mordecai’s work in saving the Jews from that plan. And that story unfolds during the many banquets described. In the beginning there are two banquets given by King Xerxes. In the middle there are two banquets given by Esther. And at the end there are two banquets celebrated by the thankful Jews.</para>
  <para style="ip">The feast of Purim continued to be celebrated for a long time. In some places it is still celebrated today. During this feast the story of Esther and Mordecai is retold. Anyone who reads this story can join in celebrating God’s saving work. They can also ask themselves the same questions Mordecai asked Esther. What goal does God have in mind for us? What good things does God want us to do?</para>
  <para style="ip">It is interesting that the story never mentions God by name. Yet God’s hand of protection can be seen throughout the story. It can be seen in the timing of events. And it can be seen in the way the events come together. God rescued the Jews so that his saving purpose for the world could continue.</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="EST 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Vashti Is Removed From Her Position as Queen</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EST 1:1"/>King Xerxes ruled over the 127 territories in his kingdom. They reached from India all the way to Cush. Here is what happened during the time Xerxes ruled over the whole Persian kingdom. <verse eid="EST 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EST 1:2"/>He was ruling from his royal throne in the fort of Susa. <verse eid="EST 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EST 1:3"/>In the third year of his rule King Xerxes gave a feast. It was for all his nobles and officials. The military leaders of Persia and Media were there. So were the princes and the nobles of the territories he ruled over.<verse eid="EST 1:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="EST 1:4"/>Every day for 180 days he showed his guests the great wealth of his kingdom. He also showed them how glorious his kingdom was. <verse eid="EST 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EST 1:5"/>When those days were over, the king gave another feast. It lasted for seven days. It was held in the garden of the king’s courtyard. It was for all the people who lived in the fort of Susa. Everyone from the least important person to the most important was invited. <verse eid="EST 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EST 1:6"/>The garden was decorated with white and blue linen banners. They hung from ropes that were made out of white linen and purple cloth. The ropes were connected to silver rings on marble pillars. There were gold and silver couches in the garden. They were placed on a floor that was made out of small stones. The floor had purple crystal, marble, mother-of-pearl and other stones of great value. <verse eid="EST 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EST 1:7"/>Royal wine was served in gold cups. Each cup was different from all the others. There was plenty of wine. The king always provided as much as his guests wanted. <verse eid="EST 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EST 1:8"/>He commanded that they should be allowed to drink as much or as little as they wished. He directed all his servants to give his guests what they asked for.<verse eid="EST 1:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="EST 1:9"/>Queen Vashti also gave a feast. Only women were invited. It was held in the royal palace of King Xerxes.<verse eid="EST 1:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="EST 1:10"/>On the seventh day Xerxes was in a good mood because he had drunk a lot of wine. So he gave a command to the seven officials who served him. They were Mehuman, Biztha, Harbona, Bigtha, Abagtha, Zethar and Karkas. <verse eid="EST 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EST 1:11"/>King Xerxes told them to bring Queen Vashti to him. He wanted her to come wearing her royal crown. He wanted to show off her beauty to the people and nobles. She was lovely to look at. <verse eid="EST 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EST 1:12"/>The attendants told Queen Vashti what the king had ordered her to do. But she refused to come. So the king became very angry.<verse eid="EST 1:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="EST 1:13"/>It was the king’s practice to ask for advice about matters of law and fairness. So he spoke with the wise men who understood what was going on at that time. <verse eid="EST 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EST 1:14"/>They were the men closest to the king. Their names were Karshena, Shethar, Admatha, Tarshish, Meres, Marsena and Memukan. They were the seven nobles of Persia and Media. They were the king’s special advisers and the most important men in the kingdom.<verse eid="EST 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="EST 1:15"/>“You know the law,” the king said. “What should I do to Queen Vashti? She hasn’t obeyed my command. The officials told her what I ordered her to do, didn’t they?”<verse eid="EST 1:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="EST 1:16"/>Then Memukan gave a reply to the king and the nobles. He said, “Queen Vashti has done what is wrong. But she didn’t do it only against you, King Xerxes. She did it also against all the nobles. And she did it against the people in all the territories you rule over. <verse eid="EST 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EST 1:17"/>All the women will hear about what the queen has done. Then they won’t respect their husbands. They’ll say, ‘King Xerxes commanded Queen Vashti to be brought to him. But she wouldn’t come.’ <verse eid="EST 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EST 1:18"/>Here is what will start today. The leading women in Persia and Media who have heard about the queen’s actions will act in the same way. They’ll disobey all your nobles, just as she disobeyed you. They won’t have any respect for their husbands. They won’t honor them.<verse eid="EST 1:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="EST 1:19"/>“So if it pleases you, send out a royal order. Let it be written down in the laws of Persia and Media. Those laws can never be changed. Let the royal order say that Vashti can never see you again. Also let her position as queen be given to someone who is better than she is. <verse eid="EST 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EST 1:20"/>And let your order be announced all through your entire kingdom. Then all women will have respect for their husbands, from the least important to the most important.”<verse eid="EST 1:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="EST 1:21"/>The king and his nobles were pleased with that advice. So he did what Memukan had suggested. <verse eid="EST 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EST 1:22"/>The king sent messages out to every territory in the kingdom. He sent them to each territory in its own writing. He sent them to every nation in its own language. The messages announced that every man should rule over his own family, using his own language.<verse eid="EST 1:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EST 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="EST 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Esther Becomes Queen of Persia</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EST 2:1"/>Later, the great anger of King Xerxes calmed down. Then he remembered Vashti and what she had done. He also remembered the royal order he had sent out concerning her. <verse eid="EST 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EST 2:2"/>At that time the king’s personal attendants made a suggestion. They said, “King Xerxes, let a search be made for some beautiful young virgins for you. <verse eid="EST 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EST 2:3"/>Appoint some officials in every territory in your kingdom. Have them bring all these beautiful young women into the fort of Susa. Put them in the special place where the virgins stay. Then put Hegai in charge of them. He’s the official who serves you. He’s in charge of the women. Let beauty care be given to the new group of women. <verse eid="EST 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EST 2:4"/>Then let the young woman who pleases you the most become queen in Vashti’s place.” The king liked that advice. So he followed it.<verse eid="EST 2:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="EST 2:5"/>There was a Jew living in the fort of Susa. He was from the tribe of Benjamin. His name was Mordecai. He was the son of Jair. Jair was the son of Shimei. Shimei was the son of Kish. <verse eid="EST 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EST 2:6"/>Nebuchadnezzar had forced Mordecai to leave Jerusalem. He was among the prisoners who were carried off along with Jehoiachin. Jehoiachin had been king of Judah. Nebuchadnezzar was king of Babylon. <verse eid="EST 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EST 2:7"/>Mordecai had a cousin named Hadassah. He had raised her because she didn’t have a father or mother. Hadassah was also called Esther. She had a lovely figure and was very beautiful. Mordecai had adopted her as his own daughter. He had done it when her father and mother died.<verse eid="EST 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="EST 2:8"/>After the king’s order and law were announced, many young women were brought to the fort of Susa. Hegai was put in charge of them. Esther was also taken to the king’s palace. She was put under the control of Hegai. He was in charge of the place where the virgins stayed. <verse eid="EST 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EST 2:9"/>Esther pleased him. He showed her how happy he was with her. Right away he provided her with her beauty care and special food. He appointed seven female attendants to help her. They were chosen from the king’s palace. He moved her and her attendants into the best part of the place where the virgins stayed.<verse eid="EST 2:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="EST 2:10"/>Esther hadn’t told anyone who her people were. She hadn’t talked about her family. That’s because Mordecai had told her not to. <verse eid="EST 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EST 2:11"/>Mordecai tried to find out how Esther was getting along. He wanted to know what was happening to her. So he walked back and forth near the courtyard by the place where the virgins stayed. He did it every day.<verse eid="EST 2:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="EST 2:12"/>Each young woman had to complete 12 months of beauty care. They used oil of myrrh for six months. And they used perfume and makeup for the other six months. A virgin’s turn to go in to King Xerxes could come only after a full 12 months had passed. <verse eid="EST 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EST 2:13"/>And here is how she would go to the king. She would be given anything she wanted from the place where the virgins stayed. She could take it with her to the king’s palace. <verse eid="EST 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EST 2:14"/>In the evening she would go there. In the morning she would leave. Then she would go to the special place where the king’s concubines stayed. She would be put under the control of Shaashgaz. He was the king’s official who was in charge of the concubines. She would never return to the king unless he was pleased with her. He had to send for her by name before she could go to him again.<verse eid="EST 2:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="EST 2:15"/>Mordecai had adopted Esther. She had been the daughter of his uncle Abihail. Her turn came to go in to the king. She only asked for what Hegai suggested. He was the king’s official who was in charge of the place where the virgins stayed. Everyone who saw Esther was pleased with her. <verse eid="EST 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EST 2:16"/>She was taken to King Xerxes in the royal house. It was now the tenth month. That was the month of Tebeth. It was the seventh year of the rule of Xerxes.<verse eid="EST 2:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="EST 2:17"/>The king liked Esther more than he liked any of the other women. She pleased him more than any of the other virgins. So he put a royal crown on her head. He made her queen in Vashti’s place. <verse eid="EST 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="EST 2:18"/>Then the king gave a feast to honor Esther. All his nobles and officials were invited. He announced a holiday all through the territories he ruled over. He freely gave many gifts in keeping with his royal wealth.<verse eid="EST 2:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Mordecai Uncovers a Plan to Kill the King</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="EST 2:19"/>The virgins were gathered together a second time. At that time Mordecai was sitting at the palace gate. <verse eid="EST 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="EST 2:20"/>Esther had kept her family history a secret. She hadn’t told anyone who her people were. Mordecai had told her not to. She continued to follow his directions. That’s what she had always done when he was bringing her up.<verse eid="EST 2:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="EST 2:21"/>Bigthana and Teresh were two of the king’s officers. They guarded the door of the royal palace. They became angry with King Xerxes. So they decided to kill him. They made their evil plans while Mordecai was sitting at the palace gate. <verse eid="EST 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EST 2:22"/>So Mordecai found out about it and told Queen Esther. Then she reported it to the king. She told him that Mordecai had uncovered the plans against him. <verse eid="EST 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="EST 2:23"/>Some people checked Esther’s report. And they found out it was true. So the two officials were put to death. Then poles were stuck through them. They were set up where people could see them. All of that was written in the official records. It was written down while the king was watching.<verse eid="EST 2:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EST 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="EST 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Haman Plans to Destroy the Jews</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EST 3:1"/>After those events, King Xerxes honored Haman. Haman was the son of Hammedatha. He was from the family line of Agag. The king gave Haman a higher position than he had before. He gave him a seat of honor. It was higher than the positions any of the other nobles had. <verse eid="EST 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EST 3:2"/>All the royal officials at the palace gate got down on their knees. They gave honor to Haman. That’s because the king had commanded them to do it. But Mordecai refused to get down on his knees. He wouldn’t give Haman any honor at all.<verse eid="EST 3:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="EST 3:3"/>The royal officials at the palace gate asked Mordecai a question. They said, “Why don’t you obey the king’s command?” <verse eid="EST 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EST 3:4"/>Day after day they spoke to him. But he still refused to obey. So they told Haman about it. They wanted to see whether he would let Mordecai get away with what he was doing. Mordecai had told them he was a Jew.<verse eid="EST 3:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="EST 3:5"/>Haman noticed that Mordecai wouldn’t get down on his knees. He wouldn’t give Haman any honor. So Haman was very angry. <verse eid="EST 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EST 3:6"/>But he had found out who Mordecai’s people were. So he didn’t want to kill only Mordecai. He also looked for a way to destroy all Mordecai’s people. They were Jews. He wanted to kill all of them everywhere in the kingdom of Xerxes.<verse eid="EST 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="EST 3:7"/>The lot was cast in front of Haman. The lot was called Pur. It was cast in the first month of the 12th year that Xerxes was king. That month was called Nisan. The lot was cast to choose a day and a month. The month chosen was the 12th month. That month was called Adar.<verse eid="EST 3:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="EST 3:8"/>Then Haman said to King Xerxes, “Certain people are scattered among the nations. They live in all the territories in your kingdom. They keep themselves separate from everyone else. Their practices are different from the practices of all other people. They don’t obey your laws. It really isn’t good for you to put up with them. <verse eid="EST 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EST 3:9"/>If it pleases you, give the order to destroy them. I’ll even add 375 tons of silver to the king’s officials for the royal treasures.”<verse eid="EST 3:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="EST 3:10"/>So the king took his ring off his finger. The ring had his royal seal on it. He gave the ring to Haman. Haman was the son of Hammedatha, the Agagite. Haman was the enemy of the Jews. <verse eid="EST 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EST 3:11"/>“Keep the money,” the king said to Haman. “Do what you want to with those people.”<verse eid="EST 3:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="EST 3:12"/>The king sent for the royal secretaries. It was the 13th day of the first month. The secretaries wrote down all Haman’s orders. They wrote them down in the writing of each territory in the kingdom. They also wrote them in the language of each nation. The orders were sent to the royal officials and to the governors of the territories. And the orders were also sent to the nobles of the nations. The orders were written in the name of King Xerxes himself. And they were stamped with his own official mark. <verse eid="EST 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EST 3:13"/>They were carried by messengers. They were sent to all the king’s territories. The orders commanded people to destroy, kill and wipe out all the Jews. That included young people and old people alike. It included women and children. All the Jews were supposed to be killed on a single day. That day was the 13th day of the 12th month. It was the month of Adar. The orders also commanded people to take everything that belonged to the Jews. <verse eid="EST 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EST 3:14"/>A copy of the order had to be sent out as law. It had to be sent to every territory in the kingdom. It had to be announced to the people of every nation. Then they would be ready for that day.<verse eid="EST 3:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="EST 3:15"/>The king commanded the messengers to go out. So they did. The order was sent out from the fort of Susa. Then the king and Haman sat down to drink wine. But the people in the city were bewildered.<verse eid="EST 3:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EST 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="EST 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Mordecai Talks Esther Into Helping the Jews</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EST 4:1"/>Mordecai found out about everything that had been done. So he tore his clothes. He put on the rough clothing people wear when they’re sad. He sat down in ashes. Then he went out into the city. He wept out loud. He cried bitter tears. <verse eid="EST 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EST 4:2"/>But he only went as far as the palace gate. That’s because no one dressed in that rough clothing was allowed to go through it. <verse eid="EST 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EST 4:3"/>All the Jews were very sad. They didn’t eat anything. They wept and cried. Many of them put on the rough clothing people wear when they’re sad. They were lying down in ashes. They did all these things in every territory where the king’s order and law had been sent.<verse eid="EST 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="EST 4:4"/>Esther’s male and female attendants came to her. They told her about Mordecai. So she became very troubled. She wanted him to take off his rough clothing. So she sent him other clothes to wear. But he wouldn’t accept them. <verse eid="EST 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="EST 4:5"/>Then Esther sent for Hathak. He was one of the king’s officials. He had been appointed to take care of her. She ordered him to find out what was troubling Mordecai. She wanted to know why he was so upset.<verse eid="EST 4:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="EST 4:6"/>So Hathak went out to see Mordecai. He was in the open area in front of the palace gate. <verse eid="EST 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EST 4:7"/>Mordecai told him everything that had happened to him. He told him about the exact amount of money Haman had promised to add to the royal treasures. He said Haman wanted it to be used to pay some men to destroy the Jews. <verse eid="EST 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EST 4:8"/>Mordecai also gave Hathak a copy of the order. It commanded people to wipe out the Jews. The order had been sent from Susa. Mordecai told Hathak to show the order to Esther. He wanted Hathak to explain it to her. Mordecai told him to tell her to go and beg the king for mercy. Mordecai wanted her to make an appeal to the king for her people.<verse eid="EST 4:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="EST 4:9"/>Hathak went back and reported to Esther what Mordecai had said. <verse eid="EST 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EST 4:10"/>Then Esther directed him to give an answer to Mordecai. She told him to say, <verse eid="EST 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EST 4:11"/>“There is a certain law that everyone knows about. All the king’s officials know about it. The people in the royal territories know about it. It applies to any man or woman who approaches the king in the inner courtyard without being sent for. It says they must be put to death. But there is a way out. Suppose the king reaches out his gold scepter toward them. Then their lives will be spared. But 30 days have gone by since the king sent for me.”<verse eid="EST 4:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="EST 4:12"/>Esther’s words were reported to Mordecai. <verse eid="EST 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EST 4:13"/>Then he sent back an answer. He said, “You live in the king’s palace. But don’t think that just because you are there you will be the only Jew who will escape. <verse eid="EST 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EST 4:14"/>What if you don’t say anything at this time? Then help for the Jews will come from another place. But you and your family will die. Who knows? It’s possible that you became queen for a time just like this.”<verse eid="EST 4:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="EST 4:15"/>Then Esther sent a reply to Mordecai. She said, <verse eid="EST 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EST 4:16"/>“Go. Gather together all the Jews who are in Susa. And fast for my benefit. Don’t eat or drink anything for three days. Don’t do it night or day. I and my attendants will fast just as you do. Then I’ll go to the king. I’ll do it even though it’s against the law. And if I have to die, I’ll die.”<verse eid="EST 4:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="EST 4:17"/>So Mordecai went away. He carried out all Esther’s directions.<verse eid="EST 4:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EST 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="EST 5"/>
  <para style="s1">Esther Asks the King for a Favor</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EST 5:1"/>On the third day Esther put on her royal robes. She stood in the inner courtyard of the palace. It was in front of the king’s hall. The king was sitting on his royal throne in the hall. He was facing the entrance. <verse eid="EST 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EST 5:2"/>He saw Queen Esther standing in the courtyard. He was pleased with her. So he reached out toward her the gold scepter that was in his hand. Then Esther approached him. She touched the tip of the scepter.<verse eid="EST 5:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="EST 5:3"/>The king asked, “What is it, Queen Esther? What do you want? I’ll give it to you. I’ll even give you up to half of my kingdom.”<verse eid="EST 5:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="EST 5:4"/>Esther replied, “King Xerxes, if it pleases you, come to a feast today. I’ve prepared it for you. Please have Haman come with you.”<verse eid="EST 5:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="EST 5:5"/>“Bring Haman at once,” the king said to his servants. “Then we’ll do what Esther asks.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="EST 5:5">So the king and Haman went to the feast Esther had prepared. <verse eid="EST 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EST 5:6"/>As they were drinking wine, the king asked Esther the same question again. He said, “What do you want? I’ll give it to you. What do you want me to do for you? I’ll even give you up to half of my kingdom.”<verse eid="EST 5:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="EST 5:7"/>Esther replied, “Here is what I want. Here is my appeal to you. <verse eid="EST 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EST 5:8"/>I hope you will be pleased to give me what I want. And I hope you will be pleased to listen to my appeal. If you are, I’d like you and Haman to come tomorrow to the feast I’ll prepare for you. Then I’ll answer your question.”<verse eid="EST 5:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Haman Is Very Angry With Mordecai</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="EST 5:9"/>That day Haman was happy. So he left the palace in a good mood. But then he saw Mordecai at the palace gate. He noticed that Mordecai didn’t stand up when he walked by. In fact, Mordecai didn’t have any respect for him at all. So he was very angry with him. <verse eid="EST 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EST 5:10"/>But Haman was able to control himself. He went on home.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="EST 5:10">Haman called together his friends and his wife Zeresh. <verse eid="EST 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="EST 5:11"/>He bragged to them about how rich he was. He talked about how many sons he had. He spoke about all the ways the king had honored him. He bragged about how the king had given him a high position. It was higher than the position of any of the other nobles and officials. <verse eid="EST 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EST 5:12"/>“And that’s not all,” Haman added. “I’m the only person Queen Esther invited to come with the king to the feast she gave. Now she has invited me along with the king tomorrow. <verse eid="EST 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EST 5:13"/>But even all of that doesn’t satisfy me. I won’t be satisfied as long as I see that Jew Mordecai sitting at the palace gate.”<verse eid="EST 5:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="EST 5:14"/>Haman’s wife Zeresh and all his friends said to him, “Get a pole. In the morning, ask the king to have Mordecai put to death. Have the pole stuck through his body. Set it up at a place where it will be 75 feet above the ground. Everyone will be able to see it there. Then go to the feast with the king. Have a good time.” Haman was delighted with that suggestion. So he got the pole ready.<verse eid="EST 5:14"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EST 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="EST 6"/>
  <para style="s1">The King Honors Mordecai</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EST 6:1"/>That night the king couldn’t sleep. So he ordered the official records of his rule to be brought in. He ordered someone to read them to him. <verse eid="EST 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EST 6:2"/>What Mordecai had done was written there. He had uncovered the plans of Bigthana and Teresh. They were two of the king’s officers who guarded the door of the royal palace. They had decided to kill King Xerxes.<verse eid="EST 6:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="EST 6:3"/>“What great honor has Mordecai received for doing that?” the king asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="EST 6:3">“Nothing has been done for him,” his attendants answered.<verse eid="EST 6:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="EST 6:4"/>The king asked, “Who is in the courtyard?” Haman had just entered the outer courtyard of the palace. He had come to speak to the king about putting Mordecai to death. He wanted to talk about putting Mordecai’s body on the pole he had prepared for him.<verse eid="EST 6:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="EST 6:5"/>The king’s attendants said to him, “Haman is standing in the courtyard.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="EST 6:5">“Bring him in,” the king ordered.<verse eid="EST 6:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="EST 6:6"/>Haman entered. Then the king asked him, “What should be done for the man I want to honor?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="EST 6:6">Haman said to himself, “Is there anyone the king would rather honor than me?” <verse eid="EST 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EST 6:7"/>So he answered the king. He said, “Here is what you should do for the man you want to honor. <verse eid="EST 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EST 6:8"/>Have your servants get a royal robe you have worn. Have them bring a horse you have ridden on. Have a royal mark placed on its head. <verse eid="EST 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EST 6:9"/>Then give the robe and horse to one of your most noble princes. Let the robe be put on the man you want to honor. Let him be led on the horse through the city streets. Let people announce in front of him, ‘This is what is done for the man the king wants to honor!’ ”<verse eid="EST 6:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="EST 6:10"/>“Go right away,” the king commanded Haman. “Get the robe. Bring the horse. Do exactly what you have suggested. Do it for Mordecai the Jew. He’s sitting out there at the palace gate. Make sure you do everything you have suggested.”<verse eid="EST 6:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="EST 6:11"/>So Haman got the robe and the horse. He put the robe on Mordecai. And he led him on horseback through the city streets. He walked along in front of him and announced, “This is what is done for the man the king wants to honor!”<verse eid="EST 6:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="EST 6:12"/>After that, Mordecai returned to the palace gate. But Haman rushed home. He covered his head because he was very sad. <verse eid="EST 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EST 6:13"/>He told his wife Zeresh everything that had happened to him. He also told all his friends.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="EST 6:13">His advisers and his wife Zeresh spoke to him. They said, “Your fall from power started with Mordecai. He’s a Jew. So now you can’t stand up against him. You are going to be destroyed!” <verse eid="EST 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="EST 6:14"/>They were still talking with him when the king’s officials arrived. They hurried Haman away to the feast Esther had prepared.<verse eid="EST 6:14"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EST 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="EST 7"/>
  <para style="s1">Haman Is Put to Death</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EST 7:1"/>So the king and Haman went to Queen Esther’s feast. <verse eid="EST 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EST 7:2"/>They were drinking wine on the second day. The king again asked, “What do you want, Queen Esther? I’ll give it to you. What do you want me to do for you? I’ll even give you up to half of my kingdom.”<verse eid="EST 7:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="EST 7:3"/>Then Queen Esther answered, “Your Majesty, I hope you will be pleased to let me live. That’s what I want. Please spare my people. That’s my appeal to you. <verse eid="EST 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EST 7:4"/>My people and I have been sold to be destroyed. We’ve been sold to be killed and wiped out. Suppose we had only been sold as male and female slaves. Then I wouldn’t have said anything. That kind of suffering wouldn’t be a good enough reason to bother you.”<verse eid="EST 7:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="EST 7:5"/>King Xerxes asked Queen Esther, “Who is the man who has dared to do such a thing? And where is he?”<verse eid="EST 7:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="EST 7:6"/>Esther said, “The man hates us! He’s our enemy! He’s this evil Haman!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="EST 7:6">Then Haman was terrified in front of the king and queen. <verse eid="EST 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EST 7:7"/>The king got up. He was very angry. He left his wine and went out into the palace garden. But Haman realized that the king had already decided what he was going to do to him. So he stayed behind to beg Queen Esther for his life.<verse eid="EST 7:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="EST 7:8"/>The king returned from the palace garden to the dinner hall. Just then he saw Haman falling on the couch where Esther was lying.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="EST 7:8">The king shouted, “Will he even treat the queen like this? Will he harm her while she’s right here with me in the palace?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="EST 7:8">As soon as the king finished speaking, his men covered Haman’s face. <verse eid="EST 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EST 7:9"/>Then Harbona said, “There’s a pole standing near Haman’s house. He has prepared it for Mordecai. Mordecai is the one who spoke up to help you. Haman had planned to have him put to death. He was going to have the pole stuck through his body. Then he was going to set it up at a place where it would be 75 feet above the ground.” Harbona was one of the officials who attended the king.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="EST 7:9">The king said to his men, “Put Haman to death! Stick the pole through his body! Set it up where everyone can see it!” <verse eid="EST 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EST 7:10"/>So they did. And they used the pole Haman had prepared for Mordecai. Then the king’s anger calmed down.<verse eid="EST 7:10"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EST 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="EST 8"/>
  <para style="s1">The King Allows the Jews to Fight for Their Lives</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EST 8:1"/>That same day King Xerxes gave Queen Esther everything Haman had owned. Haman had been the enemy of the Jews. Esther had told the king that Mordecai was her cousin. So Mordecai came to see the king. <verse eid="EST 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EST 8:2"/>The king took his ring off. It had his royal mark on it. He had taken it back from Haman. Now he gave it to Mordecai. And Esther put Mordecai in charge of everything Haman had owned.<verse eid="EST 8:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="EST 8:3"/>Esther made another appeal to the king. She fell at his feet and wept. She begged him to put an end to the evil plan of Haman, the Agagite. He had decided to kill the Jews. <verse eid="EST 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EST 8:4"/>The king reached out his gold scepter toward Esther. She got up and stood in front of him.<verse eid="EST 8:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="EST 8:5"/>She said, “King Xerxes, I hope you will think what I’m asking is the right thing to do. I hope you are pleased with me. If you are, and if it pleases you, let an order be written. Let it take the place of the messages Haman wrote. Haman was the son of Hammedatha, the Agagite. He planned to kill the Jews. He wrote orders to destroy us in all your territories. <verse eid="EST 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EST 8:6"/>I couldn’t stand by and see the horrible trouble that would fall on my people! I couldn’t stand to see my family destroyed!”<verse eid="EST 8:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="EST 8:7"/>King Xerxes gave a reply to Queen Esther and Mordecai the Jew. He said, “Haman attacked the Jews. So I’ve given Esther everything he owned. My men have stuck a pole through his dead body. And they’ve set it up where everyone can see it. <verse eid="EST 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EST 8:8"/>Now write another order in my name. Do it for the benefit of the Jews. Do what seems best to you. Stamp the order with my royal mark. Nothing that is written in my name and stamped with my mark can ever be changed.”<verse eid="EST 8:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="EST 8:9"/>Right away the king sent for the royal secretaries. It was the 23rd day of the third month. That was the month of Sivan. They wrote down all Mordecai’s orders to the Jews. They also wrote them to the royal officials, the governors and the nobles of the 127 territories in his kingdom. The territories reached from India all the way to Cush. The orders were written down in the writing of each territory. They were written in the language of each nation. They were also written to the Jews in their own writing and language. <verse eid="EST 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EST 8:10"/>Mordecai wrote the orders in the name of King Xerxes. He stamped them with the king’s royal mark. He sent them by messengers on horseback. They rode fast horses that were raised just for the king.<verse eid="EST 8:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="EST 8:11"/>The Jews in every city could now gather together and fight for their lives. The king’s order gave them that right. But suppose soldiers from any nation or territory attacked them, their women or children. Then the Jews could destroy, kill and wipe out those soldiers. They could also take the goods that belonged to their enemies. <verse eid="EST 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EST 8:12"/>A day was appointed for the Jews to do that in all the king’s territories. It was the 13th day of the 12th month. That was the month of Adar. <verse eid="EST 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="EST 8:13"/>A copy of the order was sent out as law in every territory. It was announced to the people of every nation. So the Jews would be ready on that day. They could pay back their enemies.<verse eid="EST 8:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="EST 8:14"/>The messengers rode on the royal horses. They raced along. That’s what the king commanded them to do. The order was also sent out in the fort of Susa.<verse eid="EST 8:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Jews Win the Battle Over Their Enemies</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="EST 8:15"/>Mordecai left the king and went on his way. Mordecai was wearing royal clothes when he went. They were blue and white. He was also wearing a large gold crown. And he was wearing a purple coat. It was made out of fine linen. The city of Susa celebrated with great joy. <verse eid="EST 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="EST 8:16"/>The Jews were filled with joy and happiness. They were very glad because now they were being honored. <verse eid="EST 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EST 8:17"/>They celebrated and enjoyed good food. They were glad and full of joy. That was true everywhere the king’s order came. It was true in every territory and every city. Many people from other nations announced that they had become Jews. That’s because they were so afraid of the Jews.<verse eid="EST 8:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EST 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="EST 9"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EST 9:1"/>The king’s order had to be carried out on the 13th day of the 12th month. That was the month of Adar. On that day the enemies of the Jews had hoped to win the battle over them. But now everything had changed. The Jews had gained the advantage over those who hated them. <verse eid="EST 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EST 9:2"/>The Jews gathered together in their cities. They gathered in all the territories King Xerxes ruled over. They came together to attack those who were trying to destroy them. No one could stand up against them. The people from all the other nations were afraid of them. <verse eid="EST 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EST 9:3"/>All the nobles in the territories helped the Jews. So did the royal officials, the governors and the king’s officers. That’s because they were so afraid of Mordecai. <verse eid="EST 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="EST 9:4"/>He was well known in the palace. His fame spread all through the territories. So he became more and more important.<verse eid="EST 9:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="EST 9:5"/>The Jews struck down with swords all their enemies. They killed them and destroyed them. They did what they pleased to those who hated them. <verse eid="EST 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="EST 9:6"/>The Jews killed 500 men. They destroyed them in the fort of Susa. <verse eid="EST 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="EST 9:7"/>They also killed Parshandatha, Dalphon, Aspatha, <verse eid="EST 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="EST 9:8"/>Poratha, Adalia, Aridatha, <verse eid="EST 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="EST 9:9"/>Parmashta, Arisai, Aridai and Vaizatha. <verse eid="EST 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="EST 9:10"/>They were the ten sons of Haman. He was the son of Hammedatha. Haman had been the enemy of the Jews. They didn’t take anything that belonged to their enemies.<verse eid="EST 9:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="EST 9:11"/>A report was brought to the king that same day. He was told how many men had been killed in the fort of Susa. <verse eid="EST 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="EST 9:12"/>He said to Queen Esther, “The Jews have killed 500 men. They destroyed them in the fort of Susa. They also killed the ten sons of Haman there. What have they done in the rest of my territories? Now what do you want? I’ll give it to you. What do you want me to do for you? I’ll do that too.”<verse eid="EST 9:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="EST 9:13"/>“If it pleases you,” Esther answered, “let the Jews in Susa carry out today’s order tomorrow also. Stick poles through the dead bodies of Haman’s ten sons. Set them up where everyone can see them.”<verse eid="EST 9:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="EST 9:14"/>So the king commanded that it be done. An order was sent out in Susa. And the king’s men did to the bodies of Haman’s sons everything they were told to do. <verse eid="EST 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="EST 9:15"/>The Jews in Susa came together on the 14th day of the month of Adar. They put 300 men to death in Susa. But they didn’t take anything that belonged to those men.<verse eid="EST 9:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="EST 9:16"/>During that time, the rest of the Jews also gathered together. They lived in the king’s territories. They came together to fight for their lives. They didn’t want their enemies to bother them anymore. They wanted to get some peace and rest. So they killed 75,000 of their enemies. But they didn’t take anything that belonged to them. <verse eid="EST 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="EST 9:17"/>It happened on the 13th of Adar. On the 14th day they rested. They made it a day to celebrate with great joy. And they enjoyed good food.<verse eid="EST 9:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="EST 9:18"/>But the Jews in Susa had gathered together on the 13th and 14th. Then on the 15th they rested. They made it a day to celebrate with great joy. And they enjoyed good food.<verse eid="EST 9:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="EST 9:19"/>That’s why Jews who live out in the villages celebrate on the 14th of Adar. They celebrate that day with great joy. And they enjoy good food. They also give presents to each other on that day.<verse eid="EST 9:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Purim Is Celebrated</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="EST 9:20"/>Mordecai wrote down these events. He sent letters to all the Jews all through the territories of King Xerxes. It didn’t matter whether the Jews lived nearby or far away. <verse eid="EST 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="EST 9:21"/>Mordecai told them to celebrate the 14th and 15th days of the month of Adar. He wanted them to do it every year. <verse eid="EST 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="EST 9:22"/>Mordecai told the Jews to celebrate the time when they got rest from their enemies. That was the month when their sadness was turned into joy. It was when their weeping turned into a day for celebrating. He wrote the letters to celebrate those days as times of joy. He wanted the people to enjoy good food. He told them to give presents of food to one another. He also wanted them to give gifts to people who were poor.<verse eid="EST 9:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="EST 9:23"/>So the Jews agreed to continue the celebrating they had started. They kept doing what Mordecai had written to them. <verse eid="EST 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="EST 9:24"/>Haman was the son of Hammedatha, the Agagite. He had been the enemy of all the Jews. He had planned to destroy them. He had cast the lot to destroy them completely. The lot was called Pur. <verse eid="EST 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="EST 9:25"/>But the king had found out about Haman’s evil plan. So the king had sent out written orders. He had ordered that Haman’s evil plan against the Jews should happen to him instead. The king also commanded that poles be stuck through the dead bodies of Haman and his sons. Then they should be set up where everyone could see them. <verse eid="EST 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="EST 9:26"/>The days the Jews were celebrating were called Purim. Purim comes from the word Pur. Pur means Lot. Now the Jews celebrate these two days every year. They do it because of everything that was written in Mordecai’s letter. They also do it because of what they had seen and what had happened to them. <verse eid="EST 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="EST 9:27"/>So they established it as a regular practice. They decided they would always observe these two days of the year. They would celebrate in the required way. And they would celebrate at the appointed time. They and their children after them would always observe these days. And so would all who join them. <verse eid="EST 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="EST 9:28"/>The days should be remembered and celebrated. They should be remembered by every family for all time to come. They should be celebrated in every territory and in every city. The Jews should never stop celebrating the days of Purim. Their children after them should always remember these days.<verse eid="EST 9:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="EST 9:29"/>So Queen Esther, the daughter of Abihail, wrote a second letter. She wrote it together with Mordecai the Jew. They wanted to give their full authority to this second letter about Purim. <verse eid="EST 9:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="EST 9:30"/>Mordecai sent letters to all the Jews in the 127 territories of the kingdom of Xerxes. The letters had messages of kindness and hope in them. <verse eid="EST 9:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="EST 9:31"/>The letters established the days of Purim at their appointed times. They spoke about what Mordecai the Jew and Queen Esther had ordered the people to do. Everything should be done in keeping with the directions the Jews had set up for themselves and their children after them. The directions applied to their times of fasting and sadness. <verse eid="EST 9:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="EST 9:32"/>Esther’s order established the rules about Purim. It was written down in the records.<verse eid="EST 9:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EST 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="EST 10"/>
  <para style="s1">The Greatness of Mordecai</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="EST 10:1"/>King Xerxes required people all through his kingdom to bring gifts. King Xerxes required gifts from its farthest shores. <verse eid="EST 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="EST 10:2"/>All the king’s powerful and mighty acts are written down. That includes the whole story of how important Mordecai was. The king had given him a position of great honor. All these things are written in the official records of the kings of Media and Persia. <verse eid="EST 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="EST 10:3"/>The position of Mordecai the Jew was second only to the position of King Xerxes. Mordecai was the most important Jew. All the other Jews had the highest respect for him. That’s because he worked for the good of his people. And he spoke up for the benefit of all the Jews.<verse eid="EST 10:3"/></para>
  <chapter eid="EST 10"/>
</usx>
