<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="JHN" style="id">- New International Readers Version 2014</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1995, 1996, 1998, 2014 by Biblica, Inc.</para>
  <para style="h">John</para>
  <para style="toc1">John</para>
  <para style="toc2">John</para>
  <para style="toc3">Jn</para>
  <para style="mt1">John</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">John was a disciple of Jesus. At the end of his book John tells why he wrote the story of Jesus. “But these are written so that you may believe that Jesus is the Messiah, the Son of God. If you believe this, you will have life because you belong to him.”</para>
  <para style="ip">John begins the book by using the words from the Bible’s story of creation. These words are “In the beginning.” By using these words John shows us that Jesus’ story is about a new creation. The first story of creation takes place in seven days. So John uses the number seven in his new creation story too. In the Bible the number seven means that God has finished his work. Then we can see what God wants.</para>
  <para style="ip">Seven times John shows Jesus using the words “I am” for himself. In the Old Testament God used those words to say who he was. John also shows Jesus performing seven mighty signs. All of this was to help people believe in Jesus.</para>
  <para style="ip">John tells the story of Jesus’ life in two parts. The first part tells about Jesus’ teachings and mighty acts. John does this to make clear that Jesus really is the promised king of Israel. The second part tells about Jesus’ teaching during the last week of his life. And it tells about Jesus’ death and resurrection. When Jesus was raised from the dead, John uses the words “On the first day of the week.” This shows that it was the first day of the new creation.</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="JHN 1"/>
  <para style="s1">The Word Became a Human Being</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 1:1"/>In the beginning, the Word was already there. The Word was with God, and the Word was God. <verse eid="JHN 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 1:2"/>He was with God in the beginning. <verse eid="JHN 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 1:3"/>All things were made through him. Nothing that has been made was made without him. <verse eid="JHN 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 1:4"/>Life was in him, and that life was the light for all people. <verse eid="JHN 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 1:5"/>The light shines in the darkness. But the darkness has not overcome the light.<verse eid="JHN 1:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 1:6"/>There was a man sent from God. His name was John. <verse eid="JHN 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 1:7"/>He came to be a witness about that light. He was a witness so that all people might believe. <verse eid="JHN 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 1:8"/>John himself was not the light. He came only as a witness to the light.<verse eid="JHN 1:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 1:9"/>The true light that gives light to everyone was coming into the world. <verse eid="JHN 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 1:10"/>The Word was in the world. And the world was made through him. But the world did not recognize him. <verse eid="JHN 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 1:11"/>He came to what was his own. But his own people did not accept him. <verse eid="JHN 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 1:12"/>Some people did accept him and did believe in his name. He gave them the right to become children of God. <verse eid="JHN 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 1:13"/>To be a child of God has nothing to do with human parents. Children of God are not born because of human choice or because a husband wants them to be born. They are born because of what God does.<verse eid="JHN 1:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 1:14"/>The Word became a human being. He made his home with us. We have seen his glory. It is the glory of the One and Only, who came from the Father. And the Word was full of grace and truth.<verse eid="JHN 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 1:15"/>John was a witness about the Word. John cried out and said, “This was the one I was talking about. I said, ‘He who comes after me is more important than I am. He is more important because he existed before I was born.’ ” <verse eid="JHN 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 1:16"/>God is full of grace. From him we have all received grace in place of the grace already given. <verse eid="JHN 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 1:17"/>In the past, God gave us grace through the law of Moses. Now, grace and truth come to us through Jesus Christ. <verse eid="JHN 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 1:18"/>No one has ever seen God. But the One and Only is God and is at the Father’s side. The one at the Father’s side has shown us what God is like.<verse eid="JHN 1:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">John the Baptist Says That He Is Not the Messiah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 1:19"/>The Jewish leaders in Jerusalem sent priests and Levites to ask John who he was. John spoke the truth to them. <verse eid="JHN 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 1:20"/>He did not try to hide the truth. He spoke to them openly. He said, “I am not the Messiah.”<verse eid="JHN 1:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 1:21"/>They asked him, “Then who are you? Are you Elijah?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 1:21">He said, “I am not.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 1:21">“Are you the Prophet we’ve been expecting?” they asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 1:21">“No,” he answered.<verse eid="JHN 1:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 1:22"/>They asked one last time, “Who are you? Give us an answer to take back to those who sent us. What do you say about yourself?”<verse eid="JHN 1:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 1:23"/>John replied, using the words of Isaiah the prophet. John said, “I’m the messenger who is calling out in the desert, ‘Make the way for the Lord straight.’ ” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 40:3">Isaiah 40:3</ref>)</char><verse eid="JHN 1:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 1:24"/>The Pharisees who had been sent <verse eid="JHN 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 1:25"/>asked him, “If you are not the Messiah, why are you baptizing people? Why are you doing that if you aren’t Elijah or the Prophet we’ve been expecting?”<verse eid="JHN 1:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 1:26"/>“I baptize people with water,” John replied. “But someone is standing among you whom you do not know. <verse eid="JHN 1:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 1:27"/>He is the one who comes after me. I am not good enough to untie his sandals.”<verse eid="JHN 1:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 1:28"/>This all happened at Bethany on the other side of the Jordan River. That was where John was baptizing.<verse eid="JHN 1:28"/></para>
  <para style="s1">What John Says About Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 1:29"/>The next day John saw Jesus coming toward him. John said, “Look! The Lamb of God! He takes away the sin of the world! <verse eid="JHN 1:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 1:30"/>This is the one I was talking about. I said, ‘A man who comes after me is more important than I am. That’s because he existed before I was born.’ <verse eid="JHN 1:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 1:31"/>I did not know him. But God wants to make it clear to Israel who this person is. That’s the reason I came baptizing with water.”<verse eid="JHN 1:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 1:32"/>Then John told them, “I saw the Holy Spirit come down from heaven like a dove. The Spirit remained on Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 1:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 1:33"/>I myself did not know him. But the one who sent me to baptize with water told me, ‘You will see the Spirit come down and remain on someone. He is the one who will baptize with the Holy Spirit.’ <verse eid="JHN 1:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 1:34"/>I have seen it happen. I am a witness that this is God’s Chosen One.”<verse eid="JHN 1:34"/></para>
  <para style="s1">John’s Disciples Follow Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 1:35"/>The next day John was there again with two of his disciples. <verse eid="JHN 1:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 1:36"/>He saw Jesus walking by. John said, “Look! The Lamb of God!”<verse eid="JHN 1:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 1:37"/>The two disciples heard him say this. So they followed Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 1:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 1:38"/>Then Jesus turned around and saw them following. He asked, “What do you want?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 1:38">They said, “Rabbi, where are you staying?” Rabbi means Teacher.<verse eid="JHN 1:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 1:39"/>“Come,” he replied. “You will see.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 1:39">So they went and saw where he was staying. They spent the rest of the day with him. It was about four o’clock in the afternoon.<verse eid="JHN 1:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 1:40"/>Andrew was Simon Peter’s brother. Andrew was one of the two disciples who heard what John had said. He had also followed Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 1:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 1:41"/>The first thing Andrew did was to find his brother Simon. He told him, “We have found the Messiah.” Messiah means Christ. <verse eid="JHN 1:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 1:42"/>And he brought Simon to Jesus.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 1:42">Jesus looked at him and said, “You are Simon, son of John. You will be called Cephas.” Cephas means Peter, or Rock.<verse eid="JHN 1:42"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Chooses Philip and Nathanael</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 1:43"/>The next day Jesus decided to leave for Galilee. He found Philip and said to him, “Follow me.”<verse eid="JHN 1:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 1:44"/>Philip was from the town of Bethsaida. So were Andrew and Peter. <verse eid="JHN 1:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 1:45"/>Philip found Nathanael and told him, “We have found the one whom Moses wrote about in the Law. The prophets also wrote about him. He is Jesus of Nazareth, the son of Joseph.”<verse eid="JHN 1:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 1:46"/>“Nazareth! Can anything good come from there?” Nathanael asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 1:46">“Come and see,” said Philip.<verse eid="JHN 1:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 1:47"/>Jesus saw Nathanael approaching. Here is what Jesus said about him. “He is a true Israelite. Nothing about him is false.”<verse eid="JHN 1:47"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 1:48"/>“How do you know me?” Nathanael asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 1:48">Jesus answered, “I saw you while you were still under the fig tree. I saw you there before Philip called you.”<verse eid="JHN 1:48"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 1:49"/>Nathanael replied, “Rabbi, you are the Son of God. You are the king of Israel.”<verse eid="JHN 1:49"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 1:50"/>Jesus said, “You believe because I told you I saw you under the fig tree. You will see greater things than that.” <verse eid="JHN 1:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 1:51"/>Then he said to the disciples, “What I’m about to tell you is true. You will see heaven open. You will see the angels of God going up and coming down on the Son of Man.”<verse eid="JHN 1:51"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="JHN 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Changes Water Into Wine</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 2:1"/>On the third day there was a wedding. It took place at Cana in Galilee. Jesus’ mother was there. <verse eid="JHN 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 2:2"/>Jesus and his disciples had also been invited to the wedding. <verse eid="JHN 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 2:3"/>When the wine was gone, Jesus’ mother said to him, “They have no more wine.”<verse eid="JHN 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 2:4"/>“Dear woman, why are you telling me about this?” Jesus replied. “The time for me to show who I really am isn’t here yet.”<verse eid="JHN 2:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 2:5"/>His mother said to the servants, “Do what he tells you.”<verse eid="JHN 2:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 2:6"/>Six stone water jars stood nearby. The Jews used water from that kind of jar for special washings. They did that to make themselves pure and “clean.” Each jar could hold 20 to 30 gallons.<verse eid="JHN 2:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 2:7"/>Jesus said to the servants, “Fill the jars with water.” So they filled them to the top.<verse eid="JHN 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 2:8"/>Then he told them, “Now dip some out. Take it to the person in charge of the dinner.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 2:8">They did what he said. <verse eid="JHN 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 2:9"/>The person in charge tasted the water that had been turned into wine. He didn’t realize where it had come from. But the servants who had brought the water knew. Then the person in charge called the groom to one side. <verse eid="JHN 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 2:10"/>He said to him, “Everyone brings out the best wine first. They bring out the cheaper wine after the guests have had too much to drink. But you have saved the best until now.”<verse eid="JHN 2:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 2:11"/>What Jesus did here in Cana in Galilee was the first of his signs. Jesus showed his glory by doing this sign. And his disciples believed in him.<verse eid="JHN 2:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 2:12"/>After this, Jesus went down to Capernaum. His mother and brothers and disciples went with him. They all stayed there for a few days.<verse eid="JHN 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Clears Out the Temple Courtyard</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 2:13"/>It was almost time for the Jewish Passover Feast. So Jesus went up to Jerusalem. <verse eid="JHN 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 2:14"/>In the temple courtyard he found people selling cattle, sheep and doves. Others were sitting at tables exchanging money. <verse eid="JHN 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 2:15"/>So Jesus made a whip out of ropes. He chased all the sheep and cattle from the temple courtyard. He scattered the coins of the people exchanging money. And he turned over their tables. <verse eid="JHN 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 2:16"/>He told those who were selling doves, “Get these out of here! Stop turning my Father’s house into a market!” <verse eid="JHN 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 2:17"/>His disciples remembered what had been written. It says, “My great love for your house will destroy me.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 69:9">Psalm 69:9</ref>)</char><verse eid="JHN 2:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 2:18"/>Then the Jewish leaders asked him, “What sign can you show us to prove your authority to do this?”<verse eid="JHN 2:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 2:19"/>Jesus answered them, “When you destroy this temple, I will raise it up again in three days.”<verse eid="JHN 2:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 2:20"/>They replied, “It has taken 46 years to build this temple. Are you going to raise it up in three days?” <verse eid="JHN 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 2:21"/>But the temple Jesus had spoken about was his body. <verse eid="JHN 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 2:22"/>His disciples later remembered what he had said. That was after he had been raised from the dead. Then they believed the Scripture. They also believed the words that Jesus had spoken.<verse eid="JHN 2:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 2:23"/>Meanwhile, he was in Jerusalem at the Passover Feast. Many people saw the signs he was doing. And they believed in his name. <verse eid="JHN 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 2:24"/>But Jesus did not fully trust them. He knew what people are like. <verse eid="JHN 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 2:25"/>He didn’t need anyone to tell him what people are like. He already knew why people do what they do.<verse eid="JHN 2:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="JHN 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Teaches Nicodemus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 3:1"/>There was a Pharisee named Nicodemus. He was one of the Jewish rulers. <verse eid="JHN 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 3:2"/>He came to Jesus at night and said, “Rabbi, we know that you are a teacher who has come from God. We know that God is with you. If he weren’t, you couldn’t do the signs you are doing.”<verse eid="JHN 3:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 3:3"/>Jesus replied, “What I’m about to tell you is true. No one can see God’s kingdom unless they are born again.”<verse eid="JHN 3:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 3:4"/>“How can someone be born when they are old?” Nicodemus asked. “They can’t go back inside their mother! They can’t be born a second time!”<verse eid="JHN 3:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 3:5"/>Jesus answered, “What I’m about to tell you is true. No one can enter God’s kingdom unless they are born with water and the Holy Spirit. <verse eid="JHN 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 3:6"/>People give birth to people. But the Spirit gives birth to spirit. <verse eid="JHN 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 3:7"/>You should not be surprised when I say, ‘You must all be born again.’ <verse eid="JHN 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 3:8"/>The wind blows where it wants to. You hear the sound it makes. But you can’t tell where it comes from or where it is going. It is the same with everyone who is born with the Spirit.”<verse eid="JHN 3:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 3:9"/>“How can this be?” Nicodemus asked.<verse eid="JHN 3:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 3:10"/>“You are Israel’s teacher,” said Jesus. “Don’t you understand these things? <verse eid="JHN 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 3:11"/>What I’m about to tell you is true. We speak about what we know. We are witnesses about what we have seen. But still you people do not accept what we say. <verse eid="JHN 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 3:12"/>I have spoken to you about earthly things, and you do not believe. So how will you believe if I speak about heavenly things? <verse eid="JHN 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 3:13"/>No one has ever gone into heaven except the one who came from heaven. He is the Son of Man. <verse eid="JHN 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 3:14"/>Moses lifted up the snake in the desert. In the same way, the Son of Man must also be lifted up. <verse eid="JHN 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 3:15"/>Then everyone who believes may have eternal life in him.”<verse eid="JHN 3:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 3:16"/>God so loved the world that he gave his one and only Son. Anyone who believes in him will not die but will have eternal life. <verse eid="JHN 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 3:17"/>God did not send his Son into the world to judge the world. He sent his Son to save the world through him. <verse eid="JHN 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 3:18"/>Anyone who believes in him is not judged. But anyone who does not believe is judged already. They have not believed in the name of God’s one and only Son. <verse eid="JHN 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 3:19"/>Here is the judgment. Light has come into the world, but people loved darkness instead of light. They loved darkness because what they did was evil. <verse eid="JHN 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 3:20"/>Everyone who does evil deeds hates the light. They will not come into the light. They are afraid that what they do will be seen. <verse eid="JHN 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 3:21"/>But anyone who lives by the truth comes into the light. They live by the truth with God’s help. They come into the light so that it will be easy to see their good deeds.<verse eid="JHN 3:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">John the Baptist Is a Witness About Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 3:22"/>After this, Jesus and his disciples went out into the countryside of Judea. There he spent some time with them. And he baptized people there. <verse eid="JHN 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 3:23"/>John was also baptizing. He was at Aenon near Salim, where there was plenty of water. People were coming and being baptized. <verse eid="JHN 3:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 3:24"/>This was before John was put in prison. <verse eid="JHN 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 3:25"/>Some of John’s disciples and a certain Jew began to argue. They argued about special washings to make people “clean.” <verse eid="JHN 3:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 3:26"/>They came to John and here is what they said to him. “Rabbi, that man who was with you on the other side of the Jordan River is baptizing people. He is the one you told us about. Everyone is going to him.”<verse eid="JHN 3:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 3:27"/>John replied, “A person can receive only what God gives them from heaven. <verse eid="JHN 3:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 3:28"/>You yourselves are witnesses that I said, ‘I am not the Messiah. I was sent ahead of him.’ <verse eid="JHN 3:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 3:29"/>The bride belongs to the groom. The friend who helps the groom waits and listens for him. He is full of joy when he hears the groom’s voice. That joy is mine, and it is now complete. <verse eid="JHN 3:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 3:30"/>He must become more important. I must become less important.<verse eid="JHN 3:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 3:31"/>“The one who comes from above is above everything. The one who is from the earth belongs to the earth and speaks like someone from the earth. The one who comes from heaven is above everything. <verse eid="JHN 3:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 3:32"/>He is a witness to what he has seen and heard. But no one accepts what he says. <verse eid="JHN 3:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 3:33"/>Anyone who has accepted it has said, ‘Yes. God is truthful.’ <verse eid="JHN 3:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 3:34"/>The one whom God has sent speaks God’s words. That’s because God gives the Holy Spirit without limit. <verse eid="JHN 3:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 3:35"/>The Father loves the Son and has put everything into his hands. <verse eid="JHN 3:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 3:36"/>Anyone who believes in the Son has eternal life. Anyone who does not believe in the Son will not have life. God’s anger remains on them.”<verse eid="JHN 3:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="JHN 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Talks With a Woman From Samaria</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 4:1"/>Now Jesus learned that the Pharisees had heard about him. They had heard that he was gaining and baptizing more disciples than John. <verse eid="JHN 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 4:2"/>But in fact Jesus was not baptizing. His disciples were. <verse eid="JHN 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 4:3"/>So Jesus left Judea and went back again to Galilee.<verse eid="JHN 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 4:4"/>Jesus had to go through Samaria. <verse eid="JHN 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 4:5"/>He came to a town in Samaria called Sychar. It was near the piece of land Jacob had given his son Joseph. <verse eid="JHN 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 4:6"/>Jacob’s well was there. Jesus was tired from the journey. So he sat down by the well. It was about noon.<verse eid="JHN 4:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 4:7"/>A woman from Samaria came to get some water. Jesus said to her, “Will you give me a drink?” <verse eid="JHN 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 4:8"/>His disciples had gone into the town to buy food.<verse eid="JHN 4:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 4:9"/>The Samaritan woman said to him, “You are a Jew. I am a Samaritan woman. How can you ask me for a drink?” She said this because Jews don’t have anything to do with Samaritans.<verse eid="JHN 4:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 4:10"/>Jesus answered her, “You do not know what God’s gift is. And you do not know who is asking you for a drink. If you did, you would have asked him. He would have given you living water.”<verse eid="JHN 4:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 4:11"/>“Sir,” the woman said, “you don’t have anything to get water with. The well is deep. Where can you get this living water? <verse eid="JHN 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 4:12"/>Our father Jacob gave us the well. He drank from it himself. So did his sons and his livestock. Are you more important than he is?”<verse eid="JHN 4:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 4:13"/>Jesus answered, “Everyone who drinks this water will be thirsty again. <verse eid="JHN 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 4:14"/>But anyone who drinks the water I give them will never be thirsty. In fact, the water I give them will become a spring of water in them. It will flow up into eternal life.”<verse eid="JHN 4:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 4:15"/>The woman said to him, “Sir, give me this water. Then I will never be thirsty. And I won’t have to keep coming here to get water.”<verse eid="JHN 4:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 4:16"/>He told her, “Go. Get your husband and come back.”<verse eid="JHN 4:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 4:17"/>“I have no husband,” she replied.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 4:17">Jesus said to her, “You are right when you say you have no husband. <verse eid="JHN 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 4:18"/>The fact is, you have had five husbands. And the man you live with now is not your husband. What you have just said is very true.”<verse eid="JHN 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 4:19"/>“Sir,” the woman said, “I can see that you are a prophet. <verse eid="JHN 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 4:20"/>Our people have always worshiped on this mountain. But you Jews claim that the place where we must worship is in Jerusalem.”<verse eid="JHN 4:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 4:21"/>Jesus said, “Woman, believe me. A time is coming when you will not worship the Father on this mountain or in Jerusalem. <verse eid="JHN 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 4:22"/>You Samaritans worship what you do not know. We worship what we do know. Salvation comes from the Jews. <verse eid="JHN 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 4:23"/>But a new time is coming. In fact, it is already here. True worshipers will worship the Father in the Spirit and in truth. They are the kind of worshipers the Father is looking for. <verse eid="JHN 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 4:24"/>God is spirit. His worshipers must worship him in the Spirit and in truth.”<verse eid="JHN 4:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 4:25"/>The woman said, “I know that Messiah is coming.” Messiah means Christ. “When he comes, he will explain everything to us.”<verse eid="JHN 4:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 4:26"/>Then Jesus said, “The one you’re talking about is the one speaking to you. I am he.”<verse eid="JHN 4:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Disciples Join Jesus Again</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 4:27"/>Just then Jesus’ disciples returned. They were surprised to find him talking with a woman. But no one asked, “What do you want from her?” No one asked, “Why are you talking with her?”<verse eid="JHN 4:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 4:28"/>The woman left her water jar and went back to the town. She said to the people, <verse eid="JHN 4:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 4:29"/>“Come. See a man who told me everything I’ve ever done. Could this be the Messiah?” <verse eid="JHN 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 4:30"/>The people came out of the town and made their way toward Jesus.<verse eid="JHN 4:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 4:31"/>His disciples were saying to him, “Rabbi, eat something!”<verse eid="JHN 4:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 4:32"/>But he said to them, “I have food to eat that you know nothing about.”<verse eid="JHN 4:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 4:33"/>Then his disciples asked each other, “Did someone bring him food?”<verse eid="JHN 4:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 4:34"/>Jesus said, “My food is to do what my Father sent me to do. My food is to finish his work. <verse eid="JHN 4:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 4:35"/>Don’t you have a saying? You say, ‘It’s still four months until harvest time.’ But I tell you, open your eyes! Look at the fields! They are ripe for harvest right now. <verse eid="JHN 4:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 4:36"/>Even now the one who gathers the crop is getting paid. They are already harvesting the crop for eternal life. So the one who plants and the one who gathers can now be glad together. <verse eid="JHN 4:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 4:37"/>Here is a true saying. ‘One plants and another gathers.’ <verse eid="JHN 4:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 4:38"/>I sent you to gather what you have not worked for. Others have done the hard work. You have gathered the benefits of their work.”<verse eid="JHN 4:38"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Many Samaritans Believe in Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 4:39"/>Many of the Samaritans from the town of Sychar believed in Jesus. They believed because of what the woman had said about him. She said, “He told me everything I’ve ever done.” <verse eid="JHN 4:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 4:40"/>Then the Samaritans came to him and tried to get him to stay with them. So he stayed two days. <verse eid="JHN 4:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 4:41"/>Because of what he said, many more people became believers.<verse eid="JHN 4:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 4:42"/>They said to the woman, “We no longer believe just because of what you said. We have now heard for ourselves. We know that this man really is the Savior of the world.”<verse eid="JHN 4:42"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Heals an Official’s Son</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 4:43"/>After the two days, Jesus left for Galilee. <verse eid="JHN 4:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 4:44"/>He himself had pointed out that a prophet is not respected in his own country. <verse eid="JHN 4:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 4:45"/>When he arrived in Galilee, the people living there welcomed him. They had seen everything he had done in Jerusalem at the Passover Feast. That was because they had also been there.<verse eid="JHN 4:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 4:46"/>Once more, Jesus visited Cana in Galilee. Cana is where he had turned the water into wine. A royal official was there. His son was sick in bed at Capernaum. <verse eid="JHN 4:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 4:47"/>The official heard that Jesus had arrived in Galilee from Judea. So he went to Jesus and begged him to come and heal his son. The boy was close to death.<verse eid="JHN 4:47"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 4:48"/>Jesus told him, “You people will never believe unless you see signs and wonders.”<verse eid="JHN 4:48"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 4:49"/>The royal official said, “Sir, come down before my child dies.”<verse eid="JHN 4:49"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 4:50"/>“Go,” Jesus replied. “Your son will live.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 4:50">The man believed what Jesus said, and so he left. <verse eid="JHN 4:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 4:51"/>While he was still on his way home, his slaves met him. They gave him the news that his boy was living. <verse eid="JHN 4:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="JHN 4:52"/>He asked what time his son got better. They said to him, “Yesterday, at one o’clock in the afternoon, the fever left him.”<verse eid="JHN 4:52"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="53" style="v" sid="JHN 4:53"/>Then the father realized what had happened. That was the exact time Jesus had said to him, “Your son will live.” So he and his whole family became believers.<verse eid="JHN 4:53"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="JHN 4:54"/>This was the second sign that Jesus did after coming from Judea to Galilee.<verse eid="JHN 4:54"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="JHN 5"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Heals a Man at the Pool</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 5:1"/>Some time later, Jesus went up to Jerusalem for one of the Jewish feasts. <verse eid="JHN 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 5:2"/>In Jerusalem near the Sheep Gate is a pool. In the Aramaic language it is called Bethesda. It is surrounded by five rows of columns with a roof over them. <verse eid="JHN 5:2"/><verse number="3-4" style="v" sid="JHN 5:3-4"/>Here a great number of disabled people used to lie down. Among them were those who were blind, those who could not walk, and those who could hardly move. <verse eid="JHN 5:3-4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 5:5"/>One person was there who had not been able to walk for 38 years. <verse eid="JHN 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 5:6"/>Jesus saw him lying there. He knew that the man had been in that condition for a long time. So he asked him, “Do you want to get well?”<verse eid="JHN 5:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 5:7"/>“Sir,” the disabled man replied, “I have no one to help me into the pool when an angel stirs up the water. I try to get in, but someone else always goes down ahead of me.”<verse eid="JHN 5:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 5:8"/>Then Jesus said to him, “Get up! Pick up your mat and walk.” <verse eid="JHN 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 5:9"/>The man was healed right away. He picked up his mat and walked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 5:9">This happened on a Sabbath day. <verse eid="JHN 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 5:10"/>So the Jewish leaders said to the man who had been healed, “It is the Sabbath day. The law does not allow you to carry your mat.”<verse eid="JHN 5:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 5:11"/>But he replied, “The one who made me well said to me, ‘Pick up your mat and walk.’ ”<verse eid="JHN 5:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 5:12"/>They asked him, “Who is this fellow? Who told you to pick it up and walk?”<verse eid="JHN 5:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 5:13"/>The one who was healed had no idea who it was. Jesus had slipped away into the crowd that was there.<verse eid="JHN 5:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 5:14"/>Later Jesus found him at the temple. Jesus said to him, “See, you are well again. Stop sinning, or something worse may happen to you.” <verse eid="JHN 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 5:15"/>The man went away. He told the Jewish leaders it was Jesus who had made him well.<verse eid="JHN 5:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Authority of the Son</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 5:16"/>Jesus was doing these things on the Sabbath day. So the Jewish leaders began to oppose him. <verse eid="JHN 5:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 5:17"/>Jesus defended himself. He said to them, “My Father is always doing his work. He is working right up to this day. I am working too.” <verse eid="JHN 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 5:18"/>For this reason the Jewish leaders tried even harder to kill him. According to them, Jesus was not only breaking the law of the Sabbath day. He was even calling God his own Father. He was making himself equal with God.<verse eid="JHN 5:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 5:19"/>Jesus answered, “What I’m about to tell you is true. The Son can do nothing by himself. He can do only what he sees his Father doing. What the Father does, the Son also does. <verse eid="JHN 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 5:20"/>This is because the Father loves the Son. The Father shows him everything he does. Yes, and the Father will show the Son even greater works than these. And you will be amazed. <verse eid="JHN 5:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 5:21"/>The Father raises the dead and gives them life. In the same way, the Son gives life to anyone he wants to. <verse eid="JHN 5:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 5:22"/>Also, the Father does not judge anyone. He has given the Son the task of judging. <verse eid="JHN 5:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 5:23"/>Then all people will honor the Son just as they honor the Father. Whoever does not honor the Son does not honor the Father, who sent him.<verse eid="JHN 5:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 5:24"/>“What I’m about to tell you is true. Anyone who hears my word and believes him who sent me has eternal life. They will not be judged. They have crossed over from death to life. <verse eid="JHN 5:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 5:25"/>What I’m about to tell you is true. A time is coming for me to give life. In fact, it has already begun. The dead will hear the voice of the Son of God. Those who hear it will live. <verse eid="JHN 5:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 5:26"/>The Father has life in himself. He has allowed the Son also to have life in himself. <verse eid="JHN 5:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 5:27"/>And the Father has given him the authority to judge. This is because he is the Son of Man.<verse eid="JHN 5:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 5:28"/>“Do not be amazed at this. A time is coming when all who are in their graves will hear his voice. <verse eid="JHN 5:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 5:29"/>They will all come out of their graves. People who have done what is good will rise and live again. People who have done what is evil will rise and be found guilty. <verse eid="JHN 5:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 5:30"/>I can do nothing by myself. I judge only as I hear. And my judging is fair. I do not try to please myself. I try to please the one who sent me.<verse eid="JHN 5:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Being a Witness About Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 5:31"/>“If I am a witness about myself, what I say is not true. <verse eid="JHN 5:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 5:32"/>There is someone else who is a witness in my favor. And I know that what he says about me is true.<verse eid="JHN 5:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 5:33"/>“You have sent people to John the Baptist. He has been a witness to the truth. <verse eid="JHN 5:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 5:34"/>I do not accept what a person says. I only talk about what John says so that you can be saved. <verse eid="JHN 5:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 5:35"/>John was like a lamp that burned and gave light. For a while you chose to enjoy his light.<verse eid="JHN 5:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 5:36"/>“What I say about myself is more important than what John says about me. I am doing the works the Father gave me to finish. These works are a witness that the Father has sent me. <verse eid="JHN 5:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 5:37"/>The Father who sent me is himself a witness about me. You have never heard his voice. You have never seen what he really looks like. <verse eid="JHN 5:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 5:38"/>And his word does not live in you. That’s because you do not believe the one he sent. <verse eid="JHN 5:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 5:39"/>You study the Scriptures carefully. You study them because you think they will give you eternal life. The Scriptures you study are a witness about me. <verse eid="JHN 5:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 5:40"/>But you refuse to come to me and receive life.<verse eid="JHN 5:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 5:41"/>“I do not accept praise from human beings. <verse eid="JHN 5:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 5:42"/>But I know you. I know that you do not have love for God in your hearts. <verse eid="JHN 5:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 5:43"/>I have come in my Father’s name, and you do not accept me. But if someone else comes in his own name, you will accept him. <verse eid="JHN 5:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 5:44"/>You accept praise from one another. But you do not seek the praise that comes from the only God. So how can you believe?<verse eid="JHN 5:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 5:45"/>“Do not think I will bring charges against you in front of the Father. Moses is the one who does that. And he is the one you build your hopes on. <verse eid="JHN 5:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 5:46"/>Do you believe Moses? Then you should believe me. He wrote about me. <verse eid="JHN 5:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 5:47"/>But you do not believe what he wrote. So how are you going to believe what I say?”<verse eid="JHN 5:47"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="JHN 6"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Feeds the Five Thousand</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 6:1"/>Some time after this, Jesus crossed over to the other side of the Sea of Galilee. It is also called the Sea of Tiberias. <verse eid="JHN 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 6:2"/>A large crowd of people followed him. They had seen the signs he had done by healing sick people. <verse eid="JHN 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 6:3"/>Then Jesus went up on a mountainside. There he sat down with his disciples. <verse eid="JHN 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 6:4"/>The Jewish Passover Feast was near.<verse eid="JHN 6:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 6:5"/>Jesus looked up and saw a large crowd coming toward him. So he said to Philip, “Where can we buy bread for these people to eat?” <verse eid="JHN 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 6:6"/>He asked this only to test Philip. He already knew what he was going to do.<verse eid="JHN 6:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 6:7"/>Philip answered him, “Suppose we were able to buy enough bread for each person to have just a bite. That would take more than half a year’s pay!”<verse eid="JHN 6:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 6:8"/>Another of his disciples spoke up. It was Andrew, Simon Peter’s brother. He said, <verse eid="JHN 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 6:9"/>“Here is a boy with five small loaves of barley bread. He also has two small fish. But how far will that go in such a large crowd?”<verse eid="JHN 6:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 6:10"/>Jesus said, “Have the people sit down.” There was plenty of grass in that place, and they sat down. About 5,000 men were there. <verse eid="JHN 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 6:11"/>Then Jesus took the loaves and gave thanks. He handed out the bread to those who were seated. He gave them as much as they wanted. And he did the same with the fish.<verse eid="JHN 6:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 6:12"/>When all of them had enough to eat, Jesus spoke to his disciples. “Gather the leftover pieces,” he said. “Don’t waste anything.” <verse eid="JHN 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 6:13"/>So they gathered what was left over from the five barley loaves. They filled 12 baskets with the pieces left by those who had eaten.<verse eid="JHN 6:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 6:14"/>The people saw the sign that Jesus did. Then they began to say, “This must be the Prophet who is supposed to come into the world.” <verse eid="JHN 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 6:15"/>But Jesus knew that they planned to come and force him to be their king. So he went away again to a mountain by himself.<verse eid="JHN 6:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Walks on the Water</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 6:16"/>When evening came, Jesus’ disciples went down to the Sea of Galilee. <verse eid="JHN 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 6:17"/>There they got into a boat and headed across the lake toward Capernaum. By now it was dark. Jesus had not yet joined them. <verse eid="JHN 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 6:18"/>A strong wind was blowing, and the water became rough. <verse eid="JHN 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 6:19"/>They rowed about three or four miles. Then they saw Jesus coming toward the boat. He was walking on the water. They were frightened. <verse eid="JHN 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 6:20"/>But he said to them, “It is I. Don’t be afraid.” <verse eid="JHN 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 6:21"/>Then they agreed to take him into the boat. Right away the boat reached the shore where they were heading.<verse eid="JHN 6:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 6:22"/>The next day the crowd that had stayed on the other side of the lake realized something. They saw that only one boat had been there. They knew that Jesus had not gotten into it with his disciples. And they knew that the disciples had gone away alone. <verse eid="JHN 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 6:23"/>Then some boats arrived from Tiberias. It was near the place where the people had eaten the bread after the Lord gave thanks. <verse eid="JHN 6:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 6:24"/>The crowd realized that Jesus and his disciples were not there. So they got into boats and went to Capernaum to look for Jesus.<verse eid="JHN 6:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Is the Bread of Life</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 6:25"/>They found him on the other side of the lake. They asked him, “Rabbi, when did you get here?”<verse eid="JHN 6:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 6:26"/>Jesus answered, “What I’m about to tell you is true. You are not looking for me because you saw the signs I did. You are looking for me because you ate the loaves until you were full. <verse eid="JHN 6:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 6:27"/>Do not work for food that spoils. Work for food that lasts forever. That is the food the Son of Man will give you. For God the Father has put his seal of approval on him.”<verse eid="JHN 6:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 6:28"/>Then they asked him, “What does God want from us? What works does he want us to do?”<verse eid="JHN 6:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 6:29"/>Jesus answered, “God’s work is to believe in the one he has sent.”<verse eid="JHN 6:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 6:30"/>So they asked him, “What sign will you give us? What will you do so we can see it and believe you? <verse eid="JHN 6:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 6:31"/>Long ago our people ate the manna in the desert. It is written in Scripture, ‘The Lord gave them bread from heaven to eat.’ ” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="EXO 16:4">Exodus 16:4</ref>; <ref loc="NEH 9:15">Nehemiah 9:15</ref>; <ref loc="PSA 78:24">Psalm 78:24</ref>,<ref loc="PSA 78:25">25</ref>)</char><verse eid="JHN 6:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 6:32"/>Jesus said to them, “What I’m about to tell you is true. It is not Moses who has given you the bread from heaven. It is my Father who gives you the true bread from heaven. <verse eid="JHN 6:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 6:33"/>The bread of God is the bread that comes down from heaven. He gives life to the world.”<verse eid="JHN 6:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 6:34"/>“Sir,” they said, “always give us this bread.”<verse eid="JHN 6:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 6:35"/>Then Jesus said, “I am the bread of life. Whoever comes to me will never go hungry. And whoever believes in me will never be thirsty. <verse eid="JHN 6:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 6:36"/>But it is just as I told you. You have seen me, and you still do not believe. <verse eid="JHN 6:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 6:37"/>Everyone the Father gives me will come to me. I will never send away anyone who comes to me. <verse eid="JHN 6:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 6:38"/>I have not come down from heaven to do what I want to do. I have come to do what the one who sent me wants me to do. <verse eid="JHN 6:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 6:39"/>The one who sent me doesn’t want me to lose anyone he has given me. He wants me to raise them up on the last day. <verse eid="JHN 6:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 6:40"/>My Father wants all who look to the Son and believe in him to have eternal life. I will raise them up on the last day.”<verse eid="JHN 6:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 6:41"/>Then the Jews there began to complain about Jesus. That was because he said, “I am the bread that came down from heaven.” <verse eid="JHN 6:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 6:42"/>They said, “Isn’t this Jesus, the son of Joseph? Don’t we know his father and mother? How can he now say, ‘I came down from heaven’?”<verse eid="JHN 6:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 6:43"/>“Stop complaining among yourselves,” Jesus answered. <verse eid="JHN 6:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 6:44"/>“No one can come to me unless the Father who sent me brings them. Then I will raise them up on the last day. <verse eid="JHN 6:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 6:45"/>It is written in the Prophets, ‘God will teach all of them.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 54:13">Isaiah 54:13</ref>)</char> Everyone who has heard the Father and learned from him comes to me. <verse eid="JHN 6:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 6:46"/>No one has seen the Father except the one who has come from God. Only he has seen the Father. <verse eid="JHN 6:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 6:47"/>What I’m about to tell you is true. Everyone who believes has life forever. <verse eid="JHN 6:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 6:48"/>I am the bread of life. <verse eid="JHN 6:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 6:49"/>Long ago your people ate the manna in the desert, and they still died. <verse eid="JHN 6:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 6:50"/>But here is the bread that comes down from heaven. A person can eat it and not die. <verse eid="JHN 6:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 6:51"/>I am the living bread that came down from heaven. Everyone who eats some of this bread will live forever. This bread is my body. I will give it for the life of the world.”<verse eid="JHN 6:51"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="52" style="v" sid="JHN 6:52"/>Then the Jews began to argue sharply among themselves. They said, “How can this man give us his body to eat?”<verse eid="JHN 6:52"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="53" style="v" sid="JHN 6:53"/>Jesus said to them, “What I’m about to tell you is true. You must eat the Son of Man’s body and drink his blood. If you don’t, you have no life in you. <verse eid="JHN 6:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="JHN 6:54"/>Anyone who eats my body and drinks my blood has eternal life. I will raise them up on the last day. <verse eid="JHN 6:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="JHN 6:55"/>My body is real food. My blood is real drink. <verse eid="JHN 6:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="JHN 6:56"/>Anyone who eats my body and drinks my blood remains in me. And I remain in them. <verse eid="JHN 6:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="JHN 6:57"/>The living Father sent me, and I live because of him. In the same way, those who feed on me will live because of me. <verse eid="JHN 6:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="JHN 6:58"/>This is the bread that came down from heaven. Long ago your people ate manna and died. But whoever eats this bread will live forever.” <verse eid="JHN 6:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="JHN 6:59"/>He said this while he was teaching in the synagogue in Capernaum.<verse eid="JHN 6:59"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Many Disciples Leave Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="60" style="v" sid="JHN 6:60"/>Jesus’ disciples heard this. Many of them said, “This is a hard teaching. Who can accept it?”<verse eid="JHN 6:60"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="61" style="v" sid="JHN 6:61"/>Jesus was aware that his disciples were complaining about his teaching. So he said to them, “Does this upset you? <verse eid="JHN 6:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="JHN 6:62"/>Then what if you see the Son of Man go up to where he was before? <verse eid="JHN 6:62"/><verse number="63" style="v" sid="JHN 6:63"/>The Holy Spirit gives life. The body means nothing at all. The words I have spoken to you are full of the Spirit. They give life. <verse eid="JHN 6:63"/><verse number="64" style="v" sid="JHN 6:64"/>But there are some of you who do not believe.” Jesus had known from the beginning which of them did not believe. And he had known who was going to hand him over to his enemies. <verse eid="JHN 6:64"/><verse number="65" style="v" sid="JHN 6:65"/>So he continued speaking. He said, “This is why I told you that no one can come to me unless the Father helps them.”<verse eid="JHN 6:65"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="66" style="v" sid="JHN 6:66"/>From this time on, many of his disciples turned back. They no longer followed him.<verse eid="JHN 6:66"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="67" style="v" sid="JHN 6:67"/>“You don’t want to leave also, do you?” Jesus asked the 12 disciples.<verse eid="JHN 6:67"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="68" style="v" sid="JHN 6:68"/>Simon Peter answered him, “Lord, who can we go to? You have the words of eternal life. <verse eid="JHN 6:68"/><verse number="69" style="v" sid="JHN 6:69"/>We have come to believe and to know that you are the Holy One of God.”<verse eid="JHN 6:69"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="70" style="v" sid="JHN 6:70"/>Then Jesus replied, “Didn’t I choose you, the 12 disciples? But one of you is a devil!” <verse eid="JHN 6:70"/><verse number="71" style="v" sid="JHN 6:71"/>He meant Judas, the son of Simon Iscariot. Judas was one of the 12 disciples. But later he was going to hand Jesus over to his enemies.<verse eid="JHN 6:71"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="JHN 7"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Goes to the Feast of Booths</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 7:1"/>After this, Jesus went around in Galilee. He didn’t want to travel around in Judea. That was because the Jewish leaders there were looking for a way to kill him. <verse eid="JHN 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 7:2"/>The Jewish Feast of Booths was near. <verse eid="JHN 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 7:3"/>Jesus’ brothers said to him, “Leave Galilee and go to Judea. Then your disciples there will see the works that you do. <verse eid="JHN 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 7:4"/>No one who wants to be well known does things in secret. Since you are doing these things, show yourself to the world.” <verse eid="JHN 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 7:5"/>Even Jesus’ own brothers did not believe in him.<verse eid="JHN 7:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 7:6"/>So Jesus told them, “The time for me to show who I really am is not here yet. For you, any time would be the right time. <verse eid="JHN 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 7:7"/>The people of the world can’t hate you. But they hate me. This is because I am a witness that their works are evil. <verse eid="JHN 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 7:8"/>You go to the feast. I am not going up to this feast. This is because my time has not yet fully come.” <verse eid="JHN 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 7:9"/>After he said this, he stayed in Galilee.<verse eid="JHN 7:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 7:10"/>But when his brothers had left for the feast, he went also. But he went secretly, not openly. <verse eid="JHN 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 7:11"/>At the feast the Jewish leaders were watching for Jesus. They were asking, “Where is he?”<verse eid="JHN 7:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 7:12"/>Many people in the crowd were whispering about him. Some said, “He is a good man.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 7:12">Others replied, “No. He fools the people.” <verse eid="JHN 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 7:13"/>But no one would say anything about him openly. They were afraid of the leaders.<verse eid="JHN 7:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Teaches at the Feast</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 7:14"/>Jesus did nothing until halfway through the feast. Then he went up to the temple courtyard and began to teach. <verse eid="JHN 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 7:15"/>The Jews there were amazed. They asked, “How did this man learn so much without being taught?”<verse eid="JHN 7:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 7:16"/>Jesus answered, “What I teach is not my own. It comes from the one who sent me. <verse eid="JHN 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 7:17"/>Here is how someone can find out whether my teaching comes from God or from me. That person must choose to do what God wants them to do. <verse eid="JHN 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 7:18"/>Whoever speaks on their own does it to get personal honor. But someone who works for the honor of the one who sent him is truthful. Nothing about him is false. <verse eid="JHN 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 7:19"/>Didn’t Moses give you the law? But not one of you obeys the law. Why are you trying to kill me?”<verse eid="JHN 7:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 7:20"/>“You are controlled by demons,” the crowd answered. “Who is trying to kill you?”<verse eid="JHN 7:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 7:21"/>Jesus said to them, “I did one miracle, and you are all amazed. <verse eid="JHN 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 7:22"/>Moses gave you circumcision, and so you circumcise a child on the Sabbath day. But circumcision did not really come from Moses. It came from Abraham. <verse eid="JHN 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 7:23"/>You circumcise a boy on the Sabbath day. You think that if you do, you won’t break the law of Moses. Then why are you angry with me? I healed a man’s entire body on the Sabbath day! <verse eid="JHN 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 7:24"/>Stop judging only by what you see. Judge in the right way.”<verse eid="JHN 7:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">People Don’t Agree About Who Jesus Is</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 7:25"/>Then some of the people of Jerusalem began asking questions. They said, “Isn’t this the man some people are trying to kill? <verse eid="JHN 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 7:26"/>Here he is! He is speaking openly. They aren’t saying a word to him. Have the authorities really decided that he is the Messiah? <verse eid="JHN 7:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 7:27"/>But we know where this man is from. When the Messiah comes, no one will know where he is from.”<verse eid="JHN 7:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 7:28"/>Jesus was still teaching in the temple courtyard. He cried out, “Yes, you know me. And you know where I am from. I am not here on my own authority. The one who sent me is true. You do not know him. <verse eid="JHN 7:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 7:29"/>But I know him. I am from him, and he sent me.”<verse eid="JHN 7:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 7:30"/>When he said this, they tried to arrest him. But no one laid a hand on him. The time for him to show who he really was had not yet come. <verse eid="JHN 7:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 7:31"/>Still, many people in the crowd believed in him. They said, “How will it be when the Messiah comes? Will he do more signs than this man?”<verse eid="JHN 7:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 7:32"/>The Pharisees heard the crowd whispering things like this about him. Then the chief priests and the Pharisees sent temple guards to arrest him.<verse eid="JHN 7:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 7:33"/>Jesus said, “I am with you for only a short time. Then I will go to the one who sent me. <verse eid="JHN 7:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 7:34"/>You will look for me, but you won’t find me. You can’t come where I am going.”<verse eid="JHN 7:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 7:35"/>The Jews said to one another, “Where does this man plan to go? Does he think we can’t find him? Will he go where our people live scattered among the Greeks? Will he go there to teach the Greeks? <verse eid="JHN 7:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 7:36"/>What did he mean when he said, ‘You will look for me, but you won’t find me’? And what did he mean when he said, ‘You can’t come where I am going’?”<verse eid="JHN 7:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 7:37"/>It was the last and most important day of the feast. Jesus stood up and spoke in a loud voice. He said, “Let anyone who is thirsty come to me and drink. <verse eid="JHN 7:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 7:38"/>Does anyone believe in me? Then, just as Scripture says, rivers of living water will flow from inside them.” <verse eid="JHN 7:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 7:39"/>When he said this, he meant the Holy Spirit. Those who believed in Jesus would receive the Spirit later. Up to that time, the Spirit had not been given. This was because Jesus had not yet received glory.<verse eid="JHN 7:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 7:40"/>The people heard his words. Some of them said, “This man must be the Prophet we’ve been expecting.”<verse eid="JHN 7:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 7:41"/>Others said, “He is the Messiah.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 7:41">Still others asked, “How can the Messiah come from Galilee? <verse eid="JHN 7:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 7:42"/>Doesn’t Scripture say that the Messiah will come from the family line of David? Doesn’t it say that he will come from Bethlehem, the town where David lived?” <verse eid="JHN 7:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 7:43"/>So the people did not agree about who Jesus was. <verse eid="JHN 7:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 7:44"/>Some wanted to arrest him. But no one laid a hand on him.<verse eid="JHN 7:44"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Jewish Leaders Do Not Believe</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 7:45"/>Finally the temple guards went back to the chief priests and the Pharisees. They asked the guards, “Why didn’t you bring him in?”<verse eid="JHN 7:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 7:46"/>“No one ever spoke the way this man does,” the guards replied.<verse eid="JHN 7:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 7:47"/>“You mean he has fooled you also?” the Pharisees asked. <verse eid="JHN 7:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 7:48"/>“Have any of the rulers or Pharisees believed in him? <verse eid="JHN 7:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 7:49"/>No! But this mob knows nothing about the law. There is a curse on them.”<verse eid="JHN 7:49"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 7:50"/>Then Nicodemus, a Pharisee, spoke. He was the one who had gone to Jesus earlier. He asked, <verse eid="JHN 7:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 7:51"/>“Does our law find a man guilty without hearing him first? Doesn’t it want to find out what he is doing?”<verse eid="JHN 7:51"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="52" style="v" sid="JHN 7:52"/>They replied, “Are you from Galilee too? Look into it. You will find that a prophet does not come out of Galilee.”<verse eid="JHN 7:52"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="53" style="v" sid="JHN 7:53"/>Then they all went home.<verse eid="JHN 7:53"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="JHN 8"/>
  <para style="nb">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 8:1"/>But Jesus went to the Mount of Olives.<verse eid="JHN 8:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 8:2"/>At sunrise he arrived again in the temple courtyard. All the people gathered around him there. He sat down to teach them. <verse eid="JHN 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 8:3"/>The teachers of the law and the Pharisees brought in a woman. She had been caught committing adultery. They made her stand in front of the group. <verse eid="JHN 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 8:4"/>They said to Jesus, “Teacher, this woman was caught sleeping with a man who was not her husband. <verse eid="JHN 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 8:5"/>In the Law, Moses commanded us to kill such women by throwing stones at them. Now what do you say?” <verse eid="JHN 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 8:6"/>They were trying to trap Jesus with that question. They wanted to have a reason to bring charges against him.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 8:6">But Jesus bent down and started to write on the ground with his finger. <verse eid="JHN 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 8:7"/>They kept asking him questions. So he stood up and said to them, “Has any one of you not sinned? Then you be the first to throw a stone at her.” <verse eid="JHN 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 8:8"/>He bent down again and wrote on the ground.<verse eid="JHN 8:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 8:9"/>Those who heard what he had said began to go away. They left one at a time, the older ones first. Soon only Jesus was left. The woman was still standing there. <verse eid="JHN 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 8:10"/>Jesus stood up and asked her, “Woman, where are they? Hasn’t anyone found you guilty?”<verse eid="JHN 8:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 8:11"/>“No one, sir,” she said.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 8:11">“Then I don’t find you guilty either,” Jesus said. “Go now and leave your life of sin.”<verse eid="JHN 8:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Challenge to What Jesus Says About Himself</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 8:12"/>Jesus spoke to the people again. He said, “I am the light of the world. Anyone who follows me will never walk in darkness. They will have that light. They will have life.”<verse eid="JHN 8:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 8:13"/>The Pharisees argued with him. “Here you are,” they said, “appearing as your own witness. But your witness does not count.”<verse eid="JHN 8:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 8:14"/>Jesus answered, “Even if I am a witness about myself, what I say does count. I know where I came from. And I know where I am going. But you have no idea where I come from or where I am going. <verse eid="JHN 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 8:15"/>You judge by human standards. I don’t judge anyone. <verse eid="JHN 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 8:16"/>But if I do judge, what I decide is true. This is because I am not alone. I stand with the Father, who sent me. <verse eid="JHN 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 8:17"/>Your own Law says that the witness of two people proves the truth about something. <verse eid="JHN 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 8:18"/>I am a witness about myself. The other witness about me is the Father, who sent me.”<verse eid="JHN 8:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 8:19"/>Then they asked him, “Where is your father?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 8:19">“You do not know me or my Father,” Jesus replied. “If you knew me, you would know my Father also.” <verse eid="JHN 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 8:20"/>He spoke these words while he was teaching in the temple courtyard. He was near the place where the offerings were put. But no one arrested him. That’s because the time for him to die had not yet come.<verse eid="JHN 8:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Challenge to Who Jesus Claims to Be</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 8:21"/>Once more Jesus said to them, “I am going away. You will look for me, and you will die in your sin. You can’t come where I am going.”<verse eid="JHN 8:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 8:22"/>This made the Jews ask, “Will he kill himself? Is that why he says, ‘You can’t come where I am going’?”<verse eid="JHN 8:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 8:23"/>But Jesus said, “You are from below. I am from heaven. You are from this world. I am not from this world. <verse eid="JHN 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 8:24"/>I told you that you would die in your sins. This will happen if you don’t believe that I am he. If you don’t believe, you will certainly die in your sins.”<verse eid="JHN 8:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 8:25"/>“Who are you?” they asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 8:25">“Just what I have been telling you from the beginning,” Jesus replied. <verse eid="JHN 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 8:26"/>“I have a lot to say that will judge you. But the one who sent me can be trusted. And I tell the world what I have heard from him.”<verse eid="JHN 8:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 8:27"/>They did not understand that Jesus was telling them about his Father. <verse eid="JHN 8:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 8:28"/>So Jesus said, “You will lift up the Son of Man. Then you will know that I am he. You will also know that I do nothing on my own. I speak just what the Father has taught me. <verse eid="JHN 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 8:29"/>The one who sent me is with me. He has not left me alone, because I always do what pleases him.” <verse eid="JHN 8:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 8:30"/>Even while Jesus was speaking, many people believed in him.<verse eid="JHN 8:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Challenge to the Claim to Be Children of Abraham</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 8:31"/>Jesus spoke to the Jews who had believed him. “If you obey my teaching,” he said, “you are really my disciples. <verse eid="JHN 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 8:32"/>Then you will know the truth. And the truth will set you free.”<verse eid="JHN 8:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 8:33"/>They answered him, “We are Abraham’s children. We have never been slaves of anyone. So how can you say that we will be set free?”<verse eid="JHN 8:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 8:34"/>Jesus replied, “What I’m about to tell you is true. Everyone who sins is a slave of sin. <verse eid="JHN 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 8:35"/>A slave has no lasting place in the family. But a son belongs to the family forever. <verse eid="JHN 8:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 8:36"/>So if the Son of Man sets you free, you will really be free. <verse eid="JHN 8:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 8:37"/>I know that you are Abraham’s children. But you are looking for a way to kill me. You have no room for my word. <verse eid="JHN 8:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 8:38"/>I am telling you what I saw when I was with my Father. You are doing what you have heard from your father.”<verse eid="JHN 8:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 8:39"/>“Abraham is our father,” they answered.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 8:39">Jesus said, “Are you really Abraham’s children? If you are, you will do what Abraham did. <verse eid="JHN 8:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 8:40"/>But you are looking for a way to kill me. I am a man who has told you the truth I heard from God. Abraham didn’t do the things you want to do. <verse eid="JHN 8:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 8:41"/>You are doing what your own father does.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 8:41">“We have the right to claim to be God’s children,” they objected. “The only Father we have is God himself.”<verse eid="JHN 8:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 8:42"/>Jesus said to them, “If God were your Father, you would love me. I have come here from God. I have not come on my own. God sent me. <verse eid="JHN 8:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 8:43"/>Why aren’t my words clear to you? Because you can’t really hear what I say. <verse eid="JHN 8:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 8:44"/>You belong to your father, the devil. You want to obey your father’s wishes. From the beginning, the devil was a murderer. He has never obeyed the truth. There is no truth in him. When he lies, he speaks his natural language. He does this because he is a liar. He is the father of lies. <verse eid="JHN 8:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 8:45"/>But because I tell the truth, you don’t believe me! <verse eid="JHN 8:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 8:46"/>Can any of you prove I am guilty of sinning? Am I not telling the truth? Then why don’t you believe me? <verse eid="JHN 8:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 8:47"/>Whoever belongs to God hears what God says. The reason you don’t hear is that you don’t belong to God.”<verse eid="JHN 8:47"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Makes Claims About Himself</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 8:48"/>The Jews answered Jesus, “Aren’t we right when we say you are a Samaritan? Aren’t you controlled by a demon?”<verse eid="JHN 8:48"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 8:49"/>“I am not controlled by a demon,” said Jesus. “I honor my Father. You do not honor me. <verse eid="JHN 8:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 8:50"/>I am not seeking glory for myself. But there is one who brings glory to me. He is the judge. <verse eid="JHN 8:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 8:51"/>What I’m about to tell you is true. Whoever obeys my word will never die.”<verse eid="JHN 8:51"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="52" style="v" sid="JHN 8:52"/>Then they cried out, “Now we know you are controlled by a demon! Abraham died. So did the prophets. But you say that whoever obeys your word will never die. <verse eid="JHN 8:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JHN 8:53"/>Are you greater than our father Abraham? He died. So did the prophets. Who do you think you are?”<verse eid="JHN 8:53"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="JHN 8:54"/>Jesus replied, “If I bring glory to myself, my glory means nothing. You claim that my Father is your God. He is the one who brings glory to me. <verse eid="JHN 8:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="JHN 8:55"/>You do not know him. But I know him. If I said I did not, I would be a liar like you. But I do know him. And I obey his word. <verse eid="JHN 8:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="JHN 8:56"/>Your father Abraham was filled with joy at the thought of seeing my day. He saw it and was glad.”<verse eid="JHN 8:56"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="57" style="v" sid="JHN 8:57"/>“You are not even 50 years old,” they said to Jesus. “And you have seen Abraham?”<verse eid="JHN 8:57"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="58" style="v" sid="JHN 8:58"/>“What I’m about to tell you is true,” Jesus answered. “Before Abraham was born, I am!” <verse eid="JHN 8:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="JHN 8:59"/>When he said this, they picked up stones to kill him. But Jesus hid himself. He slipped away from the temple area.<verse eid="JHN 8:59"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="JHN 9"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Heals a Man Born Blind</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 9:1"/>As Jesus went along, he saw a man who was blind. He had been blind since he was born. <verse eid="JHN 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 9:2"/>Jesus’ disciples asked him, “Rabbi, who sinned? Was this man born blind because he sinned? Or did his parents sin?”<verse eid="JHN 9:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 9:3"/>“It isn’t because this man sinned,” said Jesus. “It isn’t because his parents sinned. He was born blind so that God’s power could be shown by what’s going to happen. <verse eid="JHN 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 9:4"/>While it is still day, we must do the works of the one who sent me. Night is coming. Then no one can work. <verse eid="JHN 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 9:5"/>While I am in the world, I am the light of the world.”<verse eid="JHN 9:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 9:6"/>After he said this, he spit on the ground. He made some mud with the spit. Then he put the mud on the man’s eyes. <verse eid="JHN 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 9:7"/>“Go,” he told him. “Wash in the Pool of Siloam.” Siloam means Sent. So the man went and washed. And he came home able to see.<verse eid="JHN 9:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 9:8"/>His neighbors and people who had seen him earlier begging asked questions. “Isn’t this the same man who used to sit and beg?” they asked. <verse eid="JHN 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 9:9"/>Some claimed that he was.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 9:9">Others said, “No. He only looks like him.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 9:9">But the man who had been blind kept saying, “I am the man.”<verse eid="JHN 9:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 9:10"/>“Then how were your eyes opened?” they asked.<verse eid="JHN 9:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 9:11"/>He replied, “The man they call Jesus made some mud and put it on my eyes. He told me to go to Siloam and wash. So I went and washed. Then I could see.”<verse eid="JHN 9:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 9:12"/>“Where is this man?” they asked him.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 9:12">“I don’t know,” he said.<verse eid="JHN 9:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Pharisees Want to Know How the Blind Man Was Healed</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 9:13"/>They brought to the Pharisees the man who had been blind. <verse eid="JHN 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 9:14"/>The day Jesus made the mud and opened the man’s eyes was a Sabbath day. <verse eid="JHN 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 9:15"/>So the Pharisees also asked him how he was able to see. “He put mud on my eyes,” the man replied. “Then I washed. And now I can see.”<verse eid="JHN 9:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 9:16"/>Some of the Pharisees said, “Jesus has not come from God. He does not keep the Sabbath day.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 9:16">But others asked, “How can a sinner do such signs?” So the Pharisees did not agree with one another.<verse eid="JHN 9:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 9:17"/>Then they turned again to the blind man. “What do you have to say about him?” they asked. “It was your eyes he opened.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 9:17">The man replied, “He is a prophet.”<verse eid="JHN 9:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 9:18"/>They still did not believe that the man had been blind and now could see. So they sent for his parents. <verse eid="JHN 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 9:19"/>“Is this your son?” they asked. “Is this the one you say was born blind? How is it that now he can see?”<verse eid="JHN 9:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 9:20"/>“We know he is our son,” the parents answered. “And we know he was born blind. <verse eid="JHN 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 9:21"/>But we don’t know how he can now see. And we don’t know who opened his eyes. Ask him. He is an adult. He can speak for himself.” <verse eid="JHN 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 9:22"/>His parents said this because they were afraid of the Jewish leaders. The leaders had already made this decision about Jesus. Anyone who said Jesus was the Messiah would be put out of the synagogue. <verse eid="JHN 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 9:23"/>That was why the man’s parents said, “He is an adult. Ask him.”<verse eid="JHN 9:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 9:24"/>Again the Pharisees called the man who had been blind to come to them. “Give glory to God by telling the truth!” they said. “We know that the man who healed you is a sinner.”<verse eid="JHN 9:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 9:25"/>He replied, “I don’t know if he is a sinner or not. I do know one thing. I was blind, but now I can see!”<verse eid="JHN 9:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 9:26"/>Then they asked him, “What did he do to you? How did he open your eyes?”<verse eid="JHN 9:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 9:27"/>He answered, “I have already told you. But you didn’t listen. Why do you want to hear it again? Do you want to become his disciples too?”<verse eid="JHN 9:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 9:28"/>Then they began to attack him with their words. “You are this fellow’s disciple!” they said. “We are disciples of Moses! <verse eid="JHN 9:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 9:29"/>We know that God spoke to Moses. But we don’t even know where this fellow comes from.”<verse eid="JHN 9:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 9:30"/>The man answered, “That is really surprising! You don’t know where he comes from, and yet he opened my eyes. <verse eid="JHN 9:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 9:31"/>We know that God does not listen to sinners. He listens to the godly person who does what he wants them to do. <verse eid="JHN 9:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 9:32"/>Nobody has ever heard of anyone opening the eyes of a person born blind. <verse eid="JHN 9:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 9:33"/>If this man had not come from God, he could do nothing.”<verse eid="JHN 9:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 9:34"/>Then the Pharisees replied, “When you were born, you were already deep in sin. How dare you talk like that to us!” And they threw him out of the synagogue.<verse eid="JHN 9:34"/></para>
  <para style="s1">People Who Can’t See the Truth</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 9:35"/>Jesus heard that the Pharisees had thrown the man out of the synagogue. When Jesus found him, he said, “Do you believe in the Son of Man?”<verse eid="JHN 9:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 9:36"/>“Who is he, sir?” the man asked. “Tell me, so I can believe in him.”<verse eid="JHN 9:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 9:37"/>Jesus said, “You have now seen him. In fact, he is the one speaking with you.”<verse eid="JHN 9:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 9:38"/>Then the man said, “Lord, I believe.” And he worshiped him.<verse eid="JHN 9:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 9:39"/>Jesus said, “I have come into this world to judge it. I have come so that people who are blind will see. I have come so that people who can see will become blind.”<verse eid="JHN 9:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 9:40"/>Some Pharisees who were with him heard him say this. They asked, “What? Are we blind too?”<verse eid="JHN 9:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 9:41"/>Jesus said, “If you were blind, you would not be guilty of sin. But since you claim you can see, you remain guilty.<verse eid="JHN 9:41"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="JHN 10"/>
  <para style="s1">The Good Shepherd and His Sheep</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 10:1"/>“What I’m about to tell you Pharisees is true. What if someone does not enter the sheep pen through the gate but climbs in another way? That person is a thief and a robber. <verse eid="JHN 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 10:2"/>The one who enters through the gate is the shepherd of the sheep. <verse eid="JHN 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 10:3"/>The gatekeeper opens the gate for him. The sheep listen to his voice. He calls his own sheep by name and leads them out. <verse eid="JHN 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 10:4"/>When he has brought out all his own sheep, he goes on ahead of them. His sheep follow him because they know his voice. <verse eid="JHN 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 10:5"/>But they will never follow a stranger. In fact, they will run away from him. They don’t recognize a stranger’s voice.” <verse eid="JHN 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 10:6"/>Jesus told this story. But the Pharisees didn’t understand what he was telling them.<verse eid="JHN 10:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 10:7"/>So Jesus said again, “What I’m about to tell you is true. I am like a gate for the sheep. <verse eid="JHN 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 10:8"/>All who have come before me are thieves and robbers. But the sheep have not listened to them. <verse eid="JHN 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 10:9"/>I’m like a gate. Anyone who enters through me will be saved. They will come in and go out. And they will find plenty of food. <verse eid="JHN 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 10:10"/>A thief comes only to steal and kill and destroy. I have come so they may have life. I want them to have it in the fullest possible way.<verse eid="JHN 10:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 10:11"/>“I am the good shepherd. The good shepherd gives his life for the sheep. <verse eid="JHN 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 10:12"/>The hired man is not the shepherd and does not own the sheep. So when the hired man sees the wolf coming, he leaves the sheep and runs away. Then the wolf attacks the flock and scatters it. <verse eid="JHN 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 10:13"/>The man runs away because he is a hired man. He does not care about the sheep.<verse eid="JHN 10:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 10:14"/>“I am the good shepherd. I know my sheep, and my sheep know me. <verse eid="JHN 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 10:15"/>They know me just as the Father knows me and I know the Father. And I give my life for the sheep. <verse eid="JHN 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 10:16"/>I have other sheep that do not belong to this sheep pen. I must bring them in too. They also will listen to my voice. Then there will be one flock and one shepherd. <verse eid="JHN 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 10:17"/>The reason my Father loves me is that I give up my life. But I will take it back again. <verse eid="JHN 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 10:18"/>No one takes it from me. I give it up myself. I have the authority to give it up. And I have the authority to take it back again. I received this command from my Father.”<verse eid="JHN 10:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 10:19"/>The Jews who heard these words could not agree with one another. <verse eid="JHN 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 10:20"/>Many of them said, “He is controlled by a demon. He has gone crazy! Why should we listen to him?”<verse eid="JHN 10:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 10:21"/>But others said, “A person controlled by a demon does not say things like this. Can a demon open the eyes of someone who is blind?”<verse eid="JHN 10:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Another Challenge to Jesus’ Claims</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 10:22"/>Then came the Feast of Hanukkah at Jerusalem. It was winter. <verse eid="JHN 10:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 10:23"/>Jesus was in the temple courtyard walking in Solomon’s Porch. <verse eid="JHN 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 10:24"/>The Jews who were gathered there around Jesus spoke to him. They said, “How long will you keep us waiting? If you are the Messiah, tell us plainly.”<verse eid="JHN 10:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 10:25"/>Jesus answered, “I did tell you. But you do not believe. The works that I do in my Father’s name are a witness for me. <verse eid="JHN 10:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 10:26"/>But you do not believe, because you are not my sheep. <verse eid="JHN 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 10:27"/>My sheep listen to my voice. I know them, and they follow me. <verse eid="JHN 10:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 10:28"/>I give them eternal life, and they will never die. No one will steal them out of my hand. <verse eid="JHN 10:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 10:29"/>My Father, who has given them to me, is greater than anyone. No one can steal them out of my Father’s hand. <verse eid="JHN 10:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 10:30"/>I and the Father are one.”<verse eid="JHN 10:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 10:31"/>Again the Jews who had challenged him picked up stones to kill him. <verse eid="JHN 10:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 10:32"/>But Jesus said to them, “I have shown you many good works from the Father. Which good work are you throwing stones at me for?”<verse eid="JHN 10:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 10:33"/>“We are not throwing stones at you for any good work,” they replied. “We are stoning you for saying a very evil thing. You are only a man. But you claim to be God.”<verse eid="JHN 10:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 10:34"/>Jesus answered them, “Didn’t God say in your Law, ‘I have said you are “gods” ’? <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 82:6">Psalm 82:6</ref>)</char> <verse eid="JHN 10:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 10:35"/>We know that Scripture is always true. God spoke to some people and called them ‘gods.’ <verse eid="JHN 10:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 10:36"/>If that is true, what about the one the Father set apart as his very own? What about this one the Father sent into the world? Why do you charge me with saying a very evil thing? Is it because I said, ‘I am God’s Son’? <verse eid="JHN 10:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 10:37"/>Don’t believe me unless I do the works of my Father. <verse eid="JHN 10:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 10:38"/>But what if I do them? Even if you don’t believe me, believe these works. Then you will know and understand that the Father is in me and I am in the Father.” <verse eid="JHN 10:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 10:39"/>Again they tried to arrest him. But he escaped from them.<verse eid="JHN 10:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 10:40"/>Then Jesus went back across the Jordan River. He went to the place where John had been baptizing in the early days. There he stayed. <verse eid="JHN 10:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 10:41"/>Many people came to him. They said, “John never performed a sign. But everything he said about this man was true.” <verse eid="JHN 10:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 10:42"/>And in that place many believed in Jesus.<verse eid="JHN 10:42"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="JHN 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Lazarus Dies</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 11:1"/>A man named Lazarus was sick. He was from Bethany, the village where Mary and her sister Martha lived. <verse eid="JHN 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 11:2"/>Mary would later pour perfume on the Lord. She would also wipe Jesus’ feet with her hair. It was her brother Lazarus who was sick in bed. <verse eid="JHN 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 11:3"/>So the sisters sent a message to Jesus. “Lord,” they told him, “the one you love is sick.”<verse eid="JHN 11:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 11:4"/>When Jesus heard this, he said, “This sickness will not end in death. No, it is for God’s glory. God’s Son will receive glory because of it.” <verse eid="JHN 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 11:5"/>Jesus loved Martha and her sister and Lazarus. <verse eid="JHN 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 11:6"/>So after he heard Lazarus was sick, he stayed where he was for two more days. <verse eid="JHN 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 11:7"/>And then he said to his disciples, “Let us go back to Judea.”<verse eid="JHN 11:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 11:8"/>“But Rabbi,” they said, “a short time ago the Jews there tried to kill you with stones. Are you still going back?”<verse eid="JHN 11:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 11:9"/>Jesus answered, “Aren’t there 12 hours of daylight? Anyone who walks during the day won’t trip and fall. They can see because of this world’s light. <verse eid="JHN 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 11:10"/>But when they walk at night, they’ll trip and fall. They have no light.”<verse eid="JHN 11:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 11:11"/>After he said this, Jesus went on speaking to them. “Our friend Lazarus has fallen asleep,” he said. “But I am going there to wake him up.”<verse eid="JHN 11:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 11:12"/>His disciples replied, “Lord, if he’s sleeping, he will get better.” <verse eid="JHN 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 11:13"/>Jesus had been speaking about the death of Lazarus. But his disciples thought he meant natural sleep.<verse eid="JHN 11:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 11:14"/>So then he told them plainly, “Lazarus is dead. <verse eid="JHN 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 11:15"/>For your benefit, I am glad I was not there. Now you will believe. But let us go to him.”<verse eid="JHN 11:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 11:16"/>Then Thomas, who was also called Didymus, spoke to the rest of the disciples. “Let us go also,” he said. “Then we can die with Jesus.”<verse eid="JHN 11:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Comforts the Sisters of Lazarus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 11:17"/>When Jesus arrived, he found out that Lazarus had already been in the tomb for four days. <verse eid="JHN 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 11:18"/>Bethany was less than two miles from Jerusalem. <verse eid="JHN 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 11:19"/>Many Jews had come to Martha and Mary. They had come to comfort them because their brother was dead. <verse eid="JHN 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 11:20"/>When Martha heard that Jesus was coming, she went out to meet him. But Mary stayed at home.<verse eid="JHN 11:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 11:21"/>“Lord,” Martha said to Jesus, “I wish you had been here! Then my brother would not have died. <verse eid="JHN 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 11:22"/>But I know that even now God will give you anything you ask for.”<verse eid="JHN 11:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 11:23"/>Jesus said to her, “Your brother will rise again.”<verse eid="JHN 11:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 11:24"/>Martha answered, “I know he will rise again. This will happen when people are raised from the dead on the last day.”<verse eid="JHN 11:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 11:25"/>Jesus said to her, “I am the resurrection and the life. Anyone who believes in me will live, even if they die. <verse eid="JHN 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 11:26"/>And whoever lives by believing in me will never die. Do you believe this?”<verse eid="JHN 11:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 11:27"/>“Yes, Lord,” she replied. “I believe that you are the Messiah, the Son of God. I believe that you are the one who is supposed to come into the world.”<verse eid="JHN 11:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 11:28"/>After she said this, she went back home. She called her sister Mary to one side to talk to her. “The Teacher is here,” Martha said. “He is asking for you.” <verse eid="JHN 11:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 11:29"/>When Mary heard this, she got up quickly and went to him. <verse eid="JHN 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 11:30"/>Jesus had not yet entered the village. He was still at the place where Martha had met him. <verse eid="JHN 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 11:31"/>Some Jews had been comforting Mary in the house. They noticed how quickly she got up and went out. So they followed her. They thought she was going to the tomb to mourn there.<verse eid="JHN 11:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 11:32"/>Mary reached the place where Jesus was. When she saw him, she fell at his feet. She said, “Lord, I wish you had been here! Then my brother would not have died.”<verse eid="JHN 11:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 11:33"/>Jesus saw her crying. He saw that the Jews who had come along with her were crying also. His spirit became very sad, and he was troubled. <verse eid="JHN 11:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 11:34"/>“Where have you put him?” he asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 11:34">“Come and see, Lord,” they replied.<verse eid="JHN 11:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 11:35"/>Jesus wept.<verse eid="JHN 11:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 11:36"/>Then the Jews said, “See how much he loved him!”<verse eid="JHN 11:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 11:37"/>But some of them said, “He opened the eyes of the blind man. Couldn’t he have kept this man from dying?”<verse eid="JHN 11:37"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Raises Lazarus From the Dead</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 11:38"/>Once more Jesus felt very sad. He came to the tomb. It was a cave with a stone in front of the entrance. <verse eid="JHN 11:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 11:39"/>“Take away the stone,” he said.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 11:39">“But, Lord,” said Martha, the sister of the dead man, “by this time there is a bad smell. Lazarus has been in the tomb for four days.”<verse eid="JHN 11:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 11:40"/>Then Jesus said, “Didn’t I tell you that if you believe, you will see God’s glory?”<verse eid="JHN 11:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 11:41"/>So they took away the stone. Then Jesus looked up. He said, “Father, I thank you for hearing me. <verse eid="JHN 11:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 11:42"/>I know that you always hear me. But I said this for the benefit of the people standing here. I said it so they will believe that you sent me.”<verse eid="JHN 11:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 11:43"/>Then Jesus called in a loud voice. He said, “Lazarus, come out!” <verse eid="JHN 11:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 11:44"/>The dead man came out. His hands and feet were wrapped with strips of linen. A cloth was around his face.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 11:44">Jesus said to them, “Take off the clothes he was buried in and let him go.”<verse eid="JHN 11:44"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Plan to Kill Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 11:45"/>Many of the Jews who had come to visit Mary saw what Jesus did. So they believed in him. <verse eid="JHN 11:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 11:46"/>But some of them went to the Pharisees. They told the Pharisees what Jesus had done. <verse eid="JHN 11:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 11:47"/>Then the chief priests and the Pharisees called a meeting of the Sanhedrin.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 11:47">“What can we do?” they asked. “This man is performing many signs. <verse eid="JHN 11:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 11:48"/>If we let him keep on doing this, everyone will believe in him. Then the Romans will come. They will take away our temple and our nation.”<verse eid="JHN 11:48"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 11:49"/>One of the Jewish leaders spoke up. His name was Caiaphas. He was high priest at that time. He said, “You don’t know anything at all! <verse eid="JHN 11:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 11:50"/>You don’t realize what is good for you. It is better if one man dies for the people than if the whole nation is destroyed.”<verse eid="JHN 11:50"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 11:51"/>He did not say this on his own because he was high priest at that time. He prophesied that Jesus would die for the Jewish nation. <verse eid="JHN 11:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="JHN 11:52"/>He also prophesied that Jesus would die for God’s children scattered everywhere. He would die to bring them together and make them one. <verse eid="JHN 11:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JHN 11:53"/>So from that day on, the Jewish rulers planned to kill Jesus.<verse eid="JHN 11:53"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="JHN 11:54"/>Jesus no longer moved around openly among the people of Judea. Instead, he went away to an area near the desert. He went to a village called Ephraim. There he stayed with his disciples.<verse eid="JHN 11:54"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="55" style="v" sid="JHN 11:55"/>It was almost time for the Jewish Passover Feast. Many people went up from the country to Jerusalem. They went there for the special washing that would make them pure before the Passover Feast. <verse eid="JHN 11:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="JHN 11:56"/>They kept looking for Jesus as they stood in the temple courtyard. They asked one another, “What do you think? Isn’t he coming to the feast at all?” <verse eid="JHN 11:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="JHN 11:57"/>But the chief priests and the Pharisees had given orders. They had commanded anyone who found out where Jesus was staying to report it. Then they could arrest him.<verse eid="JHN 11:57"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="JHN 12"/>
  <para style="s1">Mary Pours Perfume on Jesus at Bethany</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 12:1"/>It was six days before the Passover Feast. Jesus came to Bethany, where Lazarus lived. Lazarus was the one Jesus had raised from the dead. <verse eid="JHN 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 12:2"/>A dinner was given at Bethany to honor Jesus. Martha served the food. Lazarus was among the people at the table with Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 12:3"/>Then Mary took about a pint of pure nard. It was an expensive perfume. She poured it on Jesus’ feet and wiped them with her hair. The house was filled with the sweet smell of the perfume.<verse eid="JHN 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 12:4"/>But Judas Iscariot didn’t like what Mary did. He was one of Jesus’ disciples. Later he was going to hand Jesus over to his enemies. Judas said, <verse eid="JHN 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 12:5"/>“Why wasn’t this perfume sold? Why wasn’t the money given to poor people? It was worth a year’s pay.” <verse eid="JHN 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 12:6"/>He didn’t say this because he cared about the poor. He said it because he was a thief. Judas was in charge of the money bag. He used to help himself to what was in it.<verse eid="JHN 12:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 12:7"/>“Leave her alone,” Jesus replied. “The perfume was meant for the day I am buried. <verse eid="JHN 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 12:8"/>You will always have the poor among you. But you won’t always have me.”<verse eid="JHN 12:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 12:9"/>Meanwhile a large crowd of Jews found out that Jesus was there, so they came. But they did not come only because of Jesus. They also came to see Lazarus. After all, Jesus had raised him from the dead. <verse eid="JHN 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 12:10"/>So the chief priests made plans to kill Lazarus too. <verse eid="JHN 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 12:11"/>Because of Lazarus, many of the Jews were starting to follow Jesus. They were believing in him.<verse eid="JHN 12:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Comes to Jerusalem as King</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 12:12"/>The next day the large crowd that had come for the feast heard that Jesus was on his way to Jerusalem. <verse eid="JHN 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 12:13"/>So they took branches from palm trees and went out to meet him. They shouted,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 12:13">“Hosanna!”</para>
  <para style="b" vid="JHN 12:13"/>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 12:13">“Blessed is the one who comes in the name of the Lord!” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 118:25">Psalm 118:25</ref>,<ref loc="PSA 118:26">26</ref>)</char></para>
  <para style="b" vid="JHN 12:13"/>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 12:13">“Blessed is the king of Israel!”<verse eid="JHN 12:13"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 12:14"/>Jesus found a young donkey and sat on it. This is just as it is written in Scripture. It says,<verse eid="JHN 12:14"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 12:15"/>“City of Zion, do not be afraid.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JHN 12:15">See, your king is coming.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JHN 12:15">He is sitting on a donkey’s colt.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ZEC 9:9">Zechariah 9:9</ref>)</char><verse eid="JHN 12:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 12:16"/>At first, Jesus’ disciples did not understand all this. They realized it only after he had received glory. Then they realized that these things had been written about him. They realized that these things had been done to him.<verse eid="JHN 12:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 12:17"/>A crowd had been with Jesus when he called Lazarus from the tomb and raised him from the dead. So they continued to tell everyone about what had happened. <verse eid="JHN 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 12:18"/>Many people went out to meet him. They had heard that he had done this sign. <verse eid="JHN 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 12:19"/>So the Pharisees said to one another, “This isn’t getting us anywhere. Look how the whole world is following him!”<verse eid="JHN 12:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Tells About His Coming Death</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 12:20"/>There were some Greeks among the people who went up to worship during the feast. <verse eid="JHN 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 12:21"/>They came to ask Philip for a favor. Philip was from Bethsaida in Galilee. “Sir,” they said, “we would like to see Jesus.” <verse eid="JHN 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 12:22"/>Philip went to tell Andrew. Then Andrew and Philip told Jesus.<verse eid="JHN 12:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 12:23"/>Jesus replied, “The time has come for the Son of Man to receive glory. <verse eid="JHN 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 12:24"/>What I’m about to tell you is true. Unless a grain of wheat falls to the ground and dies, it remains only one seed. But if it dies, it produces many seeds. <verse eid="JHN 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 12:25"/>Anyone who loves their life will lose it. But anyone who hates their life in this world will keep it and have eternal life. <verse eid="JHN 12:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 12:26"/>Anyone who serves me must follow me. And where I am, my servant will also be. My Father will honor the one who serves me.<verse eid="JHN 12:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 12:27"/>“My soul is troubled. What should I say? ‘Father, keep me from having to go through with this’? No. This is the very reason I have come to this point in my life. <verse eid="JHN 12:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 12:28"/>Father, bring glory to your name!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 12:28">Then a voice came from heaven. It said, “I have brought glory to my name. I will bring glory to it again.” <verse eid="JHN 12:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 12:29"/>The crowd there heard the voice. Some said it was thunder. Others said an angel had spoken to Jesus.<verse eid="JHN 12:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 12:30"/>Jesus said, “This voice was for your benefit, not mine. <verse eid="JHN 12:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 12:31"/>Now it is time for the world to be judged. Now the prince of this world will be thrown out. <verse eid="JHN 12:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 12:32"/>And I am going to be lifted up from the earth. When I am, I will bring all people to myself.” <verse eid="JHN 12:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 12:33"/>He said this to show them how he was going to die.<verse eid="JHN 12:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 12:34"/>The crowd spoke up. “The Law tells us that the Messiah will remain forever,” they said. “So how can you say, ‘The Son of Man must be lifted up’? Who is this ‘Son of Man’?”<verse eid="JHN 12:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 12:35"/>Then Jesus told them, “You are going to have the light just a little while longer. Walk while you have the light. Do this before darkness catches up with you. Whoever walks in the dark does not know where they are going. <verse eid="JHN 12:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 12:36"/>While you have the light, believe in it. Then you can become children of light.” When Jesus had finished speaking, he left and hid from them.<verse eid="JHN 12:36"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Some Jews Believe and Some Don’t</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 12:37"/>Jesus had performed so many signs in front of them. But they still would not believe in him. <verse eid="JHN 12:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 12:38"/>This happened as Isaiah the prophet had said it would. He had said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 12:38">“Lord, who has believed what we’ve been saying?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JHN 12:38">Who has seen the Lord’s saving power?” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 53:1">Isaiah 53:1</ref>)</char><verse eid="JHN 12:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 12:39"/>For this reason, they could not believe. As Isaiah says in another place,<verse eid="JHN 12:39"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 12:40"/>“The Lord has blinded their eyes.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JHN 12:40">He has closed their minds.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 12:40">So they can’t see with their eyes.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JHN 12:40">They can’t understand with their minds.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JHN 12:40">They can’t turn to the Lord. If they could, he would heal them.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ISA 6:10">Isaiah 6:10</ref>)</char><verse eid="JHN 12:40"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 12:41"/>Isaiah said this because he saw Jesus’ glory and spoke about him.<verse eid="JHN 12:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 12:42"/>At the same time that Jesus did those signs, many of the Jewish leaders believed in him. But because of the Pharisees, they would not openly admit they believed. They were afraid they would be thrown out of the synagogue. <verse eid="JHN 12:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 12:43"/>They loved praise from people more than praise from God.<verse eid="JHN 12:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 12:44"/>Then Jesus cried out, “Whoever believes in me does not believe in me only. They also believe in the one who sent me. <verse eid="JHN 12:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 12:45"/>The one who looks at me sees the one who sent me. <verse eid="JHN 12:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 12:46"/>I have come into the world to be its light. So no one who believes in me will stay in darkness.<verse eid="JHN 12:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 12:47"/>“I don’t judge a person who hears my words but does not obey them. I didn’t come to judge the world. I came to save the world. <verse eid="JHN 12:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 12:48"/>But there is a judge for anyone who does not accept me and my words. These words I have spoken will judge them on the last day. <verse eid="JHN 12:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 12:49"/>I did not speak on my own. The Father who sent me commanded me to say all that I have said. <verse eid="JHN 12:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 12:50"/>I know that his command leads to eternal life. So everything I say is just what the Father has told me to say.”<verse eid="JHN 12:50"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="JHN 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Washes His Disciples’ Feet</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 13:1"/>It was just before the Passover Feast. Jesus knew that the time had come for him to leave this world. It was time for him to go to the Father. Jesus loved his disciples who were in the world. So he now loved them to the very end.<verse eid="JHN 13:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 13:2"/>They were having their evening meal. The devil had already tempted Judas, son of Simon Iscariot. He had urged Judas to hand Jesus over to his enemies. <verse eid="JHN 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 13:3"/>Jesus knew that the Father had put everything under his power. He also knew he had come from God and was returning to God. <verse eid="JHN 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 13:4"/>So he got up from the meal and took off his outer clothes. He wrapped a towel around his waist. <verse eid="JHN 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 13:5"/>After that, he poured water into a large bowl. Then he began to wash his disciples’ feet. He dried them with the towel that was wrapped around him.<verse eid="JHN 13:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 13:6"/>He came to Simon Peter. “Lord,” Peter said to him, “are you going to wash my feet?”<verse eid="JHN 13:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 13:7"/>Jesus replied, “You don’t realize now what I am doing. But later you will understand.”<verse eid="JHN 13:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 13:8"/>“No,” said Peter. “You will never wash my feet.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 13:8">Jesus answered, “Unless I wash you, you can’t share life with me.”<verse eid="JHN 13:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 13:9"/>“Lord,” Simon Peter replied, “not just my feet! Wash my hands and my head too!”<verse eid="JHN 13:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 13:10"/>Jesus answered, “People who have had a bath need to wash only their feet. The rest of their body is clean. And you are clean. But not all of you are.” <verse eid="JHN 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 13:11"/>Jesus knew who was going to hand him over to his enemies. That was why he said not every one was clean.<verse eid="JHN 13:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 13:12"/>When Jesus finished washing their feet, he put on his clothes. Then he returned to his place. “Do you understand what I have done for you?” he asked them. <verse eid="JHN 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 13:13"/>“You call me ‘Teacher’ and ‘Lord.’ You are right. That is what I am. <verse eid="JHN 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 13:14"/>I, your Lord and Teacher, have washed your feet. So you also should wash one another’s feet. <verse eid="JHN 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 13:15"/>I have given you an example. You should do as I have done for you. <verse eid="JHN 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 13:16"/>What I’m about to tell you is true. A slave is not more important than his master. And a messenger is not more important than the one who sends him. <verse eid="JHN 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 13:17"/>Now you know these things. So you will be blessed if you do them.<verse eid="JHN 13:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Tells What Judas Will Do</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 13:18"/>“I am not talking about all of you. I know the ones I have chosen. But this will happen so that this passage of Scripture will come true. It says, ‘The one who shared my bread has turned against me.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 41:9">Psalm 41:9</ref>)</char><verse eid="JHN 13:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 13:19"/>“I am telling you now, before it happens. When it does happen, you will believe that I am who I am. <verse eid="JHN 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 13:20"/>What I’m about to tell you is true. Anyone who accepts someone I send accepts me. And anyone who accepts me accepts the one who sent me.”<verse eid="JHN 13:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 13:21"/>After he had said this, Jesus’ spirit was troubled. He said, “What I’m about to tell you is true. One of you is going to hand me over to my enemies.”<verse eid="JHN 13:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 13:22"/>His disciples stared at one another. They had no idea which one of them he meant. <verse eid="JHN 13:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 13:23"/>The disciple Jesus loved was next to him at the table. <verse eid="JHN 13:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 13:24"/>Simon Peter motioned to that disciple. He said, “Ask Jesus which one he means.”<verse eid="JHN 13:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 13:25"/>The disciple was leaning back against Jesus. He asked him, “Lord, who is it?”<verse eid="JHN 13:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 13:26"/>Jesus answered, “It is the one I will give this piece of bread to. I will give it to him after I have dipped it in the dish.” He dipped the piece of bread. Then he gave it to Judas, son of Simon Iscariot. <verse eid="JHN 13:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 13:27"/>As soon as Judas took the bread, Satan entered into him.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 13:27">So Jesus told him, “Do quickly what you are going to do.” <verse eid="JHN 13:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 13:28"/>But no one at the meal understood why Jesus said this to him. <verse eid="JHN 13:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 13:29"/>Judas was in charge of the money. So some of the disciples thought Jesus was telling him to buy what was needed for the feast. Others thought Jesus was talking about giving something to poor people. <verse eid="JHN 13:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 13:30"/>As soon as Judas had taken the bread, he went out. And it was night.<verse eid="JHN 13:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Peter Will Say He Does Not Know Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 13:31"/>After Judas was gone, Jesus spoke. He said, “Now the Son of Man receives glory. And he brings glory to God. <verse eid="JHN 13:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 13:32"/>If the Son brings glory to God, God himself will bring glory to the Son. God will do it at once.<verse eid="JHN 13:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 13:33"/>“My children, I will be with you only a little longer. You will look for me. Just as I told the Jews, so I am telling you now. You can’t come where I am going.<verse eid="JHN 13:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 13:34"/>“I give you a new command. Love one another. You must love one another, just as I have loved you. <verse eid="JHN 13:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 13:35"/>If you love one another, everyone will know you are my disciples.”<verse eid="JHN 13:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 13:36"/>Simon Peter asked him, “Lord, where are you going?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 13:36">Jesus replied, “Where I am going you can’t follow now. But you will follow me later.”<verse eid="JHN 13:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 13:37"/>“Lord,” Peter asked, “why can’t I follow you now? I will give my life for you.”<verse eid="JHN 13:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 13:38"/>Then Jesus answered, “Will you really give your life for me? What I’m about to tell you is true. Before the rooster crows, you will say three times that you don’t know me!<verse eid="JHN 13:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="JHN 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Comforts His Disciples</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 14:1"/>“Do not let your hearts be troubled. You believe in God. Believe in me also. <verse eid="JHN 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 14:2"/>There are many rooms in my Father’s house. If this were not true, would I have told you that I am going there? Would I have told you that I would prepare a place for you there? <verse eid="JHN 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 14:3"/>If I go and do that, I will come back. And I will take you to be with me. Then you will also be where I am. <verse eid="JHN 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 14:4"/>You know the way to the place where I am going.”<verse eid="JHN 14:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Is the Way to the Father</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 14:5"/>Thomas said to him, “Lord, we don’t know where you are going. So how can we know the way?”<verse eid="JHN 14:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 14:6"/>Jesus answered, “I am the way and the truth and the life. No one comes to the Father except through me. <verse eid="JHN 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 14:7"/>If you really know me, you will know my Father also. From now on, you do know him. And you have seen him.”<verse eid="JHN 14:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 14:8"/>Philip said, “Lord, show us the Father. That will be enough for us.”<verse eid="JHN 14:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 14:9"/>Jesus answered, “Don’t you know me, Philip? I have been among you such a long time! Anyone who has seen me has seen the Father. So how can you say, ‘Show us the Father’? <verse eid="JHN 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 14:10"/>Don’t you believe that I am in the Father? Don’t you believe that the Father is in me? The words I say to you I do not speak on my own authority. The Father lives in me. He is the one who is doing his work. <verse eid="JHN 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 14:11"/>Believe me when I say I am in the Father. Also believe that the Father is in me. Or at least believe what the works I have been doing say about me. <verse eid="JHN 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 14:12"/>What I’m about to tell you is true. Anyone who believes in me will do the works I have been doing. In fact, they will do even greater things. That’s because I am going to the Father. <verse eid="JHN 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 14:13"/>And I will do anything you ask in my name. Then the Father will receive glory from the Son. <verse eid="JHN 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 14:14"/>You may ask me for anything in my name. I will do it.<verse eid="JHN 14:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Promises That the Holy Spirit Will Come</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 14:15"/>“If you love me, obey my commands. <verse eid="JHN 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 14:16"/>I will ask the Father. And he will give you another friend to help you and to be with you forever. <verse eid="JHN 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 14:17"/>That friend is the Spirit of truth. The world can’t accept him. That’s because the world does not see him or know him. But you know him. He lives with you, and he will be in you. <verse eid="JHN 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 14:18"/>I will not leave you like children who don’t have parents. I will come to you. <verse eid="JHN 14:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 14:19"/>Before long, the world will not see me anymore. But you will see me. Because I live, you will live also. <verse eid="JHN 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 14:20"/>On that day you will realize that I am in my Father. You will know that you are in me, and I am in you. <verse eid="JHN 14:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 14:21"/>Anyone who has my commands and obeys them loves me. My Father will love the one who loves me. I too will love them. And I will show myself to them.”<verse eid="JHN 14:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 14:22"/>Then Judas spoke. “Lord,” he said, “why do you plan to show yourself only to us? Why not also to the world?” The Judas who spoke those words was not Judas Iscariot.<verse eid="JHN 14:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 14:23"/>Jesus replied, “Anyone who loves me will obey my teaching. My Father will love them. We will come to them and make our home with them. <verse eid="JHN 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 14:24"/>Anyone who does not love me will not obey my teaching. The words you hear me say are not my own. They belong to the Father who sent me.<verse eid="JHN 14:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 14:25"/>“I have spoken all these things while I am still with you. <verse eid="JHN 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 14:26"/>But the Father will send the Friend in my name to help you. The Friend is the Holy Spirit. He will teach you all things. He will remind you of everything I have said to you. <verse eid="JHN 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 14:27"/>I leave my peace with you. I give my peace to you. I do not give it to you as the world does. Do not let your hearts be troubled. And do not be afraid.<verse eid="JHN 14:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 14:28"/>“You heard me say, ‘I am going away. And I am coming back to you.’ If you loved me, you would be glad I am going to the Father. The Father is greater than I am. <verse eid="JHN 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 14:29"/>I have told you now before it happens. Then when it does happen, you will believe. <verse eid="JHN 14:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 14:30"/>I will not say much more to you. The prince of this world is coming. He has no power over me. <verse eid="JHN 14:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 14:31"/>But he comes so that the world may learn that I love the Father. They must also learn that I do exactly what my Father has commanded me to do.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 14:31">“Come now. Let us leave.<verse eid="JHN 14:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="JHN 15"/>
  <para style="s1">The Vine and the Branches</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 15:1"/>“I am the true vine. My Father is the gardener. <verse eid="JHN 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 15:2"/>He cuts off every branch joined to me that does not bear fruit. He trims every branch that does bear fruit. Then it will bear even more fruit. <verse eid="JHN 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 15:3"/>You are already clean because of the word I have spoken to you. <verse eid="JHN 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 15:4"/>Remain joined to me, just as I also remain joined to you. No branch can bear fruit by itself. It must remain joined to the vine. In the same way, you can’t bear fruit unless you remain joined to me.<verse eid="JHN 15:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 15:5"/>“I am the vine. You are the branches. If you remain joined to me, and I to you, you will bear a lot of fruit. You can’t do anything without me. <verse eid="JHN 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 15:6"/>If you don’t remain joined to me, you are like a branch that is thrown away and dries up. Branches like those are picked up. They are thrown into the fire and burned. <verse eid="JHN 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 15:7"/>If you remain joined to me and my words remain in you, ask for anything you wish. And it will be done for you. <verse eid="JHN 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 15:8"/>When you bear a lot of fruit, it brings glory to my Father. It shows that you are my disciples.<verse eid="JHN 15:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 15:9"/>“Just as the Father has loved me, I have loved you. Now remain in my love. <verse eid="JHN 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 15:10"/>If you obey my commands, you will remain in my love. In the same way, I have obeyed my Father’s commands and remain in his love. <verse eid="JHN 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 15:11"/>I have told you this so that you will have the same joy that I have. I also want your joy to be complete. <verse eid="JHN 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 15:12"/>Here is my command. Love one another, just as I have loved you. <verse eid="JHN 15:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 15:13"/>No one has greater love than the one who gives their life for their friends. <verse eid="JHN 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 15:14"/>You are my friends if you do what I command. <verse eid="JHN 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 15:15"/>I do not call you slaves anymore. Slaves do not know their master’s business. Instead, I have called you friends. I have told you everything I learned from my Father. <verse eid="JHN 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 15:16"/>You did not choose me. Instead, I chose you. I appointed you so that you might go and bear fruit that will last. I also appointed you so that the Father will give you what you ask for. He will give you whatever you ask for in my name. <verse eid="JHN 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 15:17"/>Here is my command. Love one another.<verse eid="JHN 15:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The World Hates the Disciples</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 15:18"/>“My disciples, does the world hate you? Remember that it hated me first. <verse eid="JHN 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 15:19"/>If you belonged to the world, it would love you like one of its own. But you do not belong to the world. I have chosen you out of the world. That is why the world hates you. <verse eid="JHN 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 15:20"/>Remember what I told you. I said, ‘A slave is not more important than his master.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="JHN 13:16">John 13:16</ref>)</char> If people hated me and tried to hurt me, they will do the same to you. If they obeyed my teaching, they will obey yours also. <verse eid="JHN 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 15:21"/>They will treat you like that because of my name. They do not know the one who sent me. <verse eid="JHN 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 15:22"/>If I had not come and spoken to them, they would not be guilty of sin. But now they have no excuse for their sin. <verse eid="JHN 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 15:23"/>Whoever hates me hates my Father also. <verse eid="JHN 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 15:24"/>I did works among them that no one else did. If I hadn’t, they would not be guilty of sin. But now they have seen those works. And still they have hated both me and my Father. <verse eid="JHN 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 15:25"/>This has happened so that what is written in their Law would come true. It says, ‘They hated me without any reason.’ <char style="rq">(<char style="xt" link-href="PSA 35:19">Psalms <ref loc="PSA 35:19">35:19</ref></char>; <char style="xt" link-href="PSA 69:4"><ref loc="PSA 69:4">69:4</ref></char>)</char><verse eid="JHN 15:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Work of the Holy Spirit</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 15:26"/>“I will send the Friend to you from the Father. He is the Spirit of truth, who comes out from the Father. When the Friend comes to help you, he will be a witness about me. <verse eid="JHN 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 15:27"/>You must also be witnesses about me. That’s because you have been with me from the beginning.<verse eid="JHN 15:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="JHN 16"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 16:1"/>“I have told you all this so that you will not turn away from the truth. <verse eid="JHN 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 16:2"/>You will be thrown out of the synagogue. In fact, the time is coming when someone may kill you. And they will think they are doing God a favor. <verse eid="JHN 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 16:3"/>They will do things like that because they do not know the Father or me. <verse eid="JHN 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 16:4"/>Why have I told you this? So that when their time comes, you will remember that I warned you about them. I didn’t tell you this from the beginning because I was with you. <verse eid="JHN 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 16:5"/>But now I am going to the one who sent me. None of you asks me, ‘Where are you going?’ <verse eid="JHN 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 16:6"/>Instead, you are filled with sadness because I have said these things. <verse eid="JHN 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 16:7"/>But what I’m about to tell you is true. It is for your good that I am going away. Unless I go away, the Friend will not come to help you. But if I go, I will send him to you. <verse eid="JHN 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 16:8"/>When he comes, he will prove that the world’s people are guilty. He will prove their guilt concerning sin and godliness and judgment. <verse eid="JHN 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 16:9"/>The world is guilty as far as sin is concerned. That’s because people do not believe in me. <verse eid="JHN 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 16:10"/>The world is guilty as far as godliness is concerned. That’s because I am going to the Father, where you can’t see me anymore. <verse eid="JHN 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 16:11"/>The world is guilty as far as judgment is concerned. That’s because the devil, the prince of this world, has already been judged.<verse eid="JHN 16:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 16:12"/>“I have much more to say to you. It is more than you can handle right now. <verse eid="JHN 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 16:13"/>But when the Spirit of truth comes, he will guide you into all the truth. He will not speak on his own. He will speak only what he hears. And he will tell you what is still going to happen. <verse eid="JHN 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 16:14"/>He will bring me glory. That’s because what he receives from me he will show to you. <verse eid="JHN 16:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 16:15"/>Everything that belongs to the Father is mine. That is why I said what the Holy Spirit receives from me he will show to you.”<verse eid="JHN 16:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Disciples’ Sadness Will Turn Into Joy</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 16:16"/>Jesus continued, “In a little while, you will no longer see me. Then after a little while, you will see me.”<verse eid="JHN 16:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 16:17"/>After they heard this, some of his disciples spoke to one another. They said, “What does he mean by saying, ‘In a little while, you will no longer see me. Then after a little while, you will see me’? And what does he mean by saying, ‘I am going to the Father’?” <verse eid="JHN 16:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 16:18"/>They kept asking, “What does he mean by ‘a little while’? We don’t understand what he is saying.”<verse eid="JHN 16:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 16:19"/>Jesus saw that they wanted to ask him about these things. So he said to them, “Are you asking one another what I meant? Didn’t you understand when I said, ‘In a little while, you will no longer see me. Then after a little while, you will see me’? <verse eid="JHN 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 16:20"/>What I’m about to tell you is true. You will weep and mourn while the world is full of joy. You will be sad, but your sadness will turn into joy. <verse eid="JHN 16:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 16:21"/>A woman giving birth to a baby has pain. That’s because her time to give birth has come. But when her baby is born, she forgets the pain. She forgets because she is so happy that a baby has been born into the world. <verse eid="JHN 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 16:22"/>That’s the way it is with you. Now it’s your time to be sad. But I will see you again. Then you will be full of joy. And no one will take away your joy. <verse eid="JHN 16:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 16:23"/>When that day comes, you will no longer ask me for anything. What I’m about to tell you is true. My Father will give you anything you ask for in my name. <verse eid="JHN 16:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 16:24"/>Until now you have not asked for anything in my name. Ask, and you will receive what you ask for. Then your joy will be complete.<verse eid="JHN 16:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 16:25"/>“I have not been speaking to you plainly. But a time is coming when I will speak clearly. Then I will tell you plainly about my Father. <verse eid="JHN 16:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 16:26"/>When that day comes, you will ask for things in my name. I am not saying I will ask the Father instead of you asking him. <verse eid="JHN 16:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 16:27"/>No, the Father himself loves you because you have loved me. He also loves you because you have believed that I came from God. <verse eid="JHN 16:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 16:28"/>I came from the Father and entered the world. Now I am leaving the world and going back to the Father.”<verse eid="JHN 16:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 16:29"/>Then Jesus’ disciples said, “Now you are speaking plainly. You are using examples that are clear. <verse eid="JHN 16:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 16:30"/>Now we can see that you know everything. You don’t even need anyone to ask you questions. This makes us believe that you came from God.”<verse eid="JHN 16:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 16:31"/>“Do you believe now?” Jesus replied. <verse eid="JHN 16:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 16:32"/>“A time is coming when you will be scattered and go to your own homes. In fact, that time is already here. You will leave me all alone. But I am not really alone. My Father is with me.<verse eid="JHN 16:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 16:33"/>“I have told you these things, so that you can have peace because of me. In this world you will have trouble. But be encouraged! I have won the battle over the world.”<verse eid="JHN 16:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="JHN 17"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Prays for Himself</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 17:1"/>After Jesus said this, he looked toward heaven and prayed. He said,</para>
  <para style="pm" vid="JHN 17:1">“Father, the time has come. Bring glory to your Son. Then your Son will bring glory to you. <verse eid="JHN 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 17:2"/>You gave him authority over all people. He gives eternal life to all those you have given him. <verse eid="JHN 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 17:3"/>And what is eternal life? It is knowing you, the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom you have sent. <verse eid="JHN 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 17:4"/>I have brought you glory on earth. I have finished the work you gave me to do. <verse eid="JHN 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 17:5"/>So now, Father, give glory to me in heaven where your throne is. Give me the glory I had with you before the world began.<verse eid="JHN 17:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Prays for His Disciples</para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 17:6"/>“I have shown you to the disciples you gave me out of the world. They were yours. You gave them to me. And they have obeyed your word. <verse eid="JHN 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 17:7"/>Now they know that everything you have given me comes from you. <verse eid="JHN 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 17:8"/>I gave them the words you gave me. And they accepted them. They knew for certain that I came from you. They believed that you sent me. <verse eid="JHN 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 17:9"/>I pray for them. I am not praying for the world. I am praying for those you have given me, because they are yours. <verse eid="JHN 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 17:10"/>All I have is yours, and all you have is mine. Glory has come to me because of my disciples. <verse eid="JHN 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 17:11"/>I will not remain in the world any longer. But they are still in the world, and I am coming to you. Holy Father, keep them safe by the power of your name. It is the name you gave me. Keep them safe so they can be one, just as you and I are one. <verse eid="JHN 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 17:12"/>While I was with them, I guarded them. I kept them safe through the name you gave me. None of them has been lost, except the one who was headed for ruin. It happened so that Scripture would come true.<verse eid="JHN 17:12"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 17:13"/>“I am coming to you now. But I say these things while I am still in the world. I say them so that those you gave me can have the same joy that I have. <verse eid="JHN 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 17:14"/>I have given them your word. The world has hated them. That’s because they are not part of the world any more than I am. <verse eid="JHN 17:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 17:15"/>I do not pray that you will take them out of the world. I pray that you will keep them safe from the evil one. <verse eid="JHN 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 17:16"/>They do not belong to the world, just as I do not belong to it. <verse eid="JHN 17:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 17:17"/>Use the truth to make them holy. Your word is truth. <verse eid="JHN 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 17:18"/>You sent me into the world. In the same way, I have sent them into the world. <verse eid="JHN 17:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 17:19"/>I make myself holy for them so that they too can be made holy by the truth.<verse eid="JHN 17:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Prays for All Believers</para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 17:20"/>“I do not pray only for them. I pray also for everyone who will believe in me because of their message. <verse eid="JHN 17:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 17:21"/>Father, I pray they will be one, just as you are in me and I am in you. I want them also to be in us. Then the world will believe that you have sent me. <verse eid="JHN 17:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 17:22"/>I have given them the glory you gave me. I did this so they would be one, just as we are one. <verse eid="JHN 17:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 17:23"/>I will be in them, just as you are in me. This is so that they may be brought together perfectly as one. Then the world will know that you sent me. It will also show the world that you have loved those you gave me, just as you have loved me.<verse eid="JHN 17:23"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 17:24"/>“Father, I want those you have given me to be with me where I am. I want them to see my glory, the glory you have given me. You gave it to me because you loved me before the world was created.<verse eid="JHN 17:24"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 17:25"/>“Father, you are holy. The world does not know you, but I know you. Those you have given me know you have sent me. <verse eid="JHN 17:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 17:26"/>I have shown you to them. And I will continue to show you to them. Then the love you have for me will be in them. I myself will be in them.”<verse eid="JHN 17:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="JHN 18"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Is Arrested</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 18:1"/>When Jesus had finished praying, he left with his disciples. They crossed the Kidron Valley. On the other side there was a garden. Jesus and his disciples went into it.<verse eid="JHN 18:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 18:2"/>Judas knew the place. He was going to hand Jesus over to his enemies. Jesus had often met in that place with his disciples. <verse eid="JHN 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 18:3"/>So Judas came to the garden. He was guiding a group of soldiers and some officials. The chief priests and the Pharisees had sent them. They were carrying torches, lanterns and weapons.<verse eid="JHN 18:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 18:4"/>Jesus knew everything that was going to happen to him. So he went out and asked them, “Who do you want?”<verse eid="JHN 18:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 18:5"/>“Jesus of Nazareth,” they replied.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 18:5">“I am he,” Jesus said. Judas, who was going to hand Jesus over, was standing there with them. <verse eid="JHN 18:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 18:6"/>When Jesus said, “I am he,” they moved back. Then they fell to the ground.<verse eid="JHN 18:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 18:7"/>He asked them again, “Who do you want?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 18:7">“Jesus of Nazareth,” they said.<verse eid="JHN 18:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 18:8"/>Jesus answered, “I told you I am he. If you are looking for me, then let these men go.” <verse eid="JHN 18:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 18:9"/>This happened so that the words Jesus had spoken would come true. He had said, “I have not lost anyone God has given me.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="JHN 6:39">John 6:39</ref>)</char><verse eid="JHN 18:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 18:10"/>Simon Peter had a sword and pulled it out. He struck the high priest’s slave and cut off his right ear. The slave’s name was Malchus.<verse eid="JHN 18:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 18:11"/>Jesus commanded Peter, “Put your sword away! Shouldn’t I drink the cup of suffering the Father has given me?”<verse eid="JHN 18:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 18:12"/>Then the group of soldiers, their commander and the Jewish officials arrested Jesus. They tied him up <verse eid="JHN 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 18:13"/>and brought him first to Annas. He was the father-in-law of Caiaphas, the high priest at that time. <verse eid="JHN 18:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 18:14"/>Caiaphas had advised the Jewish leaders that it would be good if one man died for the people.<verse eid="JHN 18:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Peter Says He Is Not Jesus’ Disciple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 18:15"/>Simon Peter and another disciple were following Jesus. The high priest knew the other disciple. So that disciple went with Jesus into the high priest’s courtyard. <verse eid="JHN 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 18:16"/>But Peter had to wait outside by the door. The other disciple came back. He was the one the high priest knew. He spoke to the servant woman who was on duty there. Then he brought Peter in.<verse eid="JHN 18:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 18:17"/>She asked Peter, “You aren’t one of Jesus’ disciples too, are you?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 18:17">“I am not,” he replied.<verse eid="JHN 18:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 18:18"/>It was cold. The slaves and officials stood around a fire. They had made it to keep warm. Peter was also standing with them. He was warming himself.<verse eid="JHN 18:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The High Priest Questions Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 18:19"/>Meanwhile, the high priest questioned Jesus. He asked him about his disciples and his teaching.<verse eid="JHN 18:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 18:20"/>“I have spoken openly to the world,” Jesus replied. “I always taught in synagogues or at the temple, where all the Jews come together. I didn’t say anything in secret. <verse eid="JHN 18:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 18:21"/>Why question me? Ask the people who heard me. They certainly know what I said.”<verse eid="JHN 18:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 18:22"/>When Jesus said that, one of the officials nearby slapped him in the face. “Is this any way to answer the high priest?” he asked.<verse eid="JHN 18:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 18:23"/>“Have I said something wrong?” Jesus replied. “If I have, then tell everyone what it was. But if I spoke the truth, why did you hit me?” <verse eid="JHN 18:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 18:24"/>Annas sent him, tied up, to Caiaphas, the high priest.<verse eid="JHN 18:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Peter Again Says He Is Not Jesus’ Disciple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 18:25"/>Meanwhile, Simon Peter was still standing there warming himself by the fire. So they asked him, “You aren’t one of Jesus’ disciples too, are you?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 18:25">He said, “I am not.”<verse eid="JHN 18:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 18:26"/>One of the high priest’s slaves was a relative of the man whose ear Peter had cut off. He said to Peter, “Didn’t I see you with Jesus in the garden?” <verse eid="JHN 18:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 18:27"/>Again Peter said no. At that exact moment a rooster began to crow.<verse eid="JHN 18:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Is Brought to Pilate</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 18:28"/>Then the Jewish leaders took Jesus from Caiaphas to the palace of the Roman governor. By now it was early morning. The Jewish leaders did not want to be made “unclean.” They wanted to be able to eat the Passover meal. So they did not enter the palace. <verse eid="JHN 18:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 18:29"/>Pilate came out to them. He asked, “What charges are you bringing against this man?”<verse eid="JHN 18:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 18:30"/>“He has committed crimes,” they replied. “If he hadn’t, we would not have handed him over to you.”<verse eid="JHN 18:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 18:31"/>Pilate said, “Take him yourselves. Judge him by your own law.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 18:31">“But we don’t have the right to put anyone to death,” they complained. <verse eid="JHN 18:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 18:32"/>This happened so that what Jesus said about how he was going to die would come true.<verse eid="JHN 18:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 18:33"/>Then Pilate went back inside the palace. He ordered Jesus to be brought to him. Pilate asked him, “Are you the king of the Jews?”<verse eid="JHN 18:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 18:34"/>“Is that your own idea?” Jesus asked. “Or did others talk to you about me?”<verse eid="JHN 18:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 18:35"/>“Am I a Jew?” Pilate replied. “Your own people and chief priests handed you over to me. What have you done?”<verse eid="JHN 18:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 18:36"/>Jesus said, “My kingdom is not from this world. If it were, those who serve me would fight. They would try to keep the Jewish leaders from arresting me. My kingdom is from another place.”<verse eid="JHN 18:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 18:37"/>“So you are a king, then!” said Pilate.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 18:37">Jesus answered, “You say that I am a king. In fact, that’s the reason I was born. I was born and came into the world to be a witness to the truth. Everyone who is on the side of truth listens to me.”<verse eid="JHN 18:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 18:38"/>“What is truth?” Pilate replied. Then Pilate went out again to the Jews gathered there. He said, “I find no basis for any charge against him. <verse eid="JHN 18:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 18:39"/>But you have a practice at Passover time. At that time, you ask me to set one prisoner free for you. Do you want me to set ‘the king of the Jews’ free?”<verse eid="JHN 18:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 18:40"/>They shouted back, “No! Not him! Give us Barabbas!” Barabbas had taken part in an armed struggle against the country’s rulers.<verse eid="JHN 18:40"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="JHN 19"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Is Sentenced to Be Crucified</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 19:1"/>Then Pilate took Jesus and had him whipped. <verse eid="JHN 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 19:2"/>The soldiers twisted thorns together to make a crown. They put it on Jesus’ head. Then they put a purple robe on him. <verse eid="JHN 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 19:3"/>They went up to him again and again. They kept saying, “We honor you, king of the Jews!” And they slapped him in the face.<verse eid="JHN 19:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 19:4"/>Once more Pilate came out. He said to the Jews gathered there, “Look, I am bringing Jesus out to you. I want to let you know that I find no basis for a charge against him.” <verse eid="JHN 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 19:5"/>Jesus came out wearing the crown of thorns and the purple robe. Then Pilate said to them, “Here is the man!”<verse eid="JHN 19:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 19:6"/>As soon as the chief priests and their officials saw him, they shouted, “Crucify him! Crucify him!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 19:6">But Pilate answered, “You take him and crucify him. I myself find no basis for a charge against him.”<verse eid="JHN 19:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 19:7"/>The Jewish leaders replied, “We have a law. That law says he must die. He claimed to be the Son of God.”<verse eid="JHN 19:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 19:8"/>When Pilate heard that, he was even more afraid. <verse eid="JHN 19:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 19:9"/>He went back inside the palace. “Where do you come from?” he asked Jesus. But Jesus did not answer him. <verse eid="JHN 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 19:10"/>“Do you refuse to speak to me?” Pilate said. “Don’t you understand? I have the power to set you free or to nail you to a cross.”<verse eid="JHN 19:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 19:11"/>Jesus answered, “You were given power from heaven. If you weren’t, you would have no power over me. So the one who handed me over to you is guilty of a greater sin.”<verse eid="JHN 19:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 19:12"/>From then on, Pilate tried to set Jesus free. But the Jewish leaders kept shouting, “If you let this man go, you are not Caesar’s friend! Anyone who claims to be a king is against Caesar!”<verse eid="JHN 19:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 19:13"/>When Pilate heard that, he brought Jesus out. Pilate sat down on the judge’s seat. It was at a place called the Stone Walkway. In the Aramaic language it was called Gabbatha. <verse eid="JHN 19:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 19:14"/>It was about noon on Preparation Day in Passover Week.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 19:14">“Here is your king,” Pilate said to the Jews.<verse eid="JHN 19:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 19:15"/>But they shouted, “Take him away! Take him away! Crucify him!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 19:15">“Should I crucify your king?” Pilate asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 19:15">“We have no king but Caesar,” the chief priests answered.<verse eid="JHN 19:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 19:16"/>Finally, Pilate handed Jesus over to them to be nailed to a cross.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="JHN 19:16">Jesus Is Nailed to a Cross</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 19:16">So the soldiers took charge of Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 19:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 19:17"/>He had to carry his own cross. He went out to a place called the Skull. In the Aramaic language it was called Golgotha. <verse eid="JHN 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 19:18"/>There they nailed Jesus to the cross. Two other men were crucified with him. One was on each side of him. Jesus was in the middle.<verse eid="JHN 19:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 19:19"/>Pilate had a notice prepared. It was fastened to the cross. It read,</para>
  <para style="pc" vid="JHN 19:19">Jesus of Nazareth, the King of the Jews.<verse eid="JHN 19:19"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 19:20"/>Many of the Jews read the sign. That’s because the place where Jesus was crucified was near the city. And the sign was written in the Aramaic, Latin and Greek languages. <verse eid="JHN 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 19:21"/>The chief priests of the Jews argued with Pilate. They said, “Do not write ‘The King of the Jews.’ Write that this man claimed to be king of the Jews.”<verse eid="JHN 19:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 19:22"/>Pilate answered, “I have written what I have written.”<verse eid="JHN 19:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 19:23"/>When the soldiers crucified Jesus, they took his clothes. They divided them into four parts. Each soldier got one part. All that was left was Jesus’ long, inner robe. It did not have any seams. It was made out of one piece of cloth from top to bottom.<verse eid="JHN 19:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 19:24"/>“Let’s not tear it,” they said to one another. “Let’s cast lots to see who will get it.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 19:24">This happened so that Scripture would come true. It says,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 19:24">“They divided up my clothes among them.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JHN 19:24">They cast lots for what I was wearing.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="PSA 22:18">Psalm 22:18</ref>)</char></para>
  <para style="m" vid="JHN 19:24">So that is what the soldiers did.<verse eid="JHN 19:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 19:25"/>Jesus’ mother stood near his cross. So did his mother’s sister, Mary the wife of Clopas, and Mary Magdalene. <verse eid="JHN 19:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 19:26"/>Jesus saw his mother there. He also saw the disciple he loved standing nearby. Jesus said to his mother, “Dear woman, here is your son.” <verse eid="JHN 19:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 19:27"/>He said to the disciple, “Here is your mother.” From that time on, the disciple took her into his home.<verse eid="JHN 19:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Dies</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 19:28"/>Later, Jesus knew that everything had now been finished. He also knew that what Scripture said must come true. So he said, “I am thirsty.” <verse eid="JHN 19:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 19:29"/>A jar of wine vinegar was there. So they soaked a sponge in it. They put the sponge on the stem of a hyssop plant. Then they lifted it up to Jesus’ lips. <verse eid="JHN 19:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 19:30"/>After Jesus drank he said, “It is finished.” Then he bowed his head and died.<verse eid="JHN 19:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 19:31"/>It was Preparation Day. The next day would be a special Sabbath day. The Jewish leaders did not want the bodies left on the crosses during the Sabbath day. So they asked Pilate to have the legs broken and the bodies taken down. <verse eid="JHN 19:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 19:32"/>The soldiers came and broke the legs of the first man who had been crucified with Jesus. Then they broke the legs of the other man. <verse eid="JHN 19:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 19:33"/>But when they came to Jesus, they saw that he was already dead. So they did not break his legs. <verse eid="JHN 19:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 19:34"/>Instead, one of the soldiers stuck his spear into Jesus’ side. Right away, blood and water flowed out. <verse eid="JHN 19:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 19:35"/>The man who saw it has been a witness about it. And what he has said is true. He knows that he tells the truth. He is a witness so that you also may believe. <verse eid="JHN 19:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 19:36"/>These things happened in order that Scripture would come true. It says, “Not one of his bones will be broken.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="EXO 12:46">Exodus 12:46</ref>; <ref loc="NUM 9:12">Numbers 9:12</ref>; <ref loc="PSA 34:20">Psalm 34:20</ref>)</char> <verse eid="JHN 19:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 19:37"/>Scripture also says, “They will look to the one they have pierced.” <char style="rq">(<ref loc="ZEC 12:10">Zechariah 12:10</ref>)</char><verse eid="JHN 19:37"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Is Buried</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 19:38"/>Later Joseph asked Pilate for Jesus’ body. Joseph was from the town of Arimathea. He was a follower of Jesus. But he followed Jesus secretly because he was afraid of the Jewish leaders. After Pilate gave him permission, Joseph came and took the body away. <verse eid="JHN 19:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 19:39"/>Nicodemus went with Joseph. He was the man who had earlier visited Jesus at night. Nicodemus brought some mixed spices that weighed about 75 pounds. <verse eid="JHN 19:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 19:40"/>The two men took Jesus’ body. They wrapped it in strips of linen cloth, along with the spices. That was the way the Jews buried people. <verse eid="JHN 19:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 19:41"/>At the place where Jesus was crucified, there was a garden. A new tomb was there. No one had ever been put in it before. <verse eid="JHN 19:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 19:42"/>That day was the Jewish Preparation Day, and the tomb was nearby. So they placed Jesus there.<verse eid="JHN 19:42"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="JHN 20"/>
  <para style="s1">The Tomb Is Empty</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 20:1"/>Early on the first day of the week, Mary Magdalene went to the tomb. It was still dark. She saw that the stone had been moved away from the entrance. <verse eid="JHN 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 20:2"/>So she ran to Simon Peter and another disciple, the one Jesus loved. She said, “They have taken the Lord out of the tomb! We don’t know where they have put him!”<verse eid="JHN 20:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 20:3"/>So Peter and the other disciple started out for the tomb. <verse eid="JHN 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 20:4"/>Both of them were running. The other disciple ran faster than Peter. He reached the tomb first. <verse eid="JHN 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 20:5"/>He bent over and looked in at the strips of linen lying there. But he did not go in. <verse eid="JHN 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 20:6"/>Then Simon Peter came along behind him. He went straight into the tomb. He saw the strips of linen lying there. <verse eid="JHN 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 20:7"/>He also saw the funeral cloth that had been wrapped around Jesus’ head. The cloth was still lying in its place. It was separate from the linen. <verse eid="JHN 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 20:8"/>The disciple who had reached the tomb first also went inside. He saw and believed. <verse eid="JHN 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 20:9"/>They still did not understand from Scripture that Jesus had to rise from the dead. <verse eid="JHN 20:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 20:10"/>Then the disciples went back to where they were staying.<verse eid="JHN 20:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Appears to Mary Magdalene</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 20:11"/>But Mary stood outside the tomb crying. As she cried, she bent over to look into the tomb. <verse eid="JHN 20:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 20:12"/>She saw two angels dressed in white. They were seated where Jesus’ body had been. One of them was where Jesus’ head had been laid. The other sat where his feet had been placed.<verse eid="JHN 20:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 20:13"/>They asked her, “Woman, why are you crying?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 20:13">“They have taken my Lord away,” she said. “I don’t know where they have put him.” <verse eid="JHN 20:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 20:14"/>Then she turned around and saw Jesus standing there. But she didn’t realize that it was Jesus.<verse eid="JHN 20:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 20:15"/>He asked her, “Woman, why are you crying? Who are you looking for?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 20:15">She thought he was the gardener. So she said, “Sir, did you carry him away? Tell me where you put him. Then I will go and get him.”<verse eid="JHN 20:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 20:16"/>Jesus said to her, “Mary.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 20:16">She turned toward him. Then she cried out in the Aramaic language, <char style="tl">“Rabboni!”</char> Rabboni means Teacher.<verse eid="JHN 20:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 20:17"/>Jesus said, “Do not hold on to me. I have not yet ascended to the Father. Instead, go to those who believe in me. Tell them, ‘I am ascending to my Father and your Father, to my God and your God.’ ”<verse eid="JHN 20:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 20:18"/>Mary Magdalene went to the disciples with the news. She said, “I have seen the Lord!” And she told them that he had said these things to her.<verse eid="JHN 20:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Appears to His Disciples</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 20:19"/>On the evening of that first day of the week, the disciples were together. They had locked the doors because they were afraid of the Jewish leaders. Jesus came in and stood among them. He said, “May peace be with you!” <verse eid="JHN 20:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 20:20"/>Then he showed them his hands and his side. The disciples were very happy when they saw the Lord.<verse eid="JHN 20:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 20:21"/>Again Jesus said, “May peace be with you! The Father has sent me. So now I am sending you.” <verse eid="JHN 20:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 20:22"/>He then breathed on them. He said, “Receive the Holy Spirit. <verse eid="JHN 20:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 20:23"/>If you forgive anyone’s sins, their sins are forgiven. If you do not forgive them, they are not forgiven.”<verse eid="JHN 20:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Appears to Thomas</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 20:24"/>Thomas was one of the 12 disciples. He was also called Didymus. He was not with the other disciples when Jesus came. <verse eid="JHN 20:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 20:25"/>So they told him, “We have seen the Lord!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 20:25">But he said to them, “First I must see the nail marks in his hands. I must put my finger where the nails were. I must put my hand into his side. Only then will I believe.”<verse eid="JHN 20:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 20:26"/>A week later, Jesus’ disciples were in the house again. Thomas was with them. Even though the doors were locked, Jesus came in and stood among them. He said, “May peace be with you!” <verse eid="JHN 20:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 20:27"/>Then he said to Thomas, “Put your finger here. See my hands. Reach out your hand and put it into my side. Stop doubting and believe.”<verse eid="JHN 20:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 20:28"/>Thomas said to him, “My Lord and my God!”<verse eid="JHN 20:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 20:29"/>Then Jesus told him, “Because you have seen me, you have believed. Blessed are those who have not seen me but still have believed.”<verse eid="JHN 20:29"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Purpose of John’s Gospel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 20:30"/>Jesus performed many other signs in front of his disciples. They are not written down in this book. <verse eid="JHN 20:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 20:31"/>But these are written so that you may believe that Jesus is the Messiah, the Son of God. If you believe this, you will have life because you belong to him.<verse eid="JHN 20:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="JHN 21"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus and the Miracle of Many Fish</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 21:1"/>After this, Jesus appeared to his disciples again. It was by the Sea of Galilee. Here is what happened. <verse eid="JHN 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 21:2"/>Simon Peter and Thomas, who was also called Didymus, were there together. Nathanael from Cana in Galilee and the sons of Zebedee were with them. So were two other disciples. <verse eid="JHN 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 21:3"/>“I’m going out to fish,” Simon Peter told them. They said, “We’ll go with you.” So they went out and got into the boat. That night they didn’t catch anything.<verse eid="JHN 21:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 21:4"/>Early in the morning, Jesus stood on the shore. But the disciples did not realize that it was Jesus.<verse eid="JHN 21:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 21:5"/>He called out to them, “Friends, don’t you have any fish?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 21:5">“No,” they answered.<verse eid="JHN 21:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 21:6"/>He said, “Throw your net on the right side of the boat. There you will find some fish.” When they did, they could not pull the net into the boat. There were too many fish in it.<verse eid="JHN 21:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 21:7"/>Then the disciple Jesus loved said to Simon Peter, “It is the Lord!” As soon as Peter heard that, he put his coat on. He had taken it off earlier. Then he jumped into the water. <verse eid="JHN 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 21:8"/>The other disciples followed in the boat. They were towing the net full of fish. The shore was only about 100 yards away. <verse eid="JHN 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 21:9"/>When they landed, they saw a fire of burning coals. There were fish on it. There was also some bread.<verse eid="JHN 21:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 21:10"/>Jesus said to them, “Bring some of the fish you have just caught.” <verse eid="JHN 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 21:11"/>So Simon Peter climbed back into the boat. He dragged the net to shore. It was full of large fish. There were 153 of them. But even with that many fish the net was not torn. <verse eid="JHN 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 21:12"/>Jesus said to them, “Come and have breakfast.” None of the disciples dared to ask him, “Who are you?” They knew it was the Lord. <verse eid="JHN 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 21:13"/>Jesus came, took the bread and gave it to them. He did the same thing with the fish. <verse eid="JHN 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 21:14"/>This was the third time Jesus appeared to his disciples after he was raised from the dead.<verse eid="JHN 21:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus Gives Peter His Task</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 21:15"/>When Jesus and the disciples had finished eating, Jesus spoke to Simon Peter. He asked, “Simon, son of John, do you love me more than these others do?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 21:15">“Yes, Lord,” he answered. “You know that I love you.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 21:15">Jesus said, “Feed my lambs.”<verse eid="JHN 21:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 21:16"/>Again Jesus asked, “Simon, son of John, do you love me?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 21:16">He answered, “Yes, Lord. You know that I love you.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 21:16">Jesus said, “Take care of my sheep.”<verse eid="JHN 21:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 21:17"/>Jesus spoke to him a third time. He asked, “Simon, son of John, do you love me?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 21:17">Peter felt bad because Jesus asked him the third time, “Do you love me?” He answered, “Lord, you know all things. You know that I love you.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 21:17">Jesus said, “Feed my sheep. <verse eid="JHN 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 21:18"/>What I’m about to tell you is true. When you were younger, you dressed yourself. You went wherever you wanted to go. But when you are old, you will stretch out your hands. Someone else will dress you. Someone else will lead you where you do not want to go.” <verse eid="JHN 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 21:19"/>Jesus said this to point out how Peter would die. His death would bring glory to God. Then Jesus said to him, “Follow me!”<verse eid="JHN 21:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 21:20"/>Peter turned around. He saw that the disciple Jesus loved was following them. He was the one who had leaned back against Jesus at the supper. He had said, “Lord, who is going to hand you over to your enemies?” <verse eid="JHN 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 21:21"/>When Peter saw that disciple, he asked, “Lord, what will happen to him?”<verse eid="JHN 21:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 21:22"/>Jesus answered, “Suppose I want him to remain alive until I return. What does that matter to you? You must follow me.” <verse eid="JHN 21:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 21:23"/>Because of what Jesus said, a false report spread among the believers. The story was told that the disciple Jesus loved wouldn’t die. But Jesus did not say he would not die. He only said, “Suppose I want him to remain alive until I return. What does that matter to you?”<verse eid="JHN 21:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 21:24"/>This is the disciple who is a witness about these things. He also wrote them down. We know that what he says is true.<verse eid="JHN 21:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 21:25"/>Jesus also did many other things. What if every one of them were written down? I suppose that even the whole world would not have room for the books that would be written.<verse eid="JHN 21:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 21"/>
</usx>
