<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="JOS" style="id">- New International Readers Version 2014</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1995, 1996, 1998, 2014 by Biblica, Inc.</para>
  <para style="h">Joshua</para>
  <para style="toc1">Joshua</para>
  <para style="toc2">Joshua</para>
  <para style="toc3">Jos</para>
  <para style="mt1">Joshua</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">The books of Joshua and Judges present the early years of the nation of Israel. The Israelites had become a great number of people. They were divided into 12 groups or tribes. The book of Joshua tells how the tribes of Israel prepared to fight the people living in Canaan. It tells about the battles they win and lose. As the Israelites win their battles, they take over the land. Then the land is divided among the 12 tribes. And the Israelites make their homes in their new land.</para>
  <para style="ip">But living in the land of Canaan isn’t easy for the Israelites. Their neighbors don’t know or love the one true God. The Israelites struggle with the way God wants them to live. Their leader, Joshua, asks the Israelites to promise to follow the way of life God taught them.</para>
  <para style="ip">This story continues in the book of Judges. It tells the stories of 12 judges who lead the 12 tribes of Israel. And it tells about Israel’s struggle to keep their agreement with God.</para>
  <para style="ip">The Israelites do not obey God’s laws, rules, and commands. Because they disobey God, the Israelites are conquered by other nations. The Israelites must live under the rules and commands of other people. Then the Israelites call out to God for help. God hears their prayers. God brings a person called a judge to save them. The judge leads the Israelites back to God. And the Israelites say they will follow God’s way of life. They follow God’s commands for a while. But then the Israelites forget their agreement with God and they forget his commands. So their problems begin all over again.</para>
  <para style="ip">The Israelites continue to go their own way. They say no to God who is their true judge and ruler. As they continue to disobey God’s commands, their need for a king become clear. As the book of Judges ends, there are some important questions. Can Israel accomplish its calling to be God’s light to the nations around it? How can Israel find a good leader to help them do this?</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="JOS 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Joshua Becomes Israel’s Leader</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 1:1"/>Moses, the servant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, died. After that, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Joshua, the son of Nun. Joshua was Moses’ helper. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Joshua, <verse eid="JOS 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 1:2"/>“My servant Moses is dead. Now then, I want you and all these people to get ready to go across the Jordan River. I want all of you to go into the land I am about to give to the Israelites. <verse eid="JOS 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 1:3"/>I will give all of you every place you walk on, just as I promised Moses. <verse eid="JOS 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 1:4"/>Your territory will reach from the Negev Desert all the way to Lebanon. The great Euphrates River will be to the east. The Mediterranean Sea will be to the west. Your territory will include all the Hittite country. <verse eid="JOS 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 1:5"/>Joshua, no one will be able to oppose you as long as you live. I will be with you, just as I was with Moses. I will never leave you. I will never desert you. <verse eid="JOS 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 1:6"/>Be strong and brave. You will lead these people. They will take the land as their very own. It is the land I promised to give their people of long ago.<verse eid="JOS 1:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 1:7"/>“Be strong and very brave. Make sure you obey the whole law my servant Moses gave you. Do not turn away from it to the right or the left. Then you will have success everywhere you go. <verse eid="JOS 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 1:8"/>Never stop reading this Book of the Law. Day and night you must think about what it says. Make sure you do everything written in it. Then things will go well with you. And you will have great success. <verse eid="JOS 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 1:9"/>Here is what I am commanding you to do. Be strong and brave. Do not be afraid. Do not lose hope. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. I will be with you everywhere you go.”<verse eid="JOS 1:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 1:10"/>So Joshua gave orders to the officers of the people. He said, <verse eid="JOS 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 1:11"/>“Go through the camp. Tell the people, ‘Get your supplies ready. Three days from now you will go across the Jordan River right here. You will go in and take over the land. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving it to you as your very own.’ ”<verse eid="JOS 1:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 1:12"/>Joshua also spoke to the tribes of Reuben and Gad and half of the tribe of Manasseh. He said to them, <verse eid="JOS 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 1:13"/>“Remember what Moses, the servant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, commanded you. He said, ‘The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving you this land. It’s a place where you can make your homes and live in peace and rest.’ <verse eid="JOS 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 1:14"/>Your wives, children and livestock can stay here east of the Jordan River. Moses gave you this land. But all your fighting men must get ready for battle. They must go across ahead of the other tribes. You must help them <verse eid="JOS 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 1:15"/>until the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gives them rest. In the same way, he has already given you rest. You must help them until they also have taken over their land. It’s the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is giving them. After that, you can come back here. Then you can live in your own land. It’s the land that Moses, the servant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, gave you east of the Jordan River. It’s toward the sunrise.”<verse eid="JOS 1:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 1:16"/>Then the tribes of Reuben and Gad and half of the tribe of Manasseh answered Joshua. They said, “We’ll do what you have commanded us to do. We’ll go where you send us. <verse eid="JOS 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 1:17"/>We obeyed Moses completely. And we’ll obey you just as completely. But may the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God be with you, just as he was with Moses. <verse eid="JOS 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 1:18"/>Suppose people question your authority. And suppose they refuse to obey anything you command them to do. Then they will be put to death. Just be strong and brave!”<verse eid="JOS 1:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="JOS 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Rahab Helps the Spies</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 2:1"/>Joshua, the son of Nun, sent two spies from Shittim. He sent them in secret. He said to them, “Go and look over the land. Most of all, check out Jericho.” So they went to Jericho. They stayed at the house of a prostitute. Her name was Rahab.<verse eid="JOS 2:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 2:2"/>The king of Jericho was told, “Look! Some of the Israelites have come here tonight. They’ve come to check out the land.” <verse eid="JOS 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 2:3"/>So the king sent a message to Rahab. It said, “Bring out the men who came into your house. They’ve come to check out the whole land.”<verse eid="JOS 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 2:4"/>But the woman had hidden the two men. She said, “It’s true that the men came here. But I didn’t know where they had come from. <verse eid="JOS 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 2:5"/>They left at sunset, when it was time to close the city gate. I don’t know which way they went. Go after them quickly. You might catch up with them.” <verse eid="JOS 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 2:6"/>But in fact she had taken them up on the roof. There she had hidden them under some flax she had piled up. <verse eid="JOS 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 2:7"/>The king’s men left to hunt down the spies. They took the road that leads to where the Jordan River can be crossed. As soon as they had gone out of the city, the gate was shut.<verse eid="JOS 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 2:8"/>Rahab went up on the roof before the spies settled down for the night. <verse eid="JOS 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 2:9"/>She said to them, “I know that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has given you this land. We are very much afraid of you. Everyone who lives in this country is weak with fear because of you. <verse eid="JOS 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 2:10"/>We’ve heard how the <char style="nd">Lord</char> dried up the Red Sea for you when you came out of Egypt. We’ve heard what you did to Sihon and Og, the two Amorite kings. They ruled east of the Jordan River. You completely destroyed them. <verse eid="JOS 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 2:11"/>When we heard about it, we were terrified. Because of you, we aren’t brave anymore. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is the God who rules in heaven above and on the earth below.<verse eid="JOS 2:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 2:12"/>“Now then, please give me your word. Promise me in the name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> that you will be kind to my family. I’ve been kind to you. Promise me <verse eid="JOS 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 2:13"/>that you will spare the lives of my father and mother. Spare my brothers and sisters. Also spare everyone in their families. Promise that you won’t put any of us to death.”<verse eid="JOS 2:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 2:14"/>So the men made a promise to her. “If you save our lives, we’ll save yours,” they said. “Just don’t tell anyone what we’re doing. Then we’ll be kind and faithful to you when the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gives us the land.”<verse eid="JOS 2:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 2:15"/>The house Rahab lived in was part of the city wall. So she let the spies down by a rope through the window. <verse eid="JOS 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 2:16"/>She said to them, “Go up into the hills. The men chasing you won’t be able to find you. Hide yourselves there for three days until they return. Then you can go on your way.”<verse eid="JOS 2:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 2:17"/>The spies had said to her, “You made us give our word. But we won’t keep our promise <verse eid="JOS 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 2:18"/>unless you do what we say. When we enter the land, you must tie this bright red rope in the window. Tie it in the window you let us down through. Bring your father and mother into your house. Also bring in your brothers and everyone else in your family. <verse eid="JOS 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 2:19"/>None of you must go out into the street. If you do, anything that happens to you will be your own fault. We won’t be responsible. But if anyone hurts someone who is inside the house with you, it will be our fault. We will be responsible. <verse eid="JOS 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 2:20"/>Don’t tell anyone what we’re doing. If you do, we won’t have to keep the promise you asked us to make.”<verse eid="JOS 2:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 2:21"/>“I agree,” Rahab replied. “I’ll do as you say.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 2:21">So she sent them away, and they left. Then she tied the bright red rope in the window.<verse eid="JOS 2:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 2:22"/>When the spies left, they went up into the hills. They stayed there for three days. By that time the men chasing them had searched all along the road. They couldn’t find them. So they returned. <verse eid="JOS 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 2:23"/>Then the two spies started back. They went down out of the hills. They went across the Jordan River. They came to Joshua, the son of Nun. They told him everything that had happened to them. <verse eid="JOS 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 2:24"/>They said, “We’re sure the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has given the whole land over to us. All the people there are weak with fear because of us.”<verse eid="JOS 2:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="JOS 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Israel Goes Across the Jordan River</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 3:1"/>Early one morning Joshua and all the Israelites started out from Shittim. They went down to the Jordan River. They camped there before they went across it. <verse eid="JOS 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 3:2"/>After three days the officers went all through the camp. <verse eid="JOS 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 3:3"/>They gave orders to the people. They said, “Watch for the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. The priests, who are Levites, will be carrying it. When you see it, you must move out from where you are and follow it. <verse eid="JOS 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 3:4"/>Then you will know which way to go. You have never gone this way before. But don’t go near the ark. Stay about 1,000 yards away from it.”<verse eid="JOS 3:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 3:5"/>Joshua said to the people, “Set yourselves apart to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Tomorrow he’ll do amazing things among you.”<verse eid="JOS 3:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 3:6"/>Joshua said to the priests, “Go and get the ark of the covenant. Walk on ahead of the people.” So they went and got it. Then they walked on ahead of them.<verse eid="JOS 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 3:7"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Joshua, “Today I will begin to honor you in the eyes of all the Israelites. Then they will know that I am with you, just as I was with Moses. <verse eid="JOS 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 3:8"/>Speak to the priests who carry the ark of the covenant. Tell them, ‘When you reach the edge of the Jordan River, go into the water and stand there.’ ”<verse eid="JOS 3:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 3:9"/>Joshua said to the Israelites, “Come here. Listen to what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is saying. <verse eid="JOS 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 3:10"/>You will soon know that the living God is among you. He will certainly drive out the people now living in the land. He’ll do it to make room for you. He’ll drive out the Canaanites, Hittites, Hivites, Perizzites, Girgashites, Amorites and Jebusites. <verse eid="JOS 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 3:11"/>The ark will go into the Jordan River ahead of you. It’s the ark of the covenant of the Lord of the whole earth. <verse eid="JOS 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 3:12"/>Choose 12 men from the tribes of Israel. Choose one from each tribe. <verse eid="JOS 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 3:13"/>The priests will carry the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He’s the Lord of the whole earth. As soon as the priests step into the Jordan, it will stop flowing. The water that’s coming down the river will pile up in one place. That’s how you will know that the living God is among you.”<verse eid="JOS 3:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 3:14"/>So the people took their tents down. They prepared to go across the Jordan River. The priests carrying the ark of the covenant went ahead of them. <verse eid="JOS 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 3:15"/>The water of the Jordan was going over its banks. It always does that at the time the crops are being gathered. The priests came to the river. Their feet touched the water’s edge. <verse eid="JOS 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 3:16"/>Right away the water coming down the river stopped flowing. It piled up far away at a town called Adam near Zarethan. The water flowing down to the Dead Sea was completely cut off. So the people went across the Jordan River opposite Jericho. <verse eid="JOS 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 3:17"/>The priests carried the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They stopped in the middle of the river and stood on dry ground. They stayed there until the whole nation of Israel had gone across on dry ground.<verse eid="JOS 3:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="JOS 4"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 4:1"/>After the whole nation had gone across the Jordan River, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Joshua. He said, <verse eid="JOS 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 4:2"/>“Choose 12 men from among the people. Choose one from each tribe. <verse eid="JOS 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 4:3"/>Tell them to get 12 stones from the middle of the river. They must pick them up from right where the priests stood. They must carry the stones over with all of you. And they must put them down at the place where you will stay tonight.”<verse eid="JOS 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 4:4"/>So Joshua called together the 12 men he had appointed from among the Israelites. There was one man from each tribe. <verse eid="JOS 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 4:5"/>He said to them, “Go back to the middle of the Jordan River. Go to where the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is. Each one of you must pick up a stone. You must carry it on your shoulder. There will be as many stones as there are tribes in Israel. <verse eid="JOS 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 4:6"/>The stones will serve as a reminder to you. In days to come, your children will ask you, ‘What do these stones mean?’ <verse eid="JOS 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 4:7"/>Tell them that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> cut off the flow of water in the Jordan River. Tell them its water stopped flowing when the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> went across. The stones will always remind the Israelites of what happened there.”<verse eid="JOS 4:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 4:8"/>So the Israelites did as Joshua commanded them. They took 12 stones from the middle of the Jordan River. There was one stone for each of the tribes of Israel. It was just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had told Joshua. The people carried the stones with them to their camp. There they put them down. <verse eid="JOS 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 4:9"/>Joshua also piled up 12 stones in the middle of the river. He piled them up right where the priests who carried the ark of the covenant had stood. And they are still there to this very day.<verse eid="JOS 4:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 4:10"/>The priests who carried the ark remained standing in the middle of the Jordan River. They stayed there until the people had done everything the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded Joshua. It was just as Moses had directed Joshua. All the people went across quickly. <verse eid="JOS 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 4:11"/>As soon as they did, the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> and the priests also went across to the other side. The people were watching them. <verse eid="JOS 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 4:12"/>Among the people who went across the river were men from the tribes of Reuben and Gad and half of the tribe of Manasseh. The men were ready for battle. They went across ahead of the rest of the Israelites. It was just as Moses had directed them. <verse eid="JOS 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 4:13"/>There were about 40,000 of them. All of them were ready for battle. They went across in front of the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They marched to the plains around Jericho. They were prepared to go to war.<verse eid="JOS 4:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 4:14"/>That day the <char style="nd">Lord</char> honored Joshua in the eyes of all the Israelites. They had respect for Joshua as long as he lived. They respected him just as much as they had respected Moses.<verse eid="JOS 4:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 4:15"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Joshua. He said, <verse eid="JOS 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 4:16"/>“Command the priests to come up out of the Jordan River. They are carrying the ark where the tablets of the covenant law are kept.”<verse eid="JOS 4:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 4:17"/>So Joshua gave a command to the priests. He said, “Come up out of the Jordan River.”<verse eid="JOS 4:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 4:18"/>Then the priests came up out of the river. They were carrying the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. As soon as they stepped out on dry ground, the water of the Jordan began to flow again. It went over its banks, just as it had done before.<verse eid="JOS 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 4:19"/>On the tenth day of the first month the people went up out of the Jordan River. They camped at Gilgal on the eastern border of Jericho. <verse eid="JOS 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 4:20"/>Joshua set up the 12 stones at Gilgal. They were the ones the people had taken out of the Jordan. <verse eid="JOS 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 4:21"/>Then he spoke to the Israelites. He said, “In days to come, your children after you will ask their parents, ‘What do these stones mean?’ <verse eid="JOS 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 4:22"/>Their parents must tell them, ‘Israel went across the Jordan River on dry ground.’ <verse eid="JOS 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 4:23"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God dried up the Jordan for you until you had gone across it. He did to the Jordan River the same thing he had done to the Red Sea. He dried up the Red Sea ahead of us until we had gone across it. <verse eid="JOS 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 4:24"/>He did it so that all the nations on earth would know that he is powerful. He did it so that you would always have respect for the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.”<verse eid="JOS 4:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="JOS 5"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 5:1"/>All the Amorite and Canaanite kings heard how the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had dried up the Jordan River. They heard how he had dried it up for the Israelites until they had gone across it. The Amorite kings lived west of the Jordan. The kings of Canaan lived along the Mediterranean Sea. When all those kings heard what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had done, they were terrified. They weren’t brave enough to face the Israelites anymore.<verse eid="JOS 5:1"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Circumcision and Passover at Gilgal</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 5:2"/>At that time the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Joshua, “Make knives out of flint. Use them to circumcise the men of Israel.” <verse eid="JOS 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 5:3"/>So Joshua made knives out of flint. Then he used them to circumcise the men of Israel at Gibeath Haaraloth.<verse eid="JOS 5:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 5:4"/>Here is why Joshua circumcised them. All the men who came out of Egypt had died. They died while they were wandering through the Sinai Desert. They were the men old enough to serve in the army. <verse eid="JOS 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 5:5"/>All the men who came out had been circumcised. But all the men born in the desert during the journey from Egypt hadn’t been circumcised. <verse eid="JOS 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 5:6"/>The Israelites had moved around in the desert for 40 years. By the end of that time all the men old enough to serve in the army when they left Egypt had died. That’s because they hadn’t obeyed the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He had made a promise to them. He had told them they wouldn’t see the land. It’s the land he had promised to their people to give us. It’s a land that has plenty of milk and honey. <verse eid="JOS 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 5:7"/>Because they hadn’t obeyed him, he raised up their sons to take their place. They were the ones Joshua circumcised. They hadn’t been circumcised yet. That’s because no one had circumcised them during the journey. <verse eid="JOS 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 5:8"/>So Joshua circumcised all those men. The whole nation remained in the camp until the men were healed.<verse eid="JOS 5:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 5:9"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Joshua. He said, “Today I have taken away from you the shame of being slaves in Egypt.” That’s why the place where the men were circumcised has been called Gilgal to this very day.<verse eid="JOS 5:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 5:10"/>The Israelites celebrated the Passover Feast. They observed it on the evening of the 14th day of the month. They did it while they were camped at Gilgal on the plains around Jericho. <verse eid="JOS 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 5:11"/>The day after the Passover, they ate some of the food grown in the land. On that same day they ate grain that had been cooked. They also ate bread made without yeast. <verse eid="JOS 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 5:12"/>The manna stopped coming down the day after they ate the food grown in the land. The Israelites didn’t have manna anymore. Instead, that year they ate food grown in Canaan.<verse eid="JOS 5:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Israel Captures Jericho</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 5:13"/>When Joshua was near Jericho, he looked up and saw a man standing in front of him. The man was holding a sword. He was ready for battle. Joshua went up to him. He asked, “Are you on our side? Or are you on the side of our enemies?”<verse eid="JOS 5:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 5:14"/>“I am not on either side,” he replied. “I have come as the commander of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s army.” Then Joshua fell with his face to the ground. He asked the man, “What message does my Lord have for me?”<verse eid="JOS 5:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 5:15"/>The commander of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s army replied, “Take off your sandals. The place you are standing on is holy ground.” So Joshua took them off.<verse eid="JOS 5:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="JOS 6"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 6:1"/>The gates of Jericho were shut tight and guarded closely because of the Israelites. No one went out. No one came in.<verse eid="JOS 6:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 6:2"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Joshua, “I have handed Jericho over to you. I have also handed over to you its king and its fighting men. <verse eid="JOS 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 6:3"/>March around the city once with all your fighting men. In fact, do it for six days. <verse eid="JOS 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 6:4"/>Have seven priests get trumpets made out of rams’ horns. They must carry them in front of the ark. On the seventh day, march around the city seven times. Tell the priests to blow the trumpets as you march. <verse eid="JOS 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 6:5"/>You will hear them blow a long blast on the trumpets. When you do, tell the whole army to give a loud shout. The wall of the city will fall down. Then the whole army will march up to the city. Everyone will go straight in.”<verse eid="JOS 6:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 6:6"/>So Joshua, the son of Nun, called for the priests. He said to them, “Go and get the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. I want seven of you to carry trumpets in front of it.” <verse eid="JOS 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 6:7"/>He gave an order to the army. He said, “Move out! March around the city. Some of the fighting men must march in front of the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.”<verse eid="JOS 6:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 6:8"/>When Joshua had spoken to the men, the seven priests went forward. They were carrying the seven trumpets as they marched in front of the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They were blowing the trumpets. The ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s covenant was carried behind the priests. <verse eid="JOS 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 6:9"/>Some of the fighting men marched ahead of the priests who were blowing the trumpets. The others followed behind the ark and guarded all the priests. That whole time the priests were blowing the trumpets. <verse eid="JOS 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 6:10"/>But Joshua had given an order to the army. He had said, “Don’t give a war cry. Don’t raise your voices. Don’t say a word until the day I tell you to shout. Then shout!” <verse eid="JOS 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 6:11"/>So he had the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> carried around the city once. Then the army returned to camp. They spent the night there.<verse eid="JOS 6:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 6:12"/>Joshua got up early the next morning. The priests went and got the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="JOS 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 6:13"/>The seven priests carrying the seven trumpets started out. They marched in front of the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They blew the trumpets. Some of the fighting men marched ahead of them. The others followed behind the ark and guarded all of them. The priests kept blowing the trumpets. <verse eid="JOS 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 6:14"/>On the second day they marched around the city once. Then the army returned to camp. They did all those things for six days.<verse eid="JOS 6:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 6:15"/>On the seventh day, they got up at sunrise. They marched around the city, just as they had done before. But on that day they went around it seven times. <verse eid="JOS 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 6:16"/>On the seventh time around, the priests blew a long blast on the trumpets. Then Joshua gave a command to the army. He said, “Shout! The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has given you the city! <verse eid="JOS 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 6:17"/>The city and everything in it must be set apart to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> to be destroyed. But the prostitute Rahab and all those with her in her house must be spared. That’s because she hid the spies we sent. <verse eid="JOS 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 6:18"/>But keep away from the things that have been set apart to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. If you take any of them, you will be destroyed. And you will bring trouble on the camp of Israel. You will cause it to be destroyed. <verse eid="JOS 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 6:19"/>All the silver and gold is holy. It is set apart to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. So are all the things made out of bronze and iron. All those things must be added to the treasures kept in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s house.”<verse eid="JOS 6:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 6:20"/>The priests blew the trumpets. As soon as the army heard the sound, they gave a loud shout. Then the wall fell down. Everyone charged straight in. So they took the city. <verse eid="JOS 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 6:21"/>They set it apart to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> to be destroyed. They destroyed every living thing in it with their swords. They killed men and women. They wiped out young people and old people. They destroyed cattle, sheep and donkeys.<verse eid="JOS 6:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 6:22"/>Then Joshua spoke to the two men who had gone in to check out the land. He said, “Go into the prostitute’s house. Bring her out. Also bring out everyone with her. That’s what you promised her you would do.” <verse eid="JOS 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 6:23"/>So the young men who had checked out the land went into Rahab’s house. They brought her out along with her parents and brothers and sisters. They brought out everyone else there with her. They put them in a place outside the camp of Israel.<verse eid="JOS 6:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 6:24"/>Then they burned the whole city and everything in it. But they added the silver and gold to the treasures kept in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s house. They also put there the things made out of bronze and iron. <verse eid="JOS 6:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 6:25"/>But Joshua spared the prostitute Rahab. He spared her family. He also spared everyone else in the house with her. He did it because she hid the spies he had sent to Jericho. Rahab lives among the Israelites to this day.<verse eid="JOS 6:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 6:26"/>At that time Joshua made a promise and called down a curse. He said, “May the person who tries to rebuild this city of Jericho be under the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s curse.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JOS 6:26">“If that person lays its foundations,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JOS 6:26">it will cost the life of his oldest son.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JOS 6:26">If he sets up its gates,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JOS 6:26">it will cost the life of his youngest son.”<verse eid="JOS 6:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 6:27"/>So the <char style="nd">Lord</char> was with Joshua. And Joshua became famous everywhere in the land.<verse eid="JOS 6:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="JOS 7"/>
  <para style="s1">Achan Sins Against the <char style="nd">Lord</char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 7:1"/>But the Israelites weren’t faithful to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They didn’t destroy what had been set apart to him. So they did not do what they had been told to do. Achan had taken some of those things. So the <char style="nd">Lord</char> became very angry with Israel. Achan was the son of Karmi. Karmi was the son of Zimri. And Zimri was the son of Zerah. Achan and all his relatives were from the tribe of Judah.<verse eid="JOS 7:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 7:2"/>Joshua sent men from Jericho to Ai. Ai is near Beth Aven east of Bethel. Joshua told the men, “Go up and check out the area around Ai.” So the men went up and checked it out.<verse eid="JOS 7:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 7:3"/>Then they returned to Joshua. They said, “The whole army doesn’t have to go up and attack Ai. Send only two or three thousand men. They can take the city. Don’t make the whole army go up there. Only a few people live in Ai.” <verse eid="JOS 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 7:4"/>So only about 3,000 troops went up. But the men of Ai drove them away. <verse eid="JOS 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 7:5"/>They chased the Israelites from the city gate all the way to Shebarim. They killed about 36 of them on the way down. So the Israelites were terrified.<verse eid="JOS 7:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 7:6"/>Joshua and the elders of Israel became sad. Joshua tore his clothes. He fell in front of the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> with his face to the ground. He remained there until evening. The elders did the same thing. They also sprinkled dust on their heads. <verse eid="JOS 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 7:7"/>Joshua said, “<char style="nd">Lord</char> and King, why did you ever bring these people across the Jordan River? Did you want to hand us over to the Amorites? Did you want them to destroy us? I wish we had been content to stay on the other side of the Jordan! <verse eid="JOS 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 7:8"/>Lord, our enemies have driven us away. What can I say? <verse eid="JOS 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 7:9"/>The Canaanites will hear about it. So will everyone else in the country. They will surround us. They’ll erase any mention of our name from the face of the earth. Then what will you do when people don’t honor your great name anymore?”<verse eid="JOS 7:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 7:10"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Joshua, “Get up! What are you doing down there on your face? <verse eid="JOS 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 7:11"/>Israel has sinned. I made a covenant with them. I commanded them to keep it. But they have broken it. They have taken some of the things that had been set apart to me in a special way to be destroyed. They have stolen. They have lied. They have taken the things they stole and have put them with their own things. <verse eid="JOS 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 7:12"/>That is why the Israelites can’t stand up against their enemies. They turn their backs and run. That’s because I have decided to let them be destroyed. You must destroy the things you took that had been set apart to me. If you do not, I will not be with you anymore.<verse eid="JOS 7:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 7:13"/>“Go and set the people apart. Tell them, ‘Make yourselves pure. Get ready for tomorrow. Here is what the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, wants you to do. He says, “People of Israel, you have kept some of the things that had been set apart to me to be destroyed. You can’t stand up against your enemies until you get rid of those things.”<verse eid="JOS 7:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 7:14"/>“ ‘In the morning, come forward tribe by tribe. The tribe the <char style="nd">Lord</char> chooses will come forward group by group. The group the <char style="nd">Lord</char> chooses will come forward family by family. And the men in the family the <char style="nd">Lord</char> chooses will come forward one by one. <verse eid="JOS 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 7:15"/>Whoever is caught with the things that had been set apart to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will be destroyed by fire. Everything that belongs to that person will also be destroyed. He has broken the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s covenant. He has done a very terrible thing in Israel!’ ”<verse eid="JOS 7:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 7:16"/>Early the next morning Joshua had Israel come forward by tribes. The tribe of Judah was chosen. <verse eid="JOS 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 7:17"/>The groups of Judah came forward. The group of Zerah was chosen. Joshua had the group of Zerah come forward by families. The family of Zimri was chosen. <verse eid="JOS 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 7:18"/>He had their men come forward one by one. Achan was chosen. Achan was the son of Karmi. Karmi was the son of Zimri. And Zimri was the son of Zerah. Zerah was from the tribe of Judah.<verse eid="JOS 7:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 7:19"/>Joshua said to Achan, “My son, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is the God of Israel. So give him glory and honor him by telling the truth! Tell me what you have done. Don’t hide it from me.”<verse eid="JOS 7:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 7:20"/>Achan replied, “It’s true! I’ve sinned against the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, the God of Israel. Here is what I’ve done. <verse eid="JOS 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 7:21"/>I saw a beautiful robe from Babylonia among the things we had taken. I saw five pounds of silver. And I saw a gold bar that weighed 20 ounces. I wanted them, so I took them. I hid them in the ground inside my tent. The silver is on the bottom.”<verse eid="JOS 7:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 7:22"/>So Joshua sent some messengers. They ran to Achan’s tent. And there was everything, hidden in his tent! The silver was on the bottom. <verse eid="JOS 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 7:23"/>They brought the things out of the tent. They took them to Joshua and all the Israelites. And they spread them out in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="JOS 7:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 7:24"/>Then Joshua and all the people grabbed Achan, the son of Zerah. They took the silver, the robe and the gold bar. They took Achan’s sons and daughters. They took his cattle, donkeys and sheep. They also took his tent and everything he had. They carried all of it out to the Valley of Achor. <verse eid="JOS 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 7:25"/>Joshua said to Achan, “Why have you brought this trouble on us? The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will bring trouble on you today.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 7:25">Then all the people killed Achan by throwing stones at him. They also killed the rest of his family with stones. They burned all of them up. <verse eid="JOS 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 7:26"/>They placed a large pile of rocks on top of Achan’s body. The place has been called the Valley of Achor ever since. That pile is still there to this day. After the people killed Achan, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> was no longer angry with them.<verse eid="JOS 7:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="JOS 8"/>
  <para style="s1">Israel Destroys Ai</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 8:1"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Joshua, “Do not be afraid. Do not lose hope. Go up and attack Ai. Take the whole army with you. I have handed the king of Ai over to you. I have given you his people, his city and his land. <verse eid="JOS 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 8:2"/>Remember what you did to Jericho and its king. You will do the same thing to Ai and its king. But this time you can keep for yourselves the livestock and everything else you take from them. Have some of your fighting men hide behind the city and take them by surprise.”<verse eid="JOS 8:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 8:3"/>So Joshua and the whole army moved out to attack Ai. He chose 30,000 of his best fighting men. He sent them out at night. <verse eid="JOS 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 8:4"/>He gave them orders. He said, “Listen carefully to what I’m saying. You must hide behind the city. Don’t go very far away from it. All of you must be ready to attack it. <verse eid="JOS 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 8:5"/>I and all those with me will march up to the city. The men of Ai will come out to fight against us, just as they did before. Then we’ll run away from them. <verse eid="JOS 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 8:6"/>They’ll chase us until we’ve drawn them away from the city. They’ll say, ‘They are running away from us, just as they did before.’ When we run away from them, <verse eid="JOS 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 8:7"/>come out of your hiding place. Capture the city. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will hand it over to you. <verse eid="JOS 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 8:8"/>When you have taken it, set it on fire. Do what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has commanded. Make sure you obey my orders.”<verse eid="JOS 8:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 8:9"/>Then Joshua sent them away. They went to the place where they had planned to hide. They hid in a place west of Ai. It was between Bethel and Ai. But Joshua spent that night with his troops.<verse eid="JOS 8:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 8:10"/>Early the next morning Joshua brought together his army. He and the leaders of Israel marched in front of them to Ai. <verse eid="JOS 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 8:11"/>The whole army that was with him marched up to the city. They stopped in front of it. They set up camp north of Ai. There was a valley between them and the city. <verse eid="JOS 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 8:12"/>Joshua had chosen about 5,000 soldiers. He had ordered them to hide in a place west of Ai. It was between Bethel and Ai. <verse eid="JOS 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 8:13"/>The men took up their battle positions. All the men in the camp north of the city took up their positions. So did those who were supposed to hide west of the city. That night Joshua went into the valley.<verse eid="JOS 8:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 8:14"/>The king of Ai saw what the troops with Joshua were doing. So the king and all his men hurried out of the city early in the morning. They marched out to meet Israel in battle. They went to a place that looked out over the Arabah Valley. The king didn’t know that some of Israel’s fighting men were hiding behind the city. <verse eid="JOS 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 8:15"/>Joshua and all his men let the men of Ai drive them back. The Israelites ran away toward the desert. <verse eid="JOS 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 8:16"/>All the men of Ai were called out to chase them. They chased Joshua. So they were drawn away from the city. <verse eid="JOS 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 8:17"/>Not even one man remained in Ai or Bethel. All of them went out to chase Israel. When they did, they left the city wide open.<verse eid="JOS 8:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 8:18"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Joshua, “Hold out toward Ai the javelin that is in your hand. I will give the city to you.” So Joshua held out toward the city the javelin in his hand. <verse eid="JOS 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 8:19"/>As soon as he did, the men hiding behind the city got up quickly. They came out of their hiding places and rushed forward. They entered the city and captured it. They quickly set it on fire.<verse eid="JOS 8:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 8:20"/>The men of Ai looked back. They saw smoke rising up from the city into the sky. But they couldn’t escape in any direction. The Israelites had been running away toward the desert. But now they turned around to face those chasing them. <verse eid="JOS 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 8:21"/>Joshua and all his men saw that the men who had been hiding behind the city had captured it. They also saw that smoke was going up from it. So they turned around and attacked the men of Ai. <verse eid="JOS 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 8:22"/>The men who had set Ai on fire came out of the city. They also fought against the men of Ai. So the men of Ai were caught in the middle. The army of Israel was on both sides of them. Israel struck them down. They didn’t let anyone remain alive or get away. <verse eid="JOS 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 8:23"/>But they captured the king of Ai alive. They brought him to Joshua.<verse eid="JOS 8:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 8:24"/>Israel finished killing all the men of Ai. They destroyed them in the fields and in the desert where they had chased them. They struck down every one of them with their swords. Then all the Israelites returned to Ai. And they killed those who were left in it. <verse eid="JOS 8:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 8:25"/>The total number of men and women they killed that day was 12,000. The Israelites put to death all the people of Ai. <verse eid="JOS 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 8:26"/>Joshua continued to hold out his javelin toward Ai. He didn’t lower his hand until he and his men had totally destroyed everyone who lived there. <verse eid="JOS 8:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 8:27"/>But this time Israel kept for themselves the livestock and everything else they had taken from the city. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> had directed Joshua to let them do it.<verse eid="JOS 8:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 8:28"/>So Joshua burned down Ai. He tore it down so it could never be built again. It has been deserted to this very day. <verse eid="JOS 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 8:29"/>Joshua killed the king of Ai. He stuck a pole through the body. Then he set it up where people could see it. He left it there until evening. At sunset, Joshua ordered his men to remove the body from the pole. He told them to throw the body down at the entrance of the city gate. They put a large pile of rocks over the body. That pile is still there to this day.<verse eid="JOS 8:29"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Joshua Reads the Book of the Law to the People</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 8:30"/>Joshua built an altar to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, the God of Israel. He built it on Mount Ebal. <verse eid="JOS 8:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 8:31"/>Moses, the servant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, had commanded the Israelites to do that. Joshua built the altar according to what is written in the Book of the Law of Moses. Joshua built the altar out of stones that iron tools had never touched. Then the people offered on the altar burnt offerings to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They also sacrificed friendship offerings on it. <verse eid="JOS 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 8:32"/>Joshua copied the law of Moses on stones. He did it while all the Israelites were watching. <verse eid="JOS 8:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 8:33"/>They were standing on both sides of the ark of the covenant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. All the Israelites, including outsiders and citizens, were there. Israel’s elders, officials and judges were also there. All of them faced the priests, who were Levites. They were carrying the ark. Half of the people stood in front of Mount Gerizim. The other half stood in front of Mount Ebal. Moses, the servant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, had earlier told them to do it. Moses told them to do it when he had given directions to bless the Israelites.<verse eid="JOS 8:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 8:34"/>Then Joshua read all the words of the law out loud. He read the blessings and the curses. He read them just as they are written in the Book of the Law. <verse eid="JOS 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 8:35"/>Joshua read every word Moses had commanded. He read them to the whole community of Israel. That included the women and children. It also included the outsiders living among them.<verse eid="JOS 8:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="JOS 9"/>
  <para style="s1">The People of Gibeon Trick Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 9:1"/>All the kings who ruled west of the Jordan River heard about the battles Israel had won. That included the kings who ruled in the central hill country and the western hills. It also included those who ruled along the entire coast of the Mediterranean Sea all the way to Lebanon. They were the kings of the Hittites, Amorites, Canaanites, Perizzites, Hivites and Jebusites. <verse eid="JOS 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 9:2"/>They brought their armies together to fight against Joshua and Israel.<verse eid="JOS 9:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 9:3"/>The people of Gibeon heard about what Joshua had done to Jericho and Ai. <verse eid="JOS 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 9:4"/>So they decided to trick the Israelites. They packed supplies as if they were going on a long trip. They loaded their donkeys with old sacks and old wineskins. The wineskins were cracked but had been mended. <verse eid="JOS 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 9:5"/>They put worn-out sandals on their feet. The sandals had been patched. They also wore old clothes. All the bread they took along was dry and moldy. <verse eid="JOS 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 9:6"/>They went to Joshua in the camp at Gilgal. They spoke to him and the Israelites. They said, “We’ve come from a country that’s far away. Make a peace treaty with us.”<verse eid="JOS 9:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 9:7"/>The Israelites said to the Hivites, “But suppose you live close to us. If you do, we can’t make a peace treaty with you.”<verse eid="JOS 9:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 9:8"/>“We’ll serve you,” they said to Joshua.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 9:8">But Joshua asked, “Who are you? Where do you come from?”<verse eid="JOS 9:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 9:9"/>They answered, “We’ve come from a country that’s very far away. We’ve come because the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God is famous. We’ve heard reports about him. We’ve heard about everything he did in Egypt. <verse eid="JOS 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 9:10"/>We’ve heard about everything he did to Sihon and Og. They were the two kings of the Amorites. They ruled east of the Jordan River. Sihon was the king of Heshbon. Og was the king of Bashan. He ruled in Ashtaroth. <verse eid="JOS 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 9:11"/>Our elders and all the people living in our country spoke to us. They said, ‘Take supplies for your trip. Go and meet the Israelites. Say to them, “We’ll serve you. Make a peace treaty with us.” ’ <verse eid="JOS 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 9:12"/>Look at our bread. It was warm when we packed it. We packed it at home the day we left to come and see you. But look at how dry and moldy it is now. <verse eid="JOS 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 9:13"/>When we filled these wineskins, they were new. But look at how cracked they are now. And our clothes and sandals are worn out because we’ve traveled so far.”<verse eid="JOS 9:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 9:14"/>The Israelites looked over the supplies those people had brought. But they didn’t ask the <char style="nd">Lord</char> what they should do. <verse eid="JOS 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 9:15"/>Joshua made a peace treaty with the people who had come. He agreed to let them live. The leaders of the community gave their word that they agreed with the treaty.<verse eid="JOS 9:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 9:16"/>So the Israelites made a peace treaty with the people of Gibeon. But three days later they heard that the people of Gibeon lived close to them. <verse eid="JOS 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 9:17"/>So the Israelites started out to go to the cities of those people. On the third day they came to Gibeon, Kephirah, Beeroth and Kiriath Jearim. <verse eid="JOS 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 9:18"/>But they didn’t attack those cities. That’s because the leaders of the community had given their word and made a peace treaty with them. They had given their word in the name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, the God of Israel.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 9:18">The whole community told the leaders they weren’t happy with them. <verse eid="JOS 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 9:19"/>But all the leaders answered, “We’ve made a peace treaty with them. We’ve given our word in the name of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, the God of Israel. So we can’t touch them now. <verse eid="JOS 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 9:20"/>But here is what we’ll do to them. We’ll let them live. Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> won’t be angry with us because we didn’t keep our promise.” <verse eid="JOS 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 9:21"/>They continued, “Let them live. But make them cut wood and carry water to serve the whole community.” So the leaders kept their promise to them.<verse eid="JOS 9:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 9:22"/>Joshua sent for the people of Gibeon. He said to them, “Why did you trick us? You said, ‘We live far away from you.’ But in fact you live close to us. <verse eid="JOS 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 9:23"/>So now you are under a curse. You will always serve us. You will always cut wood and carry water for the house of my God.”<verse eid="JOS 9:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 9:24"/>They answered Joshua, “We were clearly told what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God had commanded his servant Moses to do. He commanded him to give you the whole land. He also ordered him to wipe out all its people to make room for you. So we were afraid you would kill us. That’s why we tricked you. <verse eid="JOS 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 9:25"/>We are now under your control. Do to us what you think is good and right.”<verse eid="JOS 9:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 9:26"/>So Joshua saved the people of Gibeon. He didn’t let the Israelites kill them. <verse eid="JOS 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 9:27"/>That day he made them cut wood and carry water. They had to serve the community of Israel. They also had to do work connected with the altar of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. The altar would be at the place the <char style="nd">Lord</char> would choose. And they still serve the Israelites to this day.<verse eid="JOS 9:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="JOS 10"/>
  <para style="s1">The Sun Stands Still</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 10:1"/>Adoni-Zedek was the king of Jerusalem. He heard that Joshua had captured Ai. He found out that the city had been set apart to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> in a special way to be destroyed. He heard that Joshua had done to Ai and its king the same thing he had done to Jericho and its king. Adoni-Zedek heard that the people of Gibeon had made a peace treaty with Israel. He also found out that they were living among the Israelites. <verse eid="JOS 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 10:2"/>The things he heard alarmed him and his people very much. That’s because Gibeon was an important city. It was like one of the royal cities. It was larger than Ai. All its men were good soldiers. <verse eid="JOS 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 10:3"/>So Adoni-Zedek, the king of Jerusalem, made an appeal to Hoham, the king of Hebron. He appealed to Piram, the king of Jarmuth. He appealed to Japhia, the king of Lachish. He also made an appeal to Debir, the king of Eglon. <verse eid="JOS 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 10:4"/>“Come up and help me attack Gibeon,” he said. “Its people have made peace with Joshua and the Israelites.”<verse eid="JOS 10:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 10:5"/>Then the kings of Jerusalem, Hebron, Jarmuth, Lachish and Eglon gathered their armies together. Those five Amorite kings moved all their troops into position to fight against Gibeon. Then they attacked it.<verse eid="JOS 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 10:6"/>Joshua was in the camp at Gilgal. The people of Gibeon sent a message to him there. They said, “Don’t desert us. We serve you. Come up to us quickly! Save us! Help us! All the Amorite kings from the central hill country have gathered their armies together to fight against us.”<verse eid="JOS 10:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 10:7"/>So Joshua marched up from Gilgal with his whole army. The army included all his best fighting men. <verse eid="JOS 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 10:8"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Joshua, “Do not be afraid of them. I have handed them over to you. Not one of them will be able to fight against you and win.”<verse eid="JOS 10:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 10:9"/>Joshua marched all night from Gilgal. He took the Amorite armies by surprise. <verse eid="JOS 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 10:10"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> threw them into a panic as Israel marched toward them. Then Joshua and the Israelites won a complete victory over them at Gibeon. The Israelites chased them along the road that goes up to Beth Horon. They struck them down all the way to Azekah and Makkedah. <verse eid="JOS 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 10:11"/>The Amorites tried to escape as Israel marched toward them. They ran down the road from Beth Horon to Azekah. Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> threw large hailstones down on them. The hailstones killed more of them than the swords of the Israelites did.<verse eid="JOS 10:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 10:12"/>So the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave the Amorites over to Israel. On that day Joshua spoke to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> while the Israelites were listening. He said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JOS 10:12">“Sun, stand still over Gibeon.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JOS 10:12">And you, moon, stand still over the Valley of Aijalon.”<verse eid="JOS 10:12"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 10:13"/>So the sun stood still.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JOS 10:13">The moon stopped.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JOS 10:13">They didn’t move again until the nation won the battle over its enemies.</para>
  <para style="m" vid="JOS 10:13">You can read about it in the Book of Jashar.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 10:13">The sun stopped in the middle of the sky. It didn’t go down for about a full day. <verse eid="JOS 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 10:14"/>There has never been a day like it before or since. It was a day when the <char style="nd">Lord</char> listened to a mere human being. Surely the <char style="nd">Lord</char> was fighting for Israel!<verse eid="JOS 10:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 10:15"/>Joshua and his whole army returned to the camp at Gilgal.<verse eid="JOS 10:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Joshua Kills the Five Amorite Kings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 10:16"/>The five Amorite kings had run away. They had hidden in the cave at Makkedah. <verse eid="JOS 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 10:17"/>Joshua was told that the five kings had been found. He was also told that they were hiding in the cave at Makkedah. <verse eid="JOS 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 10:18"/>He said, “Roll some large rocks up to the opening of the cave. Put some men there to guard it. <verse eid="JOS 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 10:19"/>But keep on going! Chase your enemies! Attack them from behind. Don’t let them get back to their cities. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has handed them over to you.”<verse eid="JOS 10:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 10:20"/>So Joshua and the men of Israel had complete victory over them. They killed almost every one of them. But a few escaped. They went back to their cities that had high walls around them. <verse eid="JOS 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 10:21"/>Then Israel’s whole army returned safely to Joshua. He was in the camp at Makkedah. No one in the land dared to say anything against the Israelites.<verse eid="JOS 10:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 10:22"/>Joshua said, “Open up the cave. Bring those five kings out to me.” <verse eid="JOS 10:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 10:23"/>So Joshua’s men brought the kings out of the cave. They were the kings of Jerusalem, Hebron, Jarmuth, Lachish and Eglon. <verse eid="JOS 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 10:24"/>The men brought them to Joshua. Then he sent for all the men of Israel. He spoke to the army commanders who had come with him. He said, “Come here. Put your feet on the necks of these kings.” So they came forward and placed their feet on the necks of the kings.<verse eid="JOS 10:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 10:25"/>Joshua said to them, “Don’t be afraid. Don’t lose hope. Be strong and brave. This is what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will do to all the enemies you are going to fight.” <verse eid="JOS 10:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 10:26"/>Joshua put the five kings to death. He stuck a pole through each of their bodies. Then he set the poles up where people could see the bodies. He left them there until evening.<verse eid="JOS 10:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 10:27"/>At sunset Joshua ordered his men to take down the bodies. So they took them down from the poles and threw them into the cave where the kings had been hiding. They placed large rocks at the opening of the cave. And the rocks are still there to this day.<verse eid="JOS 10:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Campaign Against the Cities in the South</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 10:28"/>That day Joshua captured Makkedah. He cut down its people and their king. He totally destroyed everyone in it. He didn’t leave anyone alive. He did to the king of Makkedah the same thing he had done to the king of Jericho.<verse eid="JOS 10:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 10:29"/>Joshua moved on from Makkedah to Libnah. Israel’s whole army went with him. They attacked Libnah. <verse eid="JOS 10:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 10:30"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> also handed that city and its king over to Israel. Joshua destroyed the city. He and his men killed everyone in it with their swords. He didn’t leave anyone alive there. He did to its king the same thing he had done to the king of Jericho.<verse eid="JOS 10:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 10:31"/>Joshua moved on from Libnah to Lachish. Israel’s whole army went with him. The men took up their battle positions. Then Joshua attacked Lachish. <verse eid="JOS 10:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 10:32"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> handed it over to Israel. Joshua captured the city on the second day of the battle. He destroyed the city. He and his men killed everyone in it with their swords. He had done the same thing to Libnah. <verse eid="JOS 10:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 10:33"/>While all that was happening, Horam had come up to help Lachish. He was the king of Gezer. But Joshua won the battle over him and his army. No one was left alive.<verse eid="JOS 10:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 10:34"/>Joshua moved on from Lachish to Eglon. Israel’s whole army went with him. They took up their battle positions. Then they attacked Eglon. <verse eid="JOS 10:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 10:35"/>They captured it that same day. They totally destroyed everyone in it with their swords. They had done the same thing to Lachish.<verse eid="JOS 10:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOS 10:36"/>Joshua went up from Eglon to Hebron. Israel’s whole army went with him. Then they attacked Hebron. <verse eid="JOS 10:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOS 10:37"/>They captured the city. They destroyed it and its villages. They killed all its people and their king with their swords. They didn’t leave anyone alive. They totally destroyed the city and everyone in it. They had done the same thing at Eglon.<verse eid="JOS 10:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOS 10:38"/>Joshua turned back and attacked Debir. Israel’s whole army went with him. <verse eid="JOS 10:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOS 10:39"/>They captured the city, its king and its villages. They totally destroyed everyone in Debir with their swords. They didn’t leave anyone alive. They did to Debir and its king the same thing they had done to Libnah and its king. They had also done the same thing to Hebron.<verse eid="JOS 10:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOS 10:40"/>So Joshua brought the whole area under his control. That included the central hill country and the Negev Desert. It included the western hills and the mountain slopes. It also included all the kings in that whole area. Joshua didn’t leave anyone alive. He totally destroyed everyone who breathed. He did just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, had commanded. <verse eid="JOS 10:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOS 10:41"/>Joshua brought everyone from Kadesh Barnea to Gaza under his control. He did the same thing to everyone from the whole area of Goshen to Gibeon. <verse eid="JOS 10:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JOS 10:42"/>He won the battle over all those kings and their lands. He did it in one campaign. That’s because the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, fought for Israel.<verse eid="JOS 10:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="JOS 10:43"/>Then Joshua returned to the camp at Gilgal. Israel’s whole army went with him.<verse eid="JOS 10:43"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="JOS 11"/>
  <para style="s1">The Campaign Against the Cities in the North</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 11:1"/>Jabin was the king of Hazor. He heard about the battles Israel had won. So he sent a message to Jobab. Jobab was the king of Madon. Jabin sent the same message to the kings of Shimron and Akshaph. <verse eid="JOS 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 11:2"/>He also sent it to many other kings. Some ruled in the mountains in the north. Some ruled in the Arabah Valley south of Kinnereth. Others ruled in the western hills. Still others ruled in Naphoth Dor in the west. <verse eid="JOS 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 11:3"/>Jabin sent the same message to the people of east Canaan and west Canaan. He sent it to the Amorites, Hittites, Perizzites and Jebusites. They lived in the central hill country. He also sent it to the Hivites who lived below Mount Hermon in the area of Mizpah. <verse eid="JOS 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 11:4"/>Those kings marched out with all their troops. They had a large number of horses and chariots. It was a huge army. The fighting men were as many as the grains of sand on the seashore. <verse eid="JOS 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 11:5"/>All those kings gathered their armies together to fight against Israel. They set up camp together at the Waters of Merom.<verse eid="JOS 11:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 11:6"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Joshua, “Do not be afraid of them. By this time tomorrow I will hand all of them over to Israel. All of them will be killed. You must cut the legs of their horses. You must burn their chariots.”<verse eid="JOS 11:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 11:7"/>So Joshua and his whole army attacked them suddenly. They fought against them at the Waters of Merom. <verse eid="JOS 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 11:8"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> handed them over to Israel. The Israelites won the battle over them. They hunted them down all the way to Greater Sidon. They chased them to Misrephoth Maim. They chased them to the Valley of Mizpah in the east. Not one of them was left alive. <verse eid="JOS 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 11:9"/>Joshua did to them what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had ordered him to do. He cut the legs of their horses. He burned up their chariots.<verse eid="JOS 11:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 11:10"/>At that time Joshua turned back. He captured Hazor. He killed its king with his sword. Hazor was the most important city in all those kingdoms. <verse eid="JOS 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 11:11"/>The army of Israel killed everyone in Hazor with their swords. Its people had been set apart to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> to be destroyed. Israel’s army didn’t spare anyone who breathed. Then Joshua burned down the city.<verse eid="JOS 11:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 11:12"/>Joshua captured all those royal cities and their kings. He and his men killed everyone in those cities with their swords. He totally destroyed them. He did just as Moses, the servant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, had commanded. <verse eid="JOS 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 11:13"/>Many cities were built on top of earlier cities that had been destroyed. Israel didn’t burn any of those except Hazor. Joshua burned it down. <verse eid="JOS 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 11:14"/>The army of Israel kept for themselves the livestock and everything else they took from those cities. But they killed all the people with their swords. They completely destroyed them. They didn’t spare anyone who breathed. <verse eid="JOS 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 11:15"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded his servant Moses to do all these things. Moses had passed that command on to Joshua. And Joshua carried it out. He did everything the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded Moses.<verse eid="JOS 11:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 11:16"/>So Joshua captured the whole land. He took over the central hill country and the whole Negev Desert. He took over the whole area of Goshen. He took over the western hills. He took over the Arabah Valley. He took over the mountains of Israel and the hills around them. <verse eid="JOS 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 11:17"/>He took over the area that begins at Mount Halak, which rises toward Seir. The area ends at Baal Gad in the Valley of Lebanon below Mount Hermon. Joshua captured the kings who ruled over that whole land. He put them to death. <verse eid="JOS 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 11:18"/>He fought battles against all those kings for a long time. <verse eid="JOS 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 11:19"/>Only the Hivites who lived in Gibeon made a peace treaty with the Israelites. No other city made a treaty with them. So Israel captured all those cities in battle. <verse eid="JOS 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 11:20"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> himself made their people stubborn. He made them go to war against Israel so he could totally destroy them. He wanted to wipe them out. He didn’t show them any mercy. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded Moses to destroy the Canaanites.<verse eid="JOS 11:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 11:21"/>At that time Joshua went and destroyed the Anakites. They lived all through the hill country of Judah and Israel. They lived in Hebron, Debir and Anab. Joshua totally destroyed the Anakites and their towns. <verse eid="JOS 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 11:22"/>There weren’t any Anakites left alive in Israel’s territory. But a few were left alive in Gaza, Gath and Ashdod.<verse eid="JOS 11:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 11:23"/>So Joshua captured the whole land, just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had directed Moses. Joshua gave the land to Israel as their very own. He divided it up and gave each tribe its share. Then the land had peace and rest.<verse eid="JOS 11:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="JOS 12"/>
  <para style="s1">Israel Wins the Battle Over the Kings in the Land</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 12:1"/>The Israelites took over the territory east of the Jordan River. The land they captured reached from the Arnon River valley to Mount Hermon. It included the whole east side of the Arabah Valley. Israel won the battle over the kings of that whole territory. Here are the lands Israel captured from the kings they won the battle over.<verse eid="JOS 12:1"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 12:2"/>They took over the land of Sihon. He was the king of the Amorites. He ruled in Heshbon.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 12:2">The land he ruled over begins at Aroer. Aroer is on the rim of the Arnon River valley. Sihon ruled from the middle of the valley to the Jabbok River. The Jabbok is the border of Ammon. Sihon’s territory included half of Gilead.<verse eid="JOS 12:2"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 12:3"/>He also ruled over the east side of the Arabah Valley. That land begins at the Sea of Galilee. It goes to the Dead Sea and over to Beth Jeshimoth. Then it goes south, below the slopes of Pisgah.<verse eid="JOS 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 12:4"/>Israel also took over the territory of Og. He was the king of Bashan. He was one of the last of the Rephaites. He ruled in Ashtaroth and Edrei.<verse eid="JOS 12:4"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 12:5"/>He ruled over Mount Hermon, Salekah and the whole land of Bashan. Og’s kingdom reached all the way to the border of Geshur and Maakah. He ruled over half of Gilead. His land reached the border of Sihon, the king of Heshbon.<verse eid="JOS 12:5"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 12:6"/>Moses was the servant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Moses and the Israelites won the battle over those two kings. He gave their land to the tribes of Reuben and Gad and half of the tribe of Manasseh. He gave it to them as their share.<verse eid="JOS 12:6"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 12:7"/>Joshua and the Israelites won the battle over the kings who ruled west of the Jordan River. The lands of those kings reached from Baal Gad in the Valley of Lebanon to Mount Halak, which rises toward Seir. Joshua gave their lands to the tribes of Israel as their very own. He divided them up and gave each tribe its share. <verse eid="JOS 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 12:8"/>Those lands included the central hill country, the western hills and the Arabah Valley. They also included the mountain slopes, the Desert of Judah and the Negev Desert. Those lands belonged to the Hittites, Amorites, Canaanites, Perizzites, Hivites and Jebusites.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="JOS 12:8"/>
  <para style="li4" vid="JOS 12:8">Here are the kings Israel won the battle over.<verse eid="JOS 12:8"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <table>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 12:9"/>the king of Jericho </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Ai, which is near Bethel </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:9"/>
        <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 12:10"/>the king of Jerusalem </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Hebron </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:10"/>
        <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 12:11"/>the king of Jarmuth </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Lachish </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:11"/>
        <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 12:12"/>the king of Eglon </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Gezer </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:12"/>
        <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 12:13"/>the king of Debir </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Geder </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:13"/>
        <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 12:14"/>the king of Hormah </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Arad </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:14"/>
        <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 12:15"/>the king of Libnah </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Adullam </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:15"/>
        <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 12:16"/>the king of Makkedah </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Bethel </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:16"/>
        <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 12:17"/>the king of Tappuah </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Hepher </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:17"/>
        <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 12:18"/>the king of Aphek </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Lasharon </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:18"/>
        <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 12:19"/>the king of Madon </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Hazor </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:19"/>
        <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 12:20"/>the king of Shimron Meron </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Akshaph </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:20"/>
        <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 12:21"/>the king of Taanach </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Megiddo </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:21"/>
        <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 12:22"/>the king of Kedesh </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Jokneam in Carmel </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:22"/>
        <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 12:23"/>the king of Dor in Naphoth Dor </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Goyim in Gilgal </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:23"/>
        <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 12:24"/>the king of Tirzah </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
  </table>
  <para style="b" vid="JOS 12:24"/>
  <para style="li4" vid="JOS 12:24">The total number of kings was 31.<verse eid="JOS 12:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="JOS 13"/>
  <para style="s1">The Land That Remained to Be Taken Over</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 13:1"/>Joshua was now very old. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to him, “You are very old. And there are still very large areas of land that have not yet been taken over.<verse eid="JOS 13:1"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 13:2"/>“Here is the land that remains to be taken over.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="JOS 13:2"/>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 13:2">“It includes all the areas of Philistia and Geshur. <verse eid="JOS 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 13:3"/>Those areas begin at the Shihor River in the eastern part of Egypt. They go to the territory of Ekron in the north. All that land is considered Canaanite even though it is controlled by five Philistine rulers. They rule over Gaza, Ashdod, Ashkelon, Gath and Ekron.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 13:3">The Avvites <verse eid="JOS 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 13:4"/>live south of them.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 13:4">The rest of the land of Canaan that remains to be taken over reaches from Arah all the way to Aphek. Arah belongs to the people of Sidon. The land that remains to be taken reaches the border of Amorite territory.<verse eid="JOS 13:4"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 13:5"/>It includes the area of Byblos.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 13:5">It also includes all of Lebanon to the east. It reaches from Baal Gad below Mount Hermon all the way to Lebo Hamath.<verse eid="JOS 13:5"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 13:6"/>“I myself will drive out all the people who live in the mountain areas. Those areas reach from Lebanon to Misrephoth Maim. They include the area where all the people of Sidon live. I myself will drive out those people to make room for the Israelites. Make sure you set that land apart for Israel. Give it to them as their share, just as I have directed you. <verse eid="JOS 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 13:7"/>Divide it up among the nine tribes and half of the tribe of Manasseh. Give each tribe its share.”<verse eid="JOS 13:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land for the Tribes East of the Jordan River</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 13:8"/>The other half of Manasseh’s tribe had already received the share of land Moses had given them. Their share was east of the Jordan River. The tribes of Reuben and Gad had already received their share too. Moses, the servant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, had given it to them.<verse eid="JOS 13:8"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 13:9"/>That land starts at Aroer on the rim of the Arnon River valley. It includes the town in the middle of the valley. It includes the high plains of Medeba all the way to Dibon. <verse eid="JOS 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 13:10"/>It also includes all the towns of Sihon, the king of the Amorites. He had ruled in Heshbon. That area reaches to the border of Ammon.<verse eid="JOS 13:10"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 13:11"/>It also includes Gilead. It includes the territory of Geshur and Maakah. It includes Mount Hermon and the whole land of Bashan all the way to Salekah. <verse eid="JOS 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 13:12"/>So it includes the entire kingdom of Og in Bashan. Og had ruled in Ashtaroth and Edrei. He was the last of the Rephaites. Moses had won the battle over Sihon and Og. He had taken over their land. <verse eid="JOS 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 13:13"/>But the Israelites didn’t drive out the people of Geshur and Maakah. So they continue to live among the Israelites to this day.<verse eid="JOS 13:13"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 13:14"/>Moses hadn’t given any share of the land to the tribe of Levi. That’s because the food offerings are their share. Those offerings are presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, the God of Israel. Moses gave the Levites what he had promised them.<verse eid="JOS 13:14"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 13:15"/>Here is what Moses had given to the tribe of Reuben, according to its family groups.<verse eid="JOS 13:15"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 13:16"/>Their territory starts at Aroer on the rim of the Arnon River valley. It includes the town in the middle of the valley. It includes all of the high plains near Medeba. <verse eid="JOS 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 13:17"/>It includes Heshbon and all its towns on those plains. Those towns include Dibon, Bamoth Baal, Beth Baal Meon, <verse eid="JOS 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 13:18"/>Jahaz, Kedemoth and Mephaath. <verse eid="JOS 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 13:19"/>They include Kiriathaim, Sibmah and Zereth Shahar on the hill in the valley. <verse eid="JOS 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 13:20"/>They also include Beth Peor, Beth Jeshimoth and the slopes of Pisgah. <verse eid="JOS 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 13:21"/>All those towns are on the high plains. The territory includes the whole kingdom of Sihon, the king of the Amorites. He had ruled in Heshbon. Moses had won the battle over him and over the chiefs of Midian. Those chiefs were Evi, Rekem, Zur, Hur and Reba. They were princes who helped Sihon fight against Israel. They lived in that country. <verse eid="JOS 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 13:22"/>The Israelites killed many of them in battle. They also killed Balaam with their swords. He was the son of Beor. Balaam had used evil magic to find out what was going to happen.<verse eid="JOS 13:22"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 13:23"/>The border of the tribe of Reuben was the bank of the Jordan River. All those towns and their villages were given to the tribe of Reuben as their very own. Each family group received its share.<verse eid="JOS 13:23"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 13:24"/>Here is what Moses had given to the tribe of Gad, according to its family groups.<verse eid="JOS 13:24"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 13:25"/>Their territory includes Jazer and all the towns of Gilead. It includes half of the country of Ammon all the way to Aroer, which was near Rabbah. <verse eid="JOS 13:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 13:26"/>Their territory reaches from Heshbon to Ramath Mizpah and Betonim. It reaches from Mahanaim to the territory of Debir. <verse eid="JOS 13:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 13:27"/>In the valley their land includes Beth Haram, Beth Nimrah, Sukkoth and Zaphon. It also includes the rest of the kingdom of Sihon. He was the king of Heshbon. His kingdom included the east side of the Jordan River. It reached up to the south end of the Sea of Galilee.<verse eid="JOS 13:27"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 13:28"/>All those towns and their villages were given to the tribe of Gad as their very own. Each family group received its share.<verse eid="JOS 13:28"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 13:29"/>Here is what Moses had given to half of the tribe of Manasseh, according to its family groups. It’s what Moses had given to half of Manasseh’s family line.<verse eid="JOS 13:29"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 13:30"/>Their territory starts at Mahanaim. It includes the whole land of Bashan. That was the entire kingdom of Og, the king of Bashan. Manasseh’s territory includes all the 60 towns of Jair in Bashan. <verse eid="JOS 13:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 13:31"/>It includes half of the land of Gilead. It also includes Ashtaroth and Edrei. They were the royal cities of Og in Bashan.</para>
  <para style="li4" vid="JOS 13:31">That land was given to half of the family line of Makir. He was the son of Manasseh. Each family group received its share.<verse eid="JOS 13:31"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 13:32"/>Those were the shares of land Moses had given the eastern tribes when he was in the plains of Moab. The plains are across the Jordan River east of Jericho. <verse eid="JOS 13:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 13:33"/>But Moses hadn’t given any share to the tribe of Levi. The <char style="nd">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, is their share. Moses gave the Levites what he had promised them.<verse eid="JOS 13:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="JOS 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Land for the Tribes West of the Jordan River</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 14:1"/>The rest of the tribes of Israel received their shares of land in Canaan. Eleazar the priest and Joshua, the son of Nun, decided what each of the tribes should receive. The leaders of the tribes helped them make these decisions. <verse eid="JOS 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 14:2"/>The shares of nine tribes and half of the tribe of Manasseh were decided by casting lots. That’s what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded through Moses. <verse eid="JOS 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 14:3"/>Moses had given two tribes and the other half of the tribe of Manasseh their shares east of the Jordan River. But Moses had not given the Levites a share among the other tribes. <verse eid="JOS 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 14:4"/>Manasseh and Ephraim were the sons of Joseph. They had become two tribes. The Levites didn’t receive any share of the land. They only received towns to live in and grasslands for their flocks and herds. <verse eid="JOS 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 14:5"/>So the Israelites divided up the land, just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded Moses.<verse eid="JOS 14:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Joshua Gives Hebron to Caleb</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 14:6"/>The people of Judah approached Joshua at Gilgal. Caleb, the son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite, spoke to Joshua. He said, “You know what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Moses, the man of God. He spoke to him at Kadesh Barnea about you and me. <verse eid="JOS 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 14:7"/>Moses, the servant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, sent me from Kadesh Barnea to check out the land. I was 40 years old at that time. I brought back an honest report to him. I told him exactly what I had seen. <verse eid="JOS 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 14:8"/>Several other men of Israel went up with me. What they reported terrified the people. But I followed the <char style="nd">Lord</char> my God with my whole heart. <verse eid="JOS 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 14:9"/>So on that day Moses made a promise to me. He said, ‘The land you have walked on will be your share. It will be the share of your children forever. That’s because you have followed the <char style="nd">Lord</char> my God with your whole heart.’ <char style="rq">(<ref loc="DEU 1:36">Deuteronomy 1:36</ref>)</char><verse eid="JOS 14:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 14:10"/>“The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has done just as he promised. He made the promise while Israel was wandering around in the desert. That was 45 years ago. He has kept me alive all this time. So here I am today, 85 years old! <verse eid="JOS 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 14:11"/>I’m still as strong today as I was the day Moses sent me out. I’m just as able to go out to battle now as I was then. <verse eid="JOS 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 14:12"/>So give me this hill country. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> promised it to me that day. At that time you yourself heard that the Anakites were living there. You also heard that their cities were large and had high walls around them. But I’ll drive them out, just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said I would. He will help me do it.”<verse eid="JOS 14:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 14:13"/>Then Joshua blessed Caleb, the son of Jephunneh. He gave him Hebron as his share. <verse eid="JOS 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 14:14"/>So ever since that time Hebron has belonged to Caleb, the son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite. That’s because he followed the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, with his whole heart. <verse eid="JOS 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 14:15"/>Hebron used to be called Kiriath Arba. It was named after Arba. He was the greatest man among the Anakites.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 14:15">So the land had peace and rest.<verse eid="JOS 14:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="JOS 15"/>
  <para style="s1">Land Is Given to Judah</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 15:1"/>Land was given to the tribe of Judah, according to its family groups. It reached down to the territory of Edom. It went as far south as the Desert of Zin.<verse eid="JOS 15:1"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 15:2"/>Judah’s border on the south started from the bay at the south end of the Dead Sea. <verse eid="JOS 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 15:3"/>It went across to the south of Scorpion Pass. It continued on to Zin. It went over to the south of Kadesh Barnea. Then it ran past Hezron up to Addar. It curved around to Karka. <verse eid="JOS 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 15:4"/>It then went along to Azmon. There it joined the Wadi of Egypt and ended at the Mediterranean Sea. That was the southern border of Judah.<verse eid="JOS 15:4"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 15:5"/>The border on the east was the Dead Sea. It went north all the way to where the Jordan River enters the sea.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 15:5">The border on the north started at the bay of the Dead Sea. That’s where the Jordan River enters the sea. <verse eid="JOS 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 15:6"/>From there it went up to Beth Hoglah. It continued north of Beth Arabah to the Stone of Bohan, the son of Reuben. <verse eid="JOS 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 15:7"/>Then it went from the Valley of Achor up to Debir. It turned north to Gilgal. Gilgal faces the Pass of Adummim south of the valley. The border continued along to the springs of En Shemesh. It came to an end at En Rogel. <verse eid="JOS 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 15:8"/>Then it ran up the Valley of Ben Hinnom. It went along the south slope of Jerusalem. From there it climbed to the top of the hill west of the Hinnom Valley. The hill is also at the north end of the Valley of Rephaim. <verse eid="JOS 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 15:9"/>From the top of the hill the border headed toward the springs of Nephtoah. It went to the towns near Mount Ephron. It went down toward Kiriath Jearim. <verse eid="JOS 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 15:10"/>Then it curved west from Kiriath Jearim to Mount Seir. It ran along the north slope of Mount Kesalon. It continued down to Beth Shemesh and crossed over to Timnah. <verse eid="JOS 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 15:11"/>It went to the north slope of Ekron. Then it turned toward Shikkeron. It passed along to Mount Baalah and reached Jabneel. The border came to an end at the Mediterranean Sea.<verse eid="JOS 15:11"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 15:12"/>The border on the west was the coastline of the Mediterranean Sea.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="JOS 15:12"/>
  <para style="li4" vid="JOS 15:12">Those were the borders of the family groups of the tribe of Judah.<verse eid="JOS 15:12"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 15:13"/>Joshua gave a part of Judah’s share of land to Caleb, the son of Jephunneh. That was according to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s command to Joshua. The share Caleb received was the city of Hebron. It was also called Kiriath Arba. Anak came from the family line of Arba. <verse eid="JOS 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 15:14"/>Caleb drove three Anakites out of Hebron. Their names were Sheshai, Ahiman and Talmai. They were from the family line of Anak. <verse eid="JOS 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 15:15"/>From Hebron, Caleb marched out against the people living in Debir. It used to be called Kiriath Sepher. <verse eid="JOS 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 15:16"/>Caleb said, “I will give my daughter Aksah to be married. She’ll be the wife of the man who attacks and captures Kiriath Sepher.” <verse eid="JOS 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 15:17"/>Othniel captured it. So Caleb gave his daughter Aksah to him to be his wife. Othniel was the son of Kenaz. He was Caleb’s brother.<verse eid="JOS 15:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 15:18"/>One day Aksah came to Othniel. She begged him to ask her father for a field. When she got off her donkey, Caleb spoke to her. He asked, “What can I do for you?”<verse eid="JOS 15:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 15:19"/>She replied, “Do me a special favor. You have given me some land in the Negev Desert. Give me springs of water also.” So Caleb gave her the upper and lower springs.<verse eid="JOS 15:19"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 15:20"/>Here is the share of land given to the tribe of Judah, according to its family groups.<verse eid="JOS 15:20"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 15:21"/>The towns farthest south that were given to Judah were in the Negev Desert. They were near the border of Edom. Here is a list of those towns.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 15:21">Kabzeel, Eder, Jagur, <verse eid="JOS 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 15:22"/>Kinah, Dimonah, Adadah, <verse eid="JOS 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 15:23"/>Kedesh, Hazor, Ithnan, <verse eid="JOS 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 15:24"/>Ziph, Telem, Bealoth, <verse eid="JOS 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 15:25"/>Hazor Hadattah, Hazor, <verse eid="JOS 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 15:26"/>Amam, Shema, Moladah, <verse eid="JOS 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 15:27"/>Hazar Gaddah, Heshmon, Beth Pelet, <verse eid="JOS 15:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 15:28"/>Hazar Shual, Beersheba, Biziothiah, <verse eid="JOS 15:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 15:29"/>Baalah, Iyim, Ezem, <verse eid="JOS 15:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 15:30"/>Eltolad, Kesil, Hormah, <verse eid="JOS 15:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 15:31"/>Ziklag, Madmannah, Sansannah, <verse eid="JOS 15:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 15:32"/>Lebaoth, Shilhim, Ain and Rimmon. The total number of towns was 29. Some of them had villages near them.<verse eid="JOS 15:32"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 15:33"/>Towns were also given to Judah in the western hills. Here is a list of those towns.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 15:33">Eshtaol, Zorah, Ashnah, <verse eid="JOS 15:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 15:34"/>Zanoah, En Gannim, Tappuah, Enam, <verse eid="JOS 15:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 15:35"/>Jarmuth, Adullam, Sokoh, Azekah, <verse eid="JOS 15:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOS 15:36"/>Shaaraim, Adithaim and Gederah. Gederah is also called Gederothaim. The total number of towns was 14. Some of them had villages near them.<verse eid="JOS 15:36"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOS 15:37"/>Here’s another list of towns given to Judah in the western hills.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 15:37">Zenan, Hadashah, Migdal Gad, <verse eid="JOS 15:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOS 15:38"/>Dilean, Mizpah, Joktheel, <verse eid="JOS 15:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOS 15:39"/>Lachish, Bozkath, Eglon, <verse eid="JOS 15:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOS 15:40"/>Kabbon, Lahmas, Kitlish, <verse eid="JOS 15:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOS 15:41"/>Gederoth, Beth Dagon, Naamah and Makkedah. The total number of towns was 16. Some of them had villages near them.<verse eid="JOS 15:41"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="JOS 15:42"/>Here’s another list of towns given to Judah in the western hills.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 15:42">Libnah, Ether, Ashan, <verse eid="JOS 15:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JOS 15:43"/>Iphtah, Ashnah, Nezib, <verse eid="JOS 15:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JOS 15:44"/>Keilah, Akzib and Mareshah. The total number of towns was nine. Some of them had villages near them.<verse eid="JOS 15:44"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="JOS 15:45"/>Judah was also given Ekron and the settlements and villages around it. <verse eid="JOS 15:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JOS 15:46"/>West of Ekron, Judah was given all the settlements and villages near Ashdod. <verse eid="JOS 15:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JOS 15:47"/>Judah was given Ashdod and the settlements and villages around it. And Judah was given Gaza and its settlements and villages. Judah’s territory went all the way to the Wadi of Egypt and the coast of the Mediterranean Sea.<verse eid="JOS 15:47"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="JOS 15:48"/>Towns were also given to Judah in the central hill country. Here is a list of those towns.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 15:48">Shamir, Jattir, Sokoh, <verse eid="JOS 15:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JOS 15:49"/>Dannah, Debir, <verse eid="JOS 15:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JOS 15:50"/>Anab, Eshtemoh, Anim, <verse eid="JOS 15:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JOS 15:51"/>Goshen, Holon and Giloh. The total number of towns was 11. Some of them had villages near them.<verse eid="JOS 15:51"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="52" style="v" sid="JOS 15:52"/>Here’s another list of towns given to Judah in the central hill country.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 15:52">Arab, Dumah, Eshan, <verse eid="JOS 15:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JOS 15:53"/>Janim, Beth Tappuah, Aphekah, <verse eid="JOS 15:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="JOS 15:54"/>Humtah, Hebron and Zior. The total number of towns was nine. Some of them had villages near them.<verse eid="JOS 15:54"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="55" style="v" sid="JOS 15:55"/>Here’s another list of towns given to Judah in the central hill country.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 15:55">Maon, Carmel, Ziph, Juttah, <verse eid="JOS 15:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="JOS 15:56"/>Jezreel, Jokdeam, Zanoah, <verse eid="JOS 15:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="JOS 15:57"/>Kain, Gibeah and Timnah. The total number of towns was ten. Some of them had villages near them.<verse eid="JOS 15:57"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="58" style="v" sid="JOS 15:58"/>Here’s another list of towns given to Judah in the central hill country.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 15:58">Halhul, Beth Zur, Gedor, <verse eid="JOS 15:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="JOS 15:59"/>Maarath, Beth Anoth and Eltekon. The total number of towns was six. Some of them had villages near them.<verse eid="JOS 15:59"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="60" style="v" sid="JOS 15:60"/>Here’s another list of towns given to Judah in the central hill country.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 15:60">Kiriath Jearim and Rabbah. The total number of towns was two. They had villages near them.<verse eid="JOS 15:60"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="61" style="v" sid="JOS 15:61"/>Towns were also given to Judah in the desert. Here is a list of those towns.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 15:61">Beth Arabah, Middin, Sekakah, <verse eid="JOS 15:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="JOS 15:62"/>Nibshan, the City of Salt and En Gedi. The total number of towns was six. Some of them had villages near them.<verse eid="JOS 15:62"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="63" style="v" sid="JOS 15:63"/>Judah couldn’t drive out the Jebusites who were living in Jerusalem. So they live there with the people of Judah to this day.<verse eid="JOS 15:63"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="JOS 16"/>
  <para style="s1">Land Is Given to Ephraim and Manasseh</para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 16:1"/>The land given to the two tribes in the family line of Joseph began at the Jordan River. Their border started east of the springs of Jericho. It went up from there through the desert into the hill country of Bethel. <verse eid="JOS 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 16:2"/>Bethel is also called Luz. From Bethel the border crossed over to Ataroth. That’s where the Arkites live. <verse eid="JOS 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 16:3"/>Then it went west down to the territory of the Japhletites. It went all the way to the area of Lower Beth Horon. It went on to Gezer. The border came to an end at the Mediterranean Sea.<verse eid="JOS 16:3"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 16:4"/>The tribes of Manasseh and Ephraim were from the family line of Joseph. So they received that land as their share.<verse eid="JOS 16:4"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 16:5"/>Here is the territory given to the tribe of Ephraim, according to its family groups.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="JOS 16:5"/>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 16:5">The border of their share of land started at Ataroth Addar in the east. It went to Upper Beth Horon. <verse eid="JOS 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 16:6"/>It continued toward the Mediterranean Sea. From Mikmethath on the north, it curved toward the east. It went to Taanath Shiloh. It passed by Taanath Shiloh to Janoah on the east. <verse eid="JOS 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 16:7"/>Then it went down from Janoah to Ataroth and Naarah. It touched Jericho and came to an end at the Jordan River. <verse eid="JOS 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 16:8"/>From Tappuah the border went west to the Kanah Valley. It came to an end at the Mediterranean Sea. That was the land given to the tribe of Ephraim. Each family group received its share.<verse eid="JOS 16:8"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 16:9"/>The tribe of Ephraim was also given other towns and villages that were set apart for them. Those towns and villages were in the share of land given to the tribe of Manasseh.<verse eid="JOS 16:9"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 16:10"/>The people of Ephraim didn’t drive out the Canaanites living in Gezer. The Canaanites live among the people of Ephraim to this day. But they are forced to work hard for the people of Ephraim.<verse eid="JOS 16:10"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="JOS 17"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 17:1"/>Land was given to the tribe of Manasseh. It was given to Makir. Manasseh was Joseph’s oldest son. Makir was Manasseh’s oldest son. The people of Gilead came from the family line of Makir. The people of Gilead had received the lands of Gilead and Bashan. That’s because the people of Makir were great soldiers. <verse eid="JOS 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 17:2"/>So land was given to the rest of the people of Manasseh. It was given to the family groups of Abiezer, Helek, Asriel, Shechem, Hepher and Shemida. They were the other men in the family line of Manasseh, the son of Joseph. Those were their names by their family groups.<verse eid="JOS 17:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 17:3"/>Makir was the son of Manasseh. Gilead was the son of Makir. Hepher was the son of Gilead. And Zelophehad was the son of Hepher. Zelophehad didn’t have any sons. He only had daughters. Their names were Mahlah, Noah, Hoglah, Milkah and Tirzah. <verse eid="JOS 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 17:4"/>The daughters of Zelophehad went to Eleazar the priest and to Joshua, the son of Nun. They also went to the other leaders. They said, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded Moses to give us our share of land among our male relatives.” So Joshua gave them land along with their male relatives. That was according to what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded. <verse eid="JOS 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 17:5"/>Manasseh’s share was made up of ten pieces of land. That land was in addition to Gilead and Bashan east of the Jordan River. <verse eid="JOS 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 17:6"/>So the five granddaughters of Hepher in the family line of Manasseh received land, just as the other five sons of Manasseh did. The land of Gilead belonged to the rest of the family line of Manasseh.<verse eid="JOS 17:6"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 17:7"/>The territory of Manasseh reached from Asher to Mikmethath. Mikmethath was east of Shechem. The border ran south from Mikmethath. The people living at En Tappuah were inside the border. <verse eid="JOS 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 17:8"/>Manasseh had the land around Tappuah. But the town of Tappuah itself was on the border of Manasseh’s land. It belonged to the people of Ephraim. <verse eid="JOS 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 17:9"/>The border continued south to the Kanah Valley. Some of the towns that belonged to Ephraim were located among the towns of Manasseh. But the border of Manasseh was the north side of the valley. The border came to an end at the Mediterranean Sea. <verse eid="JOS 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 17:10"/>The land on the south belonged to Ephraim. The land on the north belonged to Manasseh. The territory of Manasseh reached the Mediterranean Sea. The tribe of Asher was the border on the north. The tribe of Issachar was the border on the east.<verse eid="JOS 17:10"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 17:11"/>Inside the land given to Issachar and Asher, the towns of Beth Shan and Ibleam belonged to Manasseh. The towns of Dor, Endor, Taanach and Megiddo and their people also belonged to Manasseh. Manasseh was given all those towns and the settlements around them. The third town in the list was also called Naphoth Dor.<verse eid="JOS 17:11"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 17:12"/>But the people of Manasseh weren’t able to take over those towns. That’s because the Canaanites had made up their minds to live in that area. <verse eid="JOS 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 17:13"/>The Israelites grew stronger. Then they forced the Canaanites to work hard for them. But they didn’t drive them out completely.<verse eid="JOS 17:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 17:14"/>The people in the family line of Joseph spoke to Joshua. They said, “Why have you given us only one share of the land to have as our own? There are large numbers of us. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has blessed us greatly.”<verse eid="JOS 17:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 17:15"/>“That’s true,” Joshua said. “There are large numbers of you. And the hill country of Ephraim is too small for you. So go up into the forest. Clear out some land for yourselves in the territory of the Perizzites and Rephaites.”<verse eid="JOS 17:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 17:16"/>The people in Joseph’s family line replied, “The hill country isn’t big enough for us. And all the Canaanites who live in the plains use chariots that have iron parts. They include the people of Beth Shan and its settlements. They also include the people who live in the Valley of Jezreel.”<verse eid="JOS 17:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 17:17"/>Joshua spoke again to the people in Joseph’s family line. He said to the people of Ephraim and Manasseh, “There are large numbers of you. And you are very powerful. You will have more than one piece of land. <verse eid="JOS 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 17:18"/>You will also have the central hill country. It’s covered with trees. Cut them down and clear the land. That whole land from one end to the other will belong to you. The Canaanites use chariots that have iron parts. And those people are strong. But you can drive them out.”<verse eid="JOS 17:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="JOS 18"/>
  <para style="s1">The Rest of the Land Is Divided Up</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 18:1"/>The whole community of Israel gathered together at Shiloh. They set up the tent of meeting there. The country was brought under their control. <verse eid="JOS 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 18:2"/>But there were still seven tribes in Israel who had not yet received their shares of land.<verse eid="JOS 18:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 18:3"/>So Joshua spoke to the Israelites. He said, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char>, the God of your people, has given you this land. How long will you wait before you begin to take it over? <verse eid="JOS 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 18:4"/>Appoint three men from each tribe. I’ll send them to map out the land. Then they’ll write a report about its features. The report will point out the share of land each tribe will receive. Then the men will return to me. <verse eid="JOS 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 18:5"/>You must divide the land up into seven shares. Judah must remain in its territory in the south. The people in Joseph’s family line must remain in their territory in the north. <verse eid="JOS 18:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 18:6"/>Write reports about the features of those seven shares of land. Bring them here to me. Then I’ll cast lots for you in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God. <verse eid="JOS 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 18:7"/>But the Levites don’t get any share of your land. That’s because their share is to serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as priests. The tribes of Gad and Reuben and half of the tribe of Manasseh have already received their shares. They are on the east side of the Jordan River. Moses, the servant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, gave their shares to them.”<verse eid="JOS 18:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 18:8"/>The men started out on their way to map out the land. Joshua directed them, “Go and map out the land. Write a report about its features. Then return to me. I’ll cast lots for you here at Shiloh in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.” <verse eid="JOS 18:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 18:9"/>So the men left and went through the land. They wrote a report about its features on a scroll. It showed how they divided up the land into seven shares. It listed the towns in each share. The men returned to Joshua in the camp at Shiloh.<verse eid="JOS 18:9"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 18:10"/>Then Joshua cast lots for them in Shiloh in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. There he gave out a share of land to each of the remaining tribes in Israel.<verse eid="JOS 18:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land Is Given to Benjamin</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 18:11"/>The first lot drawn out was for the tribe of Benjamin, according to its family groups. The territory they were given was located between the tribes of the people of Judah and the people of Joseph. Here are the borders of Benjamin’s territory.<verse eid="JOS 18:11"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 18:12"/>On the north side their border started at the Jordan River. It went past the north slope of Jericho. Then it headed west into the central hill country. It came to an end at the Desert of Beth Aven. <verse eid="JOS 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 18:13"/>From there the border crossed to the south slope of Bethel. Then it went down to Ataroth Addar on the hill south of Lower Beth Horon.<verse eid="JOS 18:13"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 18:14"/>From the hill that faces Beth Horon on the south the border turned south. Then the border went along the west side of the hill. It came to an end at Kiriath Jearim. That town belongs to the people of Judah. That was the border on the west.<verse eid="JOS 18:14"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 18:15"/>The border on the south side started at the west edge of Kiriath Jearim. It came to an end at the springs of Nephtoah. <verse eid="JOS 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 18:16"/>It went down to the foot of the hill that faces the Valley of Ben Hinnom. The hill is north of the Valley of Rephaim. The border continued down the Hinnom Valley. It went along the south slope of Jerusalem, where the people of Jebus live. It continued on to En Rogel. <verse eid="JOS 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 18:17"/>Then it curved north. It went to En Shemesh. It continued on to Geliloth. Geliloth faces the Pass of Adummim. The border ran down to the Stone of Bohan, the son of Reuben. <verse eid="JOS 18:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 18:18"/>It continued to the north slope of Beth Arabah. It went on down into the Arabah Valley. <verse eid="JOS 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 18:19"/>From there it went to the north slope of Beth Hoglah. It came to an end at the north bay of the Dead Sea. That’s where the Jordan River flows into the Dead Sea. That was the border on the south.<verse eid="JOS 18:19"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 18:20"/>The Jordan River formed the border on the east side.</para>
  <para style="li4" vid="JOS 18:20">Those were the borders that marked out on all sides the land the family groups of Benjamin received as their share.<verse eid="JOS 18:20"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 18:21"/>Here is a list of towns given to the tribe of Benjamin, according to its family groups.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 18:21">Jericho, Beth Hoglah, Emek Keziz, <verse eid="JOS 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 18:22"/>Beth Arabah, Zemaraim, Bethel, <verse eid="JOS 18:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 18:23"/>Avvim, Parah, Ophrah, <verse eid="JOS 18:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 18:24"/>Kephar Ammoni, Ophni and Geba. The total number of towns and their villages was 12.<verse eid="JOS 18:24"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 18:25"/>Here is another list of towns given to Benjamin.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 18:25">Gibeon, Ramah, Beeroth, <verse eid="JOS 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 18:26"/>Mizpah, Kephirah, Mozah, <verse eid="JOS 18:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 18:27"/>Rekem, Irpeel, Taralah, <verse eid="JOS 18:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 18:28"/>Zelah, Haeleph, Jerusalem, Gibeah and Kiriath. The total number of towns and their villages was 14.</para>
  <para style="li4" vid="JOS 18:28">That was the share of land the family groups of Benjamin received.<verse eid="JOS 18:28"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <chapter eid="JOS 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="JOS 19"/>
  <para style="s1">Land Is Given to Simeon</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 19:1"/>The second lot drawn out was for the tribe of Simeon, according to its family groups. The share of land they were given was in the territory of Judah.<verse eid="JOS 19:1"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 19:2"/>Here is what Simeon’s share included.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 19:2">Beersheba, Moladah, <verse eid="JOS 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 19:3"/>Hazar Shual, Balah, Ezem, <verse eid="JOS 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 19:4"/>Eltolad, Bethul, Hormah, <verse eid="JOS 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 19:5"/>Ziklag, Beth Markaboth, Hazar Susah, <verse eid="JOS 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 19:6"/>Beth Lebaoth and Sharuhen. The total number of towns was 13. Some of them had villages near them.<verse eid="JOS 19:6"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 19:7"/>Here’s another list of towns given to Simeon.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 19:7">Ain, Rimmon, Ether and Ashan. The total number of towns was four. Some of them had villages near them. <verse eid="JOS 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 19:8"/>The towns and all the villages around them reached all the way to Ramah in the Negev Desert.</para>
  <para style="li4" vid="JOS 19:8">That was the share of land the tribe of Simeon received, according to its family groups. <verse eid="JOS 19:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 19:9"/>Simeon’s share of land was taken from Judah’s share. That’s because Judah had more land than they needed. So the people of Simeon received their share of land inside the territory of Judah.<verse eid="JOS 19:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land Is Given to Zebulun</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 19:10"/>The third lot drawn out was for the tribe of Zebulun, according to its family groups. Here are the borders of Zebulun’s territory.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 19:10">The border of their share of land went as far as Sarid. <verse eid="JOS 19:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 19:11"/>It ran west to Maralah and touched Dabbesheth. It reached to the valley near Jokneam. <verse eid="JOS 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 19:12"/>It turned east from Sarid toward the sunrise. It went to the territory of Kisloth Tabor. It went on to Daberath and up to Japhia. <verse eid="JOS 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 19:13"/>Then it continued east to Gath Hepher and Eth Kazin. It came to an end at Rimmon and turned toward Neah. <verse eid="JOS 19:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 19:14"/>There the border went around on the north to Hannathon. It came to an end at the Valley of Iphtah El.<verse eid="JOS 19:14"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 19:15"/>Zebulun’s territory included Kattath, Nahalal, Shimron, Idalah and Bethlehem.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 19:15">The total number of towns was 12. Some of them had villages near them.<verse eid="JOS 19:15"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 19:16"/>Those towns and their villages were Zebulun’s share, according to its family groups.<verse eid="JOS 19:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land Is Given to Issachar</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 19:17"/>The fourth lot drawn out was for the tribe of Issachar, according to its family groups. <verse eid="JOS 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 19:18"/>Here is what Issachar’s share included.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 19:18">Jezreel, Kesulloth, Shunem, <verse eid="JOS 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 19:19"/>Hapharaim, Shion, Anaharath, <verse eid="JOS 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 19:20"/>Rabbith, Kishion, Ebez, <verse eid="JOS 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 19:21"/>Remeth, En Gannim, En Haddah and Beth Pazzez.<verse eid="JOS 19:21"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 19:22"/>The border touched Tabor, Shahazumah and Beth Shemesh. It came to an end at the Jordan River.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 19:22">The total number of towns was 16. Some of them had villages near them.<verse eid="JOS 19:22"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 19:23"/>Those towns and their villages were the share the tribe of Issachar received, according to its family groups.<verse eid="JOS 19:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land Is Given to Asher</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 19:24"/>The fifth lot drawn out was for the tribe of Asher, according to its family groups. <verse eid="JOS 19:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 19:25"/>Here is what Asher’s share included.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 19:25">Helkath, Hali, Beten, Akshaph, <verse eid="JOS 19:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 19:26"/>Allammelek, Amad and Mishal. On the west the border touched Carmel and Shihor Libnath. <verse eid="JOS 19:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 19:27"/>Then it turned east toward Beth Dagon. It touched Zebulun and the Valley of Iphtah El. It went north to Beth Emek and Neiel. It went past Kabul on the left. <verse eid="JOS 19:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 19:28"/>It went to Abdon, Rehob, Hammon and Kanah. It reached all the way to Greater Sidon. <verse eid="JOS 19:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 19:29"/>The border then turned back toward Ramah. It went to Tyre, a city that had high walls around it. It turned toward Hosah. It came to an end at the Mediterranean Sea in the area of Akzib, <verse eid="JOS 19:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 19:30"/>Ummah, Aphek and Rehob.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 19:30">The total number of towns was 22. Some of them had villages near them.<verse eid="JOS 19:30"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 19:31"/>Those towns and their villages were the share the tribe of Asher received, according to its family groups.<verse eid="JOS 19:31"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land Is Given to Naphtali</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 19:32"/>The sixth lot drawn out was for Naphtali, according to its family groups.<verse eid="JOS 19:32"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 19:33"/>Their border started at Heleph and the large tree in Zaanannim. It went past Adami Nekeb and Jabneel. It went to Lakkum and came to an end at the Jordan River. <verse eid="JOS 19:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 19:34"/>The border ran west through Aznoth Tabor. It came to an end at Hukkok. It touched Zebulun on the south. It touched Asher on the west. It touched the Jordan on the east.<verse eid="JOS 19:34"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 19:35"/>The towns that had high walls around them were Ziddim, Zer, Hammath, Rakkath, Kinnereth, <verse eid="JOS 19:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOS 19:36"/>Adamah, Ramah, Hazor, <verse eid="JOS 19:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOS 19:37"/>Kedesh, Edrei, En Hazor, <verse eid="JOS 19:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOS 19:38"/>Iron, Migdal El, Horem, Beth Anath and Beth Shemesh.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 19:38">The total number of towns was 19. Some of them had villages near them.<verse eid="JOS 19:38"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOS 19:39"/>Those towns and their villages were the share the tribe of Naphtali received, according to its family groups.<verse eid="JOS 19:39"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land Is Given to Dan</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOS 19:40"/>The seventh lot drawn out was for the tribe of Dan, according to its family groups. <verse eid="JOS 19:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOS 19:41"/>Here is what Dan’s share of land included.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 19:41">Zorah, Eshtaol, Ir Shemesh, <verse eid="JOS 19:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JOS 19:42"/>Shaalabbin, Aijalon, Ithlah, <verse eid="JOS 19:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JOS 19:43"/>Elon, Timnah, Ekron, <verse eid="JOS 19:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JOS 19:44"/>Eltekeh, Gibbethon, Baalath, <verse eid="JOS 19:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JOS 19:45"/>Jehud, Bene Berak, Gath Rimmon, <verse eid="JOS 19:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JOS 19:46"/>Me Jarkon and Rakkon. Dan’s share included the area that faces Joppa.<verse eid="JOS 19:46"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="JOS 19:47"/>The people of Dan lost their territory. So they went up and attacked Leshem. They captured it. They killed its people with their swords. Then they moved into Leshem and made their homes there. They named it Dan. That’s because they traced their family line back to him.<verse eid="JOS 19:47"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="JOS 19:48"/>All those towns and their villages were the share the tribe of Dan received, according to its family groups.<verse eid="JOS 19:48"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land Is Given to Joshua</para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="JOS 19:49"/>The Israelites finished dividing up the shares of land the tribes received. Then they gave a share to Joshua, the son of Nun. <verse eid="JOS 19:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JOS 19:50"/>They did what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded them to do. They gave Joshua the town he asked for. It was Timnath Serah in the hill country of Ephraim. He built up the town and made his home there.<verse eid="JOS 19:50"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="51" style="v" sid="JOS 19:51"/>All those territories were given out by casting lots at Shiloh. The lots were drawn out by Eleazar the priest and by Joshua, the son of Nun. The leaders of the tribes of Israel helped them. The lots were drawn out in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> at the entrance to the tent of meeting. So the work of dividing up the land was finished.<verse eid="JOS 19:51"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="JOS 20"/>
  <para style="s1">Cities to Run to for Safety</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 20:1"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Joshua. He said, <verse eid="JOS 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 20:2"/>“Tell the Israelites to choose the cities to go to for safety, just as I directed you through Moses. <verse eid="JOS 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 20:3"/>Anyone who kills a person by accident can run there for safety. So can anyone who kills a person without meaning to. The one charged with murder will be kept safe from the nearest male relative of the person killed. <verse eid="JOS 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 20:4"/>Suppose those who are charged with murder run for safety to one of these cities. Then they must stand in the entrance of the city gate. They must state their case in front of the elders of that city. The elders must let them come into their city. The elders must provide a place for them to live in their city. <verse eid="JOS 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 20:5"/>Suppose the nearest male relative of the person killed chases the one charged with murder. Then the elders must not hand them over to that relative. That’s because that person didn’t mean to kill their neighbor. They didn’t make evil plans to do it. <verse eid="JOS 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 20:6"/>They must stay in that city until their case has been brought to the community court. They must stay there until the high priest serving at that time dies. Then they can go back to their own home. They can return to the town they ran away from.”<verse eid="JOS 20:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 20:7"/>So the Israelites set apart Kedesh in Galilee. It’s in the hill country of Naphtali. They set apart Shechem. It’s in the hill country of Ephraim. They set apart Kiriath Arba. It’s in the hill country of Judah. Kiriath Arba is also called Hebron. <verse eid="JOS 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 20:8"/>On the east side of the Jordan River near Jericho they chose Bezer. It’s in the desert on the high plains. It’s in the territory of the tribe of Reuben. They chose Ramoth in Gilead. It’s in the territory of the tribe of Gad. They chose Golan in the land of Bashan. It’s in the territory of the tribe of Manasseh. <verse eid="JOS 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 20:9"/>Suppose you kill someone by accident. Or another Israelite does it. Or an outsider who lives among you does it. Then any of you can run for safety to one of these cities that have been chosen. There you won’t be killed by the nearest male relative of the person killed by accident. First your case must be brought to the community court.<verse eid="JOS 20:9"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="JOS 21"/>
  <para style="s1">Towns Are Given to the Levites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 21:1"/>The leaders of the Levite family groups approached Eleazar the priest and Joshua, the son of Nun. They also approached the leaders of the family groups of Israel’s other tribes. <verse eid="JOS 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 21:2"/>They went to all of them at Shiloh in Canaan. They said to them, “Give us towns to live in. Also give us grasslands for our livestock. That’s what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded through Moses.”<verse eid="JOS 21:2"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 21:3"/>So the Israelites gave the Levites towns and grasslands out of their own shares of land. They did what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded. Here are the towns the Levites were given.<verse eid="JOS 21:3"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 21:4"/>The first lot drawn out was for the people of Kohath, according to their family groups. Some of the Levites came from the family line of Aaron the priest. They were given 13 towns from the tribes of Judah, Simeon and Benjamin.<verse eid="JOS 21:4"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 21:5"/>The rest of Kohath’s family groups were given ten towns. Those towns were from the family groups of the tribes of Ephraim and Dan and half of the tribe of Manasseh.<verse eid="JOS 21:5"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 21:6"/>The family groups of Gershon were given 13 towns. Those towns were from the family groups of the tribes of Issachar, Asher and Naphtali and half of the tribe of Manasseh. That part of Manasseh was in the land of Bashan.<verse eid="JOS 21:6"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 21:7"/>The family groups of Merari received 12 towns from the tribes of Reuben, Gad and Zebulun. Each family group received its share.<verse eid="JOS 21:7"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 21:8"/>So the Israelites gave those towns and their grasslands to the Levites. They did what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded through Moses.<verse eid="JOS 21:8"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 21:9"/>Some towns were given from the territories of the tribes of Judah and Simeon. <verse eid="JOS 21:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 21:10"/>The Israelites gave them to the members of the family line of Aaron. The towns were given to the family groups of Kohath. They were Levites. The first lot drawn out was for them. Here are the towns the family groups of Kohath were given.<verse eid="JOS 21:10"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 21:11"/>The Israelites gave them Kiriath Arba and the grasslands around it. Kiriath Arba is also called Hebron. It’s in the hill country of Judah. Anak came from the family line of Arba. <verse eid="JOS 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 21:12"/>But Israel had already given away the fields and villages around the city. They had given them to Caleb as his share. Caleb was the son of Jephunneh. <verse eid="JOS 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 21:13"/>So they gave Hebron to the members of the family line of Aaron the priest. Hebron was a city where anyone charged with murder could go for safety. They also gave them Libnah, <verse eid="JOS 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 21:14"/>Jattir, Eshtemoa, <verse eid="JOS 21:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 21:15"/>Holon, Debir, <verse eid="JOS 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 21:16"/>Ain, Juttah and Beth Shemesh. They gave those towns and their grasslands to the family groups of Kohath. The total number of towns from the tribes of Judah and Simeon came to nine.<verse eid="JOS 21:16"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 21:17"/>The Israelites gave some towns from the tribe of Benjamin to the family groups of Kohath.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:17">The towns were Gibeon, Geba, <verse eid="JOS 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 21:18"/>Anathoth and Almon. The total number of these towns and their grasslands came to four.<verse eid="JOS 21:18"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 21:19"/>So the total number of towns and their grasslands given to the priests in Aaron’s family line came to 13.<verse eid="JOS 21:19"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 21:20"/>There were other family groups of Kohath among the Levites. They were given towns from the tribe of Ephraim. Here are the towns those other family groups of Kohath were given.<verse eid="JOS 21:20"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 21:21"/>In the hill country of Ephraim they were given</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:21">Shechem. It was a city where anyone charged with murder could go for safety. They were also given Gezer, <verse eid="JOS 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 21:22"/>Kibzaim and Beth Horon. The total number of these towns and their grasslands came to four.<verse eid="JOS 21:22"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 21:23"/>From the tribe of Dan they received</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:23">Eltekeh, Gibbethon, <verse eid="JOS 21:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 21:24"/>Aijalon and Gath Rimmon. The total number of these towns and their grasslands came to four.<verse eid="JOS 21:24"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 21:25"/>From half of the tribe of Manasseh they received</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:25">Taanach and Gath Rimmon. The total number of these towns and their grasslands came to two.<verse eid="JOS 21:25"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 21:26"/>So all these ten towns and their grasslands were given to the other family groups of Kohath.<verse eid="JOS 21:26"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 21:27"/>Here are the towns given to the family groups of Gershon among the Levites.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 21:27">From half of the tribe of Manasseh they received</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:27">Golan in the land of Bashan. Golan was a city where anyone charged with murder could go for safety. They also received Be Eshterah. The total number of these towns and their grasslands came to two.<verse eid="JOS 21:27"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 21:28"/>From the tribe of Issachar they received</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:28">Kishion, Daberath, <verse eid="JOS 21:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 21:29"/>Jarmuth and En Gannim. The total number of these towns and their grasslands came to four.<verse eid="JOS 21:29"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 21:30"/>From the tribe of Asher they received</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:30">Mishal, Abdon, <verse eid="JOS 21:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 21:31"/>Helkath and Rehob. The total number of these towns and their grasslands came to four.<verse eid="JOS 21:31"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 21:32"/>From the tribe of Naphtali they received</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:32">Kedesh in Galilee. Kedesh was a city where anyone charged with murder could go for safety. They also received Hammoth Dor and Kartan. The total number of these towns and their grasslands came to three.<verse eid="JOS 21:32"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 21:33"/>So the total number of towns and their grasslands given to the family groups of Gershon came to 13.<verse eid="JOS 21:33"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 21:34"/>The rest of the Levites were from the family groups of Merari. Here are the towns they were given.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 21:34">From the tribe of Zebulun they received</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:34">Jokneam, Kartah, <verse eid="JOS 21:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 21:35"/>Dimnah and Nahalal. The total number of these towns and their grasslands came to four.<verse eid="JOS 21:35"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOS 21:36"/>From the tribe of Reuben they received</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:36">Bezer, Jahaz, <verse eid="JOS 21:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOS 21:37"/>Kedemoth and Mephaath. The total number of these towns and their grasslands came to four.<verse eid="JOS 21:37"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOS 21:38"/>From the tribe of Gad they received</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:38">Ramoth in Gilead. Ramoth was a city where anyone charged with murder could go for safety. They also received Mahanaim, <verse eid="JOS 21:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOS 21:39"/>Heshbon and Jazer. The total number of these towns and their grasslands came to four.<verse eid="JOS 21:39"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOS 21:40"/>So the total number of towns given to the family groups of Merari came to 12. That concludes the list of towns the rest of the Levites received.<verse eid="JOS 21:40"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOS 21:41"/>The total number of Levite towns and their grasslands in the territory given to Israel came to 48. <verse eid="JOS 21:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JOS 21:42"/>Each of those towns had grasslands around it. That was true of all of them.<verse eid="JOS 21:42"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="JOS 21:43"/>So the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave Israel all the land he had promised to give to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. And Israel took it over. Then they made their homes there. <verse eid="JOS 21:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JOS 21:44"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave them peace and rest on every side. He had promised their people of long ago that he would do that. Not one of Israel’s enemies was able to fight against them and win. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> handed all their enemies over to them. <verse eid="JOS 21:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JOS 21:45"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> kept all the good promises he had made to the Israelites. Every one of them came true.<verse eid="JOS 21:45"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="JOS 22"/>
  <para style="s1">The Eastern Tribes Return Home</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 22:1"/>Joshua sent for the tribes of Reuben and Gad and half of the tribe of Manasseh. <verse eid="JOS 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 22:2"/>He said to them, “You have done everything that Moses, the servant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, commanded. You have also obeyed everything I commanded. <verse eid="JOS 22:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 22:3"/>For a long time now you haven’t deserted the other Israelites. Instead, you have done what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God sent you to do. You have obeyed him right up to this day. <verse eid="JOS 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 22:4"/>Now the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has given the other tribes peace and rest. That’s what he promised to do. So return to your homes. They are in the land that Moses, the servant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, gave you. It’s on the east side of the Jordan River. <verse eid="JOS 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 22:5"/>Be very careful to obey the law that Moses, the servant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, gave you. He commanded you to love the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. He told you to live exactly as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> wants you to. He told you to obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s commands. He told you to remain faithful to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. And he told you to serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char> with all your heart and with all your soul.”<verse eid="JOS 22:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 22:6"/>Joshua gave the eastern tribes his blessing. Then he sent them home. So they went. <verse eid="JOS 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 22:7"/>Moses had given land in Bashan to half of the tribe of Manasseh. Joshua had given land to the other half of the tribe. He had given it to them along with the other tribes on the west side of the Jordan River. When Joshua sent them home, he blessed them. <verse eid="JOS 22:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 22:8"/>He said, “Return to your homes. Take your great wealth with you. Return with your large herds of livestock. Take your silver, gold, bronze and iron with you. Return with all the extra clothes you acquired. Divide up the things you have taken from your enemies. Share them with your people.”<verse eid="JOS 22:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 22:9"/>So the tribes of Reuben and Gad and half of the tribe of Manasseh went home. They left the other Israelites at Shiloh in Canaan. They returned to Gilead. That was their own land. They had acquired it according to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s command through Moses.<verse eid="JOS 22:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 22:10"/>The tribes of Reuben and Gad and half of the tribe of Manasseh came to Geliloth. It was near the Jordan River in the land of Canaan. They built a large altar there by the Jordan. <verse eid="JOS 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 22:11"/>The rest of the Israelites heard that the eastern tribes had built the altar. They heard that it had been built on the border of Canaan at Geliloth. It was near the Jordan River on the west side. <verse eid="JOS 22:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 22:12"/>So the whole community of Israel gathered together at Shiloh. They decided to go to war against the eastern tribes.<verse eid="JOS 22:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 22:13"/>The Israelites sent Phinehas the priest to the land of Gilead. Phinehas was the son of Eleazar. They sent him to the tribes of Reuben and Gad and half of the tribe of Manasseh. <verse eid="JOS 22:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 22:14"/>They sent ten of their leaders with him. There was one from each of the tribes of Israel. Each man was the leader of a family group among the larger family groups of Israel.<verse eid="JOS 22:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 22:15"/>Those leaders went to the tribes of Reuben and Gad and half of the tribe of Manasseh. Those tribes were in the land of Gilead. The leaders said to them, <verse eid="JOS 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 22:16"/>“We’re speaking for the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s whole community. How could you disobey the God of Israel like this? How could you turn away from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>? How could you disobey him by building an altar for yourselves? <verse eid="JOS 22:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 22:17"/>Don’t you remember how we sinned at Peor? The <char style="nd">Lord</char> struck us with a plague because of what we did. Up to this day we’re still suffering because of that sin. <verse eid="JOS 22:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 22:18"/>Are you turning away from the <char style="nd">Lord</char> now?</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 22:18">“Suppose you disobey the <char style="nd">Lord</char> today. If you do, he’ll be angry with the whole community of Israel tomorrow. <verse eid="JOS 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 22:19"/>If your own land is ‘unclean,’ come over to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s land. It’s where his holy tent stands. Share our land with us. But don’t disobey the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Don’t turn against us by building an altar for yourselves. Don’t build any altar other than the altar of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God. <verse eid="JOS 22:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 22:20"/>Remember what happened to Achan, the son of Zerah. Achan wasn’t faithful to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He took the things that had been set apart to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> in a special way to be destroyed. Didn’t the whole community of Israel experience the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s anger? Achan wasn’t the only one who died because of his sin.”<verse eid="JOS 22:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 22:21"/>Then the tribes of Reuben and Gad and half of the tribe of Manasseh replied. They answered the leaders of the family groups of Israel. <verse eid="JOS 22:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 22:22"/>They said, “The Mighty One, God, the <char style="nd">Lord</char>! The Mighty One, God, the <char style="nd">Lord</char>! He knows! And we want Israel to know! Have we opposed the <char style="nd">Lord</char>? Have we refused to obey him? If we have, don’t spare us today. <verse eid="JOS 22:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 22:23"/>Have we built our own altar so we can turn away from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>? Have we built it to offer burnt offerings and grain offerings on it? Have we built it to sacrifice friendship offerings on it? If we have, may the <char style="nd">Lord</char> himself hold us accountable.<verse eid="JOS 22:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 22:24"/>“No! We built it because we were afraid. Someday your children might speak to our children. We were afraid they might say, ‘What do you have to do with the <char style="nd">Lord</char>? What do you have to do with the God of Israel? <verse eid="JOS 22:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 22:25"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has made the Jordan River a border between us and you. You people of Reuben! You people of Gad! You don’t have anything to do with the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.’ If your children say that, they might cause our children to stop worshiping the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="JOS 22:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 22:26"/>“That’s why we said to ourselves, ‘Let’s get ready and build an altar. But let’s not build it to offer burnt offerings or sacrifices on it.’ <verse eid="JOS 22:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 22:27"/>So just the opposite is true. The altar will be a witness between us and you. It will be a witness between our children and yours after us. It will also be a witness that we will worship the <char style="nd">Lord</char> at his sacred tent. We’ll worship him there with our burnt offerings, sacrifices and friendship offerings. Then in days to come your children won’t be able to say to ours, ‘You don’t have anything to do with the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.’<verse eid="JOS 22:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 22:28"/>“So we said to ourselves, ‘Suppose they say that to us sometime. Or suppose they say it to our children after us. Then we’ll answer, “Look at this altar. It’s exactly like the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s altar. Our people built it. They didn’t build it to offer burnt offerings and sacrifices on it. Instead, they built it to be a witness between us and you.” ’<verse eid="JOS 22:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 22:29"/>“We would never refuse to obey the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. We would never turn away from him now. We wouldn’t build an altar to offer burnt offerings, grain offerings and sacrifices on it. We wouldn’t use any altar other than the altar of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God. That altar stands in front of his holy tent.”<verse eid="JOS 22:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 22:30"/>Phinehas the priest heard what the tribes of Reuben, Gad and Manasseh had to say. The leaders of the family groups of the community of Israel heard it too. All of them were pleased with what they heard. <verse eid="JOS 22:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 22:31"/>Phinehas the priest spoke to the tribes of Reuben, Gad and Manasseh. Phinehas was the son of Eleazar. He said, “Today we know that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is with us. That’s because you have been faithful to him in this matter. Now you have saved the Israelites from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s anger against them.”<verse eid="JOS 22:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 22:32"/>Then Phinehas the priest, the son of Eleazar, returned to Canaan. So did the leaders. All of them went back from their meeting with the tribes of Reuben and Gad in Gilead. They brought a report back to the Israelites. <verse eid="JOS 22:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 22:33"/>The people were glad to hear the report. They praised God. They didn’t talk anymore about going to war against the eastern tribes. And they didn’t talk anymore about destroying the country where the tribes of Reuben and Gad lived.<verse eid="JOS 22:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 22:34"/>The tribes of Reuben and Gad gave the altar a name. They called it A Witness Between Us that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is God.<verse eid="JOS 22:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="JOS 23"/>
  <para style="s1">Joshua Says Goodbye to the Leaders</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 23:1"/>A long time had passed. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> had given Israel peace and rest from all their enemies around them. By that time Joshua was very old. <verse eid="JOS 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 23:2"/>So he sent for all the elders, leaders, judges and officials of Israel. He said to them, “I’m very old. <verse eid="JOS 23:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 23:3"/>You yourselves have seen everything the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has done. You have seen what he’s done to all these nations because of you. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God fought for you. <verse eid="JOS 23:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 23:4"/>Remember how I’ve given you all the land of the nations that remain here. I’ve given each of your tribes a share of it. It’s the land of the nations I conquered. It’s between the Jordan River and the Mediterranean Sea in the west. <verse eid="JOS 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 23:5"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God himself will drive those nations out of your way. He will push them out to make room for you. You will take over their land, just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God promised you.<verse eid="JOS 23:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 23:6"/>“Be very strong. Be careful to obey everything written in the Book of the Law of Moses. Don’t turn away from it to the right or the left. <verse eid="JOS 23:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 23:7"/>Don’t have anything to do with the nations that remain among you. Don’t use the names of their gods for any reason at all. Don’t give your word and make promises in their names. You must not serve them. You must not bow down to them. <verse eid="JOS 23:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 23:8"/>You must remain true to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God, just as you have done until now.<verse eid="JOS 23:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 23:9"/>“The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has driven out great and powerful nations to make room for you. To this day no one has been able to fight against you and win. <verse eid="JOS 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 23:10"/>One of you can chase a thousand away. That’s because the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God fights for you, just as he promised he would. <verse eid="JOS 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 23:11"/>So be very careful to love the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="JOS 23:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 23:12"/>“But suppose you turn away from him. You mix with the people who are left alive in the nations that remain among you. Later, you and they get married to each other. And you do other kinds of things with them. <verse eid="JOS 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 23:13"/>Then you can be sure of what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God will do. He won’t drive out those nations to make room for you anymore. Instead, they will become traps and snares for you. They will be like whips on your backs. They will be like thorns in your eyes. All that will continue until you are destroyed. It will continue until you are removed from this good land. It’s the land the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has given you.<verse eid="JOS 23:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 23:14"/>“Now I’m about to die, just as everyone else on earth does. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has kept all the good promises he gave you. Every one of them has come true. Not one has failed to come true. And you know that with all your heart and soul. <verse eid="JOS 23:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 23:15"/>Every good thing has come to pass that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God has promised you. So you know that he can also bring against you all the evil things he has warned you about. He’ll do it until he has destroyed you. He’ll do it until he has removed you from this good land. It’s the land he has given you. <verse eid="JOS 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 23:16"/>Suppose you break the covenant the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God made with you. He commanded you to obey it. But suppose you go and serve other gods. And you bow down to them. Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will be very angry with you. You will quickly be destroyed. You will be removed from the good land he has given you.”<verse eid="JOS 23:16"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="JOS 24"/>
  <para style="s1">The Covenant Is Renewed at Shechem</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 24:1"/>Joshua gathered all Israel’s tribes together at Shechem. He sent for the elders, leaders, judges and officials of Israel. They came and stood there in the sight of God.<verse eid="JOS 24:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 24:2"/>Joshua spoke to all the people. He said, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is the God of Israel. He says, ‘Long ago your people lived east of the Euphrates River. They worshiped other gods there. Your people included Terah. He was the father of Abraham and Nahor. <verse eid="JOS 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 24:3"/>I took your father Abraham from the land east of the Euphrates. I led him all through Canaan. I gave him many children and grandchildren. I gave him Isaac. <verse eid="JOS 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 24:4"/>To Isaac I gave Jacob and Esau. I gave the hill country of Seir to Esau. But Jacob and his family went down to Egypt.<verse eid="JOS 24:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 24:5"/>“ ‘Then I sent Moses and Aaron. I made the people of Egypt suffer because of the plagues I sent on them. But I brought you out of Egypt. <verse eid="JOS 24:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 24:6"/>When I brought your people out, they came to the Red Sea. The people of Egypt chased them with chariots and with men on horses. They chased them all the way to the sea. <verse eid="JOS 24:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 24:7"/>But your people cried out to me for help. So I put darkness between you and the people of Egypt. I swept them into the sea. It completely covered them. Your own eyes saw what I did to them. After that, you lived in the desert for a long time.<verse eid="JOS 24:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 24:8"/>“ ‘I brought you to the land of the Amorites. They lived east of the Jordan River. They fought against you. But I handed them over to you. I destroyed them to make room for you. Then you took over their land. <verse eid="JOS 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 24:9"/>Balak, the son of Zippor, prepared to fight against Israel. Balak was the king of Moab. He sent for Balaam, the son of Beor. Balak wanted Balaam to put a curse on you. <verse eid="JOS 24:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 24:10"/>But I would not listen to Balaam’s curses. So he blessed you again and again. And I saved you from his power.<verse eid="JOS 24:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 24:11"/>“ ‘Then you went across the Jordan River. You came to Jericho. Its people fought against you. So did the Amorites, Perizzites, Canaanites, Hittites, Girgashites, Hivites and Jebusites. But I handed them over to you. <verse eid="JOS 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 24:12"/>I sent hornets ahead of you. They drove your enemies out to make room for you. That included the two Amorite kings. You did not do that with your own swords and bows. <verse eid="JOS 24:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 24:13"/>So I gave you a land you had never farmed. I gave you cities you had not built. You are now living in them. And you are eating the fruit of vineyards and olive trees you did not plant.’<verse eid="JOS 24:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 24:14"/>“So have respect for the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Serve him. Be completely faithful to him. Throw away the gods your people worshiped east of the Euphrates River and in Egypt. Serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="JOS 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 24:15"/>But suppose you don’t want to serve him. Then choose for yourselves right now whom you will serve. You can choose the gods your people served east of the Euphrates River. Or you can serve the gods of the Amorites. After all, you are living in their land. But as for me and my family, we will serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.”<verse eid="JOS 24:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 24:16"/>Then the people answered Joshua, “We would never desert the <char style="nd">Lord</char>! We would never serve other gods! <verse eid="JOS 24:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 24:17"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God himself brought us and our parents up out of Egypt. He brought us out of that land where we were slaves. With our own eyes, we saw those great signs he did. He kept us safe on our entire journey. He kept us safe as we traveled through all the nations. <verse eid="JOS 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 24:18"/>He drove them out to make room for us. That included the Amorites. They also lived in the land. We too will serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. That’s because he is our God.”<verse eid="JOS 24:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 24:19"/>Joshua said to the people, “You aren’t able to serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He is a holy God. He is a jealous God. He won’t forgive you when you disobey him. He won’t forgive you when you sin against him. <verse eid="JOS 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 24:20"/>Suppose you desert the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Suppose you serve the gods that people in other lands serve. If you do, he will turn against you. He will bring trouble on you. He will destroy you, even though he has been good to you.”<verse eid="JOS 24:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 24:21"/>But the people said to Joshua, “No! We will serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.”<verse eid="JOS 24:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 24:22"/>Then Joshua said, “You are witnesses against yourselves. You have said that you have chosen to serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 24:22">“Yes. We are witnesses,” they replied.<verse eid="JOS 24:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 24:23"/>“Now then,” said Joshua, “throw away the statues of the gods that are among you. People from other lands serve those gods. Give yourselves completely to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He is the God of Israel.”<verse eid="JOS 24:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 24:24"/>Then the people said to Joshua, “We will serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char> our God. We will obey him.”<verse eid="JOS 24:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 24:25"/>On that day Joshua made a covenant for the people. There at Shechem he reminded them of its rules and laws. <verse eid="JOS 24:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 24:26"/>He recorded these things in the Book of the Law of God. Then he got a large stone. He set it up in Shechem under the oak tree. It was near the place that had been set apart for the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="JOS 24:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 24:27"/>“Look!” he said to all the people. “This stone will be a witness against us. It has heard all the words the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has spoken to us. Suppose you aren’t faithful to your God. Then the stone will be a witness against you.”<verse eid="JOS 24:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 24:28"/>Joshua sent the people away. He sent all of them to their own shares of land.<verse eid="JOS 24:28"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Joshua Is Buried in the Promised Land</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 24:29"/>Then Joshua, the servant of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, died. He was the son of Nun. He was 110 years old when he died. <verse eid="JOS 24:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 24:30"/>His people buried him at Timnath Serah on his own property. It’s north of Mount Gaash in the hill country of Ephraim.<verse eid="JOS 24:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 24:31"/>Israel served the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as long as Joshua lived. They also served him as long as the elders lived. Those were the elders who lived longer than Joshua did. They had seen for themselves everything the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had done for Israel.<verse eid="JOS 24:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 24:32"/>The Israelites had brought Joseph’s bones up from Egypt. They buried his bones at Shechem in the piece of land Jacob had bought. He had bought it from the sons of Hamor. He had paid 100 pieces of silver for it. Hamor was the father of Shechem. That piece of land became the share that belonged to Joseph’s children after him.<verse eid="JOS 24:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 24:33"/>Aaron’s son Eleazar died. He was buried at Gibeah in the hill country of Ephraim. Gibeah had been given to Eleazar’s son Phinehas.<verse eid="JOS 24:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 24"/>
</usx>
