<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="LEV" style="id">- New International Readers Version 2014</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1995, 1996, 1998, 2014 by Biblica, Inc.</para>
  <para style="h">Leviticus</para>
  <para style="toc1">Leviticus</para>
  <para style="toc2">Leviticus</para>
  <para style="toc3">Lev</para>
  <para style="mt1">Leviticus</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">See the Invitation to Exodus, Leviticus and Numbers on p. <char style="xt"><ref loc="EXO 1">Exodus 1:0</ref></char>.</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="LEV 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Rules for Burnt Offerings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 1:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> called out to Moses. He spoke to him from the tent of meeting. He said, <verse eid="LEV 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 1:2"/>“Speak to the Israelites. Tell them, ‘Suppose anyone among you brings an offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They must bring an animal from their herd or flock.<verse eid="LEV 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 1:3"/>“ ‘If someone brings a burnt offering from the herd, they must offer a male animal. It must not have any flaws. They must bring it to the entrance to the tent of meeting. Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will accept it. <verse eid="LEV 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 1:4"/>They must place their hand on the head of the burnt offering. Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will accept it in place of them. It will pay for their sin. <verse eid="LEV 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 1:5"/>The young bull must be killed there in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Then the priests in Aaron’s family line must bring its blood to the altar. They must splash it against the sides of the altar. The altar stands at the entrance to the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 1:6"/>The skin must be removed from the animal brought for the burnt offering. Then the animal must be cut into pieces. <verse eid="LEV 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 1:7"/>The priests in Aaron’s family line must build a fire on the altar. They must place wood on the fire. <verse eid="LEV 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 1:8"/>Then they must place the pieces of the animal on the burning wood on the altar. The pieces include the head and the fat. <verse eid="LEV 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 1:9"/>The inside parts of the animal must be washed with water. The legs must also be washed. The priest must burn all of it on the altar. It is a burnt offering. It is a food offering. Its smell pleases the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 1:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 1:10"/>“ ‘If someone offers a burnt offering from the flock, it must be a male animal. It can be a sheep or a goat. It must not have any flaws. <verse eid="LEV 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 1:11"/>They must kill it at the north side of the altar in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. The priests in Aaron’s family line must splash its blood against the sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 1:12"/>They must cut the animal into pieces. The priest must place the pieces on the burning wood on the altar. The pieces include the head and the fat. <verse eid="LEV 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 1:13"/>They must wash the inside parts with water. The legs must also be washed. The priest must bring all the parts to the altar. He must burn them there. It is a burnt offering. It is a food offering. Its smell pleases the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 1:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 1:14"/>“ ‘If someone offers to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> a burnt offering of birds, it must be a dove or a young pigeon. <verse eid="LEV 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 1:15"/>The priest must bring it to the altar. He must twist its head off. Then he must burn the rest of the bird on the altar. Its blood must be emptied out on the side of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 1:16"/>The priest must remove the small bag inside the bird’s throat. He must also remove the feathers. Then he must throw them to the east side of the altar. That is where the ashes are. <verse eid="LEV 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 1:17"/>He must take hold of the wings of the bird and tear it open. But he must not tear it in two. Then the priest will burn it on the wood burning on the altar. It is a burnt offering. It is a food offering. Its smell pleases the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 1:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="LEV 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Rules for Grain Offerings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 2:1"/>“ ‘Suppose anyone brings a grain offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Then their offering must be made out of the finest flour. They must pour olive oil on it. They must also put incense on it. <verse eid="LEV 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 2:2"/>They must take it to the priests in Aaron’s family line. A priest must take a handful of the flour and oil. He must mix them with all the incense. Then he must burn that part on the altar. It will be a reminder that all good things come from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It is a food offering. Its smell pleases the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 2:3"/>The rest of the grain offering belongs to Aaron and to the priests in his family line. It is a very holy part of the food offerings presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 2:4"/>“ ‘If you bring a grain offering baked in an oven, make it out of the finest flour. It can be thick loaves of bread made without yeast. Mix them with olive oil. Or it can be thin loaves of bread that are made without yeast. Spread olive oil on them. <verse eid="LEV 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 2:5"/>If your grain offering is cooked on a metal plate, make your offering out of the finest flour. Mix it with oil. Make it without yeast. <verse eid="LEV 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 2:6"/>Break it into pieces. Pour oil on it. It is a grain offering. <verse eid="LEV 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 2:7"/>If your grain offering is cooked in a pan, make your offering out of the finest flour and some olive oil. <verse eid="LEV 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 2:8"/>Bring to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your grain offering made out of all these things. Give it to the priest. He must take it to the altar. <verse eid="LEV 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 2:9"/>All good things come from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. The priest must take out the part of the grain offering that reminds you of this. He must burn it on the altar. It is a food offering. Its smell pleases the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 2:10"/>The rest of the grain offering belongs to Aaron and the priests in his family line. It is a very holy part of the food offerings presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 2:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 2:11"/>“ ‘Every grain offering you bring to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> must be made without yeast. You must not add any yeast or honey to a food offering presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 2:12"/>You can bring them to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as an offering of the first share of food you gather or produce. But they must not be offered on the altar as a pleasant smell. <verse eid="LEV 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 2:13"/>Put salt on all your grain offerings. Salt stands for the lasting covenant between you and your God. So do not leave it out of your grain offerings. Add salt to all your offerings.<verse eid="LEV 2:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 2:14"/>“ ‘Suppose you bring to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> a grain offering of the first share of your food. Then offer crushed heads of your first grain that have been cooked in fire. <verse eid="LEV 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 2:15"/>Put olive oil and incense on the grain. It is a grain offering. <verse eid="LEV 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 2:16"/>The priest must burn part of the crushed grain and the oil. It will remind you that all good things come from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. The priest must burn it together with all the incense. It is a food offering presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 2:16"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="LEV 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Rules for Friendship Offerings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 3:1"/>“ ‘Suppose someone brings a friendship offering. If they offer an animal from the herd, it can be either male or female. It must not have any flaws. They must offer it in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 3:2"/>They must place their hand on the animal’s head. It must be killed at the entrance to the tent of meeting. Then the priests in Aaron’s family line must splash the blood against the sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 3:3"/>Part of the friendship offering must be given to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as a food offering. It must include all the fat that is connected to them. <verse eid="LEV 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 3:4"/>It must include both kidneys with the fat on them next to the lower back muscles. It must also include the long part of the liver. All of it must be removed together with the kidneys. <verse eid="LEV 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 3:5"/>Then the priests in Aaron’s family line must burn it on the altar. They must burn it on top of the burnt offering that is lying on the burning wood. It is a food offering. Its smell pleases the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 3:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 3:6"/>“ ‘Suppose someone brings an animal from the flock as a friendship offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It can be either male or female. It must not have any flaws. <verse eid="LEV 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 3:7"/>If they bring a lamb, they must offer it in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 3:8"/>They must place their hand on the lamb’s head. It must be killed there in front of the tent of meeting. Then the priests in Aaron’s family line must splash its blood against the sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 3:9"/>Part of the offering must be brought as a sacrifice presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It must include the lamb’s fat and the entire fat tail cut off close to the backbone. It must include all the fat that is connected to them. <verse eid="LEV 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 3:10"/>It must include both kidneys with the fat on them next to the lower back muscles. The offering must also include the long part of the liver. That must be removed together with the kidneys. <verse eid="LEV 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 3:11"/>Then the priest must burn the offering on the altar as food. It is a food offering presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 3:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 3:12"/>“ ‘If someone brings a goat, they must offer it in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 3:13"/>They must place their hand on its head. It must be killed there in front of the tent of meeting. Then the priests in Aaron’s family line must splash its blood against the sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 3:14"/>Part of the offering must be brought as a food offering presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It must include all the fat that is connected to them. <verse eid="LEV 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 3:15"/>It must include both kidneys with the fat on them next to the lower back muscles. It must also include the long part of the liver. That must be removed together with the kidneys. <verse eid="LEV 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 3:16"/>Then the priest must burn the offering on the altar as food. It is a food offering. It has a pleasant smell. All the fat belongs to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 3:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 3:17"/>“ ‘You must not eat any fat or any blood. That is a law that will last for all time to come. It applies no matter where you live.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 3:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="LEV 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Rules for Sin Offerings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 4:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 4:2"/>“Speak to the Israelites. Tell them, ‘Suppose someone sins without meaning to. And that person does something the <char style="nd">Lord</char> commands us not to do.<verse eid="LEV 4:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 4:3"/>“ ‘Suppose it is the anointed priest who sins. And suppose he brings guilt on the people. Then he must bring a young bull to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It must not have any flaws. He must bring it as a sin offering for the sin he has committed. <verse eid="LEV 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 4:4"/>He must bring the bull to the entrance to the tent of meeting in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He must place his hand on its head. He must kill it there in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 4:5"/>Then the anointed priest must take some of the bull’s blood. He must carry it into the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 4:6"/>He must dip his finger into the blood. He must sprinkle some of it seven times in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He must do it in front of the curtain of the Most Holy Room. <verse eid="LEV 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 4:7"/>Then the priest must put some of the blood on the horns of the altar for burning incense. The horns stick out from the upper four corners of the altar. The incense burned on that altar has a sweet smell. The altar stands in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> in the tent of meeting. The priest must pour out the rest of the bull’s blood at the bottom of the altar for burnt offerings. That altar stands at the entrance to the tent. <verse eid="LEV 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 4:8"/>He must remove all the fat from the bull for the sin offering. It includes the fat that is connected to the inside parts. <verse eid="LEV 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 4:9"/>It includes both kidneys with the fat on them next to the lower back muscles. It also includes the long part of the liver. He must remove all of it together with the kidneys. <verse eid="LEV 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 4:10"/>He must remove it in the same way the fat is removed from an ox sacrificed as a friendship offering. Then the priest must burn all of it on the altar for burnt offerings. <verse eid="LEV 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 4:11"/>But the bull’s hide must be taken away. So must all its meat. So must its head and legs. And so must its inside parts and guts. <verse eid="LEV 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 4:12"/>In other words, all the rest of the bull must be taken away. The priest must take it outside the camp. He must take it to a “clean” place. He must take it to the place where the ashes are thrown. Then he must burn it there in a wood fire on a pile of ashes.<verse eid="LEV 4:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 4:13"/>“ ‘Or suppose the whole community of Israel sins without meaning to. They do something the <char style="nd">Lord</char> commands us not to do. Suppose they realize their guilt. <verse eid="LEV 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 4:14"/>And suppose their sin becomes known. Then they must bring a young bull as a sin offering. They must offer it in front of the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 4:15"/>The elders of the community must place their hands on the bull’s head in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. The bull must be killed in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 4:16"/>Then the anointed priest must take some of the bull’s blood into the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 4:17"/>He must dip his finger into the blood. He must sprinkle it seven times in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He must do it in front of the curtain. <verse eid="LEV 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 4:18"/>He must put some of the blood on the horns that stick out from the upper four corners of the altar. The altar stands in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> in the tent of meeting. The priest must pour out the rest of the blood at the bottom of the altar for burnt offerings. That altar stands at the entrance to the tent. <verse eid="LEV 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 4:19"/>He must remove all the fat from the bull. He must burn it on the altar. <verse eid="LEV 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 4:20"/>He must do the same thing with that bull as he did with the bull for the sin offering. When he does, he will pay for the sin of the community. And they will be forgiven. <verse eid="LEV 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 4:21"/>Then he must take the bull outside the camp. He must burn it just as he burned the first bull. It is the sin offering for the whole community.<verse eid="LEV 4:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 4:22"/>“ ‘Or suppose a leader sins without meaning to. He disobeys any of the commands of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> his God. <verse eid="LEV 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 4:23"/>And suppose he realizes his guilt and his sin becomes known. Then he must bring an offering. It must be a male goat. It must not have any flaws. <verse eid="LEV 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 4:24"/>He must place his hand on the goat’s head. He must kill it. He must do it at the place where the animals for burnt offerings are killed in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. His offering is a sin offering. <verse eid="LEV 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 4:25"/>Then the priest must dip his finger into some of the blood of the sin offering. He must put it on the horns that stick out from the upper four corners of the altar for burnt offerings. He must pour out the rest of the blood at the bottom of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 4:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 4:26"/>He must burn all the fat on the altar. He must burn it in the same way he burned the fat of the friendship offering. When he does, he will pay for the sin of the leader. And the leader will be forgiven.<verse eid="LEV 4:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 4:27"/>“ ‘Or suppose someone in the community sins without meaning to. They disobey any of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s commands. <verse eid="LEV 4:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 4:28"/>And suppose they realize their guilt and their sin becomes known. Then they must bring an offering for the sin they have committed. It must be a female goat. It must not have any flaws. <verse eid="LEV 4:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 4:29"/>They must place their hand on the head of the animal for the sin offering. It must be killed at the place where the animals for burnt offerings are killed. <verse eid="LEV 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 4:30"/>Then the priest must dip his finger into some of the blood. He must put it on the horns that stick out from the upper four corners of the altar for burnt offerings. He must pour out the rest of the blood at the bottom of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 4:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 4:31"/>They must remove all the fat in the same way the fat is removed from the friendship offering. The priest must burn it on the altar. Its smell pleases the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. When the priest burns the offering, he will pay for their sin. And they will be forgiven.<verse eid="LEV 4:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 4:32"/>“ ‘Suppose someone brings a lamb as their sin offering. Then they must bring a female animal. It must not have any flaws. <verse eid="LEV 4:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 4:33"/>They must place their hand on its head. They must kill it as a sin offering. They must do it at the place where the animals for burnt offerings are killed. <verse eid="LEV 4:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 4:34"/>Then the priest must dip his finger into some of the blood of the sin offering. He must put it on the horns that stick out from the upper four corners of the altar for burnt offerings. He must pour out the rest of the blood at the bottom of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 4:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 4:35"/>They must remove all the fat in the same way the fat is removed from the lamb for the friendship offering. The priest must burn it on the altar on top of the food offerings presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. When he does, he will pay for the sin they have committed. And they will be forgiven.<verse eid="LEV 4:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="LEV 5"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 5:1"/>“ ‘Suppose someone has been called as a witness to something they have seen or learned about. Then if they do not tell what they know, they have sinned. And they will be held responsible for it.<verse eid="LEV 5:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 5:2"/>“ ‘Or suppose someone touches something not “clean.” It could be the dead bodies of wild animals or of livestock. Or it could be the dead bodies of creatures that move along the ground. Even though those people are not aware that they touched them, they have become “unclean.” And they are guilty. <verse eid="LEV 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 5:3"/>Or suppose they touch something “unclean” that comes from a human being. It could be anything that would make them “unclean.” Suppose they are not aware that they touched it. When they find out about it, they will be guilty. <verse eid="LEV 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 5:4"/>Or suppose someone makes a promise to do something without thinking it through. It does not matter what they promised. It does not matter whether they made the promise without thinking about it carefully. And suppose they are not aware that they did not think it through. When they find out about it, they will be guilty. <verse eid="LEV 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 5:5"/>When someone is guilty in any of those ways, they must admit they have sinned. <verse eid="LEV 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 5:6"/>They must bring a sin offering to pay for the sin they have committed. They must bring to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> a female lamb or goat from the flock. The priest will sacrifice the animal. That will pay for the person’s sin.<verse eid="LEV 5:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 5:7"/>“ ‘Suppose they can’t afford a lamb. Then they must get two doves or two young pigeons. They must bring them to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> to pay for their sin. One of them is for a sin offering. The other is for a burnt offering. <verse eid="LEV 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 5:8"/>They must bring them to the priest. The priest will offer the one for the sin offering first. He must twist its head. But he must not twist it off completely. <verse eid="LEV 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 5:9"/>Then he must splash some of the blood of the sin offering against the side of the altar. He must empty out the rest of the blood at the bottom of the altar. It is a sin offering. <verse eid="LEV 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 5:10"/>Then the priest will offer the other bird as a burnt offering. He must do it in the way the law requires. That will pay for the sin they have committed. And they will be forgiven.<verse eid="LEV 5:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 5:11"/>“ ‘But suppose they can’t afford two doves or two young pigeons. Then they must bring three and a half pounds of the finest flour as an offering for their sin. It is a sin offering. They must not put olive oil or incense on it. That is because it is a sin offering. <verse eid="LEV 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 5:12"/>They must bring it to the priest. The priest must take a handful of it. He must burn that part on the altar. It will be a reminder that all good things come from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. The priest must burn it on top of the food offerings presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It is a sin offering. <verse eid="LEV 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 5:13"/>In that way the priest will pay for any of the sins they have committed. And they will be forgiven. The rest of the offering will belong to the priest. It is the same as in the case of the grain offering.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 5:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Rules for Guilt Offerings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 5:14"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 5:15"/>“Suppose someone is unfaithful to me and sins. And they do it without meaning to. Here is how they sin against me or my priests. They refuse to give the priests one of the holy things set apart for them. Then they must bring me a ram from the flock. It must not have any flaws. It must be worth the required amount of silver. The silver must be weighed out in keeping with the standard weights that are used in the sacred tent. The ram is a guilt offering. It will pay for their sin. <verse eid="LEV 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 5:16"/>They must also pay for the holy thing they refused to give. They must add a fifth of its value to it. They must give all of it to the priest. The priest will pay for their sin with the ram. It is a guilt offering. And they will be forgiven.<verse eid="LEV 5:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 5:17"/>“Suppose someone sins by doing something I command them not to do. Even though they do not know it, they are guilty. They will be held responsible for it. <verse eid="LEV 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 5:18"/>They must bring to the priest a ram from the flock as a guilt offering. It must not have any flaws. And it must be worth the required amount of money. The priest will sacrifice the animal. That will pay for what they have done wrong without meaning to. And they will be forgiven. <verse eid="LEV 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 5:19"/>It is a guilt offering. They have been guilty of doing wrong against me.”<verse eid="LEV 5:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="LEV 6"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 6:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 6:2"/>“Suppose someone sins by not being faithful to me. They do it by tricking their neighbors. They trick them in connection with something their neighbors have placed in their care. They steal from their neighbors. Or they cheat them. <verse eid="LEV 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 6:3"/>Or they find something their neighbors have lost and then tell a lie about it. Or they go to court. They promise to tell the truth. But instead they tell a lie when they are a witness about it. Or they lie when they are witnesses about any other sin like those sins. <verse eid="LEV 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 6:4"/>When they sin in any of these ways and realize their guilt, they must return what they stole. They must give back what they took by cheating their neighbors. They must return what their neighbors placed in their care. They must return the lost property they found. <verse eid="LEV 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 6:5"/>They must return anything they told a lie about when they were witnesses in court. They must pay back everything in full. They must add a fifth of its value to it. They must give all of it to the owner on the day they bring their guilt offering. <verse eid="LEV 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 6:6"/>He must bring their guilt offering to the priest to pay for their sin. It is an offering to me. They must bring a ram from the flock. It must not have any flaws. It must be worth the required amount of money. <verse eid="LEV 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 6:7"/>The priest will sacrifice the ram to pay for their sin. He will do it in my sight. And they will be forgiven for any of the things they did that made them guilty.”<verse eid="LEV 6:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">More Rules for Burnt Offerings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 6:8"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 6:9"/>“Give Aaron and the priests in his family line a command. Tell them, ‘Here are some more rules for burnt offerings. The burnt offering must remain on the altar through the whole night. The fire on the altar must be kept burning until morning. <verse eid="LEV 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 6:10"/>The priest must put on his linen clothes. He must put on linen underwear next to his body. He must remove the ashes of the burnt offering that the fire has burned up on the altar. He must place them beside the altar. <verse eid="LEV 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 6:11"/>Then he must take his clothes off and put others on. He must carry the ashes outside the camp to a “clean” place. <verse eid="LEV 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 6:12"/>The fire on the altar must be kept burning. It must not go out. Every morning the priest must add more wood to the fire. He must place the burnt offering on the fire. He must burn the fat of the friendship offerings on it. <verse eid="LEV 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 6:13"/>The fire must be kept burning on the altar all the time. It must not go out.<verse eid="LEV 6:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">More Rules for Grain Offerings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 6:14"/>“ ‘Here are some more rules for grain offerings. The priests in Aaron’s family line must bring the grain offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> in front of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 6:15"/>The priest must take a handful of the finest flour and olive oil. He must add to it all the incense on the grain offering. He must burn that part on the altar. It will remind him that all good things come from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Its smell pleases the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 6:16"/>Aaron and the priests in his family line will eat the rest of it. But they must eat it without yeast in the holy area. They must eat it in the courtyard of the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 6:17"/>It must not be baked with yeast added to it. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has given it to the priests as their share of the food offerings presented to him. It is very holy, just like the sin offering and the guilt offering. <verse eid="LEV 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 6:18"/>Any priests in Aaron’s family line can eat it. It is their share of the food offerings presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It is their share for all time to come. Anyone who touches these offerings will become holy.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 6:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 6:19"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 6:20"/>“On the day each high priest in Aaron’s family line is anointed, he must bring an offering to me. He must bring three and a half pounds of the finest flour as a regular grain offering. He must bring half of it in the morning. He must bring the other half in the evening. <verse eid="LEV 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 6:21"/>Mix it with olive oil. Cook it on a metal plate. Break it in pieces. Bring it as a grain offering. Its smell pleases the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 6:22"/>The son of Aaron who will become the next high priest after him will prepare the grain offering. It is the share that must be given to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for all time to come. It must be completely burned up. <verse eid="LEV 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 6:23"/>Every grain offering a high priest offers must be completely burned up. It must not be eaten.”<verse eid="LEV 6:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">More Rules for Sin Offerings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 6:24"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 6:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 6:25"/>“Speak to Aaron and the priests in his family line. Tell them, ‘Here are some more rules for sin offerings. You must kill the animal for the sin offering in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Kill it in the place where the burnt offering is killed. It is very holy. <verse eid="LEV 6:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 6:26"/>The priest who offers it will eat it. He must eat it in the holy area. He must eat it in the courtyard of the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 6:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 6:27"/>Anyone who touches any of its meat will become holy. Suppose some of the blood is spilled on someone’s clothes. Then you must wash them in the holy area. <verse eid="LEV 6:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 6:28"/>Break the clay pot the meat is cooked in. But suppose you cook it in a bronze pot. Then you must scrub the pot and rinse it with water. <verse eid="LEV 6:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 6:29"/>Any male in a priest’s family may eat the meat. It is very holy. <verse eid="LEV 6:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 6:30"/>But suppose some of the blood of a sin offering is brought into the tent of meeting. And that blood is brought into the Holy Room to pay for sin. Then that sin offering must not be eaten. It must be burned up.<verse eid="LEV 6:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="LEV 7"/>
  <para style="s1">More Rules for Guilt Offerings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 7:1"/>“ ‘Here are some more rules for guilt offerings. The guilt offering is very holy. <verse eid="LEV 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 7:2"/>You must kill the animal for the guilt offering where you kill the animal for the burnt offering. Splash its blood against the sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 7:3"/>Offer all its fat. It must include the fat tail and the fat that covers the inside parts. <verse eid="LEV 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 7:4"/>It must include both kidneys with the fat on them next to the lower back muscles. It must also include the long part of the liver. Remove all of it together with the kidneys. <verse eid="LEV 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 7:5"/>The priest must burn all of it on the altar. It is a food offering presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It is a guilt offering. <verse eid="LEV 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 7:6"/>Any male in a priest’s family can eat it. But he must eat it in the holy area. It is very holy.<verse eid="LEV 7:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 7:7"/>“ ‘The same law applies to the sin offering and the guilt offering. Both of them belong to the priest who offers them to pay for sin. <verse eid="LEV 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 7:8"/>The priest who offers a burnt offering for anyone can keep its hide for himself. <verse eid="LEV 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 7:9"/>Every grain offering baked in an oven belongs to the priest who offers it. So does every grain offering cooked in a pan or on a metal plate. <verse eid="LEV 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 7:10"/>Every grain offering belongs equally to all the priests in Aaron’s family line. That is true whether it is mixed with olive oil or it is dry.<verse eid="LEV 7:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">More Rules for Friendship Offerings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 7:11"/>“ ‘Here are some more rules for friendship offerings anyone may bring to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 7:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 7:12"/>“ ‘Suppose they offer a friendship offering to show they are thankful. Then together with the thank offering they must offer thick loaves of bread. They must make them without yeast. They must mix them with olive oil. Or they must offer thin loaves of bread made without yeast. They must spread olive oil on them. Or they must offer thick loaves of bread made out of the finest flour. They must add olive oil to it. They must work the flour and prepare it well. <verse eid="LEV 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 7:13"/>They must bring another friendship offering along with their thank offering. It should be thick loaves of bread made with yeast. <verse eid="LEV 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 7:14"/>They must bring one of each kind of bread as an offering. One kind is made with yeast. The other is not. Both of them are a gift to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They belong to the priest who splashes the blood of the friendship offering against the altar. <verse eid="LEV 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 7:15"/>The person must eat the meat from their thank offering on the day they offer it. They must not leave any of it until morning.<verse eid="LEV 7:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 7:16"/>“ ‘But suppose they bring a friendship offering to keep a promise they have made. Or suppose they bring an offering they choose to give. Then they must eat the sacrifice on the day they offer it. But if anything is left over, they may eat it the next day. <verse eid="LEV 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 7:17"/>They must burn up any meat from the sacrifice left over until the third day. <verse eid="LEV 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 7:18"/>Suppose they eat any meat from the friendship offering on the third day. Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will not accept the offering. He will not accept it as a gift from them. It is not pure. If they eat any of it, they will be held responsible for it.<verse eid="LEV 7:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 7:19"/>“ ‘They must not eat meat that touches anything “unclean.” They must burn it up. Anyone “clean” may eat any other meat. <verse eid="LEV 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 7:20"/>But suppose an “unclean” person eats any meat from the friendship offering that belongs to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Then they will be separated from their people. <verse eid="LEV 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 7:21"/>Suppose someone touches something “unclean.” It does not matter whether it comes from a human being who is not “clean.” It does not matter whether it comes from an “unclean” animal. It does not matter whether it comes from something hated and “unclean.” And suppose they eat any of the meat from the friendship offering that belongs to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Then they will be separated from their people.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 7:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Israel Must Not Eat Fat or Blood</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 7:22"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 7:23"/>“Speak to the Israelites. Tell them, ‘Do not eat any of the fat of cattle, sheep or goats. <verse eid="LEV 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 7:24"/>Do not eat the fat of any animal found dead. Do not eat the fat of an animal that wild animals have torn apart. But you can use the fat for any other purpose. <verse eid="LEV 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 7:25"/>Suppose an animal has been sacrificed as a food offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. No one may eat its fat. If they do, they will be separated from their people. <verse eid="LEV 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 7:26"/>No matter where you live, do not eat the blood of any bird or animal. <verse eid="LEV 7:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 7:27"/>Anyone who eats blood must be separated from their people.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 7:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Share That Belongs to the Priests</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 7:28"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 7:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 7:29"/>“Speak to the Israelites. Tell them, ‘Suppose someone brings a friendship offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Then they must bring part of it as their special gift to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 7:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 7:30"/>They must bring it with their own hands. It is a food offering presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They must bring the fat together with the breast. They must lift the breast up and wave it in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as a wave offering. <verse eid="LEV 7:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 7:31"/>The priest will burn the fat on the altar. But the breast belongs to Aaron and the priests in his family line. <verse eid="LEV 7:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 7:32"/>Give the right thigh from your friendship offerings to the priest as a gift. <verse eid="LEV 7:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 7:33"/>The priest who offers the blood and fat from the friendship offering must be given the right thigh. It is his share. <verse eid="LEV 7:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 7:34"/>I, the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, have taken the breast that is waved and the thigh that is given. I have taken them from the friendship offerings of the Israelites. And I have given them to Aaron the priest and the priests in his family line. The offerings will be their share from the Israelites for all time to come.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 7:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 7:35"/>That is the part of the food offerings presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It is given to Aaron and the priests in his family line. It was given to Aaron and his sons on the day they were set apart to serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as priests. <verse eid="LEV 7:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 7:36"/>On the day they were anointed, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded the Israelites to give that part to them. For all time to come, it will be the share of Aaron and the priests in his family line.<verse eid="LEV 7:36"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 7:37"/>These are the rules for burnt offerings, grain offerings, sin offerings, guilt offerings and friendship offerings. They are also the rules for the offerings that are given when priests are being prepared to serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 7:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 7:38"/>They are the rules the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave Moses on Mount Sinai. He gave them on the day he commanded the Israelites to bring their offerings to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. That took place in the Sinai Desert.<verse eid="LEV 7:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="LEV 8"/>
  <para style="s1">Preparing the Priests to Serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 8:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 8:2"/>“Bring Aaron and his sons to the entrance to the tent of meeting. Bring their clothes and the anointing oil. Bring the bull for the sin offering. Also bring two rams. And bring the basket with the bread made without yeast. <verse eid="LEV 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 8:3"/>Then gather the whole community at the entrance to the tent of meeting.” <verse eid="LEV 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 8:4"/>Moses did just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded him. All the people gathered together at the entrance to the tent of meeting.<verse eid="LEV 8:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 8:5"/>Moses said to the people, “Here is what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has commanded us to do.” <verse eid="LEV 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 8:6"/>Then Moses brought Aaron and his sons to the people. He washed Aaron and his sons with water. <verse eid="LEV 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 8:7"/>He put the inner robe on Aaron. He tied the belt around him. He dressed him in the outer robe. He put the linen apron on him. He took the skillfully made waistband and tied the apron on him with it. He wanted to make sure it was securely tied to him. <verse eid="LEV 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 8:8"/>Moses placed the chest cloth on Aaron. He put the Urim and Thummim in the chest cloth. <verse eid="LEV 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 8:9"/>Then he placed the turban on Aaron’s head. On the front of the turban he put the gold plate. It was a sacred crown. Moses did everything just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded him.<verse eid="LEV 8:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 8:10"/>Then Moses took the anointing oil and poured it on the holy tent. He also poured it on everything in it. That’s how he set apart those things for the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 8:11"/>He sprinkled some of the oil on the altar seven times. He poured oil on the altar and all its tools. He poured it on the large bowl and its stand. He did it to set them apart. <verse eid="LEV 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 8:12"/>He poured some of the anointing oil on Aaron’s head. He anointed him to set him apart to serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 8:13"/>Then Moses brought Aaron’s sons to the people. He put the inner robes on them. He tied belts around them. He put caps on their heads. He did everything just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded him.<verse eid="LEV 8:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 8:14"/>Then he brought the bull for the sin offering. Aaron and his sons placed their hands on its head. <verse eid="LEV 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 8:15"/>Moses killed the bull. He dipped his finger into some of the blood. He put it on the horns that stick out from the upper four corners of the altar. He did it to make the altar pure. He poured out the rest of the blood at the bottom of the altar. So he set it apart to make it pure. <verse eid="LEV 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 8:16"/>Moses also removed all the fat around the inside parts of the bull. He removed the long part of the liver. He took both kidneys and their fat. Then he burned all of it on the altar. <verse eid="LEV 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 8:17"/>But he burned the rest of the bull outside the camp. He burned up its hide, its meat and its guts. He did it just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded him.<verse eid="LEV 8:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 8:18"/>Then Moses brought the ram for the burnt offering. Aaron and his sons placed their hands on its head. <verse eid="LEV 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 8:19"/>Moses killed the ram. He splashed the blood against the sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 8:20"/>He cut the ram into pieces. He burned the head, the other pieces and the fat. <verse eid="LEV 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 8:21"/>He washed the inside parts and the legs with water. He burned the whole ram on the altar as a burnt offering. It had a pleasant smell. It was a food offering presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Moses did everything just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded him.<verse eid="LEV 8:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 8:22"/>Then he brought the other ram. It was sacrificed to prepare the priests for serving the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Aaron and his sons placed their hands on its head. <verse eid="LEV 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 8:23"/>Moses killed the ram. He put some of its blood on Aaron’s right earlobe. He put some on the thumb of Aaron’s right hand. He also put some on the big toe of Aaron’s right foot. <verse eid="LEV 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 8:24"/>Then Moses brought Aaron’s sons to the people. He put some of the blood on their right earlobes. He put some on the thumbs of their right hands. He also put some on the big toes of their right feet. Then he splashed the rest of the blood against the sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 8:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 8:25"/>He removed the fat, the fat tail and all the fat around the inside parts. He removed the long part of the liver. He removed both kidneys and their fat. And he removed the right thigh. <verse eid="LEV 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 8:26"/>Then he took a thick loaf of bread from the basket of bread made without yeast. The basket was in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Moses took a thick loaf of bread made with olive oil. He also took a thin loaf of bread. He put all of it on the fat parts of the ram and on its right thigh. <verse eid="LEV 8:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 8:27"/>He put everything in the hands of Aaron and his sons. He told them to lift it up and wave it in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as a wave offering. <verse eid="LEV 8:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 8:28"/>Then Moses took it from their hands. He burned it on the altar on top of the burnt offering. It was the offering that was sacrificed to prepare the priests for serving the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It had a pleasant smell. It was a food offering presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 8:29"/>Moses also lifted up the ram’s breast and waved it in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as a wave offering. The breast was Moses’ share of the ram that was sacrificed to prepare the priests for serving the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Moses did everything just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded him.<verse eid="LEV 8:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 8:30"/>Then Moses took some of the anointing oil. He also took some of the blood from the altar. He sprinkled some of the oil and blood on Aaron and his clothes. He also sprinkled some on Aaron’s sons and their clothes. That’s how he set apart Aaron and his clothes. And that’s how he set apart Aaron’s sons and their clothes.<verse eid="LEV 8:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 8:31"/>Then Moses spoke to Aaron and his sons. He said, “Cook the meat at the entrance to the tent of meeting. Eat it there along with the bread from the basket of the offerings that are brought to prepare the priests for serving the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Do it just as I was commanded. I was told, ‘Aaron and his sons must eat it.’ <verse eid="LEV 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 8:32"/>Then burn up the rest of the meat and the bread. <verse eid="LEV 8:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 8:33"/>Don’t leave the entrance to the tent of meeting for seven days. Don’t leave until the days that are required to prepare you for serving the <char style="nd">Lord</char> have been completed. Stay here for the full seven days. <verse eid="LEV 8:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 8:34"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded what has been done here today. It was done to pay for your sin. <verse eid="LEV 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 8:35"/>Stay at the entrance to the tent of meeting for seven days. Stay here day and night. Do what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> requires. Then you won’t die. That’s the command the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave me.”<verse eid="LEV 8:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 8:36"/>So Aaron and his sons did everything just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded through Moses.<verse eid="LEV 8:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="LEV 9"/>
  <para style="s1">The Priests Offer Sacrifices</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 9:1"/>On the eighth day Moses sent for Aaron, his sons and the elders of Israel. <verse eid="LEV 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 9:2"/>He said to Aaron, “Bring a bull calf for your sin offering. Bring a ram for your burnt offering. They must not have any flaws. Offer them to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 9:3"/>Then speak to the Israelites. Tell them, ‘Bring a male goat for a sin offering. Bring a calf and a lamb for a burnt offering. Both of them must be a year old. They must not have any flaws. <verse eid="LEV 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 9:4"/>Bring an ox and a ram for a friendship offering. Sacrifice all of them to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Also bring a grain offering. Mix it with olive oil. Today the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will appear to you.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 9:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 9:5"/>The people got the things Moses commanded them to get. They took them to the front of the tent of meeting. The whole community came up close to the tent. They stood there in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 9:6"/>Then Moses said, “You have done what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has commanded. So the glory of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will appear to you.”<verse eid="LEV 9:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 9:7"/>Moses said to Aaron, “Come to the altar. Sacrifice your sin offering and your burnt offering. Pay for your sin and the sin of the people. Sacrifice the people’s offering. Pay for their sin. Do just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has commanded.”<verse eid="LEV 9:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 9:8"/>So Aaron came to the altar. He killed the calf as a sin offering for himself. <verse eid="LEV 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 9:9"/>His sons brought its blood to him. He dipped his finger into the blood. He put some on the horns that stick out from the upper four corners of the altar. He poured out the rest of the blood at the bottom of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 9:10"/>He burned the fat and the kidneys on the altar. He also burned the long part of the liver. All these parts were from the sin offering. Aaron did just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded Moses. <verse eid="LEV 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 9:11"/>He burned up the meat and the hide outside the camp.<verse eid="LEV 9:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 9:12"/>Then he killed the animal for the burnt offering. His sons handed him its blood. He splashed it against the sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 9:13"/>They handed him the burnt offering piece by piece. It included the animal’s head. Aaron burned everything on the altar. <verse eid="LEV 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 9:14"/>He washed the inside parts and the legs. He burned them on top of the burnt offering on the altar.<verse eid="LEV 9:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 9:15"/>Then Aaron brought the people’s offering. He took the goat for their sin offering and killed it. He offered it for a sin offering. He did just as he had done with his own sin offering.<verse eid="LEV 9:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 9:16"/>He brought the animal for the burnt offering. He offered it in the way the law requires. <verse eid="LEV 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 9:17"/>He also brought the grain offering. He took a handful of it and burned it on the altar. It was in addition to that morning’s burnt offering.<verse eid="LEV 9:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 9:18"/>Aaron killed the ox and the ram as the friendship offering for the people. His sons handed him the blood. He splashed it against the sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 9:19"/>His sons also brought the fat parts of the ox and the ram. They included the fat tail and the layer of fat. They also included the kidneys and the long part of the liver. <verse eid="LEV 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 9:20"/>Aaron’s sons placed everything on the breasts of the animals. Aaron burned the fat on the altar. <verse eid="LEV 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 9:21"/>He lifted up the breasts and the right thigh and waved them in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as a wave offering. He did it just as Moses had commanded.<verse eid="LEV 9:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 9:22"/>Then Aaron lifted up his hands toward the people. He gave them a blessing. He had already sacrificed the sin offering, the burnt offering and the friendship offering. So he stepped down from the altar.<verse eid="LEV 9:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 9:23"/>Moses and Aaron went into the tent of meeting. When they came out, they gave the people a blessing. The glory of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> appeared to all the people. <verse eid="LEV 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 9:24"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> sent fire on the altar. The fire burned up the burnt offering along with the fat parts. All the people saw it. Then they shouted for joy. They fell with their faces to the ground.<verse eid="LEV 9:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="LEV 10"/>
  <para style="s1">The <char style="nd">Lord</char> Kills Nadab and Abihu</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 10:1"/>Nadab and Abihu were two of Aaron’s sons. They got their shallow cups for burning incense. They put fire in them. They added incense to it. They made an offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> by using fire that wasn’t allowed. They did it against his command. <verse eid="LEV 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 10:2"/>So the <char style="nd">Lord</char> sent fire on them. It burned them up. They died in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 10:3"/>Then Moses spoke to Aaron. He said, “That’s what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> was talking about when he said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LEV 10:3">“ ‘Among those who approach me</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LEV 10:3">I will show that I am holy.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LEV 10:3">In the sight of all the people</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LEV 10:3">I will be honored.’ ”</para>
  <para style="m" vid="LEV 10:3">So Aaron remained silent.<verse eid="LEV 10:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 10:4"/>Moses sent for Mishael and Elzaphan. They were sons of Aaron’s uncle Uzziel. Moses said to them, “Come here. Carry the bodies of your cousins outside the camp. Take them away from in front of the Holy Room.” <verse eid="LEV 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 10:5"/>So they came and carried them outside the camp. It was just as Moses had ordered. The bodies of Nadab and Abihu still had their inner robes on them.<verse eid="LEV 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 10:6"/>Moses spoke to Aaron and to Eleazar and Ithamar. They were Aaron’s sons. Moses said, “Don’t let your hair hang loose. Don’t tear your clothes. If you do, you will die. And the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will be angry with the whole community. But all the Israelites are allowed to show they are sad. They are your relatives. They may mourn for those the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has destroyed with fire. <verse eid="LEV 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 10:7"/>Don’t leave the entrance to the tent of meeting. If you do, you will die. That’s because the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s anointing oil has made you holy.” So they did what Moses told them to do.<verse eid="LEV 10:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 10:8"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Aaron. He said, <verse eid="LEV 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 10:9"/>“You and your sons will go into the tent of meeting. When you do, you must not drink any kind of wine. If you do, you will die. This is a law that will last for all time to come. <verse eid="LEV 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 10:10"/>This is so that you can tell the difference between what is holy and what is not. You must be able to tell the difference between what is ‘clean’ and what is not. <verse eid="LEV 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 10:11"/>Then you will be able to teach the Israelites all the rules I have given them through Moses.”<verse eid="LEV 10:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 10:12"/>Moses spoke to Aaron and to Eleazar and Ithamar. They were Aaron’s two remaining sons. Moses said, “Take the grain offering left over from the food offerings presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It is very holy. Make bread without yeast from it. Eat it beside the altar. <verse eid="LEV 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 10:13"/>Eat it in the holy area. It’s your share and your sons’ share of the food offerings presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. These rules are in keeping with the command the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave me. <verse eid="LEV 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 10:14"/>But you and your sons and your daughters can eat the breast that was waved. You can also eat the thigh that was offered. Eat them in a ‘clean’ place. They have been given to you and your children. They are your share of the friendship offerings the Israelites bring. <verse eid="LEV 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 10:15"/>The thigh that was offered must be brought together with the fat parts of the food offerings. The breast that was waved must be brought in the same way. All of it must be lifted up and waved in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as a wave offering. It will be the share for you and your children for all time to come. That’s what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has commanded.”<verse eid="LEV 10:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 10:16"/>Moses asked about the goat that was brought as the sin offering. He found out that it had been burned up. So he became angry with Eleazar and Ithamar. They were Aaron’s two remaining sons. Moses asked them, <verse eid="LEV 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 10:17"/>“Why didn’t you eat the sin offering in a place near the Holy Room? The offering is very holy. It was given to you to take the people’s guilt away. It paid for their sin in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 10:18"/>The blood of the offering wasn’t taken into the Holy Room. So you should have eaten the goat in a place near the Holy Room. That’s what I commanded.”<verse eid="LEV 10:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 10:19"/>Aaron replied to Moses, “Today the people sacrificed their sin offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They also sacrificed their burnt offerings to him. But a terrible thing has happened to me. Two of my sons have died. Would the <char style="nd">Lord</char> have been pleased if I had eaten the sin offering today?” <verse eid="LEV 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 10:20"/>When Moses heard that, he was satisfied.<verse eid="LEV 10:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="LEV 11"/>
  <para style="s1">“Clean” and “Unclean” Food</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 11:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses and Aaron. He said to them, <verse eid="LEV 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 11:2"/>“Speak to the Israelites. Tell them, ‘Many animals live on land. Here are the only ones you can eat. <verse eid="LEV 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 11:3"/>You can eat any animal that has hooves that are separated completely in two. But it must also chew the cud.<verse eid="LEV 11:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 11:4"/>“ ‘Some animals only chew the cud. Some only have hooves that are separated in two. You must not eat those animals. Camels chew the cud. But their hooves are not separated in two. So they are “unclean” for you. <verse eid="LEV 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 11:5"/>Rock badgers chew the cud. But their hooves are not separated in two. So they are “unclean” for you. <verse eid="LEV 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 11:6"/>Rabbits chew the cud. But their hooves are not separated in two. So they are “unclean” for you. <verse eid="LEV 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 11:7"/>Pigs have hooves that are separated completely in two. But they do not chew the cud. So they are “unclean” for you. <verse eid="LEV 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 11:8"/>You must not eat the meat of those animals. You must not even touch their dead bodies. They are “unclean” for you.<verse eid="LEV 11:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 11:9"/>“ ‘Many creatures live in the water of the oceans and streams. You can eat all those that have fins and scales. <verse eid="LEV 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 11:10"/>Treat as “unclean” all the creatures in the oceans or streams that do not have fins and scales. That includes all those that move together in groups and all those that do not. <verse eid="LEV 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 11:11"/>Treat them as “unclean.” Do not eat their meat. Treat their dead bodies as “unclean.” <verse eid="LEV 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 11:12"/>Regard as “unclean” everything that lives in the water that does not have fins and scales.<verse eid="LEV 11:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 11:13"/>“ ‘Here are the birds you must treat as “unclean.” Do not eat them because they are “unclean.” The birds include eagles, vultures and black vultures. <verse eid="LEV 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 11:14"/>They include red kites and all kinds of black kites. <verse eid="LEV 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 11:15"/>They include all kinds of ravens. <verse eid="LEV 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 11:16"/>They include horned owls, screech owls, gulls and all kinds of hawks. <verse eid="LEV 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 11:17"/>They include little owls, cormorants and great owls. <verse eid="LEV 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 11:18"/>They include white owls, desert owls and ospreys. <verse eid="LEV 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 11:19"/>They also include storks, hoopoes, bats and all kinds of herons.<verse eid="LEV 11:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 11:20"/>“ ‘Treat as “unclean” every flying insect that walks on all fours. <verse eid="LEV 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 11:21"/>But you can eat some flying insects that walk on all fours. Their legs have joints so they can hop on the ground. <verse eid="LEV 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 11:22"/>Here are the insects you can eat. You can eat all kinds of locusts, katydids, crickets and grasshoppers. <verse eid="LEV 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 11:23"/>Treat as “unclean” every other creature with wings and four legs.<verse eid="LEV 11:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 11:24"/>“ ‘You will make yourselves “unclean” if you eat these things. If you touch their dead bodies, you will be “unclean” until evening. <verse eid="LEV 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 11:25"/>If a person picks up one of their dead bodies, that person must wash their clothes. They will be “unclean” until evening.<verse eid="LEV 11:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 11:26"/>“ ‘Suppose an animal has hooves that are not separated completely in two. Or suppose an animal does not chew the cud. Then these animals are “unclean” for you. If you touch the dead body of any of them, you will be “unclean.” <verse eid="LEV 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 11:27"/>Many animals walk on all fours. But those that walk on their paws are “unclean” for you. Anyone who touches their dead bodies will be “unclean” until evening. <verse eid="LEV 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 11:28"/>If a person picks up their dead bodies, that person must wash their clothes. They will be “unclean” until evening. These animals are “unclean” for you.<verse eid="LEV 11:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 11:29"/>“ ‘Many animals move along the ground. Here are the ones that are “unclean” for you. They include weasels, rats and all kinds of large lizards. <verse eid="LEV 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 11:30"/>They also include geckos, monitor lizards, wall lizards, skinks and chameleons. <verse eid="LEV 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 11:31"/>These are the animals that move around on the ground that are “unclean” for you. If you touch their dead bodies, you will be “unclean” until evening. <verse eid="LEV 11:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 11:32"/>Suppose one of them dies and falls on something. Then that thing will be “unclean.” It does not matter what it is used for. It does not matter whether it is made out of wood, cloth, hide or rough cloth. Put it in water. It will be “unclean” until evening. After that, it will be “clean.” <verse eid="LEV 11:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 11:33"/>Suppose one of these animals falls into a clay pot. Then everything in the pot will be “unclean.” You must break the pot. <verse eid="LEV 11:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 11:34"/>Any food that could be eaten but has water on it that came from that pot is “unclean.” And any liquid that could be drunk from it is “unclean.” <verse eid="LEV 11:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 11:35"/>Anything that the dead body of one of these animals falls on becomes “unclean.” If it is an oven or cooking pot, break it. It is “unclean.” And you must consider it “unclean.” <verse eid="LEV 11:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 11:36"/>But a spring or a well for collecting water remains “clean.” That is true even if the dead body of one of these animals falls into it. But anyone who touches the dead body is not “clean.” <verse eid="LEV 11:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 11:37"/>If the dead body falls on any seeds that have not been planted yet, the seeds remain “clean.” <verse eid="LEV 11:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 11:38"/>But suppose water has already been put on the seeds. And suppose the dead body falls on them. Then they are “unclean” for you.<verse eid="LEV 11:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 11:39"/>“ ‘Suppose an animal you are allowed to eat dies. If anyone touches its dead body, they will be “unclean” until evening. <verse eid="LEV 11:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LEV 11:40"/>If they eat part of the dead body, they must wash their clothes. They will be “unclean” until evening. If they pick up the dead body, they must wash their clothes. They will be “unclean” until evening.<verse eid="LEV 11:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="LEV 11:41"/>“ ‘Treat as “unclean” every creature that moves along the ground. Do not eat it. <verse eid="LEV 11:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 11:42"/>Do not eat any of these creatures. It does not matter whether they move on their bellies. It does not matter whether they walk on all fours or on many feet. It is “unclean.” <verse eid="LEV 11:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 11:43"/>Do not make yourselves “unclean” by eating any of these animals. Do not make yourselves “unclean” because of them. Do not let them make you “unclean.” <verse eid="LEV 11:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 11:44"/>I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. Set yourselves apart. Be holy, because I am holy. Do not make yourselves “unclean” by eating any creatures that move around on the ground. <verse eid="LEV 11:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LEV 11:45"/>I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. I brought you up out of Egypt to be your God. So be holy, because I am holy.<verse eid="LEV 11:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="LEV 11:46"/>“ ‘These are the rules about animals and birds. These are the rules about every living thing that moves around in the water. And these are the rules about every creature that moves along the ground. <verse eid="LEV 11:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LEV 11:47"/>You must be able to tell the difference between what is “clean” and what is not. You must also be able to tell the difference between living creatures that can be eaten and those that can’t.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 11:47"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="LEV 12"/>
  <para style="s1">Becoming “Clean” After Having a Baby</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 12:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 12:2"/>“Speak to the Israelites. Tell them, ‘Suppose a woman becomes pregnant and has a baby boy. Then she will be “unclean” for seven days. It is the same as when she is “unclean” during her monthly period. <verse eid="LEV 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 12:3"/>On the eighth day the boy must be circumcised. <verse eid="LEV 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 12:4"/>After that, the woman must wait for 33 days to be made pure from her bleeding. She must not touch anything sacred until the 33 days are over. During that time she must not go to the sacred tent. <verse eid="LEV 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 12:5"/>But suppose she has a baby girl. Then she will be “unclean” for two weeks. It is the same as during her period. After the two weeks, she must wait for 66 days to be made pure from her bleeding.<verse eid="LEV 12:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 12:6"/>“ ‘After she has waited the required number of days to be made pure, she must bring two offerings. She must take them to the priest at the entrance to the tent of meeting. She must bring a lamb a year old for a burnt offering. She must also bring a young pigeon or a dove for a sin offering. <verse eid="LEV 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 12:7"/>The priest must offer them to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They will pay for her sin. Then she will be “clean” from her bleeding.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 12:7">“ ‘These are the rules for a woman who has a baby boy or girl. <verse eid="LEV 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 12:8"/>But suppose she can’t afford a lamb. Then she must bring two doves or two young pigeons. One is for a burnt offering. The other is for a sin offering. The priest will sacrifice those offerings. That will pay for her sin. And she will be “clean.” ’ ”<verse eid="LEV 12:8"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="LEV 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Rules About Skin Diseases</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 13:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses and Aaron. He told them to say to the people, <verse eid="LEV 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 13:2"/>“Suppose someone’s skin has a swelling or a rash or a shiny spot. And suppose it could become a skin disease. Then they must be brought to the priest Aaron. Or they must be brought to a priest in Aaron’s family line. <verse eid="LEV 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 13:3"/>The priest must look carefully at the sore on the person’s skin. He must see whether the hair in the sore has turned white. He must also see whether the sore seems to be under the skin. If the sore is white and is under the skin, it is a skin disease. When the priest looks that person over carefully, he must announce that the person is ‘unclean.’ <verse eid="LEV 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 13:4"/>Suppose the shiny spot on the skin is white but does not seem to be under the skin. And suppose the hair in the spot has not turned white. Then the priest must make the person stay away from everyone else for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 13:5"/>On the seventh day the priest must look carefully at the sore again. Suppose it has not changed and has not spread in the skin. Then the priest must make the person stay away from everyone else for another seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 13:6"/>On the seventh day the priest must look carefully at the sore again. If it has faded and has not spread, he must announce that the person is ‘clean.’ It is only a rash. That person must wash their clothes. They will be ‘clean.’ <verse eid="LEV 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 13:7"/>But suppose the rash spreads in the skin after they have shown themselves to the priest a second time. Then they must appear in front of the priest again. <verse eid="LEV 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 13:8"/>The priest must look carefully at the sore. If the rash has spread, he must announce that the person is ‘unclean.’ They have a skin disease.<verse eid="LEV 13:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 13:9"/>“When anyone has a skin disease, they must be brought to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 13:10"/>The priest must look them over carefully. Suppose there is a white swelling in the skin. Suppose it has turned the hair white. And suppose there are open sores in the swelling. <verse eid="LEV 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 13:11"/>Then the person has a skin disease that will never go away. The priest must announce that they are ‘unclean.’ The priest must not make them stay away from everyone else. They are already ‘unclean.’<verse eid="LEV 13:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 13:12"/>“Suppose the disease breaks out all over their skin. And suppose it covers them from head to foot, as far as the priest can tell. <verse eid="LEV 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 13:13"/>Then the priest must look them over carefully. If the disease has covered their whole body, the priest must announce that they are ‘clean.’ All their skin has turned white. So they are ‘clean.’ <verse eid="LEV 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 13:14"/>But when open sores appear on their skin, they will not be ‘clean.’ <verse eid="LEV 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 13:15"/>When the priest sees the open sores, he must announce that they are ‘unclean.’ The open sores are not ‘clean.’ They have a skin disease. <verse eid="LEV 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 13:16"/>But if the open sores change and turn white, they must go to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 13:17"/>The priest must look them over carefully. If the sores have turned white, the priest must announce that the person is ‘clean.’ Then they will be ‘clean.’<verse eid="LEV 13:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 13:18"/>“Suppose someone has a boil on their skin and it heals. <verse eid="LEV 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 13:19"/>And suppose a white swelling or shiny pink spot appears where the boil was. Then they must show themselves to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 13:20"/>The priest must look at the boil carefully. Suppose it seems to be under the skin. And suppose the hair in it has turned white. Then the priest must announce that the person is ‘unclean.’ A skin disease has broken out where the boil was. <verse eid="LEV 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 13:21"/>But suppose that when the priest looks at the boil carefully, there is no white hair in it. The boil is not under the skin. And it has faded. Then the priest must make the person stay away from everyone else for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 13:22"/>If the boil is spreading in the skin, the priest must announce that the person is ‘unclean.’ They have a skin disease. <verse eid="LEV 13:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 13:23"/>But suppose the spot has not changed. And suppose it has not spread. Then it is only a scar from the boil. And the priest must announce that the person is ‘clean.’<verse eid="LEV 13:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 13:24"/>“Suppose someone has a burn on their skin. And suppose a white or shiny pink spot shows up in the open sores of the burn. <verse eid="LEV 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 13:25"/>Then the priest must look at the spot carefully. Suppose the hair in it has turned white. And suppose the spot seems to be under the skin. Then the person has a skin disease. It has broken out where they were burned. The priest must announce that the person is ‘unclean.’ They have a skin disease. <verse eid="LEV 13:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 13:26"/>But suppose the priest looks at the spot carefully. Suppose there is no white hair in it. Suppose the spot is not under the skin. And suppose it has faded. Then the priest must make the person stay away from everyone else for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 13:27"/>On the seventh day the priest must look them over carefully. If the spot is spreading in the skin, the priest must announce that the person is ‘unclean.’ They have a skin disease. <verse eid="LEV 13:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 13:28"/>But suppose the spot has not changed. It has not spread in the skin. And it has faded. Then the burn has caused it to swell. The priest must announce that the person is ‘clean.’ It is only a scar from the burn.<verse eid="LEV 13:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 13:29"/>“Suppose a man or woman has a sore on their head or chin. <verse eid="LEV 13:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 13:30"/>Then the priest must look at the sore carefully. Suppose it seems to be under the skin. And suppose the hair in the sore is yellow and thin. Then the priest must announce that the person is ‘unclean.’ The sore is a skin disease on the head or chin. <verse eid="LEV 13:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 13:31"/>But suppose the priest looks carefully at the sore. It does not seem to be under the skin. And there is no black hair in it. Then the priest must make the person stay away from everyone else for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 13:32"/>On the seventh day the priest must look at the sore carefully. Suppose it has not spread in the skin. It does not have any yellow hair in it. And it does not seem to be under the skin. <verse eid="LEV 13:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 13:33"/>Then the man or woman must shave their head. But they must not shave the area where the disease is. And the priest must make them stay away from everyone else for another seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 13:34"/>On the seventh day the priest must look at the sore carefully. Suppose it has not spread in the skin. And suppose it does not seem to be under the skin. Then the priest must announce that the person is ‘clean.’ They must wash their clothes. They will be ‘clean.’ <verse eid="LEV 13:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 13:35"/>But suppose the sore spreads in the skin after the priest announces that the person is ‘clean.’ <verse eid="LEV 13:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 13:36"/>Then the priest must look them over carefully. Suppose the sore has spread. Then the priest does not have to look for yellow hair. The person is ‘unclean.’ <verse eid="LEV 13:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 13:37"/>But suppose the sore has stopped and black hair has grown there, as far as the priest can tell. Then the person is healed and is ‘clean.’ The priest must announce that they are ‘clean.’<verse eid="LEV 13:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 13:38"/>“Suppose a man or woman has white spots on the skin. <verse eid="LEV 13:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 13:39"/>Then the priest must look at them carefully. Suppose he sees that the spots are dull white. Then a harmless rash has broken out on the skin. That person is ‘clean.’<verse eid="LEV 13:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="LEV 13:40"/>“Suppose a man loses all the hair on his head. Then he is ‘clean.’ <verse eid="LEV 13:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LEV 13:41"/>Suppose he loses only the hair on the front of his head. Then he is ‘clean.’ <verse eid="LEV 13:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 13:42"/>But suppose he has a shiny pink sore on his head where his hair was. Then he has a skin disease. It is breaking out on his whole head or on the front of his head. <verse eid="LEV 13:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 13:43"/>The priest must look him over carefully. Suppose the swollen sore on his head or on the front of it is pink and shiny. And suppose it looks like a skin disease. <verse eid="LEV 13:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 13:44"/>Then he has a skin disease. He is ‘unclean.’ The priest must announce that the man is ‘unclean.’ That’s because he has a sore on his head.<verse eid="LEV 13:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="LEV 13:45"/>“Suppose someone has a skin disease that makes them ‘unclean.’ Then they must wear torn clothes. They must let their hair hang loose. They must cover the lower part of their face. They must cry out, ‘Unclean! Unclean!’ <verse eid="LEV 13:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LEV 13:46"/>As long as they have the disease, they remain ‘unclean.’ They must live alone. They must live outside the camp.<verse eid="LEV 13:46"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Rules About Mold</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="LEV 13:47"/>“Suppose some clothes have mold on them. The clothes could be made out of wool or linen. <verse eid="LEV 13:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LEV 13:48"/>Or there could be cloth woven or knitted out of linen or wool. There could be pieces of leather. Or there could be things that are made out of leather. <verse eid="LEV 13:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LEV 13:49"/>And suppose the mold on the clothes or on the woven or knitted cloth looks green or red. Or suppose the green or red mold is on the pieces of leather or the leather goods. Then it is mold that spreads. It must be shown to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 13:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LEV 13:50"/>The priest must look at it carefully. He must keep the thing with the mold on it away from everything else for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LEV 13:51"/>On the seventh day he must look at it carefully. Suppose the mold has spread in the clothes or in the woven or knitted cloth. Or suppose it has spread on the pieces of leather or on the leather goods. Then it is mold that destroys. The thing is ‘unclean.’ <verse eid="LEV 13:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LEV 13:52"/>The priest must burn everything with the mold in it. He must burn the clothes or the woven or knitted cloth made out of wool or linen. He must burn the leather goods. The mold destroys. So everything must be burned.<verse eid="LEV 13:52"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="53" style="v" sid="LEV 13:53"/>“But suppose the priest looks at the thing carefully. The mold has not spread in the clothes. And it has not spread in the woven or knitted cloth or in the leather goods. <verse eid="LEV 13:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="LEV 13:54"/>Then he will order someone to wash the thing with the mold on it. After that, the priest must keep that thing away from everything else for another seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LEV 13:55"/>After the thing with the mold on it has been washed, the priest must look at it again carefully. Suppose the way the mold looks has not changed. Then even though the mold has not spread, it is ‘unclean.’ Burn it. It does not matter which side of the thing the mold is on. <verse eid="LEV 13:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LEV 13:56"/>But suppose the priest looks at it carefully. And suppose the mold has faded after the thing has been washed. Then the priest must tear out the part with mold on it. He must tear it out of the clothes or leather. He must tear it out of the woven or knitted cloth. <verse eid="LEV 13:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="LEV 13:57"/>But suppose it shows up again in the clothes. Or suppose it shows up again in the woven or knitted cloth or in the leather goods. Then it is spreading. Everything with the mold on it must be burned. <verse eid="LEV 13:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="LEV 13:58"/>The clothes that have been washed and do not have any more mold on them must be washed again. So must the woven or knitted cloth or the leather goods. Then they will be ‘clean.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 13:58"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="59" style="v" sid="LEV 13:59"/>These are the rules about what to do with anything with mold on it. They apply to clothes that are made out of wool or linen. They apply to woven and knitted cloth and to leather goods. They give a priest directions about when to announce whether something is “clean” or “unclean.”<verse eid="LEV 13:59"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="LEV 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Making People “Clean” From Skin Diseases</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 14:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He told him to say to the people, <verse eid="LEV 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 14:2"/>“Here are the rules for making anyone ‘clean’ who has had a skin disease. They apply when the person is brought to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 14:3"/>The priest must go outside the camp. He must look the person over carefully. Suppose they have been healed of their skin disease. <verse eid="LEV 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 14:4"/>Then the priest will order someone to bring him two live ‘clean’ birds. He will also order someone to bring him some cedar wood, bright red yarn and branches of a hyssop plant. All these things will be used to make the person ‘clean.’ <verse eid="LEV 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 14:5"/>The priest will order someone to kill one of the birds. It must be killed over fresh water in a clay pot. <verse eid="LEV 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 14:6"/>Then the priest must take the live bird. He must dip it into the blood of the bird killed over the fresh water. He must dip it into the blood together with the cedar wood, the bright red yarn and the hyssop plant. <verse eid="LEV 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 14:7"/>The priest will sprinkle the blood on the person who had the skin disease. That will make them ‘clean.’ The priest must sprinkle them seven times. Then the priest must announce that they are ‘clean.’ After that, the priest must let the live bird go free in the open fields.<verse eid="LEV 14:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 14:8"/>“The person must also wash their clothes to be made ‘clean.’ They must shave off all their hair. They must take a bath. Then they will be ‘clean.’ After that, they may come into the camp. But they must stay outside their tent for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 14:9"/>On the seventh day they must shave off all their hair. They must shave their head. They must shave off their beard. They must also shave off their eyebrows and the rest of their hair. They must wash their clothes. They must take a bath. Then they will be ‘clean.’<verse eid="LEV 14:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 14:10"/>“On the eighth day they must bring two male lambs and one female lamb as an offering. The female must be a year old. The lambs must not have any flaws. They must also bring 11 pounds of the finest flour as a grain offering. They must mix it with olive oil. They must also bring 11 ounces of oil. <verse eid="LEV 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 14:11"/>The priest who announces that the person is ‘clean’ must bring them and their offerings to me. He must do it at the entrance to the tent of meeting.<verse eid="LEV 14:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 14:12"/>“Then the priest must take one of the male lambs. He must offer it as a guilt offering. He must offer it along with 11 ounces of oil. He must lift all of it up and wave it in front of me as a wave offering. <verse eid="LEV 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 14:13"/>He must kill the lamb in the holy area where sin offerings and burnt offerings are killed. The guilt offering belongs to the priest, just as the sin offering does. The guilt offering is very holy. <verse eid="LEV 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 14:14"/>The priest must take some of the blood from the guilt offering and put it on the person’s right earlobe. He must put some on the thumb of their right hand. He must also put some on the big toe of their right foot. <verse eid="LEV 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 14:15"/>Then the priest must take some of the oil and pour it into his own left hand. <verse eid="LEV 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 14:16"/>He must dip his right forefinger into the oil in his hand. He must use his finger to sprinkle some of the oil in front of me seven times. <verse eid="LEV 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 14:17"/>The priest must put some of the oil in his hand on the same places he put the blood of the guilt offering. He must put some on the person’s right earlobe. He must put some on the thumb of their right hand. He must put some on the big toe of their right foot. <verse eid="LEV 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 14:18"/>He must put on their head the rest of the oil in his hand. It will pay for the person’s sin in my sight.<verse eid="LEV 14:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 14:19"/>“Then the priest must sacrifice the sin offering. It will pay for the person’s sin. They will be made ‘clean’ after being ‘unclean.’ After that, the priest will kill the burnt offering. <verse eid="LEV 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 14:20"/>He will offer it on the altar. He will offer it together with the grain offering. It will pay for the person’s sin. Then they will be ‘clean.’<verse eid="LEV 14:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 14:21"/>“But suppose they are poor. Suppose they can’t afford all these offerings. Then they must bring one male lamb as a guilt offering. It must be lifted up and waved in front of me to pay for their sin. They must also bring three and a half pounds of the finest flour along with the lamb. They must mix the flour with olive oil. It is a grain offering. They must offer it along with 11 ounces of oil. <verse eid="LEV 14:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 14:22"/>They must also bring two doves or two young pigeons that they can afford. One is for a sin offering. The other is for a burnt offering.<verse eid="LEV 14:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 14:23"/>“On the eighth day they must bring them to the priest so they can be made ‘clean.’ They must bring them to the entrance to the tent of meeting. They must do it in my sight. <verse eid="LEV 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 14:24"/>The priest must take the lamb for the guilt offering. He must take it together with the 11 ounces of oil. He must lift all of it up and wave it in front of me as a wave offering. <verse eid="LEV 14:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 14:25"/>He must kill the lamb for the guilt offering. He must take some of its blood and put it on the person’s right earlobe. He must put some on the thumb of their right hand. He must also put some on the big toe of their right foot. <verse eid="LEV 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 14:26"/>The priest must pour some of the oil into his own left hand. <verse eid="LEV 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 14:27"/>He must dip his right forefinger into the oil in his hand. He must use his finger to sprinkle some of it seven times in front of me. <verse eid="LEV 14:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 14:28"/>Here is what he must do with some of the oil in his hand. He must put it on the same places where he put the blood of the guilt offering. He must put some on the person’s right earlobe. He must put some on the thumb of their right hand. He must also put some on the big toe of their right foot. <verse eid="LEV 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 14:29"/>He must put on their head the rest of the oil in his hand. It will pay for the person’s sin in my sight. <verse eid="LEV 14:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 14:30"/>The priest will sacrifice the doves or the young pigeons that the person can afford. <verse eid="LEV 14:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 14:31"/>One is for a sin offering. The other is for a burnt offering. The priest must offer them together with the grain offering. In that way he will pay for the person’s sin in my sight. He will do it to make them ‘clean.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 14:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 14:32"/>These are the rules for anyone who has a skin disease. They are for people who can’t afford the regular offerings that are required to make them “clean.”<verse eid="LEV 14:32"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Making Things “Clean” From Mold</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 14:33"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses and Aaron. He told them to say to the people, <verse eid="LEV 14:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 14:34"/>“You will enter the land of Canaan. I am giving it to you as your own. When you enter it, suppose I put mold in one of your houses. And suppose the mold spreads. <verse eid="LEV 14:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 14:35"/>Then the owner of that house must go and speak to the priest. He must say, ‘I’ve seen something that looks like mold in my house.’ <verse eid="LEV 14:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 14:36"/>The priest must order everything to be taken out of the house. It must be done before he goes in to look carefully at the mold. If it is not done, the priest must announce that everything in the house is ‘unclean.’ After the house is empty the priest must go in and check it. <verse eid="LEV 14:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 14:37"/>He must look carefully at the mold on the walls. Suppose it looks as if it has green or red dents in it. And suppose the dents look as if they are behind the surface of the wall. <verse eid="LEV 14:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 14:38"/>Then the priest must go out the door. He must close the house up for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 14:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 14:39"/>On the seventh day the priest will return to check the house. Suppose the mold on the walls has spread. <verse eid="LEV 14:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LEV 14:40"/>Then he must order someone to tear out the stones that have mold on them. He must have them thrown into an ‘unclean’ place outside the town. <verse eid="LEV 14:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LEV 14:41"/>He must have all the inside walls of the house scraped. Everything scraped off must be dumped into an ‘unclean’ place outside the town. <verse eid="LEV 14:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 14:42"/>Then other stones must be put in the place of the stones that had mold on them. The inside walls of the house must be coated with new clay.<verse eid="LEV 14:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 14:43"/>“Suppose the stones have been torn out. The house has been scraped. And the walls have been coated with new clay. But the mold appears again. <verse eid="LEV 14:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 14:44"/>Then the priest must go and look things over carefully. Suppose the mold has spread in the house. Then it is the kind of mold that destroys things. The house is not ‘clean.’ <verse eid="LEV 14:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LEV 14:45"/>It must be torn down. The stones, the wood and all the clay coating must be torn out. All of it must be taken out of the town to an ‘unclean’ place.<verse eid="LEV 14:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="LEV 14:46"/>“Suppose someone goes into the house while it is closed up. Then they will be ‘unclean’ until evening. <verse eid="LEV 14:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LEV 14:47"/>If they sleep or eat in the house, they must wash their clothes.<verse eid="LEV 14:47"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="LEV 14:48"/>“But suppose the priest comes to look things over carefully. And suppose the mold has not spread after the walls had been coated with new clay. Then he will announce that the house is ‘clean.’ The mold is gone. <verse eid="LEV 14:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LEV 14:49"/>To make the house pure, the priest must get two birds. He must also get some cedar wood, bright red yarn and branches of a hyssop plant. <verse eid="LEV 14:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LEV 14:50"/>He must kill one of the birds over fresh water in a clay pot. <verse eid="LEV 14:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LEV 14:51"/>Then he must take the cedar wood, the hyssop plant, the bright red yarn and the live bird. He must dip all of them into the blood of the dead bird. He must also dip them into the fresh water. He must sprinkle the house seven times. <verse eid="LEV 14:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LEV 14:52"/>The priest will use the blood and the water to make the house pure. He will use the live bird to make it pure. He will also use the cedar wood, the hyssop plant and the bright red yarn to make it pure. <verse eid="LEV 14:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LEV 14:53"/>Then he must let the live bird go free in the open fields outside the town. In that way he will make the house pure. It will be ‘clean.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 14:53"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="LEV 14:54"/>These are the rules for skin diseases. They apply to sores. <verse eid="LEV 14:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LEV 14:55"/>They apply to mold in clothes or in houses. <verse eid="LEV 14:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LEV 14:56"/>They also apply to swellings, rashes or shiny red spots on the skin. <verse eid="LEV 14:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="LEV 14:57"/>Use these rules to decide whether something is “clean” or not.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 14:57">These are the rules for skin diseases and for mold.<verse eid="LEV 14:57"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="LEV 15"/>
  <para style="s1">Rules About Liquid Body Wastes</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 15:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Moses and Aaron, <verse eid="LEV 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 15:2"/>“Speak to the Israelites. Tell them, ‘Suppose liquid waste is flowing out of a man’s body. That liquid is not “clean.” <verse eid="LEV 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 15:3"/>It does not matter whether it continues to flow out of his body or is blocked. It will make him “unclean.” Here is how his liquid body waste will make him “unclean.”<verse eid="LEV 15:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 15:4"/>“ ‘Any bed the man who has the flow of liquid body waste lies on will be “unclean.” Anything he sits on will be “unclean.” <verse eid="LEV 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 15:5"/>Anyone who touches the man’s bed must wash their clothes. They must take a bath. They will be “unclean” until evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 15:6"/>Suppose someone sits on something the man sat on. Then they must wash their clothes. They must take a bath. They will be “unclean” until evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 15:7"/>“ ‘Suppose someone touches the man who has the flow of liquid body waste. Then they must wash their clothes. They must take a bath. They will be “unclean” until evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 15:8"/>“ ‘Suppose someone is “clean.” And suppose the man who has the flow of liquid waste spits on them. Then they must wash their clothes. They must take a bath. They will be “unclean” until evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 15:9"/>“ ‘Everything the man sits on when he is riding will be “unclean.” <verse eid="LEV 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 15:10"/>Suppose someone touches any of the things that were under him. Then they will be “unclean” until evening. Even if they pick up those things, they must wash their clothes. They must take a bath. They will be “unclean” until evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 15:11"/>“ ‘Suppose the man who has the liquid flow touches someone. And suppose he does it without rinsing his hands with water. Then the person he touched must wash their clothes. They must take a bath. They will be “unclean” until evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 15:12"/>“ ‘Suppose the man touches a clay pot. Then that pot must be broken. Any wooden thing he touches must be rinsed with water.<verse eid="LEV 15:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 15:13"/>“ ‘Suppose the man has been healed from his liquid flow. Then he must wait seven days. He must wash his clothes. He must take a bath in fresh water. After that, he will be “clean.” <verse eid="LEV 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 15:14"/>On the eighth day he must get two doves or two young pigeons. He must come to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> at the entrance to the tent of meeting. There he must give the birds to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 15:15"/>The priest must sacrifice them. One is for a sin offering. The other is for a burnt offering. In that way the priest will pay for the man’s sin in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He will do it because the man had a liquid flow.<verse eid="LEV 15:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 15:16"/>“ ‘Suppose semen flows from a man’s body. Then he must wash his whole body with water. He will be “unclean” until evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 15:17"/>Suppose clothes or leather have semen on them. Then they must be washed with water. They will be “unclean” until evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 15:18"/>Suppose a man sleeps with a woman. And suppose semen flows from his body and touches both of them. Then they must take a bath. They will be “unclean” until evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 15:19"/>“ ‘Suppose a woman is having her regular monthly period. Then for seven days she will be “unclean.” Anyone who touches her will be “unclean” until evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 15:20"/>“ ‘Anything she lies on during her period will be “unclean.” Anything she sits on will be “unclean.” <verse eid="LEV 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 15:21"/>Anyone who touches her bed must wash their clothes. They must take a bath. They will be “unclean” until evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 15:22"/>Anyone who touches anything she sits on must wash their clothes. They must take a bath. They will be “unclean” until evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 15:23"/>It does not matter whether it was her bed or anything she was sitting on. If anyone touches it, they will be “unclean” until evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 15:24"/>“ ‘Suppose a man sleeps with that woman. And suppose blood from her monthly period touches him. Then he will be “unclean” for seven days. Any bed he lies on will be “unclean.”<verse eid="LEV 15:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 15:25"/>“ ‘Suppose blood flows from a woman’s body for many days. And it happens at a time other than her monthly period. Or blood keeps flowing after her period is over. Then she will be “unclean” as long as the blood continues to flow. She will be “unclean,” just as she is during the days of her period. <verse eid="LEV 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 15:26"/>Any bed she lies on while her blood continues to flow will be “unclean.” It is the same as it is when she is having her period. Anything she sits on will be “unclean.” <verse eid="LEV 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 15:27"/>If anyone touches those things, they will be “unclean.” They must wash their clothes. They must take a bath. They will be “unclean” until evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 15:28"/>“ ‘Suppose the woman has been healed from her flow of blood. Then she must wait seven days. After that, she will be “clean.” <verse eid="LEV 15:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 15:29"/>On the eighth day she must get two doves or two young pigeons. She must bring them to the priest at the entrance to the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 15:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 15:30"/>The priest must sacrifice them. One is for a sin offering. The other is for a burnt offering. In that way he will pay for her sin in the sight of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He will do it because her flow of blood made her “unclean.”<verse eid="LEV 15:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 15:31"/>“ ‘You must keep the Israelites away from things that make them “unclean.” Then they will not die for being “unclean.” And they will not die for making the place “unclean” where I, the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, live. It is in the middle of the camp.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 15:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 15:32"/>These are the rules for a man who has liquid waste flowing out of his body. They apply to a man made “unclean” by semen that flows from his body. <verse eid="LEV 15:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 15:33"/>They apply to a woman having her monthly period. They apply to a man or woman who has a liquid flow. And they apply to a man who sleeps with a woman who is “unclean.”<verse eid="LEV 15:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="LEV 16"/>
  <para style="s1">The Day When Sin Is Paid For</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 16:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses after two of Aaron’s sons had died. They were the sons who died when they came near the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 16:2"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Moses, “Speak to your brother Aaron. Tell him not to come into the Most Holy Room just anytime he wants to. Tell him not to come behind the curtain in front of the cover of the ark. The cover is the place where sin is paid for. If he comes behind the curtain, he will die. That is because I appear in the cloud over the cover.<verse eid="LEV 16:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 16:3"/>“Aaron must not enter the area of the Most Holy Room without bringing a sacrifice. He must bring a young bull for a sin offering. He must also bring a ram for a burnt offering. <verse eid="LEV 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 16:4"/>He must put on the sacred inner robe made out of linen. He must wear linen underwear next to his body. He must tie the linen belt around him. And he must put the linen turban on his head. Those are sacred clothes. So he must take a bath before he puts them on. <verse eid="LEV 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 16:5"/>The community of Israel must give him two male goats and a ram. The goats are for a sin offering. The ram is for a burnt offering.<verse eid="LEV 16:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 16:6"/>“Aaron must offer the bull for his own sin offering. It will pay for his own sin and the sin of his whole family. <verse eid="LEV 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 16:7"/>Then he must take the two goats and bring them to me at the entrance to the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 16:8"/>He must cast lots for the two goats. One lot is for me. The other is for the goat that carries the people’s sins away. <verse eid="LEV 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 16:9"/>Aaron must bring the goat chosen for me by lot. He must sacrifice it for a sin offering. <verse eid="LEV 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 16:10"/>But the goat chosen by the other lot must remain alive. First, it must be brought in to me to pay for the people’s sins. Then, it must be sent into the desert as a goat that carries the people’s sins away.<verse eid="LEV 16:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 16:11"/>“Aaron must bring the bull for his own sin offering. It will pay for his own sin and the sin of his whole family. He must kill the bull for his own sin offering. <verse eid="LEV 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 16:12"/>He must take a shallow cup full of burning coals from the altar in my sight. He must get two handfuls of incense completely ground up. The incense must smell sweet. He must take the cup and the incense behind the curtain. <verse eid="LEV 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 16:13"/>He must put the incense on the fire in my sight. The smoke from the incense will hide the cover of the ark where the tablets of the covenant law are kept. The cover is the place where sin is paid for. Aaron must burn the incense so that he will not die. <verse eid="LEV 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 16:14"/>He must dip his finger in the bull’s blood. He must sprinkle it on the front of the cover of the ark. He must sprinkle some in front of the cover. He must do it seven times.<verse eid="LEV 16:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 16:15"/>“Then Aaron must kill the goat for the sin offering for the people. He must take its blood behind the curtain. There he must do the same thing with it as he did with the bull’s blood. He must sprinkle it on the cover of the ark. He must also sprinkle some in front of it. <verse eid="LEV 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 16:16"/>That is how he will make the Most Holy Room pure. He must do it because the Israelites are not ‘clean.’ They have not obeyed me. They have also committed other sins. Aaron must do the same for the tent of meeting because it stands in the middle of the camp. And the camp is ‘unclean.’ <verse eid="LEV 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 16:17"/>Aaron will go into the Most Holy Room to pay for the people’s sin. While Aaron is there, no one may be in the tent of meeting. No one may enter the tent until Aaron comes out. He will not come out until he has paid for his own sin and the sin of his whole family. He will not come out until he has also paid for the sin of the whole community of Israel.<verse eid="LEV 16:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 16:18"/>“Then he will come out to the altar for burnt offerings. It is in front of the tent where the ark of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is. He will make the altar pure and clean. He will take some of the bull’s blood and some of the goat’s blood. Then he will put the blood on all the horns that stick out from the upper four corners of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 16:19"/>He will sprinkle some of the blood on it with his finger seven times. He will do it to make the altar pure. He will do it to set it apart from the Israelites. They are ‘unclean.’<verse eid="LEV 16:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 16:20"/>“Aaron will finish making the Most Holy Room pure and ‘clean.’ He will finish making the tent of meeting and the altar pure. Then he will bring out the live goat. <verse eid="LEV 16:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 16:21"/>He must place both of his hands on its head. While he does that, he must tell me about all the sins the Israelites have committed. He must tell me about all their evil acts and the times they did not obey me. In that way he puts their sins on the goat’s head. Then he will send the goat away into the desert. The goat will be led away by a man appointed to do it. <verse eid="LEV 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 16:22"/>The goat will carry all their sins on itself to a place where there are no people. And the man will set the goat free in the desert.<verse eid="LEV 16:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 16:23"/>“Then Aaron must go into the tent of meeting. He must take off the linen clothes he put on before he entered the Most Holy Room. He must leave them there. <verse eid="LEV 16:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 16:24"/>He must take a bath in the holy area. And he must put on his regular clothes. Then he will come out and sacrifice the burnt offering for himself. He will also sacrifice the burnt offering for the people. That will pay for his own sin and the people’s sin. <verse eid="LEV 16:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 16:25"/>He will also burn the fat of the sin offering on the altar.<verse eid="LEV 16:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 16:26"/>“The man who sets free the goat that carries the people’s sins away must wash his clothes. He must take a bath. After that, he can come back into the camp. <verse eid="LEV 16:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 16:27"/>The bull and the goat for the sin offerings must be taken outside the camp. Their blood was brought into the Most Holy Room. It paid for sin. The hides, meat and guts of the animals must be burned up. <verse eid="LEV 16:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 16:28"/>The man who burns them must wash his clothes. He must take a bath. After that, he can come back into the camp.<verse eid="LEV 16:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 16:29"/>“Here is a law for you that will last for all time to come. On the tenth day of the seventh month you must not eat anything. You must not do any work. It does not matter whether you are Israelites or outsiders. <verse eid="LEV 16:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 16:30"/>On that day your sin will be paid for. You will be made pure and clean. You will be clean from all your sins in my sight. <verse eid="LEV 16:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 16:31"/>That day is a sabbath for you. You must rest on it. You must not eat anything on that day. This is a law that will last for all time to come. <verse eid="LEV 16:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 16:32"/>The high priest must pay for sin. He must make everything pure and clean. He has been anointed and prepared to become the next high priest after his father. He must put on the sacred clothes that are made out of linen. <verse eid="LEV 16:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 16:33"/>He must make the Most Holy Room, the tent of meeting and the altar pure. And he must pay for the sin of the priests and all the members of the community.<verse eid="LEV 16:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 16:34"/>“Here is a law for you that will last for all time to come. Once a year you must pay for all the sin of the Israelites.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 16:34">So it was done, just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded Moses.<verse eid="LEV 16:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="LEV 17"/>
  <para style="s1">Do Not Eat Meat With Blood in It</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 17:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 17:2"/>“Speak to Aaron and his sons. Speak to all the Israelites. Tell them, ‘Here is what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has commanded. He has said, <verse eid="LEV 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 17:3"/>“Suppose someone sacrifices an ox, a lamb or a goat. They sacrifice it in the camp or outside of it. <verse eid="LEV 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 17:4"/>They do it instead of bringing the animal to the entrance to the tent of meeting. They sacrifice it instead of giving it as an offering to me in front of my holy tent. Then they will be thought of as guilty of spilling blood. Because they have done that, they must be separated from their people. <verse eid="LEV 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 17:5"/>The Israelites are now making sacrifices in the open fields. But they must bring their sacrifices to the priest. They must bring them to me at the entrance to the tent of meeting. There they must sacrifice them as friendship offerings. <verse eid="LEV 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 17:6"/>The priest must splash the blood against my altar. It is the altar at the entrance to the tent of meeting. He must burn the fat. Its smell will please me. <verse eid="LEV 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 17:7"/>The Israelites must stop offering any of their sacrifices to statues of gods that look like goats. When they offer sacrifices to those statues, they are not faithful to me. This is a law for them that will last for all time to come.” ’<verse eid="LEV 17:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 17:8"/>“Tell them, ‘Suppose someone offers a burnt offering or sacrifice. It does not matter whether they are an Israelite or an outsider. <verse eid="LEV 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 17:9"/>And suppose they do not bring it to the entrance to the tent of meeting to sacrifice it to me. Then they must be separated from their people.<verse eid="LEV 17:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 17:10"/>“ ‘Suppose someone eats meat that still has blood in it. It does not matter whether they are an Israelite or an outsider. I will turn against them if they eat it. I will separate them from their people. <verse eid="LEV 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 17:11"/>The life of each creature is in its blood. So I have given you the blood of animals to pay for your sin on the altar. Blood is life. That is why blood pays for your sin. <verse eid="LEV 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 17:12"/>So I say to the Israelites, “You must not eat meat that still has blood in it. And an outsider who lives among you must not eat it either.”<verse eid="LEV 17:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 17:13"/>“ ‘Suppose any of you hunts any animal or bird that can be eaten. It does not matter whether you are an Israelite or an outsider. You must let the blood flow out of the animal or bird. You must cover the blood with dirt. <verse eid="LEV 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 17:14"/>That is because every creature’s life is its blood. And that is why I have said to the Israelites, “You must not eat any creature’s meat that still has blood in it. Every creature’s life is its blood. Anyone who eats that kind of meat must be separated from the community of Israel.”<verse eid="LEV 17:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 17:15"/>“ ‘Suppose someone eats anything found dead or torn apart by wild animals. It does not matter whether they are an Israelite or an outsider. They must wash their clothes. They must take a bath. They will be “unclean” until evening. After that, they will be “clean.” <verse eid="LEV 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 17:16"/>But suppose they do not wash their clothes. And suppose they do not take a bath. Then they will be held responsible for what they have done.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 17:16"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="LEV 18"/>
  <para style="s1">Do Not Commit Sexual Sins</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 18:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 18:2"/>“Speak to the Israelites. Tell them, ‘I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="LEV 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 18:3"/>Do not do what the people of Egypt do. You used to live there. And do not do what the people of Canaan do. I am bringing you into their land. Do not follow their practices. <verse eid="LEV 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 18:4"/>Obey my laws. Be careful to follow my rules. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="LEV 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 18:5"/>Keep my rules and laws. The one who obeys them will benefit from living by them. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 18:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 18:6"/>“ ‘Do not have sex with any of your close relatives. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 18:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 18:7"/>“ ‘Do not bring shame on your father by having sex with your mother. Do not have sex with her. She is your mother.<verse eid="LEV 18:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 18:8"/>“ ‘Do not have sex with any other wife of your father. That would bring shame on your father.<verse eid="LEV 18:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 18:9"/>“ ‘Do not have sex with your sister. It does not matter whether she is your father’s daughter or your mother’s daughter. It does not matter whether she was born in the same home as you were or somewhere else.<verse eid="LEV 18:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 18:10"/>“ ‘Do not have sex with your son’s daughter or your daughter’s daughter. That would bring shame on you.<verse eid="LEV 18:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 18:11"/>“ ‘Do not have sex with the daughter of your father’s wife. She was born to your father. She is your sister.<verse eid="LEV 18:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 18:12"/>“ ‘Do not have sex with your father’s sister. She is a close relative on your father’s side.<verse eid="LEV 18:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 18:13"/>“ ‘Do not have sex with your mother’s sister. She is a close relative on your mother’s side.<verse eid="LEV 18:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 18:14"/>“ ‘Do not bring shame on your father’s brother by having sex with his wife. She is your aunt.<verse eid="LEV 18:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 18:15"/>“ ‘Do not have sex with your daughter-in-law. She is your son’s wife. Do not have sex with her.<verse eid="LEV 18:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 18:16"/>“ ‘Do not have sex with your brother’s wife. That would bring shame on your brother.<verse eid="LEV 18:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 18:17"/>“ ‘Do not have sex with both a woman and her daughter. Do not have sex with either her son’s daughter or her daughter’s daughter. They are close relatives on her side. Having sex with them is an evil thing.<verse eid="LEV 18:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 18:18"/>“ ‘Do not take your wife’s sister as another wife and have sex with her. Do not do it while your wife is still living.<verse eid="LEV 18:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 18:19"/>“ ‘Do not have sex with a woman during her monthly period. She is “unclean” at that time.<verse eid="LEV 18:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 18:20"/>“ ‘Do not have sex with your neighbor’s wife. That would make you “unclean.”<verse eid="LEV 18:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 18:21"/>“ ‘Do not hand over any of your children to be sacrificed to the god Molek. That would be treating my name as if it were not holy. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 18:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 18:22"/>“ ‘Do not have sex with a man as you would have sex with a woman. I hate that.<verse eid="LEV 18:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 18:23"/>“ ‘Do not have sex with an animal. Do not make yourself “unclean” by doing that. A woman must not offer herself to an animal to have sex with it. That is a wrong use of sex.<verse eid="LEV 18:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 18:24"/>“ ‘Do not make yourselves “unclean” in any of these ways. That is how other nations became “unclean.” So I am going to drive those nations out of the land to make room for you. <verse eid="LEV 18:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 18:25"/>Even their land was not “clean.” So I punished it because of its sin. The land itself threw out the people who lived there. <verse eid="LEV 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 18:26"/>But you must keep my rules and my laws. You must not do any of the things I hate. It does not matter whether you are Israelites or outsiders. <verse eid="LEV 18:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 18:27"/>All these things were done by the people who lived in the land before you. That is how the land became “unclean.” <verse eid="LEV 18:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 18:28"/>If you make the land “unclean,” it will throw you out. It will get rid of you just as it got rid of the nations there before you.<verse eid="LEV 18:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 18:29"/>“ ‘Suppose you do any of the things I hate. Then you must be separated from your people. <verse eid="LEV 18:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 18:30"/>Do exactly what I require. When you arrive in Canaan, do not follow any of the practices of its people. I hate the things they do. Do not make yourselves “unclean” by doing them. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 18:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="LEV 19"/>
  <para style="s1">Other Laws</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 19:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 19:2"/>“Speak to the whole community of Israel. Tell them, ‘Be holy, because I am holy. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 19:3"/>“ ‘All of you must have respect for your mother and father. You must always keep my Sabbath days. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 19:4"/>“ ‘Do not turn away from me to worship statues of gods. Do not make for yourselves metal statues of gods. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 19:5"/>“ ‘Suppose you sacrifice a friendship offering to me. Then do it in the right way. And I will accept it from you. <verse eid="LEV 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 19:6"/>You must eat it on the same day you sacrifice it or on the next day. Anything left over until the third day must be burned up. <verse eid="LEV 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 19:7"/>If you eat any of it on the third day, it is not pure. I will not accept it. <verse eid="LEV 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 19:8"/>Whoever eats it will be held responsible. They have misused what is holy to me. They will be separated from their people.<verse eid="LEV 19:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 19:9"/>“ ‘Suppose you are harvesting your crops. Then do not harvest all the way to the edges of your field. And do not pick up the grain you missed. <verse eid="LEV 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 19:10"/>Do not go over your vineyard a second time. Do not pick up the grapes that have fallen to the ground. Leave them for poor people and outsiders. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 19:11"/>“ ‘Do not steal.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:11">“ ‘Do not tell lies.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:11">“ ‘Do not cheat one another.<verse eid="LEV 19:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 19:12"/>“ ‘Do not give your word in my name and then be a false witness. That would be treating the name of your God as if it were not holy. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 19:13"/>“ ‘Do not cheat your neighbor. Do not rob him.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:13">“ ‘Do not hold back the pay of a hired worker until morning.<verse eid="LEV 19:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 19:14"/>“ ‘Do not ask for bad things to happen to deaf people. Do not put anything in front of blind people that will make them trip. Instead, have respect for me. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 19:15"/>“ ‘Do not make something wrong appear to be right. Treat poor people and rich people in the same way. Do not favor one person over another. Instead, judge everyone fairly.<verse eid="LEV 19:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 19:16"/>“ ‘Do not go around spreading lies among your people.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:16">“ ‘Do not do anything that puts your neighbor’s life in danger. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 19:17"/>“ ‘Do not hate another Israelite in your heart. Correct your neighbor boldly when they do something wrong. Then you will not share their guilt.<verse eid="LEV 19:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 19:18"/>“ ‘Do not try to get even. Do not hold anything against any of your people. Instead, love your neighbor as you love yourself. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 19:19"/>“ ‘Obey my rules.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:19">“ ‘Do not let different kinds of animals mate with each other.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:19">“ ‘Do not mix two kinds of seeds and then plant them in your field.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:19">“ ‘Do not wear clothes that are made out of two kinds of cloth.<verse eid="LEV 19:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 19:20"/>“ ‘Suppose a man sleeps with a female slave. But she and another man have promised to get married to each other. And her freedom has not yet been paid for or given to her. Then she and the man who slept with her must be punished. But they must not be put to death, because she had not been set free. <verse eid="LEV 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 19:21"/>The man must bring a ram to the entrance to the tent of meeting. It is for a guilt offering to me. <verse eid="LEV 19:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 19:22"/>The priest must take the ram for the guilt offering. He must sacrifice it to pay for the man’s sin in my sight. Then his sin will be forgiven.<verse eid="LEV 19:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 19:23"/>“ ‘When you enter the land, suppose you plant a fruit tree. Then do not eat its fruit for the first three years. The fruit is “unclean.” <verse eid="LEV 19:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 19:24"/>In the fourth year all the fruit will be holy. Offer it as a way of showing praise to me. <verse eid="LEV 19:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 19:25"/>But in the fifth year you can eat the fruit. Then you will gather more and more fruit. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 19:26"/>“ ‘Do not eat any meat that still has blood in it.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:26">“ ‘Do not practice any kind of evil magic.<verse eid="LEV 19:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 19:27"/>“ ‘Do not cut the hair on the sides of your head. Do not clip off the edges of your beard.<verse eid="LEV 19:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 19:28"/>“ ‘Do not make cuts on your bodies when someone dies. Do not put marks on your skin. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 19:29"/>“ ‘Do not dishonor your daughter’s body by making a prostitute out of her. If you do, the Israelites will start going to prostitutes. The land will be filled with evil.<verse eid="LEV 19:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 19:30"/>“ ‘You must always keep my Sabbath days. Have respect for my sacred tent. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 19:31"/>“ ‘Do not look for advice from people who get messages from those who have died. Do not go to people who talk to the spirits of the dead. If you do, they will make you “unclean.” I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 19:32"/>“ ‘Stand up in order to show your respect for old people. Also have respect for me. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 19:33"/>“ ‘Suppose an outsider lives with you in your land. Then do not treat them badly. <verse eid="LEV 19:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 19:34"/>Treat them as if they were one of your own people. Love them as you love yourself. Remember that all of you were outsiders in Egypt. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 19:35"/>“ ‘Be honest when you measure lengths, weights or amounts. <verse eid="LEV 19:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 19:36"/>Use honest scales and honest weights. Use honest dry measures. And use honest liquid measures. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. I brought you out of Egypt.<verse eid="LEV 19:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 19:37"/>“ ‘Obey all my rules and laws. Follow them. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 19:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="LEV 20"/>
  <para style="s1">Israel Will Be Punished for Their Sins</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 20:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 20:2"/>“Say to the Israelites, ‘Suppose a person sacrifices one of his children to the god Molek. It does not matter whether that person is an Israelite or an outsider who lives in Israel. He must be put to death. The members of the community must kill him by throwing stones at him. <verse eid="LEV 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 20:3"/>I will turn against that man. I will separate him from his people. That’s because he has sacrificed his child to Molek. He has made my sacred tent “unclean.” He has treated my name as if it were not holy. <verse eid="LEV 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 20:4"/>Suppose the members of the community act like they don’t know that the man has sacrificed his child to Molek. And suppose they don’t put him to death. <verse eid="LEV 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 20:5"/>Then I will turn against that man and his family. I will separate them from their people. I will also separate all those who follow him by joining themselves to Molek. They are not faithful to me.<verse eid="LEV 20:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 20:6"/>“ ‘Suppose someone looks for advice from people who get messages from those who have died. Or they go to people who talk to the spirits of the dead. And they do what those people say. Then they have not been faithful to me. So I will turn against them. I will separate them from their people.<verse eid="LEV 20:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 20:7"/>“ ‘Set yourselves apart for me. Be holy, because I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="LEV 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 20:8"/>Obey my rules. Follow them. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. I make you holy.<verse eid="LEV 20:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 20:9"/>“ ‘Anyone who asks for bad things to happen to their father or mother must be put to death. They have cursed their father or mother. So anything that happens to them will be their own fault.<verse eid="LEV 20:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 20:10"/>“ ‘Suppose a man commits adultery with his neighbor’s wife. Then the man and the woman must be put to death.<verse eid="LEV 20:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 20:11"/>“ ‘Suppose a man has sex with his father’s wife. Then he has brought shame on his father. The man and the woman must be put to death. Anything that happens to them will be their own fault.<verse eid="LEV 20:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 20:12"/>“ ‘Suppose a man has sex with his daughter-in-law. Then they must be put to death. They have used sex in the wrong way. Anything that happens to them will be their own fault.<verse eid="LEV 20:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 20:13"/>“ ‘Suppose a man has sex with another man as he would have sex with a woman. I hate what they have done. They must be put to death. Anything that happens to them will be their own fault.<verse eid="LEV 20:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 20:14"/>“ ‘Suppose a man gets married to both a woman and her mother. That is evil. All of them must be burned to death. Then there will not be any evil among you.<verse eid="LEV 20:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 20:15"/>“ ‘Suppose a man has sex with an animal. Then he must be put to death. You must also kill the animal.<verse eid="LEV 20:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 20:16"/>“ ‘Suppose a woman has sex with an animal. Then kill the woman and the animal. They must be put to death. Anything that happens to them will be their own fault.<verse eid="LEV 20:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 20:17"/>“ ‘Suppose a man gets married to his sister and has sex with her. That is a shameful thing to do. It does not matter whether she is the daughter of his father or of his mother. They must be separated from their community in front of everyone. That man has brought shame on his sister. He will be responsible for what he has done.<verse eid="LEV 20:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 20:18"/>“ ‘Suppose a man has sex with a woman during her monthly period. He has uncovered the place where her bleeding was coming from. And she has let him do it. So both of them must be separated from their people.<verse eid="LEV 20:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 20:19"/>“ ‘Do not have sex with the sister of either your mother or your father. That would bring shame on a close relative. Both of you would be held responsible for what you have done.<verse eid="LEV 20:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 20:20"/>“ ‘Suppose a man has sex with his aunt. Then he has brought shame on his uncle. Both of them will be held accountable for what they have done. They will die without having any children.<verse eid="LEV 20:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 20:21"/>“ ‘Suppose a man gets married to his brother’s wife. That is something that should never be done. He has brought shame on his brother. Neither of them will have any children.<verse eid="LEV 20:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 20:22"/>“ ‘Obey all my rules and laws. Follow them. Then the land where I am bringing you to live will not throw you out. <verse eid="LEV 20:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 20:23"/>To make room for you, I am going to drive out the nations that are in the land. You must not follow the practices of those nations. I hated those nations because they did all those things. <verse eid="LEV 20:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 20:24"/>But I said to you, “You will take over their land as your own. I will give it to you. It will belong to you. It is a land that has plenty of milk and honey.” I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. I have set you apart from the other nations.<verse eid="LEV 20:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 20:25"/>“ ‘So you must be able to tell the difference between animals that are “clean” and those that are not. You must know which birds are “clean” and which are not. Do not make yourselves “unclean” by eating any “unclean” animal or bird. Do not make yourselves “unclean” by eating anything that moves along the ground. I have set all of them apart as “unclean” for you. <verse eid="LEV 20:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 20:26"/>You must be holy. You must be set apart to me. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. I am holy. I have set you apart from the other nations to be my own people.<verse eid="LEV 20:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 20:27"/>“ ‘Suppose a man or woman gets messages from those who have died. Or suppose a man or woman talks to the spirits of the dead. Then you must put that man or woman to death. You must kill them by throwing stones at them. Anything that happens to them will be their own fault.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 20:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="LEV 21"/>
  <para style="s1">Rules for Priests</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 21:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Moses, “Speak to the priests, the sons of Aaron. Tell them, ‘A priest must not make himself “unclean” by going near the dead body of any of his people. <verse eid="LEV 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 21:2"/>But he can go near the body of a close relative. It could be his mother, father, son, daughter or brother. <verse eid="LEV 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 21:3"/>He can also go near a sister who is not married. She would have depended on him because she did not have a husband. The priest can make himself “unclean” by going near her body. <verse eid="LEV 21:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 21:4"/>But he must not make himself “unclean” by going near the bodies of people only related to him by marriage. Going near them would make him “unclean.”<verse eid="LEV 21:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 21:5"/>“ ‘Priests must not shave any part of their heads. They must not shave off the edges of their beards. They must not make cuts on their bodies when someone dies. <verse eid="LEV 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 21:6"/>Priests must be holy. They must be set apart for me. I am their God. They must not treat my name as if it were not holy. They must be holy because they bring food offerings to me. That is my food.<verse eid="LEV 21:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 21:7"/>“ ‘They must not get married to women who are “unclean” because they are prostitutes. They must not marry women who are divorced from their husbands. That is because priests are holy. They are set apart for me. I am their God. <verse eid="LEV 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 21:8"/>Consider them as holy, because they offer up food to me. Consider them as holy, because I am holy. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. I make you holy.<verse eid="LEV 21:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 21:9"/>“ ‘Suppose a priest’s daughter makes herself “unclean” by becoming a prostitute. Then she brings shame on her father. She must be burned to death.<verse eid="LEV 21:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 21:10"/>“ ‘The high priest is the one among his brothers whose head has been anointed with olive oil. He has been appointed to wear the priest’s clothes. When someone dies, the high priest must not let his own hair hang loose. He must not tear his clothes to show how sad he is. <verse eid="LEV 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 21:11"/>He must not enter a place where there is a dead body. He must not make himself “unclean,” even if his father or mother dies. <verse eid="LEV 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 21:12"/>He must not leave the sacred tent of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> to take part in burying a body. That would bring shame on the tent. The anointing oil has set the high priest apart. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 21:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 21:13"/>“ ‘The woman the high priest gets married to must be a virgin. <verse eid="LEV 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 21:14"/>He must not marry a widow or a woman who is divorced. He must not marry a woman who is “unclean” because she is a prostitute. He must only marry a virgin. She must come from his own people. <verse eid="LEV 21:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 21:15"/>If he doesn’t marry a virgin, he makes the children he has by her “unclean.” I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. I make him holy.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 21:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 21:16"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 21:17"/>“Speak to Aaron. Tell him, ‘No man in your family line with any flaws may come near to offer food to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. This is true for all time to come. <verse eid="LEV 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 21:18"/>No man who has any flaws can come near. No man who is blind or disabled can come. No man whose body is scarred or twisted can come. <verse eid="LEV 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 21:19"/>No man whose foot or hand is disabled can come. <verse eid="LEV 21:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 21:20"/>No man whose back is bent can come. No man who is too short can come. No man who has anything wrong with his eyes can come. No man who has boils or running sores can come. No man whose sex glands are crushed can come. <verse eid="LEV 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 21:21"/>No man with any flaws who is in the family line of Aaron the priest may come near me. He can’t come to bring the food offerings to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. If he has any flaws, he must not come near to offer food to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 21:22"/>He can eat the holy food. He can also eat my very holy food. <verse eid="LEV 21:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 21:23"/>But because he has a flaw, he must not go near the curtain or approach the altar. If he does, he will make my sacred tent “unclean.” I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. I make everything holy.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 21:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 21:24"/>So Moses told all these things to Aaron and his sons. He also told them to all the Israelites.<verse eid="LEV 21:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="LEV 22"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 22:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 22:2"/>“Here is what I want you to tell Aaron and his sons. Tell them to treat the sacred offerings with respect. They are the offerings the Israelites set apart to honor me. So Aaron and his sons must never treat my name as if it were not holy. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 22:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 22:3"/>“Say to them, ‘Suppose a man in your family line is “unclean.” And suppose he comes near the sacred offerings. They are the offerings the Israelites set apart to honor me. That man must not be allowed to serve me as a priest. That applies for all time to come. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 22:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 22:4"/>“ ‘Suppose a man in Aaron’s family line has a skin disease. Or suppose liquid waste is flowing out of his body. Then he can’t eat the sacred offerings until he is made pure and clean. Suppose he touches something made “unclean” by coming near a dead body. Or suppose he touches someone who has semen flowing from his body. Then he will be “unclean.” <verse eid="LEV 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 22:5"/>Or suppose he touches any crawling thing that makes him “unclean.” Or suppose he touches any person who makes him “unclean.” It does not matter what “unclean” thing he touches. It will make him “unclean.” <verse eid="LEV 22:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 22:6"/>The one who touches anything of that kind will be “unclean” until evening. He must not eat any of the sacred offerings unless he has taken a bath. <verse eid="LEV 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 22:7"/>When the sun goes down, he will be “clean.” After that, he can eat the sacred offerings. They are his food. <verse eid="LEV 22:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 22:8"/>He must not eat anything found dead or torn apart by wild animals. If he does, it will make him “unclean.” I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 22:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 22:9"/>“ ‘The priests must do what I require. But suppose they make fun of what I require. Then they will become guilty and die. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. I make them holy.<verse eid="LEV 22:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 22:10"/>“ ‘Only a member of a priest’s family can eat the sacred offering. The guest of a priest can’t eat it. A priest’s hired worker can’t eat it either. <verse eid="LEV 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 22:11"/>But suppose a priest buys a slave with money. Or suppose slaves are born in his house. Then they can eat the sacred food. <verse eid="LEV 22:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 22:12"/>Suppose a priest’s daughter marries someone who is not a priest. Then she can’t eat any of the food brought as a sacred gift. <verse eid="LEV 22:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 22:13"/>But suppose the priest’s daughter becomes a widow or is divorced. She does not have any children. And she returns to live in her father’s house, where she lived when she was young. Then she can eat her father’s food. But a person who does not belong to a priest’s family can’t eat any of it.<verse eid="LEV 22:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 22:14"/>“ ‘Suppose someone eats a sacred offering by mistake. Then they must pay back the priest for the offering. They must also add a fifth of its value to it. <verse eid="LEV 22:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 22:15"/>The priests must not allow the sacred offerings to become “unclean.” They are the offerings the Israelites bring to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 22:16"/>The priests must not allow the offerings to become “unclean” by letting the people eat them. If they do, they will bring guilt on the people. They will have to pay for what they have done. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. I make them holy.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 22:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Sacrifices the <char style="nd">Lord</char> Does Not Accept</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 22:17"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 22:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 22:18"/>“Speak to Aaron and his sons. Speak to all the Israelites. Tell them, ‘Suppose any of you brings a gift for a burnt offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It does not matter whether you are an Israelite or an outsider who lives in Israel. It does not matter whether you bring the offering to keep a promise or because you choose to give it. <verse eid="LEV 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 22:19"/>You must bring a male animal without any flaws if you want the <char style="nd">Lord</char> to accept it from you. It does not matter whether it is from your cattle, sheep or goats. <verse eid="LEV 22:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 22:20"/>Do not bring an animal that has any flaws. If you do, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will not accept it from you. <verse eid="LEV 22:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 22:21"/>Suppose any of you brings an animal for a friendship offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Then it must not have any flaws at all. If it does, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will not accept it. It does not matter whether the animal is from your herd or flock. It does not matter whether you bring it to keep a promise or because you choose to give it. <verse eid="LEV 22:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 22:22"/>Do not offer a blind animal to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Do not bring a hurt or wounded animal. And do not offer one that has warts or boils or running sores. Do not place any of them on the altar as a food offering presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 22:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 22:23"/>But suppose you bring an offering you choose to give. Then you can bring an ox or a sheep whose body is twisted or too small. But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will not accept it if you offer it to keep a promise. <verse eid="LEV 22:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 22:24"/>You must not offer the <char style="nd">Lord</char> a male animal whose sex glands have been hurt. The glands also must not be crushed, torn or cut. You must not offer that kind of animal in your own land. <verse eid="LEV 22:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 22:25"/>And you must not accept that kind of animal from someone who comes from another land. You must not offer it as food for your God. He will not accept it from you. Its body is twisted and has flaws.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 22:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 22:26"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 22:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 22:27"/>“When a calf, lamb or goat is born, it must remain with its mother for seven days. From the eighth day on, I will accept it as a food offering presented to me. <verse eid="LEV 22:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 22:28"/>Do not kill a cow and its calf on the same day. Do not kill a female sheep and its lamb on the same day.<verse eid="LEV 22:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 22:29"/>“Sacrifice a thank offering to me in the right way. Then I will accept it from you. <verse eid="LEV 22:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 22:30"/>You must eat it that same day. Do not leave any of it until morning. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 22:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 22:31"/>“Obey my commands. Follow them. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 22:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 22:32"/>Do not treat my name as if it were not holy. The Israelites must recognize me as the holy God. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. I made you holy. <verse eid="LEV 22:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 22:33"/>I brought you out of Egypt to be your God. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.”<verse eid="LEV 22:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="LEV 23"/>
  <para style="s1">The Appointed Feast Days</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 23:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 23:2"/>“Speak to the Israelites. Tell them, ‘Here are my appointed feast days. They are the appointed feast days of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Tell the people that they must come together for these sacred assemblies.<verse eid="LEV 23:2"/></para>
  <para style="s2">The Sabbath Day</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 23:3"/>“ ‘There are six days when you can work. But the seventh day is a day of sabbath rest. You must rest on it. Come together on that sacred day. You must not do any work on it. No matter where you live, it is a Sabbath day to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 23:3"/></para>
  <para style="s2">Passover and Unleavened Bread</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 23:4"/>“ ‘Here are the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s appointed feasts. Tell the people that they must come together for these sacred gatherings at their appointed times. <verse eid="LEV 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 23:5"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s Passover begins when the sun goes down on the 14th day of the first month. <verse eid="LEV 23:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 23:6"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s Feast of Unleavened Bread begins on the 15th day of that month. For seven days you must eat bread made without yeast. <verse eid="LEV 23:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 23:7"/>On the first day you must come together for a special service. Do not do any regular work on that day. <verse eid="LEV 23:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 23:8"/>On each of the seven days bring a food offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. On the seventh day come together for a special service. Do not do any regular work on that day.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 23:8"/></para>
  <para style="s2">The First Share of Israel’s Crops Belongs to the <char style="nd">Lord</char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 23:9"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 23:10"/>“Speak to the Israelites. Tell them, ‘When you enter the land I am going to give you, bring an offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Gather your crops. Bring the first bundle of grain to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 23:11"/>He must lift up the grain and wave it in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will accept it from you. The priest must wave it on the day after the Sabbath. <verse eid="LEV 23:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 23:12"/>On the day he waves the grain for you, you must sacrifice a burnt offering to me. It must be a lamb that does not have any flaws. It must be a year old. <verse eid="LEV 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 23:13"/>You must bring it together with its grain offering. The grain offering must be seven pounds of the finest flour. Mix it with olive oil. It is a food offering presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It has a pleasant smell. You must offer a drink offering along with the burnt offering. It must be a quart of wine. <verse eid="LEV 23:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 23:14"/>You must not eat any bread until the day you bring your offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. You must not eat any cooked grain or any of your first grain until that time. This is a law that will last for all time to come. It applies no matter where you live.<verse eid="LEV 23:14"/></para>
  <para style="s2">The Feast of Weeks</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 23:15"/>“ ‘The day you brought the grain for the wave offering was the day after the Sabbath. Count off seven full weeks from that day. <verse eid="LEV 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 23:16"/>Count off 50 days up to the day after the seventh Sabbath. On that day bring to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> an offering of your first grain. <verse eid="LEV 23:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 23:17"/>Bring two loaves of bread that are made with seven pounds of the finest flour. They must be baked with yeast. Bring them to me as a wave offering from the first share of your crops. That applies no matter where you live. <verse eid="LEV 23:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 23:18"/>Together with the bread, bring seven male lambs. Each lamb must be a year old. It must not have any flaws. Also bring one young bull and two rams. They will be a burnt offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They will be offered together with their grain offerings and drink offerings. They are food offerings. Their smell pleases the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 23:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 23:19"/>Then sacrifice one male goat for a sin offering. Also sacrifice two lambs for a friendship offering. Each of the lambs must be a year old. <verse eid="LEV 23:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 23:20"/>The priest must lift up the two lambs and wave them in front of me as a wave offering. He must offer them together with the bread made out of the first share of your crops. They are a sacred offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They will be given to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 23:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 23:21"/>On that same day tell the people that they must come together for a special worship service. They must not do any regular work. That is a law that will last for all time to come. It applies no matter where you live.<verse eid="LEV 23:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 23:22"/>“ ‘Suppose you are gathering your crops. Then do not harvest all the way to the edges of your field. And do not pick up the grain you missed. Leave some for the poor people and the outsiders who live among you. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 23:22"/></para>
  <para style="s2">The Feast of Trumpets</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 23:23"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 23:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 23:24"/>“Say to the Israelites, ‘On the first day of the seventh month you must have a day of sabbath rest. It must be a special service announced with trumpet blasts. <verse eid="LEV 23:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 23:25"/>Do not do any regular work on that day. Instead, bring a food offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 23:25"/></para>
  <para style="s2">The Day When Sin Is Paid For</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 23:26"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 23:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 23:27"/>“The tenth day of the seventh month is the day when sin is paid for. Come together for a special service. Do not eat any food. Bring a food offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 23:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 23:28"/>Do not do any work on that day. It is the day when sin is paid for. On that day your sin will be paid for in my sight. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="LEV 23:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 23:29"/>Suppose you do eat food on that day. Then you will be separated from your people. <verse eid="LEV 23:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 23:30"/>I will destroy anyone among your people who does any work on that day. <verse eid="LEV 23:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 23:31"/>You must not do any work at all. This is a law that will last for all time to come. It applies no matter where you live. <verse eid="LEV 23:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 23:32"/>That day is a day of sabbath rest for you. You must rest on it. You must not eat anything on that day. You must follow the rules of the sabbath rest. Follow them from the evening of the ninth day of the month until the following evening.”<verse eid="LEV 23:32"/></para>
  <para style="s2">The Feast of Booths</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 23:33"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 23:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 23:34"/>“Say to the Israelites, ‘On the 15th day of the seventh month the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s Feast of Booths begins. It lasts for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 23:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 23:35"/>On the first day you must come together for a special service. Do not do any regular work on that day. <verse eid="LEV 23:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 23:36"/>On each of the seven days bring a food offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. On the eighth day come together for a special service. Bring a food offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. That special service is the closing service. Do not do any regular work on that day.<verse eid="LEV 23:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 23:37"/>“ ‘These are the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s appointed feasts. Tell the people that they must come together for these sacred assemblies. During those times, the people must bring food offerings to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They are burnt offerings and grain offerings. They are sacrifices and drink offerings. Each offering must be brought at its required time. <verse eid="LEV 23:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 23:38"/>The offerings are in addition to those of the days of sabbath rest. The offerings are also in addition to your gifts and anything you have promised. They are also in addition to all the offerings you choose to give to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 23:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 23:39"/>“ ‘Begin with the 15th day of the seventh month. That is after you have gathered your crops. On that day celebrate the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s Feast of Booths for seven days. The first day is a day of rest. The eighth day is also a day of rest. <verse eid="LEV 23:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LEV 23:40"/>On the first day you must get branches from palms, willows and other leafy trees. You must be filled with joy in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 23:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LEV 23:41"/>Celebrate the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s Feast of Booths for seven days each year. This is a law that will last for all time to come. Celebrate the feast in the seventh month. <verse eid="LEV 23:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 23:42"/>Live in booths for seven days. All the Israelites must live in booths. <verse eid="LEV 23:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 23:43"/>Then your children after you will know that I made the Israelites live in booths. I made them do it after I brought them out of Egypt. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 23:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 23:44"/>So Moses announced to the Israelites the appointed feasts of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 23:44"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="LEV 24"/>
  <para style="s1">Olive Oil, Bread and Incense</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 24:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 24:2"/>“Command the Israelites to bring you clear oil made from pressed olives. Use it to keep the lamps burning and giving light all the time. <verse eid="LEV 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 24:3"/>Aaron must take care of the lamps in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> from evening until morning all the time. This is a law that will last for all time to come. The lamps are outside the curtain in front of the tablets of the covenant law in the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 24:4"/>The lamps are on the pure gold lampstand in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They must be taken care of all the time.<verse eid="LEV 24:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 24:5"/>“Get the finest flour and bake 12 loaves of bread. Use seven pounds of flour for each loaf. <verse eid="LEV 24:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 24:6"/>Arrange them in two stacks. Put six loaves in each stack on the table made out of pure gold. The table stands in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 24:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 24:7"/>By each stack put some pure incense. It will remind you that all good things come from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Burn the incense in place of the bread. The incense is a food offering presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 24:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 24:8"/>The bread must be set out in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> regularly. Do it every Sabbath day. It will be Israel’s duty to provide it for all time to come. <verse eid="LEV 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 24:9"/>The bread belongs to Aaron and his sons. They must eat it in the holy area. It is a very holy part of their regular share of the food offerings presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.”<verse eid="LEV 24:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">A Person Who Speaks Evil Is Put to Death</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 24:10"/>There was a man who had an Israelite mother. His father was born in Egypt. The man went out among the Israelites. A fight broke out in the camp between him and an Israelite. <verse eid="LEV 24:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 24:11"/>The son of the Israelite woman spoke evil things against the <char style="nd">Lord</char> by using a curse. So the people brought him to Moses. The name of the man’s mother was Shelomith. She was the daughter of Dibri. Dibri was from the tribe of Dan. <verse eid="LEV 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 24:12"/>The people kept her son under guard until they could find out what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> wanted them to do.<verse eid="LEV 24:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 24:13"/>Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses. He said, <verse eid="LEV 24:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 24:14"/>“Get the man who spoke evil things against the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Take him outside the camp. All those who heard him say those things must place their hands on his head. Then the whole community must kill him by throwing stones at him. <verse eid="LEV 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 24:15"/>Say to the Israelites, ‘Anyone who curses me will be held accountable. <verse eid="LEV 24:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 24:16"/>Anyone who speaks evil things against my Name must be put to death. The whole community must kill them by throwing stones at them. It does not matter whether they are an outsider or an Israelite. When they speak evil things against my Name, they must be put to death.<verse eid="LEV 24:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 24:17"/>“ ‘Anyone who kills another human being must be put to death. <verse eid="LEV 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 24:18"/>Anyone who kills someone’s animal must pay its owner. A life must be taken for a life. <verse eid="LEV 24:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 24:19"/>Suppose someone hurts their neighbor. Then what they have done must be done to them. <verse eid="LEV 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 24:20"/>A bone must be broken for a bone. An eye must be put out for an eye. A tooth must be knocked out for a tooth. The one who has hurt his neighbor must be hurt in the same way. <verse eid="LEV 24:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 24:21"/>Whoever kills an animal must pay its owner. But if they kill a human being, they must be put to death. <verse eid="LEV 24:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 24:22"/>The same law applies whether they are an outsider or an Israelite. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 24:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 24:23"/>Then Moses spoke to the Israelites. They got the man who had spoken evil things against the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They took him outside the camp. There they killed him by throwing stones at him. The Israelites did just as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded Moses.<verse eid="LEV 24:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 24"/>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="LEV 25"/>
  <para style="s1">The Sabbath Year</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 25:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses at Mount Sinai. He said, <verse eid="LEV 25:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 25:2"/>“Speak to the Israelites. Tell them, ‘You will enter the land I am going to give you. When you do, you must honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char> every seventh year by not farming the land that year. <verse eid="LEV 25:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 25:3"/>For six years plant your fields. Trim the branches in your vineyards and gather your crops. <verse eid="LEV 25:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 25:4"/>But the seventh year must be a year of sabbath rest for the land. The land must rest during it. It is a sabbath year to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Do not plant your fields. Do not trim the branches in your vineyards. <verse eid="LEV 25:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 25:5"/>Do not gather what grows without being planted. And do not gather the grapes from the vines you have not taken care of. The land must have a year of rest. <verse eid="LEV 25:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 25:6"/>Anything the land produces during the sabbath year will be food for you. It will be for you and your male and female servants. Your hired workers will eat it. So will people who live with you for a while. <verse eid="LEV 25:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 25:7"/>And so will your livestock and the wild animals that are in your land. Anything the land produces can be eaten.<verse eid="LEV 25:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Year of Jubilee</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 25:8"/>“ ‘Count off seven sabbath years. Count off seven times seven years. The seven sabbath years add up to a total of 49 years. <verse eid="LEV 25:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 25:9"/>The tenth day of the seventh month is the day when sin is paid for. On that day blow the trumpet all through your land. <verse eid="LEV 25:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 25:10"/>Set the 50th year apart. Announce freedom all over the land to everyone who lives there. The 50th year will be a Year of Jubilee for you. Each of you must return to your own family property. And each of you must return to your own tribe. <verse eid="LEV 25:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 25:11"/>The 50th year will be a Year of Jubilee for you. Do not plant anything. Do not gather what grows without being planted. And do not gather the grapes from the vines you have not taken care of. <verse eid="LEV 25:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 25:12"/>It is a Year of Jubilee. It will be holy for you. Eat only what the fields produce.<verse eid="LEV 25:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 25:13"/>“ ‘In the Year of Jubilee all of you must return to your own property.<verse eid="LEV 25:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 25:14"/>“ ‘Suppose you sell land to any of your own people. Or you buy land from them. Then do not take advantage of each other. <verse eid="LEV 25:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 25:15"/>The price you pay must be based on the number of years since the last Year of Jubilee. Here is how the price you charge must be decided. It must be based on the number of years left for gathering crops before the next Year of Jubilee. <verse eid="LEV 25:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 25:16"/>When there are many years left, you must raise the price. When there are only a few years left, you must lower the price. That is because what is really being sold to you is the number of crops the land will produce. <verse eid="LEV 25:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 25:17"/>Do not take advantage of each other. Instead, have respect for your God. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 25:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 25:18"/>“ ‘Follow my rules. Be careful to obey my laws. Then you will live safely in the land. <verse eid="LEV 25:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 25:19"/>The land will produce its fruit. You will eat as much as you want. And you will live there in safety. <verse eid="LEV 25:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 25:20"/>Suppose you say, “In the seventh year we will not plant anything or gather our crops. So what will we eat?” <verse eid="LEV 25:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 25:21"/>I will send you a great blessing in the sixth year. The land will produce enough for three years. <verse eid="LEV 25:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 25:22"/>While you plant during the eighth year, you will eat food from the old crop. You will continue to eat food from it until the crops from the ninth year are gathered.<verse eid="LEV 25:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 25:23"/>“ ‘The land must not be sold without a way of getting it back. That is because it belongs to me. You are only outsiders and strangers in my land. <verse eid="LEV 25:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 25:24"/>You must make sure that you can buy the land back. That applies to all the land that belongs to you.<verse eid="LEV 25:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 25:25"/>“ ‘Suppose one of your own people becomes poor. And suppose they have to sell some of their land. Then their nearest relative must come and buy back what they have sold. <verse eid="LEV 25:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 25:26"/>But suppose they do not have anyone to buy it back for them. And suppose things go well for them and they earn enough money to buy it back themselves. <verse eid="LEV 25:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 25:27"/>Then they must decide how much the crops have become worth since the time they sold the land. They must take that amount off the price the land was sold for. They must give the one selling it back to them the money that is left. Then they can go back to their own property. <verse eid="LEV 25:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 25:28"/>But suppose they have not earned enough money to pay them back. Then the buyer they sold the land to will keep it until the Year of Jubilee. At that time it will be returned to them. Then they can go back to their property.<verse eid="LEV 25:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 25:29"/>“ ‘Suppose someone sells a house in a city that has a wall around it. Then for a full year after they sell it they have the right to buy it back. <verse eid="LEV 25:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 25:30"/>But suppose they do not buy it back before the full year has passed. Then the house in the walled city will continue to belong to the buyer and the buyer’s children. It will not be returned to the seller in the Year of Jubilee. <verse eid="LEV 25:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 25:31"/>But houses in villages that do not have walls around them must be treated like property outside walled cities. Those houses can be bought back at any time. And they must be returned in the Year of Jubilee.<verse eid="LEV 25:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 25:32"/>“ ‘The Levites always have the right to buy back their houses in the towns that belong to them. <verse eid="LEV 25:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 25:33"/>So their property among the Israelites can be bought back. That applies to a house sold in any of their towns. Any house that is sold must be returned to its original owner in the Year of Jubilee. That is because the houses of the Levites will always belong to them. <verse eid="LEV 25:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 25:34"/>But the grasslands around their towns must never be sold. They will belong to them for all time to come.<verse eid="LEV 25:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 25:35"/>“ ‘Suppose any of your own people become poor. And suppose they can’t take care of themselves. Then help them just as you would help an outsider or a stranger. In that way, the poor can continue to live among you. <verse eid="LEV 25:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 25:36"/>Do not charge them interest of any kind. Instead, have respect for God. Then those who have become poor can continue to live among you. <verse eid="LEV 25:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 25:37"/>If you lend them money, you must not charge them interest. And you must not sell them food for more than it cost you. <verse eid="LEV 25:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 25:38"/>I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. I brought you out of Egypt. I did it to give you the land of Canaan. I wanted to be your God.<verse eid="LEV 25:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 25:39"/>“ ‘Suppose any of your own people become poor. And suppose they sell themselves to you. Then do not make them work as slaves. <verse eid="LEV 25:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LEV 25:40"/>You must treat them like hired workers. Or you must treat them like those living among you for a while. They must work for you until the Year of Jubilee. <verse eid="LEV 25:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LEV 25:41"/>Then they and their children must be set free. They will go back to their own tribes. They will go back to the property their people have always owned. <verse eid="LEV 25:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 25:42"/>The Israelites are my servants. I brought them out of Egypt. So they must not be sold as slaves. <verse eid="LEV 25:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 25:43"/>Show them pity when you rule over them. Have respect for God.<verse eid="LEV 25:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 25:44"/>“ ‘You must get your male and female slaves from the nations that are around you. You can buy slaves from them. <verse eid="LEV 25:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LEV 25:45"/>You can also buy as slaves some of the people living among you for a while. You can also buy members of their families born among you. They will become your property. <verse eid="LEV 25:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LEV 25:46"/>You can leave them to your children as their share of your property. You can make them slaves for life. But when you rule over your own people, you must be kind to them.<verse eid="LEV 25:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="LEV 25:47"/>“ ‘Suppose an outsider living among you for a while becomes rich. Then suppose any of your own people become poor. Then they sell themselves to the outsider living among you. Or they sell themselves to a member of the outsider’s family. <verse eid="LEV 25:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LEV 25:48"/>Then they keep the right to buy themselves back after they have sold themselves. One of their relatives can buy them back. <verse eid="LEV 25:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LEV 25:49"/>An uncle or a cousin can buy them back after they have sold themselves. In fact, any relative in their tribe can do it. Or suppose things go well for them. Then they can buy themselves back. <verse eid="LEV 25:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LEV 25:50"/>They and their buyer must count the number of years from the time of the sale up to the Year of Jubilee. The price for their freedom must be based on the amount paid to a hired man for that number of years. <verse eid="LEV 25:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LEV 25:51"/>Suppose there are many years until the Year of Jubilee. Then for their freedom they must pay a larger share of the price paid for them. <verse eid="LEV 25:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LEV 25:52"/>But suppose there are only a few years left until the Year of Jubilee. Then they must count the number of years that are left. The payment for their freedom must be based on that number. <verse eid="LEV 25:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LEV 25:53"/>They must be treated as workers hired from year to year. You must make sure that those they must work for are kind to them when they rule over them.<verse eid="LEV 25:53"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="LEV 25:54"/>“ ‘Suppose they are not bought back in any of those ways. Then they and their children must still be set free in the Year of Jubilee. <verse eid="LEV 25:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LEV 25:55"/>That’s because the Israelites belong to me. They are my servants. I brought them out of Egypt. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 25:55"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 25"/>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="LEV 26"/>
  <para style="s1">Rewards for Obeying the <char style="nd">Lord</char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 26:1"/>“ ‘Do not make statues of gods for yourselves. Do not set up a likeness of a god or a sacred stone for yourselves. Do not place a carved stone in your land and bow down in front of it. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 26:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 26:2"/>“ ‘You must always keep my Sabbath days. Have respect for my sacred tent. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 26:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 26:3"/>“ ‘Follow my rules. Be careful to obey my commands. <verse eid="LEV 26:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 26:4"/>Then I will send you rain at the right time. The ground will produce its crops. The trees will bear their fruit. <verse eid="LEV 26:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 26:5"/>You will continue to harvest your grain until you gather your grapes. You will continue to gather your grapes until you plant your crops. You will have all you want to eat. And you will live in safety in your land.<verse eid="LEV 26:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 26:6"/>“ ‘I will give you peace in the land. You will be able to sleep because no one will make you afraid. I will remove wild animals from the land. There will not be any war in your country. <verse eid="LEV 26:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 26:7"/>You will hunt down your enemies. You will kill them with your swords. <verse eid="LEV 26:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 26:8"/>Five of you will chase 100. And 100 of you will chase 10,000. You will kill your enemies with your swords.<verse eid="LEV 26:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 26:9"/>“ ‘I will bless you. I will give you many children so that there will be many of you. And I will be faithful to the covenant I made with you. <verse eid="LEV 26:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 26:10"/>You will still be eating last year’s crops when you will have to make room for new crops. <verse eid="LEV 26:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 26:11"/>I will live among you. I will not turn away from you. <verse eid="LEV 26:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 26:12"/>I will walk among you. I will be your God. And you will be my people. <verse eid="LEV 26:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 26:13"/>I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. I brought you out of Egypt. I did not want you to be slaves in Egypt anymore. I threw off your heavy load. I helped you walk with your heads held high.<verse eid="LEV 26:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Punishment for Not Obeying the <char style="nd">Lord</char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 26:14"/>“ ‘On the other hand, suppose you do not listen to me. Suppose you do not carry out all my commands. <verse eid="LEV 26:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 26:15"/>Suppose you say no to my rules and turn away from my laws. And suppose you break my covenant by failing to carry out all my commands. <verse eid="LEV 26:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 26:16"/>Then here is what I will do to you. All at once I will bring terror on you. I will send sicknesses that will make you weak. I will send fever that will destroy your sight. It will slowly take your strength away. When you plant seeds, it will not do you any good. Instead, your enemies will eat what you have planted. <verse eid="LEV 26:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 26:17"/>I will turn against you. Then your enemies will win the battle over you. Those who hate you will rule over you. You will run away even when no one is chasing you.<verse eid="LEV 26:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 26:18"/>“ ‘After all that, suppose you still will not listen to me. Then I will punish you for your sins seven times. <verse eid="LEV 26:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 26:19"/>I will break down your stubborn pride. I will make the sky above you like iron, and it will not rain. I will make the ground under you like bronze, and you will not be able to farm it. <verse eid="LEV 26:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 26:20"/>You will work with all your strength, but it will not do you any good. That is because your soil will not produce any crops. The trees of your land will not bear any fruit.<verse eid="LEV 26:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 26:21"/>“ ‘Suppose you continue to be my enemy. And suppose you still refuse to listen to me. Then I will multiply your troubles many times because of your sins. <verse eid="LEV 26:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 26:22"/>I will send wild animals against you. They will kill your children. They will destroy your cattle. There will be so few of you left that your roads will be deserted.<verse eid="LEV 26:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 26:23"/>“ ‘After all those things, suppose you still do not accept my warnings. And suppose you continue to be my enemy. <verse eid="LEV 26:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 26:24"/>Then I myself will be your enemy. I will make you suffer again and again for your sins. <verse eid="LEV 26:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 26:25"/>I will send war against you to punish you for breaking my covenant. When you go back into your cities, I will send a plague among you. You will be handed over to your enemies. <verse eid="LEV 26:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 26:26"/>I will cut off your supply of bread. Ten women will need only one oven to bake your bread. They will weigh out the bread piece by piece. Even when you eat all of it, it will not be enough to satisfy you.<verse eid="LEV 26:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 26:27"/>“ ‘After all that, suppose you still do not listen to me. And suppose you continue to be my enemy. <verse eid="LEV 26:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 26:28"/>Then I will be angry with you. I will be your enemy. I myself will again punish you for your sins over and over. <verse eid="LEV 26:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 26:29"/>You will eat the dead bodies of your sons. You will also eat the dead bodies of your daughters. <verse eid="LEV 26:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 26:30"/>I will destroy the high places where you worship other gods. I will pull down your incense altars. I will pile up your dead bodies on the lifeless statues of your gods. And I will turn away from you. <verse eid="LEV 26:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 26:31"/>I will completely destroy your cities. I will destroy your places of worship. The pleasant smell of your offerings will not give me any delight. <verse eid="LEV 26:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 26:32"/>I myself will destroy your land so completely that your enemies who live there will be shocked. <verse eid="LEV 26:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 26:33"/>I will scatter you among the nations. I will pull out my sword and hunt you down. Your land and your cities will be completely destroyed. <verse eid="LEV 26:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 26:34"/>Then the deserted land will enjoy its sabbath years. It will rest. It will not be farmed. It will enjoy its sabbaths. But you will become prisoners in the country of your enemies. <verse eid="LEV 26:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 26:35"/>The land will rest the whole time it is deserted. It was not able to rest during the sabbaths you lived in it.<verse eid="LEV 26:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 26:36"/>“ ‘Some of you will be left in the lands of your enemies. I will fill your hearts with fear. The sound of a leaf blown by the wind will scare you away. You will run as if you were escaping from swords. You will fall down, even though no one is chasing you. <verse eid="LEV 26:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 26:37"/>You will trip over one another as if you were running away from the battle. You will run away, even though no one is chasing you. You will not be able to stand and fight against your enemies. <verse eid="LEV 26:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 26:38"/>While you are still scattered among the nations, you will die. The lands of your enemies will destroy you. <verse eid="LEV 26:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 26:39"/>You who are left in those lands will become weaker and weaker. You will die because of your sins and the sins of your people who lived before you.<verse eid="LEV 26:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="LEV 26:40"/>“ ‘But suppose you admit that both you and your people who lived before you have sinned. You admit the evil and dishonest things you have done against me. And you admit you have become my enemy. <verse eid="LEV 26:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LEV 26:41"/>What you did made me become your enemy. I let your enemies take you into their land. But suppose you stop being stubborn. You stop being proud. And you pay for your sin. <verse eid="LEV 26:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 26:42"/>Then I will remember my covenant with Jacob. I will remember my covenant with Isaac. I will remember my covenant with Abraham. I will remember what I said to them about the land. <verse eid="LEV 26:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 26:43"/>You will leave the land. It will enjoy its sabbaths while it lies deserted because you are not there. You will pay for your sins because you said no to my laws. You turned away from my rules. <verse eid="LEV 26:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 26:44"/>But even after all that, I will not say no to you or turn away from you. I will not destroy you completely in the land of your enemies. I will not break my covenant with you. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="LEV 26:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LEV 26:45"/>Because of you, I will remember the covenant I made with the people of Israel who lived before you. I brought them out of Egypt to be their God. The nations saw me do it. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 26:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="LEV 26:46"/>These are the orders, the laws and the rules of the covenant the <char style="nd">Lord</char> made on Mount Sinai. He made it between himself and the Israelites through Moses.<verse eid="LEV 26:46"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 26"/>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="LEV 27"/>
  <para style="s1">Keep Your Promises to the <char style="nd">Lord</char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 27:1"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 27:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 27:2"/>“Speak to the Israelites. Tell them, ‘Suppose someone makes a special promise to set a person apart to serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Here is how much it will cost to set that person free from the promise to serve. <verse eid="LEV 27:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 27:3"/>The cost for a male between the ages of twenty and sixty is 20 ounces of silver. It must be weighed out in keeping with the standard weights that are used in the sacred tent. <verse eid="LEV 27:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 27:4"/>The cost for a female of the same age is 12 ounces of silver. <verse eid="LEV 27:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 27:5"/>The cost for a male between the ages of five and twenty is 8 ounces of silver. The cost for a female of the same age is 4 ounces of silver. <verse eid="LEV 27:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 27:6"/>The cost for a male between the ages of one month and five years is 2 ounces of silver. The cost for a female of the same age is 1 ounce of silver. <verse eid="LEV 27:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 27:7"/>The cost for a male who is sixty years old or more is 6 ounces of silver. The cost for a female of the same age is 4 ounces of silver. <verse eid="LEV 27:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 27:8"/>But suppose the one who makes the special promise is too poor to pay the required amount. Then they must bring to the priest the person who will be set free. The priest will decide the right value for that person. It will be based on how much the one who makes the promise can afford.<verse eid="LEV 27:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 27:9"/>“ ‘Suppose what they promised is an animal that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will accept as an offering. Then the animal given to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> becomes holy. <verse eid="LEV 27:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 27:10"/>The one who makes the promise must not trade it. They must not trade a good animal for a bad one. And they must not trade a bad animal for a good one. Suppose they choose one animal instead of another. Then both animals become holy. <verse eid="LEV 27:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 27:11"/>Suppose the animal they promised is not “clean.” Suppose the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will not accept it as an offering. Then the animal must be brought to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 27:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 27:12"/>He will decide whether it is good or bad. Its value will be what he decides it will be. <verse eid="LEV 27:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 27:13"/>Suppose the owner wants to buy the animal back. Then a fifth must be added to its cost.<verse eid="LEV 27:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 27:14"/>“ ‘Suppose someone sets apart their house as something holy to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Then the priest will decide whether it is good or bad. Its value will remain what he decides it will be. <verse eid="LEV 27:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 27:15"/>Suppose the person sets apart their house. And suppose later they want to buy it back. Then they must add a fifth to its value. The house will belong to them again.<verse eid="LEV 27:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 27:16"/>“ ‘Suppose someone sets apart a piece of their family’s land to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Then here is how its value must be decided. It must be based on the number of seeds that are required to grow a full crop on it. That value will be 20 ounces of silver for every 300 pounds of barley seeds. <verse eid="LEV 27:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 27:17"/>Suppose they set apart their field during the Year of Jubilee. Then the value that has been decided will not be changed. <verse eid="LEV 27:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 27:18"/>But suppose they set apart their field after the Year of Jubilee. Then here is how the priest will decide its value. It will be based on the number of years that are left until the next Year of Jubilee. The value decided will be reduced. <verse eid="LEV 27:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 27:19"/>Suppose the one who set apart their field wants to buy it back. Then they must add a fifth to its value. The field will belong to them again. <verse eid="LEV 27:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 27:20"/>But suppose they do not buy back the field. Instead, suppose they sell it to someone else. Then they can never buy it back. <verse eid="LEV 27:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 27:21"/>When the field is set free in the Year of Jubilee, it will become holy. It will be like a field set apart to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It will become the property of the priests.<verse eid="LEV 27:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 27:22"/>“ ‘Suppose someone sets apart to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> a field they have bought. And suppose it is not part of their family’s land. <verse eid="LEV 27:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 27:23"/>Then here is how the priest will decide its value. It will be based on the number of years that are left until the Year of Jubilee. The owner must pay that value on the day it is decided. The money is holy. It is set apart for the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 27:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 27:24"/>In the Year of Jubilee the field will go back to the person it was bought from. That person is the one who had owned the land before. <verse eid="LEV 27:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 27:25"/>Every amount of money must be weighed out in keeping with the standard weights used in the sacred tent.<verse eid="LEV 27:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 27:26"/>“ ‘But no one can set apart the first male animal born to its mother. That animal already belongs to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It does not matter whether it is an ox or a sheep. It belongs to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 27:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 27:27"/>Suppose it is an “unclean” animal. Then the owner may buy it back at the value that has been decided. And they must add a fifth to its value. But suppose it is not bought back. Then it must be sold at the value that has been decided.<verse eid="LEV 27:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 27:28"/>“ ‘But nothing a person owns and sets apart to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> can be sold or bought back. It does not matter whether it is a human being or an animal or a family’s land. Everything set apart to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is very holy to him.<verse eid="LEV 27:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 27:29"/>“ ‘No one set apart in a special way to be destroyed can be bought back. They must be put to death.<verse eid="LEV 27:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 27:30"/>“ ‘A tenth of everything the land produces belongs to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. That includes grain from the soil and fruit from the trees. It is holy. It is set apart for him. <verse eid="LEV 27:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 27:31"/>Suppose someone wants to buy back some of their tenth. Then they must add a fifth of the cost to it. <verse eid="LEV 27:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 27:32"/>Every tenth part of herds and flocks will be holy. They will be set apart for the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. That includes every tenth animal that its shepherd marks with his wooden staff. <verse eid="LEV 27:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 27:33"/>No one may pick out the good animals from the bad. They must not choose one animal instead of another. But if anyone does, both animals become holy. They can’t be bought back.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 27:33"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 27:34"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave Moses all these commands on Mount Sinai for the Israelites.<verse eid="LEV 27:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 27"/>
</usx>
