<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="PHP" style="id">- New International Readers Version 2014</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1995, 1996, 1998, 2014 by Biblica, Inc.</para>
  <para style="h">Philippians</para>
  <para style="toc1">Philippians</para>
  <para style="toc2">Philippians</para>
  <para style="toc3">Php</para>
  <para style="mt1">Philippians</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">Paul wrote this letter to the people in Philippi who believed in Jesus. Philippi was an important city in the Roman Empire. Many retired Roman soldiers lived there. Paul visited this city on one of his trips bringing the good news about Jesus to the Gentile world. Paul started a church in Philippi. The Philippians became Paul’s friends and gave him support for the rest of his life.</para>
  <para style="ip">The Philippians heard that Paul was a prisoner in Rome. They collected money to assist him. They sent it to Paul with one of their members. He was a man named Epaphroditus. Later Paul sent Epaphroditus back to the Philippians with a letter. In that letter he thanked them for their friendship and support.</para>
  <para style="ip">Paul knew that the faith of the Philippians was being challenged. So Paul uses his own life as an example. Paul is a prisoner of the Roman emperor. But Paul openly preaches that Jesus is the true ruler of the world. His life is an example of how to respond to hardship with joy and courage. Paul shows the strength of his faith. He hopes that the believers in Philippi will also be bold. And he hopes they will dare to preach the good news about Jesus without fear.</para>
  <para style="ip">Paul also writes a beautiful hymn about Jesus. The hymn describes how humble Jesus was. He gave up his high position to become a servant. Jesus even gave up his life for the sake of others. Paul asks the people of Philippi to think and act like Jesus. Paul says this is the new way of living as members of God’s kingdom.</para>
  <para style="ip">God’s kingdom is not completed yet. So Paul encourages the Philippians to live with hope. He tells them that Jesus will return. When that happens, believers will get new resurrection bodies just like Jesus.</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="PHP 1"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="PHP 1:1"/>We, Paul and Timothy, are writing this letter. We serve Christ Jesus.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="PHP 1:1"/>
  <para style="p" vid="PHP 1:1">We are sending this letter to you, all God’s holy people in Philippi. You belong to Christ Jesus. We are also sending this letter to your leaders and deacons.<verse eid="PHP 1:1"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="PHP 1:2"/>May God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ give you grace and peace.<verse eid="PHP 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="s1">Paul Prays and Gives Thanks</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="PHP 1:3"/>I thank my God every time I remember you. <verse eid="PHP 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PHP 1:4"/>In all my prayers for all of you, I always pray with joy. <verse eid="PHP 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PHP 1:5"/>I am happy because you have joined me in spreading the good news. You have done so from the first day until now. <verse eid="PHP 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PHP 1:6"/>God began a good work in you. And I am sure that he will carry it on until it is completed. That will be on the day Christ Jesus returns.<verse eid="PHP 1:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="PHP 1:7"/>It is right for me to feel this way about all of you. I love you with all my heart. I may be held by chains, or I may be standing up for the truth of the good news. Either way, all of you share in God’s grace together with me. <verse eid="PHP 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PHP 1:8"/>God is my witness that I long for all of you. I love you with the love that Christ Jesus gives.<verse eid="PHP 1:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="PHP 1:9"/>I pray that your love will grow more and more. And let it be based on knowledge and understanding. <verse eid="PHP 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PHP 1:10"/>Then you will be able to know what is best. Then you will be pure and without blame for the day that Christ returns. <verse eid="PHP 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PHP 1:11"/>You will be filled with the fruit of right living produced by Jesus Christ. All these things bring glory and praise to God.<verse eid="PHP 1:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Spreads the Good News While in Prison</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="PHP 1:12"/>Brothers and sisters, here is what I want you to know. What has happened to me has actually helped to spread the good news. <verse eid="PHP 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PHP 1:13"/>One thing has become clear. I am being held by chains because I am a witness for Christ. All the palace guards and everyone else know it. <verse eid="PHP 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PHP 1:14"/>And because I am a prisoner, most of the believers have become bolder in the Lord. They now dare even more to preach the good news without fear.<verse eid="PHP 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="PHP 1:15"/>It’s true that some preach about Christ because they are jealous. But others preach about Christ to help me in my work. <verse eid="PHP 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PHP 1:16"/>The last group acts out of love. They know I have been put here to be a witness for the good news. <verse eid="PHP 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PHP 1:17"/>But the others preach about Christ only to get ahead. They preach Christ for the wrong reasons. They think they can stir up trouble for me while I am being held by chains. <verse eid="PHP 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PHP 1:18"/>But what does it matter? Here is the important thing. Whether for right or wrong reasons, Christ is being preached about. That makes me very glad.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="PHP 1:18">And I will continue to be glad. <verse eid="PHP 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PHP 1:19"/>I know that you are praying for me. I also know that God will give me the Spirit of Jesus Christ to help me. So no matter what happens, I’m sure I will still be set free. <verse eid="PHP 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PHP 1:20"/>I completely expect and hope that I won’t be ashamed in any way. I’m sure I will be brave enough. Now as always Christ will receive glory because of what happens to me. He will receive glory whether I live or die. <verse eid="PHP 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PHP 1:21"/>For me, life finds all its meaning in Christ. Death also has its benefits. <verse eid="PHP 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PHP 1:22"/>Suppose I go on living in my body. Then I will be able to carry on my work. It will bear a lot of fruit. But what should I choose? I don’t know! <verse eid="PHP 1:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PHP 1:23"/>I can’t decide between the two. I long to leave this world and be with Christ. That is better by far. <verse eid="PHP 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PHP 1:24"/>But it is more important for you that I stay alive. <verse eid="PHP 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PHP 1:25"/>I’m sure of this. So I know I will remain with you. And I will continue with all of you to help you grow in your faith. I will also continue to help you be joyful in what you have been taught. <verse eid="PHP 1:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PHP 1:26"/>I’m sure I will be with you again. Then you will be able to boast in Christ Jesus even more because of me.<verse eid="PHP 1:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Living to Honor the Good News</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="PHP 1:27"/>No matter what happens, live in a way that brings honor to the good news about Christ. Then I will know that you remain strong together in the one Spirit. I will know this if I come and see you or only hear about you. I will know that you work together as one person. I will know that you work to spread the teachings about the good news. <verse eid="PHP 1:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PHP 1:28"/>So don’t be afraid in any way of those who oppose you. This will show them that they will be destroyed and that you will be saved. That’s what God will do. <verse eid="PHP 1:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PHP 1:29"/>Here is what he has given you to do for Christ. You must not only believe in him. You must also suffer for him. <verse eid="PHP 1:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PHP 1:30"/>You are going through the same struggle you saw me go through. As you have heard, I am still struggling.<verse eid="PHP 1:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="PHP 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="PHP 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Being Humble Like Christ</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="PHP 2:1"/>So does belonging to Christ help you in any way? Does his love comfort you at all? Do you share anything in common because of the Holy Spirit? Has Christ ever been gentle and loving toward you? <verse eid="PHP 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PHP 2:2"/>If any of these things has happened to you, then agree with one another. Have the same love. Be one in spirit and in the way you think and act. By doing this, you will make my joy complete. <verse eid="PHP 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PHP 2:3"/>Don’t do anything only to get ahead. Don’t do it because you are proud. Instead, be humble. Value others more than yourselves. <verse eid="PHP 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PHP 2:4"/>None of you should look out just for your own good. Each of you should also look out for the good of others.<verse eid="PHP 2:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="PHP 2:5"/>As you deal with one another, you should think and act as Jesus did.<verse eid="PHP 2:5"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="PHP 2:6"/>In his very nature he was God.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="PHP 2:6">Jesus was equal with God. But Jesus didn’t take advantage of that fact.<verse eid="PHP 2:6"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="PHP 2:7"/>Instead, he made himself nothing.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="PHP 2:7">He did this by taking on the nature of a servant.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="PHP 2:7">He was made just like human beings.<verse eid="PHP 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="PHP 2:8"/>He appeared as a man.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="PHP 2:8">He was humble and obeyed God completely.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="PHP 2:8">He did this even though it led to his death.</para>
  <para style="q3" vid="PHP 2:8">Even worse, he died on a cross!<verse eid="PHP 2:8"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="PHP 2:9"/>So God lifted him up to the highest place.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="PHP 2:9">God gave him the name that is above every name.<verse eid="PHP 2:9"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="PHP 2:10"/>When the name of Jesus is spoken, everyone will kneel down to worship him.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="PHP 2:10">Everyone in heaven and on earth and under the earth will kneel down to worship him.<verse eid="PHP 2:10"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="PHP 2:11"/>Everyone’s mouth will say that Jesus Christ is Lord.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="PHP 2:11">And God the Father will receive the glory.<verse eid="PHP 2:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Live Without Complaining</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="PHP 2:12"/>My dear friends, you have always obeyed God. You obeyed while I was with you. And you have obeyed even more while I am not with you. So continue to work out your own salvation. Do it with fear and trembling. <verse eid="PHP 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PHP 2:13"/>God is working in you. He wants your plans and your acts to fulfill his good purpose.<verse eid="PHP 2:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="PHP 2:14"/>Do everything without complaining or arguing. <verse eid="PHP 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PHP 2:15"/>Then you will be pure and without blame. You will be children of God without fault among sinful and evil people. Then you will shine among them like stars in the sky. <verse eid="PHP 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PHP 2:16"/>You will shine as you hold on tight to the word of life. Then I will be able to boast about you on the day Christ returns. I can be happy that I didn’t run or work for nothing. <verse eid="PHP 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PHP 2:17"/>But my life might even be poured out like a drink offering on your sacrifices. I’m talking about the way you serve because you believe. Even so, I am glad. I am joyful with all of you. <verse eid="PHP 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PHP 2:18"/>So you too should be glad and joyful with me.<verse eid="PHP 2:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Timothy and Epaphroditus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="PHP 2:19"/>I hope to send Timothy to you soon if the Lord Jesus allows it. Then I will be encouraged when I receive news about you. <verse eid="PHP 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PHP 2:20"/>I have no one else like Timothy. He will truly care about how you are doing. <verse eid="PHP 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PHP 2:21"/>All the others are looking out for their own interests. They are not looking out for the interests of Jesus Christ. <verse eid="PHP 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PHP 2:22"/>But you know that Timothy has proved himself. He has served with me like a son with his father in spreading the good news. <verse eid="PHP 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PHP 2:23"/>So I hope to send him as soon as I see how things go with me. <verse eid="PHP 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PHP 2:24"/>And I’m sure I myself will come soon if the Lord allows it.<verse eid="PHP 2:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="PHP 2:25"/>But I think it’s necessary to send Epaphroditus back to you. He is my brother in the Lord. He is a worker and a soldier of Christ together with me. He is also your messenger. You sent him to take care of my needs. <verse eid="PHP 2:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PHP 2:26"/>He longs for all of you. He is troubled because you heard he was sick. <verse eid="PHP 2:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PHP 2:27"/>He was very sick. In fact, he almost died. But God had mercy on him. He also had mercy on me. God spared me sadness after sadness. <verse eid="PHP 2:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PHP 2:28"/>So I want even more to send him to you. Then when you see him again, you will be glad. And I won’t worry so much. <verse eid="PHP 2:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PHP 2:29"/>So then, welcome him as a brother in the Lord with great joy. Honor people like him. <verse eid="PHP 2:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PHP 2:30"/>He almost died for the work of Christ. He put his life in danger to make up for the help you yourselves couldn’t give me.<verse eid="PHP 2:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="PHP 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="PHP 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Do Not Trust in Who You Are or What You Can Do</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="PHP 3:1"/>Further, my brothers and sisters, be joyful because you belong to the Lord! It is no trouble for me to write about some important matters to you again. If you know about them, you will have a safe path to follow. <verse eid="PHP 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PHP 3:2"/>Watch out for those dogs. They are people who do evil things. When they circumcise, it is nothing more than a useless cutting of the body. <verse eid="PHP 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PHP 3:3"/>But we have been truly circumcised. We serve God by the power of his Spirit. We boast about what Christ Jesus has done. We don’t put our trust in who we are or what we can do. <verse eid="PHP 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PHP 3:4"/>I have many reasons to trust in who I am and what I have done. Someone else may think they have reasons to trust in these things. But I have even more.<verse eid="PHP 3:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="PHP 3:5"/>I was circumcised on the eighth day. I am part of the people of Israel. I am from the tribe of Benjamin. I am a pure Hebrew. As far as the law is concerned, I am a Pharisee. <verse eid="PHP 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PHP 3:6"/>As far as being committed is concerned, I opposed and attacked the church. As far as keeping the law is concerned, I kept it perfectly.<verse eid="PHP 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="PHP 3:7"/>I thought things like that were really something great. But now I consider them to be nothing because of Christ. <verse eid="PHP 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PHP 3:8"/>Even more, I consider everything to be nothing compared to knowing Christ Jesus my Lord. To know him is worth much more than anything else. Because of him I have lost everything. But I consider all of it to be garbage so I can know Christ better. <verse eid="PHP 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PHP 3:9"/>I want to be joined to him. Being right with God does not come from my obeying the law. It comes because I believe in Christ. It comes from God because of faith. <verse eid="PHP 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PHP 3:10"/>I want to know Christ better. Yes, I want to know the power that raised him from the dead. I want to join him in his sufferings. I want to become like him by sharing in his death. <verse eid="PHP 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PHP 3:11"/>Then by God’s grace I will rise from the dead.<verse eid="PHP 3:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="PHP 3:12"/>I have not yet received all these things. I have not yet reached my goal. Christ Jesus took hold of me so that I could reach that goal. So I keep pushing myself forward to reach it. <verse eid="PHP 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PHP 3:13"/>Brothers and sisters, I don’t consider that I have taken hold of it yet. But here is the one thing I do. I forget what is behind me. I push hard toward what is ahead of me. <verse eid="PHP 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PHP 3:14"/>I push myself forward toward the goal to win the prize. God has appointed me to win it. The heavenly prize is Christ Jesus himself.<verse eid="PHP 3:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Following Paul’s Example</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="PHP 3:15"/>So all of us who are grown up in the faith should see things this way. Maybe you think differently about something. But God will make it clear to you. <verse eid="PHP 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PHP 3:16"/>Only let us live up to what we have already reached.<verse eid="PHP 3:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="PHP 3:17"/>Brothers and sisters, join together in following my example. You have us as a model. So pay close attention to those who live as we do. <verse eid="PHP 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PHP 3:18"/>I have told you these things many times before. Now I tell you again with tears in my eyes. Many people live like enemies of the cross of Christ. <verse eid="PHP 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PHP 3:19"/>The only thing they have coming to them is death. Their stomach is their god. They brag about what they should be ashamed of. They think only about earthly things. <verse eid="PHP 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PHP 3:20"/>But we are citizens of heaven. And we can hardly wait for a Savior from there. He is the Lord Jesus Christ. <verse eid="PHP 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PHP 3:21"/>He has the power to bring everything under his control. By his power he will change our earthly bodies. They will become like his glorious body.<verse eid="PHP 3:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="PHP 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="PHP 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Remain Strong in the Lord</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="PHP 4:1"/>My brothers and sisters, in this way remain strong in the Lord. I love you and long for you. Dear friends, you are my joy and my crown.<verse eid="PHP 4:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="PHP 4:2"/>Here is what I’m asking Euodia and Syntyche to do. I’m asking them to work together in the Lord. That’s because they both belong to the Lord. <verse eid="PHP 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PHP 4:3"/>My true companion, here is what I ask you to do. Help these women, because they have served at my side. They have worked with me to spread the good news. So have Clement and the rest of those who have worked together with me. Their names are all written in the book of life.<verse eid="PHP 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Final Commands</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="PHP 4:4"/>Always be joyful because you belong to the Lord. I will say it again. Be joyful! <verse eid="PHP 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PHP 4:5"/>Let everyone know how gentle you are. The Lord is coming soon. <verse eid="PHP 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PHP 4:6"/>Don’t worry about anything. No matter what happens, tell God about everything. Ask and pray, and give thanks to him. <verse eid="PHP 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PHP 4:7"/>Then God’s peace will watch over your hearts and your minds. He will do this because you belong to Christ Jesus. God’s peace can never be completely understood.<verse eid="PHP 4:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="PHP 4:8"/>Finally, my brothers and sisters, always think about what is true. Think about what is noble, right and pure. Think about what is lovely and worthy of respect. If anything is excellent or worthy of praise, think about those kinds of things. <verse eid="PHP 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PHP 4:9"/>Do what you have learned or received or heard from me. Follow my example. The God who gives peace will be with you.<verse eid="PHP 4:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Gives Thanks for the Philippians’ Gifts</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="PHP 4:10"/>At last you are concerned about me again. That makes me very happy. We belong to the Lord. I know that you were concerned. But you had no chance to show it. <verse eid="PHP 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PHP 4:11"/>I’m not saying this because I need anything. I have learned to be content no matter what happens to me. <verse eid="PHP 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PHP 4:12"/>I know what it’s like not to have what I need. I also know what it’s like to have more than I need. I have learned the secret of being content no matter what happens. I am content whether I am well fed or hungry. I am content whether I have more than enough or not enough. <verse eid="PHP 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PHP 4:13"/>I can do all this by the power of Christ. He gives me strength.<verse eid="PHP 4:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="PHP 4:14"/>But it was good of you to share in my troubles. <verse eid="PHP 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PHP 4:15"/>And you believers at Philippi know what happened when I left Macedonia. Not one church helped me in the matter of giving and receiving. You were the only one that did. That was in the early days when you first heard the good news. <verse eid="PHP 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PHP 4:16"/>Even when I was in Thessalonica, you sent me help when I needed it. And you did it more than once. <verse eid="PHP 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PHP 4:17"/>It is not that I want your gifts. What I really want is what is best for you. <verse eid="PHP 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PHP 4:18"/>I have received my full pay and have more than enough. I have everything I need. That’s because Epaphroditus brought me the gifts you sent. They are a sweet-smelling offering. They are a gift that God accepts. He is pleased with it. <verse eid="PHP 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PHP 4:19"/>My God will meet all your needs. He will meet them in keeping with his wonderful riches. These riches come to you because you belong to Christ Jesus.<verse eid="PHP 4:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="PHP 4:20"/>Give glory to our God and Father for ever and ever. Amen.<verse eid="PHP 4:20"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="s1">Final Greetings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="PHP 4:21"/>Greet all God’s people. They belong to Christ Jesus.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="PHP 4:21">The brothers and sisters who are with me send greetings.<verse eid="PHP 4:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="PHP 4:22"/>All God’s people here send you greetings. Most of all, those who live in the palace of Caesar send you greetings.<verse eid="PHP 4:22"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="PHP 4:23"/>May the grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen.<verse eid="PHP 4:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="PHP 4"/>
</usx>
