<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="RUT" style="id">- New International Readers Version 2014</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1995, 1996, 1998, 2014 by Biblica, Inc.</para>
  <para style="h">Ruth</para>
  <para style="toc1">Ruth</para>
  <para style="toc2">Ruth</para>
  <para style="toc3">Ru</para>
  <para style="mt1">Ruth</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">The book of Ruth is short but important. It connects two parts of Israel’s history as God’s chosen people. The first part of the history is in the books from Genesis to Judges. It is about Abraham’s family that came after him. It tells about how these people became a great nation. It tells of their agreement to love God. And in the promise they also agreed to obey God’s laws and commandments.</para>
  <para style="ip">The second part of Israel’s history is in the books of Samuel and Kings. These books follow the book of Ruth. They tell the story of the agreement God made with David and his sons. David was the greatest of Israel’s first kings. These books also tell the stories of the kings of Israel who follow after David.</para>
  <para style="ip">The book of Ruth connects these two parts of Israel’s history. This book begins in the time of the judges of Israel. It ends with the list of the family line of David.</para>
  <para style="ip">The purpose of this book might be to say it was okay for David to be king. David was the great-grandson of a Moabite woman named Ruth. But there is a problem. The people of Moab did not help the Israelites when they left Egypt. So, the laws of Israel did not allow for anyone from Moab to join Israel. That law was true for 10 generations. So how could the great-grandson of someone from Moab be king? This book shows how Ruth had true faith in God, even though she was from Moab.</para>
  <para style="ip">The book of Ruth also tells about how God’s plan is accomplished in the world. It is a story about God’s love and care for his people. The story reads like a play with four main parts. It begins when Ruth and Naomi return to Israel. They are protected by God’s laws. And they experience God’s love and care. They are cared for when Ruth is allowed to pick grain for food. That care is also seen when an Israelite man named Boaz marries Ruth. When Obed is born to Boaz and Ruth, the family line of David gets started. In all these events God is present. God’s laws are followed and his love can be seen.</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="RUT 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Naomi Loses Her Husband and Sons</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="RUT 1:1"/>There was a time when Israel didn’t have kings to rule over them. But they had leaders to help them. This is a story about some things that happened during that time. There wasn’t enough food in the land of Judah. So a man went to live for a while in the country of Moab. He was from Bethlehem in Judah. His wife and two sons went with him. <verse eid="RUT 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="RUT 1:2"/>The man’s name was Elimelek. His wife’s name was Naomi. The names of his two sons were Mahlon and Kilion. They were Ephrathites whose home had been in Bethlehem in Judah. They went to Moab and lived there.<verse eid="RUT 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="RUT 1:3"/>Naomi’s husband Elimelek died. So she was left with her two sons. <verse eid="RUT 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="RUT 1:4"/>They married women from Moab. One was named Orpah. The other was named Ruth. Naomi’s family lived in Moab for about ten years. <verse eid="RUT 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="RUT 1:5"/>Then Mahlon and Kilion also died. So Naomi was left without her two sons and her husband.<verse eid="RUT 1:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Naomi and Ruth Return to Bethlehem</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="RUT 1:6"/>While Naomi was in Moab, she heard that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had helped his people. He had begun to provide food for them again. So Naomi and her two daughters-in-law prepared to go from Moab back to her home. <verse eid="RUT 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="RUT 1:7"/>She left the place where she had been living. Her daughters-in-law went with her. They started out on the road that would take them back to the land of Judah.<verse eid="RUT 1:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="RUT 1:8"/>Naomi said to her two daughters-in-law, “Both of you go back. Each of you go to your own mother’s home. You were kind to your husbands, who have died. You have also been kind to me. So may the <char style="nd">Lord</char> be just as kind to you. <verse eid="RUT 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="RUT 1:9"/>May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> help each of you find rest in the home of another husband.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="RUT 1:9">Then she kissed them goodbye. They broke down and wept loudly. <verse eid="RUT 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="RUT 1:10"/>They said to her, “We’ll go back to your people with you.”<verse eid="RUT 1:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="RUT 1:11"/>But Naomi said, “Go home, my daughters. Why would you want to come with me? Am I going to have any more sons who could become your husbands? <verse eid="RUT 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="RUT 1:12"/>Go home, my daughters. I’m too old to have another husband. Suppose I thought there was still some hope for me. Suppose I married a man tonight. And later I had sons by him. <verse eid="RUT 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="RUT 1:13"/>Would you wait until they grew up? Would you stay single until you could marry them? No, my daughters. My life is more bitter than yours. The <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s power has turned against me!”<verse eid="RUT 1:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="RUT 1:14"/>When they heard that, they broke down and wept again. Then Orpah kissed her mother-in-law goodbye. But Ruth held on to her.<verse eid="RUT 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="RUT 1:15"/>“Look,” said Naomi. “Your sister-in-law is going back to her people and her gods. Go back with her.”<verse eid="RUT 1:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="RUT 1:16"/>But Ruth replied, “Don’t try to make me leave you and go back. Where you go I’ll go. Where you stay I’ll stay. Your people will be my people. Your God will be my God. <verse eid="RUT 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="RUT 1:17"/>Where you die I’ll die. And there my body will be buried. I won’t let even death separate you from me. If I do, may the <char style="nd">Lord</char> punish me greatly.” <verse eid="RUT 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="RUT 1:18"/>Naomi realized that Ruth had made up her mind to go with her. So she stopped trying to make her go back.<verse eid="RUT 1:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="RUT 1:19"/>The two women continued on their way. At last they arrived in Bethlehem. The whole town was stirred up because of them. The women in the town asked, “Can this possibly be Naomi?”<verse eid="RUT 1:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="RUT 1:20"/>“Don’t call me Naomi,” she told them. “Call me Mara. The Mighty One has made my life very bitter. <verse eid="RUT 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="RUT 1:21"/>I was full when I went away. But the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has brought me back empty. So why are you calling me Naomi? The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has made me suffer. The Mighty One has brought trouble on me.”<verse eid="RUT 1:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="RUT 1:22"/>So Naomi returned from Moab. Ruth, her daughter-in-law from Moab, came with her. They arrived in Bethlehem just when people were beginning to harvest the barley.<verse eid="RUT 1:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="RUT 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="RUT 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Ruth Meets Boaz in the Grain Field</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="RUT 2:1"/>Naomi had a relative on her husband’s side of the family. The relative’s name was Boaz. He was a very important man from the family of Elimelek.<verse eid="RUT 2:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="RUT 2:2"/>Ruth, who was from Moab, spoke to Naomi. Ruth said, “Let me go out to the fields. I’ll pick up the grain that has been left. I’ll do it behind anyone who is pleased with me.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="RUT 2:2">Naomi said to her, “My daughter, go ahead.” <verse eid="RUT 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="RUT 2:3"/>So Ruth went out to a field and began to pick up grain. She worked behind those cutting and gathering the grain. As it turned out, she was working in a field that belonged to Boaz. He was from the family of Elimelek.<verse eid="RUT 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="RUT 2:4"/>Just then Boaz arrived from Bethlehem. He greeted those cutting and gathering the grain. He said, “May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> be with you!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="RUT 2:4">“And may the <char style="nd">Lord</char> bless you!” they replied.<verse eid="RUT 2:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="RUT 2:5"/>Boaz spoke to the man in charge of his workers. He asked, “Who does that young woman belong to?”<verse eid="RUT 2:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="RUT 2:6"/>The man replied, “She’s from Moab. She came back from there with Naomi. <verse eid="RUT 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="RUT 2:7"/>The young woman said, ‘Please let me walk behind the workers. Let me pick up the grain that is left.’ She came into the field. She has kept on working here from morning until now. She took only one short rest in the shade.”<verse eid="RUT 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="RUT 2:8"/>So Boaz said to Ruth, “Dear woman, listen to me. Don’t pick up grain in any other field. Don’t go anywhere else. Stay here with the women who work for me. <verse eid="RUT 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="RUT 2:9"/>Keep your eye on the field where the men are cutting grain. Walk behind the women who are gathering it. Pick up the grain that is left. I’ve told the men not to bother you. When you are thirsty, go and get a drink. Take water from the jars the men have filled.”<verse eid="RUT 2:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="RUT 2:10"/>When Ruth heard that, she bowed down with her face to the ground. She asked him, “Why are you being so kind to me? In fact, why are you even noticing me? I’m from another country.”<verse eid="RUT 2:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="RUT 2:11"/>Boaz replied, “I’ve been told all about you. I’ve heard about everything you have done for your mother-in-law since your husband died. I know that you left your father and mother. I know that you left your country. You came to live with people you didn’t know before. <verse eid="RUT 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="RUT 2:12"/>May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> reward you for what you have done. May the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, bless you richly. You have come to him to find safety under his care.”<verse eid="RUT 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="RUT 2:13"/>“Sir, I hope you will continue to be kind to me,” Ruth said. “You have made me feel safe. You have spoken kindly to me. And I’m not even as important as one of your servants!”<verse eid="RUT 2:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="RUT 2:14"/>When it was time to eat, Boaz spoke to Ruth again. “Come over here,” he said. “Have some bread. Dip it in the wine vinegar.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="RUT 2:14">She sat down with the workers. Then Boaz offered her some grain that had been cooked. She ate all she wanted. She even had some left over. <verse eid="RUT 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="RUT 2:15"/>Ruth got up to pick up more grain. Then Boaz gave orders to his men. He said, “Let her take some stalks from what the women have tied up. Don’t tell her she can’t. <verse eid="RUT 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="RUT 2:16"/>Even pull out some stalks for her. Leave them for her to pick up. Don’t tell her she shouldn’t do it.”<verse eid="RUT 2:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="RUT 2:17"/>So Ruth picked up grain in the field until evening. Then she separated the barley from the straw. The barley weighed 30 pounds. <verse eid="RUT 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="RUT 2:18"/>She carried it back to town. Her mother-in-law saw how much she had gathered. Ruth also brought out the food left over from the lunch Boaz had given her. She gave it to Naomi.<verse eid="RUT 2:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="RUT 2:19"/>Her mother-in-law asked her, “Where did you pick up grain today? Where did you work? May the man who noticed you be blessed!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="RUT 2:19">Then Ruth told her about the man whose field she had worked in. “The name of the man I worked with today is Boaz,” she said.<verse eid="RUT 2:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="RUT 2:20"/>“May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> bless him!” Naomi said to her daughter-in-law. “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> is still being kind to those who are living and those who are dead.” She continued, “That man is a close relative of ours. He’s one of our family protectors.”<verse eid="RUT 2:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="RUT 2:21"/>Then Ruth, who was from Moab, said, “He told me more. He even said, ‘Stay with my workers until they have finished bringing in all my grain.’ ”<verse eid="RUT 2:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="RUT 2:22"/>Naomi replied to her daughter-in-law Ruth. She said, “That will be good for you, my daughter. Go with the women who work for him. You might be harmed if you go to someone else’s field.”<verse eid="RUT 2:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="RUT 2:23"/>So Ruth stayed close to the women who worked for Boaz as she picked up grain. She worked until the time when all the barley and wheat had been harvested. And she lived with her mother-in-law.<verse eid="RUT 2:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="RUT 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="RUT 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Ruth and Boaz at the Threshing Floor</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="RUT 3:1"/>One day Ruth’s mother-in-law Naomi spoke to her. She said, “My daughter, I must find a home for you. It should be a place where you will be provided for. <verse eid="RUT 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="RUT 3:2"/>You have been working with the women who work for Boaz. He’s a relative of ours. Tonight he’ll be separating the straw from his barley on the threshing floor. <verse eid="RUT 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="RUT 3:3"/>So wash yourself. Put on some perfume. And put on your best clothes. Then go down to the threshing floor. But don’t let Boaz know you are there. Wait until he has finished eating and drinking. <verse eid="RUT 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="RUT 3:4"/>Notice where he lies down. Then go over and uncover his feet. Lie down there. He’ll tell you what to do.”<verse eid="RUT 3:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="RUT 3:5"/>“I’ll do everything you say,” Ruth answered. <verse eid="RUT 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="RUT 3:6"/>So she went down to the threshing floor. She did everything her mother-in-law had told her to do.<verse eid="RUT 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="RUT 3:7"/>When Boaz had finished eating and drinking, he was in a good mood. He went over to lie down at the far end of the grain pile. Then Ruth approached quietly. She uncovered his feet and lay down there. <verse eid="RUT 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="RUT 3:8"/>In the middle of the night, something surprised Boaz and woke him up. He turned and found a woman lying there at his feet!<verse eid="RUT 3:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="RUT 3:9"/>“Who are you?” he asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="RUT 3:9">“I’m Ruth,” she said. “You are my family protector. So take good care of me by making me your wife.”<verse eid="RUT 3:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="RUT 3:10"/>“Dear woman, may the <char style="nd">Lord</char> bless you,” he replied. “You are showing even more kindness now than you did earlier. You didn’t run after the younger men, whether they were rich or poor. <verse eid="RUT 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="RUT 3:11"/>Dear woman, don’t be afraid. I’ll do for you everything you ask. All the people of my town know that you are an excellent woman. <verse eid="RUT 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="RUT 3:12"/>It’s true that I’m a relative of yours. But there’s a family protector who is more closely related to you than I am. <verse eid="RUT 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="RUT 3:13"/>So stay here for the night. In the morning if he wants to help you, good. Let him help you. But if he doesn’t want to, then I’ll do it. You can be sure that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> lives. And you can be just as sure that I’ll help you. Lie down here until morning.”<verse eid="RUT 3:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="RUT 3:14"/>So she stayed at his feet until morning. But she got up before anyone could be recognized. Boaz thought, “No one must know that a woman came to the threshing floor.”<verse eid="RUT 3:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="RUT 3:15"/>He said to Ruth, “Bring me the coat you have around you. Hold it out.” So she did. He poured more than fifty pounds of barley into it and helped her pick it up. Then he went back to town.<verse eid="RUT 3:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="RUT 3:16"/>Ruth came to her mother-in-law. Naomi asked, “How did it go, my daughter?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="RUT 3:16">Then Ruth told her everything Boaz had done for her. <verse eid="RUT 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="RUT 3:17"/>She said, “He gave me all this barley. He said, ‘Don’t go back to your mother-in-law with your hands empty.’ ”<verse eid="RUT 3:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="RUT 3:18"/>Naomi said, “My daughter, sit down until you find out what happens. The man won’t rest until he settles the whole matter today.”<verse eid="RUT 3:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="RUT 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="RUT 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Boaz Marries Ruth</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="RUT 4:1"/>Boaz went up to the town gate and sat down there. Right then, the family protector he had talked about came by. Then Boaz said, “Come over here, my friend. Sit down.” So the man went over and sat down.<verse eid="RUT 4:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="RUT 4:2"/>Boaz brought ten of the elders of the town together. He said, “Sit down here.” So they did. <verse eid="RUT 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="RUT 4:3"/>Then he spoke to the family protector. He said, “Naomi has come back from Moab. She’s selling the piece of land that belonged to our relative Elimelek. <verse eid="RUT 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="RUT 4:4"/>I thought I should bring the matter to your attention. I suggest that you buy the land. Buy it while those sitting here and the elders of my people are looking on as witnesses. If you are willing to buy it back, do it. But if you aren’t, tell me. Then I’ll know. No one has the right to buy it back except you. And I’m next in line.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="RUT 4:4">“I’ll buy it,” he said.<verse eid="RUT 4:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="RUT 4:5"/>Then Boaz said, “When you buy the property from Naomi, you must also marry Ruth. She is from Moab and is the dead man’s widow. So you must marry her. That’s because his property must continue to belong to his family.”<verse eid="RUT 4:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="RUT 4:6"/>When the family protector heard that, he said, “Then I can’t buy the land. If I did, I might put my own property in danger. So you buy it. I can’t do it.”<verse eid="RUT 4:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="RUT 4:7"/>In earlier times in Israel, there was a certain practice. It was used when family land was bought back and changed owners. The practice made the sale final. One person would take his sandal off and give it to the other. That was how people in Israel showed that a business matter had been settled.<verse eid="RUT 4:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="RUT 4:8"/>So the family protector said to Boaz, “Buy it yourself.” And he took his sandal off.<verse eid="RUT 4:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="RUT 4:9"/>Then Boaz said to the elders and all the people, “Today you are witnesses. You have seen that I have bought land from Naomi. I have bought all the property that had belonged to Elimelek, Kilion and Mahlon. <verse eid="RUT 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="RUT 4:10"/>I’ve also taken Ruth, who is from Moab, to become my wife. She is Mahlon’s widow. I’ve decided to marry her so the dead man’s name will stay with his property. Now his name won’t disappear from his family line or from his hometown. Today you are witnesses!”<verse eid="RUT 4:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="RUT 4:11"/>Then the elders and all the people at the gate said, “We are witnesses. The woman is coming into your home. May the <char style="nd">Lord</char> make her like Rachel and Leah. Together they built up the family of Israel. May you be an important person in Ephrathah. May you be famous in Bethlehem. <verse eid="RUT 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="RUT 4:12"/>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will give you children through this young woman. May your family be like the family of Perez. He was the son Tamar had by Judah.”<verse eid="RUT 4:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Naomi Gains a Son</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="RUT 4:13"/>So Boaz married Ruth. Then he slept with her. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> blessed her so that she became pregnant. And she had a son. <verse eid="RUT 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="RUT 4:14"/>The women said to Naomi, “We praise the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Today he has provided a family protector for you. May this child become famous all over Israel! <verse eid="RUT 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="RUT 4:15"/>He will make your life new again. He’ll take care of you when you are old. He’s the son of your very own daughter-in-law. She loves you. She is better to you than seven sons.”<verse eid="RUT 4:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="RUT 4:16"/>Then Naomi took the child in her arms and took care of him. <verse eid="RUT 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="RUT 4:17"/>The women living there said, “Naomi has a son!” They named him Obed. He was the father of Jesse. Jesse was the father of David.<verse eid="RUT 4:17"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="RUT 4:18"/>Here is the family line of Perez.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="RUT 4:18"/>
  <para style="li1" vid="RUT 4:18">Perez was the father of Hezron.<verse eid="RUT 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="RUT 4:19"/>Hezron was the father of Ram.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="RUT 4:19">Ram was the father of Amminadab.<verse eid="RUT 4:19"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="RUT 4:20"/>Amminadab was the father of Nahshon.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="RUT 4:20">Nahshon was the father of Salmon.<verse eid="RUT 4:20"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="RUT 4:21"/>Salmon was the father of Boaz.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="RUT 4:21">Boaz was the father of Obed.<verse eid="RUT 4:21"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="RUT 4:22"/>Obed was the father of Jesse.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="RUT 4:22">And Jesse was the father of David.<verse eid="RUT 4:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="RUT 4"/>
</usx>
