<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- SourceFormat: VL.  Converted to USX by the STEP project: 2023-08-18 -->
<usx version="2.0">
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <book code="JOB"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:1"/>There was a certain man in the land of Ausitis, whose name was Iob, and that man was genuine, blameless, righteous, religious, staying away from every evil thing.<verse eid="JOB 1:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:2"/>Now there were born to him seven sons and three daughters.<verse eid="JOB 1:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:3"/>And his livestock was: seven thousand sheep, three thousand camels, five hundred yoke of oxen, five hundred she-donkeys at pasture; as well he had very many servants and extensive activities in the land, and that man was well-born among those of the east.<verse eid="JOB 1:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:4"/>Now his sons used to gather with one another and hold a feast each day; they used take along their three sisters as well, to eat and drink with them.<verse eid="JOB 1:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:5"/>And when the feast days had run their course, Iob used to send and purify them, rising early in the morning, and he used to offer a sacrifice on their behalf, according to their number, and one bull calf as a sin offering for their souls-- for Iob said, "Perhaps my sons thought bad things in their mind toward God." So this is what Iob would always do.<verse eid="JOB 1:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:6"/>And when the set day came, then, look, the angels of God came to present themselves before the Lord, and the slanderer came with them.<verse eid="JOB 1:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:7"/>And the Lord said to the slanderer, "Where have you come from?" And the slanderer answered the Lord, "I have come, after going round the earth and walking about what lies beneath heaven."<verse eid="JOB 1:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:8"/>And the Lord said to him, "Did you give thought to your disposition against my servant Iob-- because there is no one of those on the earth like him, a man who is blameless, genuine, religious, staying away from every evil thing?"<verse eid="JOB 1:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:9"/>Then the slanderer answered and said before the Lord, "Does Iob really worship the Lord for nothing?<verse eid="JOB 1:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:10"/>Have you not put a fence around things external to him, both what is within his household as well as what is outside of all that belongs to him, all around? You blessed the works of his hands, and his livestock you increased on the earth.<verse eid="JOB 1:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:11"/>But stretch out your hand, and touch all that he has; surely he will bless<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = euphemism</char></note> you to your face!"<verse eid="JOB 1:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:12"/>Then the Lord said to the slanderer, "Look, all that he has I am giving into your power, but do not touch him." So the slanderer went out from the Lord.<verse eid="JOB 1:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:13"/>So it was, when it was the set day, Iob's sons and daughters were drinking wine in their eldest brother's house.<verse eid="JOB 1:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:14"/>And, look, a messenger came to Iob and said to him, "The yokes of oxen were plowing, and the she-donkeys were feeding beside them,<verse eid="JOB 1:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:15"/>and marauders came and carried them off, and they killed the servants with daggers, but when I alone escaped, I came to tell you."<verse eid="JOB 1:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:16"/>While he was still speaking, a further messenger came and said to Iob, "Fire fell from heaven and burned up the sheep, and it likewise consumed the shepherds, and when I alone escaped, I came to tell you."<verse eid="JOB 1:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:17"/>While he was still speaking, a further messenger came and said to Iob, "Horsemen formed three columns against us, and they encircled the camels and carried them off and killed the servants with daggers, but I alone escaped, and I came to tell you."<verse eid="JOB 1:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:18"/>While he was still speaking, another messenger came, saying to Iob, "As your sons and daughters were eating and drinking at their elder brother's,<verse eid="JOB 1:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:19"/>suddenly a great wind came from the wilderness and struck the four corners of the house, and the house fell on your children, and they died, but I alone escaped, and I came to tell you."<verse eid="JOB 1:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:20"/>So Iob arose, tore his clothes and shaved the hair of his head and fell on the ground and did obeisance and said,<verse eid="JOB 1:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:21"/>"I came naked from my mother's womb; naked also shall I return there; the Lord gave; the Lord has taken away; as it seemed good to the Lord, so it turned out; blessed be the name of the Lord."<verse eid="JOB 1:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 1:22"/>In all these things that happened to him Iob did not sin at all before the Lord, and he did not charge God with folly.<verse eid="JOB 1:22"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 2:1"/>Now it happened, when it was the set day and the angels of God came to present themselves before the Lord, the slanderer also came among them.<verse eid="JOB 2:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 2:2"/>And the Lord said to the slanderer, "Where are you coming from?" Then the slanderer said before the Lord, "I have come, after traversing what lies beneath heaven and walking about everything."<verse eid="JOB 2:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 2:3"/>Then the Lord said, "So did you notice my attendant Iob-- that there is no one of those on the earth like him, an innocent, genuine, blameless, religious man, staying away from all wrong? And he still maintains his innocence, though you said to destroy his possessions for no reason."<verse eid="JOB 2:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 2:4"/>Then the slanderer continued and said to the Lord, "Skin for skin; whatever a person has he will use to pay for his life.<verse eid="JOB 2:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 2:5"/>However, stretch out your hand, and touch his bones and his flesh; surely he will bless<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew = euphemism</char></note> you to your face!"<verse eid="JOB 2:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 2:6"/>Then the Lord said to the slanderer, "Very well, I am handing him over to you; only spare his life."<verse eid="JOB 2:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 2:7"/>So the slanderer went out from the Lord, and he struck Iob with a grievous festering sore from his feet to his head.<verse eid="JOB 2:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 2:8"/>And he took a potsherd, so that he could scrape away the pus, and sat on the rubbish heap outside the city.<verse eid="JOB 2:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 2:9"/>Then after a long time had passed, his wife said to him, "How long will you persist and say, (9a) 'Look, I will hang on a little longer, while I wait for the hope of my deliverance?' (9b) For look, your legacy has vanished from the earth-- sons and daughters, my womb's birth pangs and labors, for whom I wearied myself with hardships in vain. (9c) And you? You sit in the refuse of worms as you spend the night in the open air. (9d) As for me, I am one that wanders about and a hired servant-- from place to place and house to house, waiting for when the sun will set, so I can rest from the distresses and griefs that now beset me. (9e) Now say some word to the Lord and die!"<verse eid="JOB 2:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 2:10"/>But Iob looked up and said to her, "You have spoken like one of the foolish women. If we received the good things from the Lord's hand, shall we not bear the bad?" In all these things that happened to him Iob did not sin at all with his lips before God.<verse eid="JOB 2:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 2:11"/>Now when his three friends heard of all the troubles that had come upon him, they came to him, each one from his own country-- Eliphaz<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = 'Eliphas'</char></note>, the king of the Thaimanites, Baldad, the tyrant of the Sauchites, Sophar, the king of the Minites. And they came to him of one accord, to comfort and to visit with him.<verse eid="JOB 2:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 2:12"/>But when they saw him from a distance, they did not recognize him, and they cried out with a loud voice and wept; each of them tore his robe, and they sprinkled themselves with dust.<verse eid="JOB 2:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 2:13"/>They sat with him seven days, and none of them spoke, for they saw that the calamity was dire and very great.<verse eid="JOB 2:13"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:1"/>After this Iob opened his mouth and cursed his day<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e.'the day of his birth'</char></note>,<verse eid="JOB 3:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:2"/>saying:<verse eid="JOB 3:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:3"/>"May the day perish in which I was born, and the night in which they said, 'Look, a man-child!'<verse eid="JOB 3:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:4"/>May that day be darkness! And may the Lord above not seek it, or light come to it.<verse eid="JOB 3:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:5"/>But may darkness and deathly shadow seize it. May gloom come upon it.<verse eid="JOB 3:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:6"/>May that day and night be cursed; may darkness carry it away! May it not exist among the days of the year or be numbered among the days of the months.<verse eid="JOB 3:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:7"/>Rather, may that night be anguish, and may gladness and joy not come upon it.<verse eid="JOB 3:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:8"/>Rather, may he who curses that day curse it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'that night'</char></note>-- he who is about to subdue the great sea- monster.<verse eid="JOB 3:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:9"/>May the stars of that night be dark; may it remain so and not be lit up, and may it not see the morning-star rising--<verse eid="JOB 3:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:10"/>because it did not shut the gates of my mother's womb, for it would have put away trouble from my eyes.<verse eid="JOB 3:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:11"/>"For what reason did I not die in the womb or come forth from the belly and not perish at once?<verse eid="JOB 3:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:12"/>Why then did knees meet me? Why then did I suck breasts?<verse eid="JOB 3:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:13"/>Now I would have lain down quiet and in sleep would have been at rest,<verse eid="JOB 3:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:14"/>with kings, counselors of the earth, who used to act proudly thanks to rapiers,<verse eid="JOB 3:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:15"/>or with rulers, who had much gold, who had filled their houses with silver.<verse eid="JOB 3:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:16"/>Or why was I not like a premature birth that comes from a mother's womb or like infants that did not see the light?<verse eid="JOB 3:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:17"/>There the impious have kindled a terrible wrath; there the very weary have found rest for the body,<verse eid="JOB 3:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:18"/>and those of old, together, have not heard the voice of the tax- gatherer.<verse eid="JOB 3:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:19"/>Small and great are there, and the attendant who lived in fear of his master.<verse eid="JOB 3:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:20"/>"Why then is light given to those in bitterness, and life to souls in pain,<verse eid="JOB 3:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:21"/>who long for death and do not find it, though they are digging for it as for treasures?<verse eid="JOB 3:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:22"/>Yet they would be very joyful, if they were successful.<verse eid="JOB 3:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:23"/>Death is rest for such a man, for God shut him in.<verse eid="JOB 3:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:24"/>For sighing comes before my food, and I cry, gripped by fear.<verse eid="JOB 3:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:25"/>For fear-- which was my worry-- came to me, and the fear I dreaded befell me.<verse eid="JOB 3:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 3:26"/>I was neither at peace, nor did I have quiet, nor was I at rest, but anger came to me."<verse eid="JOB 3:26"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:1"/>Now Eliphaz<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = 'Eliphas'</char></note> the Thaimanite said in reply,<verse eid="JOB 4:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:2"/>"Have you often been addressed when in distress? But who can endure the force of your words?<verse eid="JOB 4:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:3"/>So what, if you instructed many and encouraged the hands of the weak one,<verse eid="JOB 4:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:4"/>lifted up the weak with your words and wrapped feeble knees in courage--<verse eid="JOB 4:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:5"/>but now distress has come upon you and touched you, and you acted in haste.<verse eid="JOB 4:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:6"/>Is your fear not based on a lack of sense, so too your hope and the innocence of your way?<verse eid="JOB 4:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:7"/>"Think now, who, being pure, perished, or when did the true perish root and all?<verse eid="JOB 4:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:8"/>For instance, I saw those who plow wrongs, and those who sow them reap torments for themselves.<verse eid="JOB 4:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:9"/>By the command of the Lord they will perish, and by the breath of his anger they will disappear.<verse eid="JOB 4:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:10"/>The strength of the lion and the voice of the lioness and the pride of dragons<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:10</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'fearsome creatures'</char></note> was extinguished;<verse eid="JOB 4:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:11"/>the ant lion perished for lack of food, and lions' whelps abandoned one another.<verse eid="JOB 4:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:12"/>But if there had been anything truthful in your words, nothing bad in them would have met you. "Will my ear not receive remarkable things from him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the Lord'</char></note>?<verse eid="JOB 4:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:13"/>Now there was awe and a ringing sound in the night-- an awe falling on mortals;<verse eid="JOB 4:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:14"/>then shuddering fell upon me, and a trembling, and my bones shook mightily.<verse eid="JOB 4:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:15"/>And a spirit came upon my face, and my hair and flesh quivered.<verse eid="JOB 4:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:16"/>I stood up, and I did not recognize it. I looked, and there was no shape before my eyes, though I heard a breeze and a voice:<verse eid="JOB 4:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:17"/>'What? Can a mortal be pure before the Lord, or a man be blameless in his actions?'<verse eid="JOB 4:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:18"/>Whether he believes charges against his servants, who knows<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'who knows':  Lacking in Greek</char></note>, but he took note of any crookedness in his angels.<verse eid="JOB 4:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:19"/>But as for those that inhabit houses of clay-- being their offspring, we ourselves too are of the same clay-- he struck them like a moth!<verse eid="JOB 4:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:20"/>And so between morning and evening they ceased to exist; they perished, because they were not able to help themselves.<verse eid="JOB 4:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 4:21"/>That is, he breathed on them, and they withered; they perished, because they did not possess wisdom.<verse eid="JOB 4:21"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:1"/>"But call, if anyone will respond to you or if you will see any of the holy angels.<verse eid="JOB 5:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:2"/>To be sure, anger kills the fool, and jealousy slays the one misled.<verse eid="JOB 5:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:3"/>Now, I have seen fools taking root, but at once their way of living was devoured.<verse eid="JOB 5:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:4"/>May their children be far from safety, and may they be derided at the doors of their inferiors, and there will be no one to deliver them.<verse eid="JOB 5:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:5"/>For what they gathered, the upright shall eat, and they will not be excepted from harmful things; may their strength be drained.<verse eid="JOB 5:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:6"/>For hardship shall not come from the earth, nor will trouble sprout from mountains,<verse eid="JOB 5:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:7"/>but a human being is born to hardship, whereas the vulture's young soar on high.<verse eid="JOB 5:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:8"/>"Nonetheless, I will entreat the Lord, and I will call on the Lord, the master of all,<verse eid="JOB 5:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:9"/>who does great and inscrutable things, things both glorious and extraordinary, without number,<verse eid="JOB 5:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:10"/>who gives rain on the earth, sending water on what is under heaven,<verse eid="JOB 5:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:11"/>who sets on high those that are lowly and lifts up those that are in ruin,<verse eid="JOB 5:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:12"/>frustrating the schemes of the crafty-- and their hands shall not produce what is genuine,<verse eid="JOB 5:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:13"/>he who takes the wise in their cleverness-- and he subverted the scheming of the wily.<verse eid="JOB 5:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:14"/>Darkness will meet them in the daytime, and may they grope at noonday as in the night.<verse eid="JOB 5:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:15"/>And may they perish in war, and may the powerless escape from the hand of the mighty.<verse eid="JOB 5:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:16"/>So may the powerless have hope, but the mouth of the unjust be shut.<verse eid="JOB 5:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:17"/>"But happy is the one whom the Lord reproved, and do not reject the admonition of the Almighty,<verse eid="JOB 5:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:18"/>for he makes one suffer and restores again; he struck, and his hands healed.<verse eid="JOB 5:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:19"/>Six times he will deliver you from troubles, and the seventh time no harm shall touch you.<verse eid="JOB 5:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:20"/>In famine he will rescue you from death, and in war he will free you from a blade's power.<verse eid="JOB 5:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:21"/>He shall hide you from the scourge of the tongue, and you shall not fear harmful things that come.<verse eid="JOB 5:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:22"/>At the unjust and lawless you shall laugh, and you shall not fear wild animals--<verse eid="JOB 5:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:23"/>for wild animals shall be at peace with you.<verse eid="JOB 5:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:24"/>Next, you shall know that your household will be at peace, and the livelihood of your tent shall not fall short.<verse eid="JOB 5:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:25"/>And you shall know that your descendants will be many, and your offspring shall be as the grass of the field.<verse eid="JOB 5:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:26"/>And you shall come to your grave like ripe grain, harvested at the right time, or as a heap on the threshing floor, gathered in its season.<verse eid="JOB 5:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 5:27"/>Look, these things we traced to be so. These are the things we have heard, but do know for yourself whether you have done anything."<verse eid="JOB 5:27"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:1"/>Now Iob said in reply:<verse eid="JOB 6:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:2"/>"If someone really sets about to weigh what angers me<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">6:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'what angers me':  Or 'my anger'</char></note> and to put my sorrows together in a balance,<verse eid="JOB 6:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:3"/>then indeed they will be heavier than the sand of the seashore, but as it seems, my words are careless.<verse eid="JOB 6:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:4"/>For the arrows of the Lord are in my body; their wrath drinks my blood; when I begin to speak, they pierce me.<verse eid="JOB 6:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:5"/>Why, will the wild ass bray for no reason? Is it not rather looking for grain? Yes, and will an ox break into lowing at its manger when it has food?<verse eid="JOB 6:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:6"/>Can bread be eaten without salt? And is there any taste in empty words?<verse eid="JOB 6:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:7"/>So my life cannot cease, for I loathe my food like the smell of a lion.<verse eid="JOB 6:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:8"/>"O that he were willing, and my request proceed, and the Lord would grant my hope.<verse eid="JOB 6:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:9"/>Let the Lord begin by wounding me, but let him not kill me outright.<verse eid="JOB 6:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:10"/>And may my city, whose walls I used to leap upon, be my grave-- I will not spare myself, for I did not belie the holy words of my God.<verse eid="JOB 6:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:11"/>For what is my strength, that I endure, or what is my lifespan, that my life sustains itself?<verse eid="JOB 6:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:12"/>Is my strength the strength of stones, or is my flesh bronze?<verse eid="JOB 6:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:13"/>In truth, did I not trust in him? But help is far from me.<verse eid="JOB 6:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:14"/>"Mercy has renounced me, and the visitation of the Lord has disregarded me.<verse eid="JOB 6:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:15"/>My nearest kin did not look at me; like a wadi running dry or like a wave they passed by me.<verse eid="JOB 6:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:16"/>Those who held me in respect have now fallen on me like snow or like solid ice.<verse eid="JOB 6:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:17"/>Just as, melted, with heat coming on, it was not recognized for what it was,<verse eid="JOB 6:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:18"/>so I too was abandoned by all, and I perished and became homeless.<verse eid="JOB 6:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:19"/>Look at the roads of the Thaimanites, the paths of the Sabeans, you who see so clearly.<verse eid="JOB 6:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:20"/>They also will incur shame, who put their confidence in cities and wealth.<verse eid="JOB 6:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:21"/>But yet you too trod on me without mercy; so now that you have seen my hurt, be afraid!<verse eid="JOB 6:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:22"/>What? Did I ask anything of you? Or, am I in need of your strength<verse eid="JOB 6:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:23"/>to save me from enemies or to rescue me from the hand of the powerful?<verse eid="JOB 6:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:24"/>"Teach me, and I will shut up; if I have gone wrong in any way, show me.<verse eid="JOB 6:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:25"/>Rather, it seems that the words of one who is genuine are careless, so I do not seek strength from you.<verse eid="JOB 6:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:26"/>Not even your reproof with words will make me stop, nor indeed will I endure the sound of what you say.<verse eid="JOB 6:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:27"/>Fact is, you fall on an orphan and jump on your friend.<verse eid="JOB 6:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:28"/>"But now that I have looked into your faces I will not lie.<verse eid="JOB 6:28"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:29"/>Do sit down, and may no wrong be done, and gather again with him who is just.<verse eid="JOB 6:29"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 6:30"/>For there is nothing at all unjust on my tongue-- or does my throat not endeavor understanding?<verse eid="JOB 6:30"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:1"/>"Is not the life of a human being on earth a trial, and is not his life like that of a day- laborer?<verse eid="JOB 7:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:2"/>Or like an attendant who fears his master and finds shadow, or like a wage-earner waiting for his wages?<verse eid="JOB 7:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:3"/>I too spent empty months in this way, and nights of pain have been apportioned to me.<verse eid="JOB 7:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:4"/>If I lie down, I say, 'When will it be day?' But when I get up, again I say, 'When will it be evening?' And I am full of pain from evening until morning.<verse eid="JOB 7:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:5"/>As well, my body is defiled with the rot of worms, and I dissolve, scraping away lumps of dirt with the pus.<verse eid="JOB 7:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:6"/>Again, my life is lighter than talk, and it has perished in an empty hope.<verse eid="JOB 7:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:7"/>"Remember then that my life is a breath, and my eye will never come to see good again--<verse eid="JOB 7:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:8"/><verse eid="JOB 7:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:9"/>like a cloud, cleared from the sky. For if a mortal goes down to Hades, he does not come up again,<verse eid="JOB 7:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:10"/>and he shall never return to his house, nor does his place know him any more.<verse eid="JOB 7:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:11"/>"That said, however, I will not be sparing with my mouth; I will speak, though I am in anguish; I will open up the bitterness of my soul, though I am in dire straits.<verse eid="JOB 7:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:12"/>Am I Sea or Dragon, that you placed a guard over me?<verse eid="JOB 7:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:13"/>I said, 'My couch will comfort me,' and 'I will have a word with myself privately on my bed.'<verse eid="JOB 7:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:14"/>You scare me with dreams and terrify me with visions.<verse eid="JOB 7:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:15"/>You will release my soul from my spirit and my bones from death.<verse eid="JOB 7:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:16"/>For I will not live forever, or I would be patient. Let me alone, for my life is empty.<verse eid="JOB 7:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:17"/>What then is a human being, that you made so much of him or that you turn your attention to him,<verse eid="JOB 7:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:18"/>or will visit him until the morning and scrutinize him until he goes to rest?<verse eid="JOB 7:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:19"/>How long are you going to restrict me and not let go of me, until I swallow my spittle in pain?<verse eid="JOB 7:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:20"/>If I did sin, what can I do to you, you knower of the mind of humans? Why did you make me your accuser, and why am I a burden on you?<verse eid="JOB 7:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 7:21"/>Why did you not assign my lawlessness to oblivion and my sin to purging? But now I shall depart to the ground, and early in the morning I shall be no more."<verse eid="JOB 7:21"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:1"/>Now Baldad the Sauchite said in reply:<verse eid="JOB 8:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:2"/>"How long will you say these things? They are a wordy wind of your mouth!<verse eid="JOB 8:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:3"/>Will the Lord act unjustly when he judges, or will the maker of all things pervert what is right?<verse eid="JOB 8:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:4"/>If your children sinned before him, he sent them off by force of their lawlessness.<verse eid="JOB 8:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:5"/>But you, quickly approach the Lord Almighty in prayer.<verse eid="JOB 8:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:6"/>If you are pure and genuine, he will hear your entreaty and restore to you a righteous way of life.<verse eid="JOB 8:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:7"/>Then, though your first things be few, your last things will be unspeakably many.<verse eid="JOB 8:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:8"/>"For inquire of an earlier generation, and trace it out through a line of ancestors;<verse eid="JOB 8:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:9"/>for we are of yesterday and we know nothing, for our life is a shadow on the earth.<verse eid="JOB 8:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:10"/>Really, will they not teach you and declare and bring forth words from the heart?<verse eid="JOB 8:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:11"/>"Does papyrus grow without water, or sedge become tall without drink?<verse eid="JOB 8:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:12"/>While it is still on the root, it will in no way be harvested; no plant becomes dry, in preference to drinking!<verse eid="JOB 8:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:13"/>Such indeed will be the end of all who forget the Lord, for the hope of the impious shall perish.<verse eid="JOB 8:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:14"/>For his house will be uninhabited, and his tent will prove to be a spider's web.<verse eid="JOB 8:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:15"/>If he props up his house, it will not stand, and when he lays hold of it, it will not remain,<verse eid="JOB 8:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:16"/>for he is languid beneath the sun and his shoot will spread forth out of his rottenness.<verse eid="JOB 8:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:17"/>He goes to sleep on a gathering of stones, and he will live among rubble.<verse eid="JOB 8:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:18"/>If it swallows him up, the place will deny him; you have not seen such things,<verse eid="JOB 8:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:19"/>because such is the ruin of the impious, but from the soil something else will sprout up.<verse eid="JOB 8:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:20"/>"For the Lord will not reject the blameless person, but no gift will he accept from the impious.<verse eid="JOB 8:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:21"/>But he will fill the mouths of the sincere with laughter and their lips with confession,<verse eid="JOB 8:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 8:22"/>but their enemies will clothe themselves with shame, and the way of life of the impious will be no more."<verse eid="JOB 8:22"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:1"/>Now Iob said in reply:<verse eid="JOB 9:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:2"/>"Of a truth I know that it is so, for how can a mortal be right before the Lord?<verse eid="JOB 9:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:3"/>For if one wishes to go to law with him, he will not even answer him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'he will not even answer him':  Ziegler = Under</char></note>, lest he contest one charge of his out of a thousand.<verse eid="JOB 9:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:4"/>For he is clever in mind, both powerful and big-- who, though being unyielding, has endured against him?--<verse eid="JOB 9:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:5"/>he who ages mountains, and they do not know it, who overturns them in anger,<verse eid="JOB 9:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:6"/>who shakes what is under heaven from its foundations, and its pillars tremble,<verse eid="JOB 9:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:7"/>who speaks to the sun, and it does not rise, and seals up the stars,<verse eid="JOB 9:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:8"/>who alone stretched out the sky and walks on the sea as on dry ground,<verse eid="JOB 9:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:9"/>who makes Pleiades and Venus and Arcturus and the chambers of the south,<verse eid="JOB 9:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:10"/>who does great and inscrutable things, things both glorious and extraordinary, without number.<verse eid="JOB 9:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:11"/>If he passed over me, I would certainly not see him, and if he went by me, I would not even know.<verse eid="JOB 9:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:12"/>If he takes away, who will put back? Or who will say to him, 'What did you do?'<verse eid="JOB 9:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:13"/>"For he has not turned away from anger; the sea-monsters under heaven were bowed down by him.<verse eid="JOB 9:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:14"/>But if he has me respond, he will surely judge my words with discernment.<verse eid="JOB 9:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:15"/>For if I am in the right, he will not listen to me;<verse eid="JOB 9:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:16"/>and if I call and he responds, I am not going to believe that he has given ear to me.<verse eid="JOB 9:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:17"/>Would he really crush me with gloom? But he has made my wounds many without cause.<verse eid="JOB 9:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:18"/>For he does not let me get my breath, but he has filled me with bitterness.<verse eid="JOB 9:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:19"/>Because, for one thing, he really prevails by force, who then can withstand his judgment?<verse eid="JOB 9:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:20"/>For instance, should I be right, my mouth will turn out impious! And should I be blameless, I will prove to be perverse!<verse eid="JOB 9:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:21"/>For even if I acted impiously, I do not know it within myself-- except that my life is being taken away.<verse eid="JOB 9:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:22"/>Therefore I said, 'Anger destroys the great and powerful,<verse eid="JOB 9:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:23"/>because the worthless do exceptionally well in death, but those in the right are laughed to scorn--<verse eid="JOB 9:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:24"/>for they have been given over into the hands of the wicked.'<verse eid="JOB 9:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:25"/>"Now, my life is swifter than a runner; they<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the days of my life'</char></note> fled away, and they saw nothing.<verse eid="JOB 9:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:26"/>Is any trace at all left of a way taken by ships or of an eagle flying in search of prey?<verse eid="JOB 9:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:27"/>For if in fact I say, 'I will forget about speaking,' with my face bowed down, I will groan.<verse eid="JOB 9:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:28"/>I quiver in all my limbs, for I know you will not let me be innocent.<verse eid="JOB 9:28"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:29"/>But since I am impious, why have I not died?<verse eid="JOB 9:29"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:30"/>For if I wash myself with snow and cleanse myself with pure hands,<verse eid="JOB 9:30"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:31"/>you have plunged me fully in filth, and my robe abhorred me.<verse eid="JOB 9:31"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:32"/>For you are not a mortal like me, with whom I would contend, that we should agree to come to trial.<verse eid="JOB 9:32"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:33"/>Would that there were an arbiter for us and an investigator and one to hear the case between us two.<verse eid="JOB 9:33"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:34"/>Let him remove the rod from me, and let not the fear of him distract me--<verse eid="JOB 9:34"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 9:35"/>then I will not be afraid, but I will speak; for as it is, I am baffled.<verse eid="JOB 9:35"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:1"/>"Weary within, I will let loose my words upon him in groans; I will speak, tormented by the bitterness of my soul,<verse eid="JOB 10:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:2"/>and I will say to the Lord, Do not teach me to be impious, and why did you judge me like this?<verse eid="JOB 10:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:3"/>Does it seem good to you, if I be in the wrong, that you despise the work of your hands but favored the advice of the impious?<verse eid="JOB 10:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:4"/>Do you see as a mortal sees?<verse eid="JOB 10:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:5"/>Is your life human, or your years those of a man?<verse eid="JOB 10:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:6"/>Because you sought out my lawlessness and tracked down my sins.<verse eid="JOB 10:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:7"/>For you know that I did not act impiously, but who is there to deliver from your hands?<verse eid="JOB 10:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:8"/>Your hands fashioned me and made me; then you did an about face and struck me.<verse eid="JOB 10:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:9"/>Remember that you fashioned me as clay, and you are going to return me again to earth.<verse eid="JOB 10:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:10"/>Did you not pour me out like milk and curdle me like cheese?<verse eid="JOB 10:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:11"/>You clothed me with skin and flesh and knitted me together with bones and sinews.<verse eid="JOB 10:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:12"/>Then you granted me life and mercy, and your care preserved my spirit.<verse eid="JOB 10:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:13"/>Since you have these things in you, I know that you can do anything, and nothing is impossible for you.<verse eid="JOB 10:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:14"/>For two things: should I sin, you watch me, and you have not acquitted me of lawlessness.<verse eid="JOB 10:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:15"/>For if I be impious, alas! If I be righteous, I cannot lift up my head, for I am filled with disgrace.<verse eid="JOB 10:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:16"/>To wit, I am hunted like a lion for killing, and again, you make an about face and destroy me terribly.<verse eid="JOB 10:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:17"/>You renewed your scrutiny of me and treated me with great anger and brought trials on me.<verse eid="JOB 10:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:18"/>"Why then did you bring me out of the womb? And why did I not die and no eye see me<verse eid="JOB 10:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:19"/>and I be as if I had not been? For why was I not carried from the womb to the grave?<verse eid="JOB 10:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:20"/>Is not the length of my life short? Let me rest a little<verse eid="JOB 10:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:21"/>before I go whence I will not return, to a land, dark and gloomy,<verse eid="JOB 10:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 10:22"/>to a land of perpetual darkness, where there is no light and no glimpse of human life."<verse eid="JOB 10:22"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:1"/>Now Sophar the Minite said in reply:<verse eid="JOB 11:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:2"/>"He who says much will also listen in turn, or does he who is eloquent think he is right? Blessed is the short-lived offspring of woman.<verse eid="JOB 11:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:3"/>Do not become talkative, for there is no one to contend with you.<verse eid="JOB 11:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:4"/>For example, do not say, 'I am pure in my actions and blameless before him.'<verse eid="JOB 11:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:5"/>In that case, how could the Lord speak to you?<verse eid="JOB 11:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:6"/>Then he will disclose to you the power of wisdom, because it will be double what you have. And then you will know that what has come upon you from the Lord is equal to your sins.<verse eid="JOB 11:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:7"/>"Can you find the Lord's footprint, or have you reached the limits that the Almighty made?<verse eid="JOB 11:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:8"/>Heaven is high, and what will you do? And there are deeper things than in Hades; what do you know?<verse eid="JOB 11:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:9"/>Or are they not more extensive than the measure of the earth or the breadth of the sea?<verse eid="JOB 11:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:10"/>And if he overturns all that is, who will say to him, 'What did you do?'<verse eid="JOB 11:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:11"/>Indeed he knows the deeds of the lawless, and when he sees wrongs, he will not look aside.<verse eid="JOB 11:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:12"/>On the other hand, a human keeps afloat with words, and a mortal, born of woman, is like a desert ass.<verse eid="JOB 11:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:13"/>"For if you have made your heart pure, and you lift up your hands toward him--<verse eid="JOB 11:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:14"/>if anything lawless is in your hands, put it far away from you, and let no injustice lodge in your dwelling.<verse eid="JOB 11:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:15"/>For in this way your face will shine again like pure water, and you will put away defilement, and you shall not fear.<verse eid="JOB 11:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:16"/>And you will forget trouble like a passing wave and not be terrified.<verse eid="JOB 11:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:17"/>And your prayer will be as the morning star, and at midday life will dawn for you.<verse eid="JOB 11:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:18"/>You will be confident, because there is hope for you; as well, out of worry and care peace will appear clearly for you,<verse eid="JOB 11:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:19"/>for you will be at rest, and there will be no one to fight you; instead, many will do an about face and entreat your favor.<verse eid="JOB 11:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 11:20"/>But deliverance will fail them, for their hope is destruction, and the eyes of the impious will waste away."<verse eid="JOB 11:20"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:1"/>Now Iob said in reply:<verse eid="JOB 12:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:2"/>"So you alone are human beings; surely wisdom will die with you.<verse eid="JOB 12:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:3"/>For one thing, I too have a heart, just like you.<verse eid="JOB 12:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:4"/>A just and blameless man, you see, has become a laughingstock.<verse eid="JOB 12:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:5"/>To be sure, he had been ordained to fall under others for a set time and that his houses be plundered by the lawless.<verse eid="JOB 12:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:6"/>Nonetheless, let the wicked not trust that he will be guiltless-- as many as provoke the Lord-- as if indeed there will be no scrutiny of them.<verse eid="JOB 12:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:7"/>"But, do ask the quadrupeds, if they should speak to you, and the birds of the air, if they should declare to you,<verse eid="JOB 12:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:8"/>and tell the earth in detail, if it should expound to you.<verse eid="JOB 12:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:9"/><verse eid="JOB 12:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:10"/>Is not the life of all living things in his hand, and the breath of every human being?<verse eid="JOB 12:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:11"/>For it is the mind that discerns words but the throat that tastes food.<verse eid="JOB 12:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:12"/>Wisdom comes with much time, and knowledge with much living.<verse eid="JOB 12:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:13"/>"With him<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the Lord'</char></note> are wisdom and power; counsel and understanding are his.<verse eid="JOB 12:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:14"/>If he tears down, who can rebuild? If he shuts out people, who can open?<verse eid="JOB 12:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:15"/>If he withholds the water, he will dry up the earth, but if he lets it loose, he has destroyed it completely.<verse eid="JOB 12:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:16"/>With him are strength and power; knowledge and understanding are his.<verse eid="JOB 12:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:17"/>Leading counselors away captive, he maddened earthly judges.<verse eid="JOB 12:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:18"/>Seating kings upon thrones,<verse eid="JOB 12:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:19"/>sending away priests captive, he overthrew earth's mighty ones.<verse eid="JOB 12:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:20"/>Disrupting the lips of the faithful, he found out the understanding of elders<verse eid="JOB 12:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:21"/>but healed the humble<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">12:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'but healed the humble':  Ziegler = Under</char></note>.<verse eid="JOB 12:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:22"/>Revealing deep things out of darkness, he brought death's shadow to light.<verse eid="JOB 12:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:23"/><verse eid="JOB 12:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:24"/>Changing the hearts of earthly rulers, he made them wander by a way that they did not know:<verse eid="JOB 12:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 12:25"/>'May they grope in the dark without light, and may they wander about like a drunkard.'<verse eid="JOB 12:25"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:1"/>"Look, my eye has seen these things, and my ear has heard them,<verse eid="JOB 13:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:2"/>and I know what you too understand and am no less intelligent than you.<verse eid="JOB 13:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:3"/>Nonetheless, I will speak to the Lord and argue my case before him, if he wishes.<verse eid="JOB 13:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:4"/>But you are injurious physicians and healers of wrong things, all of you.<verse eid="JOB 13:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:5"/>But oh that you would be quiet and wisdom be yours as a result.<verse eid="JOB 13:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:6"/>Hear the reasoning of my mouth, and give heed to the argument of my lips.<verse eid="JOB 13:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:7"/>Are you not speaking before the Lord and uttering deceit before him?<verse eid="JOB 13:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:8"/>Really? Will you prevaricate? Go ahead; become judges yourselves!<verse eid="JOB 13:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:9"/>It would indeed be good, if he traced your footsteps; for if, in doing everything you can, you will join yourselves to him,<verse eid="JOB 13:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:10"/>he will convict you nonetheless. And even if secretly you will show partiality,<verse eid="JOB 13:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:11"/>will not his terrors distract you and fear from him assail you?<verse eid="JOB 13:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:12"/>Your arrogance, however, will turn out to be like ashes, and your body made of clay.<verse eid="JOB 13:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:13"/>"Be quiet! so I may speak and be relieved of rage.<verse eid="JOB 13:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:14"/>Having taken my flesh in my teeth, I will put my life in my hand.<verse eid="JOB 13:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:15"/>Though the Mighty One overpower me-- inasmuch as he has begun-- certainly I will speak and argue my case before him.<verse eid="JOB 13:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:16"/>And this for me will prove to be salvation, for deceit cannot enter before him.<verse eid="JOB 13:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:17"/>Hear, hear my words, for I will declare, while you listen.<verse eid="JOB 13:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:18"/>Look, I am near my trial; I know that I will be shown to be in the right.<verse eid="JOB 13:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:19"/>For who is there that will find fault with me?<verse eid="JOB 13:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:20"/>But you shall indulge me in two things:<verse eid="JOB 13:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:21"/>withdraw your hand from me, and let fear of you not terrify me.<verse eid="JOB 13:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:22"/>Then you will call, and I will answer you, or you will speak, and I will give you a response.<verse eid="JOB 13:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:23"/>How many are my sins and my acts of lawlessness? Teach me what they are.<verse eid="JOB 13:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:24"/>Why do you hide from me and regard me your opponent?<verse eid="JOB 13:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:25"/>Will you really be wary of one that is like a windblown leaf, or do you oppose me, one like windborne grass?--<verse eid="JOB 13:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:26"/>because you wrote harmful things against me and surrounded me with the sins of my youth.<verse eid="JOB 13:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:27"/>And you put my foot in a hobble and watched all my actions, and you reached to the bottoms of my feet.<verse eid="JOB 13:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 13:28"/>A worn out thing, like a skin, I am<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">13:28</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'I am':  Lacking in Greek</char></note>, or like a moth-eaten garment.<verse eid="JOB 13:28"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:1"/>"For a mortal, born of woman, is short-lived and full of aggravation<verse eid="JOB 14:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:2"/>or, like a flower that has bloomed, drops off and flees like a shadow and will not halt.<verse eid="JOB 14:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:3"/>Of him did you not in fact take account and make him enter into judgment before you?<verse eid="JOB 14:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:4"/>For who can be pure from filth? None, not one!<verse eid="JOB 14:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:5"/>Even if his life on the earth be but one day and his months be counted out to him, you have set a time, and he shall not go beyond it.<verse eid="JOB 14:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:6"/>Depart from him, that he may have quiet and enjoy life, like a wage-earner!<verse eid="JOB 14:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:7"/>"For there is hope for a tree; for if it is cut down, it will sprout again, and its branch will not fail.<verse eid="JOB 14:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:8"/>For, if its root grow old in earth and the crown of its root die in a rock,<verse eid="JOB 14:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:9"/>at the scent of water it will sprout and produce a crop like one newly planted.<verse eid="JOB 14:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:10"/>But a man, once dead, is gone, and a mortal, once fallen, is no more.<verse eid="JOB 14:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:11"/>For a sea with time diminishes, and a river, laid waste, is dried up,<verse eid="JOB 14:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:12"/>but a person, once lying down, shall never rise again until the sky become unstitched.<verse eid="JOB 14:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:13"/>O that you had kept me in Hades and had concealed me until your anger had ceased, and you had set me a time, when you would remember me.<verse eid="JOB 14:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:14"/>For, if a person died, then would live again, when he has completed the days of his life, I would endure until I would be born again.<verse eid="JOB 14:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:15"/>Presently you would call, and I would answer you-- only do not reject the works of your hands.<verse eid="JOB 14:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:16"/>But you tabulated my pursuits, and not one of my sins will pass by you,<verse eid="JOB 14:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:17"/>and you have sealed up my lawless acts in a pouch and marked down if I had somehow transgressed inadvertently.<verse eid="JOB 14:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:18"/><verse eid="JOB 14:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:19"/><verse eid="JOB 14:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:20"/>"You thrust him aside completely, and he was gone; you set your face against him and sent him away.<verse eid="JOB 14:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:21"/>And though his sons become many, he does not know, and if they become few, he is not aware.<verse eid="JOB 14:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 14:22"/>Ah, but his flesh suffered pain, and his soul grieved."<verse eid="JOB 14:22"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:1"/>Now Eliphaz<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">15:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = 'Eliphas'</char></note> the Thaimanite said in reply:<verse eid="JOB 15:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:2"/>"Will a wise man give an answer of windy insight, and did he satisfy the ache in his belly--<verse eid="JOB 15:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:3"/>arguing with statements that are beside the point, with words that are of no benefit?<verse eid="JOB 15:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:4"/>Have you not as well set aside fear and exhausted such statements before the Lord?<verse eid="JOB 15:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:5"/>You are guilty by the statements of your mouth and did not discern statements of the mighty.<verse eid="JOB 15:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:6"/>May your mouth refute you, and not I, and your lips will testify against you.<verse eid="JOB 15:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:7"/>"What? Were you the first of the human race to be born? Or were you established before the dunes?<verse eid="JOB 15:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:8"/>Did you hear the plan of the Lord, and did wisdom reach only you?<verse eid="JOB 15:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:9"/>For what do you know that we do not know? Or what do you understand that we do not as well?<verse eid="JOB 15:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:10"/><verse eid="JOB 15:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:11"/>You have been scourged for but few of your sins; you have spoken wildly extravagantly.<verse eid="JOB 15:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:12"/>What did your heart dare, or what did your eyes set themselves upon,<verse eid="JOB 15:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:13"/>that you burst forth in rage before the Lord and brought out such remarks from your mouth?<verse eid="JOB 15:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:14"/>For who, being mortal, can be blameless, or who can be in the right, born of woman?<verse eid="JOB 15:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:15"/>If he places no faith in his holy ones, then heaven is not pure before him.<verse eid="JOB 15:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:16"/>But aha, abominable and impure, a man drinking injustices like a drink!<verse eid="JOB 15:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:17"/>"But I will declare to you; hear me; indeed, what I have seen I will declare to you--<verse eid="JOB 15:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:18"/>what sages will say and did not hide from their ancestors;<verse eid="JOB 15:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:19"/>to them alone the earth was given, and no alien came upon them.<verse eid="JOB 15:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:20"/>The entire life of the impious is spent in anxiety, and the years given to the mighty are numbered.<verse eid="JOB 15:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:21"/>And the dread of him is in his ears; just when he thinks he is at peace, his destruction will come.<verse eid="JOB 15:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:22"/>Let him not believe he will return from darkness, for he has already been consigned to a blade's power;<verse eid="JOB 15:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:23"/>moreover, he has been allocated as food for vultures, and he knows within himself that he remains as a carcass. And a dark day will whirl him around,<verse eid="JOB 15:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:24"/>and distress and anguish will take hold of him; he will be like a general falling in the front rank.<verse eid="JOB 15:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:25"/>Because he lifted his hands against the Lord and stiffened his neck against the Lord Almighty<verse eid="JOB 15:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:26"/>and ran against him with insolence,<verse eid="JOB 15:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:27"/><verse eid="JOB 15:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:28"/>then may he lodge in desolate cities and enter uninhabited houses, and what they prepared, others will carry away.<verse eid="JOB 15:28"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:29"/>Neither shall he ever become rich, nor shall his possessions last. He shall not cast a shadow upon the ground,<verse eid="JOB 15:29"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:30"/>nor shall he escape darkness. May the wind dry up his bud, and may his blossom fall off.<verse eid="JOB 15:30"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:31"/>Let him not believe that he will endure, for emptiness will turn out to be his lot.<verse eid="JOB 15:31"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:32"/>His stump will perish before its time, and his branch will provide no cover.<verse eid="JOB 15:32"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:33"/>But may he be picked like unripe grapes, before his time, and fall off, like an olive blossom.<verse eid="JOB 15:33"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:34"/>For the testimony of the impious is death, and fire will burn the houses of bribe- takers.<verse eid="JOB 15:34"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 15:35"/>And he will conceive sorrows, and his lot will turn out to be emptiness, and his belly will carry deceit."<verse eid="JOB 15:35"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:1"/>Now Iob said in reply:<verse eid="JOB 16:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:2"/>"I have heard many such things; comforters of what's worthless are you all.<verse eid="JOB 16:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:3"/>What? Is there any rhyme or reason to windy words?<verse eid="JOB 16:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:4"/>I also would talk as you do, if your life were in fact in the place of mine; then I would jump at you with words and shake my head at you.<verse eid="JOB 16:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:5"/>But may there be strength in my mouth-- then I shall not spare you the moving of my lips!<verse eid="JOB 16:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:6"/>For if I speak, I shall not aggravate my wound, but even if I remain silent, how shall I be wounded less?<verse eid="JOB 16:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:7"/>"But as it is, he has made me worn out, a fool, wasted away.<verse eid="JOB 16:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:8"/><verse eid="JOB 16:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:9"/>Acting in wrath, he has thrown me down; he has gnashed his teeth at me; his brigands' arrows fell on me.<verse eid="JOB 16:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:10"/>With darts from his eyes he dashed at me; he struck me on the cheek with something sharp, and they ran at me with one accord.<verse eid="JOB 16:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:11"/>For the Lord delivered me into the hands of the unjust and cast me to the impious.<verse eid="JOB 16:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:12"/>When I was at peace, he scattered me; he seized me by the hair and pulled it out; he set me up like a target.<verse eid="JOB 16:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:13"/>They surrounded me with spears, hurling them into my kidneys, without sparing; they poured out my gall on the ground.<verse eid="JOB 16:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:14"/>They threw me down, fall upon fall; they rushed at me powerfully.<verse eid="JOB 16:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:15"/>I sewed sackcloth upon my skin, and my strength was extinguished in dust.<verse eid="JOB 16:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:16"/>My belly is aflame from weeping, and there is a shadow on my eyelids.<verse eid="JOB 16:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:17"/>But there was nothing unjust in my hands, and my prayer was pure.<verse eid="JOB 16:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:18"/>"O earth, do not cover up the blood of my flesh, nor may there be a place for my cry.<verse eid="JOB 16:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:19"/>Even now, look, my witness is above, and my corroborator is on high.<verse eid="JOB 16:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:20"/>May my petition reach the Lord, and before him may my eye shed a tear.<verse eid="JOB 16:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:21"/>And may a man have proof before the Lord!<verse eid="JOB 16:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 16:22"/>But the numbered years have come to an end, and I shall go the way by which I shall not return.<verse eid="JOB 16:22"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 17:1"/>"I perish, being carried off by the wind, and I beg for burial and do not find it.<verse eid="JOB 17:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 17:2"/>I pray wearily, and what have I achieved?<verse eid="JOB 17:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 17:3"/>No, strangers have stolen my possessions,<verse eid="JOB 17:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 17:4"/><verse eid="JOB 17:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 17:5"/>and my eyes have dissolved over my children.<verse eid="JOB 17:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 17:6"/>"And you have made me a byword among nations, and I have become a laughing-stock to them,<verse eid="JOB 17:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 17:7"/>for my eyes have turned to stone from anger; I am greatly besieged by all.<verse eid="JOB 17:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 17:8"/>Wonder at this has seized the truthful, and may the just rise up against the transgressor,<verse eid="JOB 17:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 17:9"/>and the faithful hold to his own way, and may one with pure hands take courage.<verse eid="JOB 17:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 17:10"/>Nonetheless, you all keep pressing hard, for I find nothing true in you.<verse eid="JOB 17:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 17:11"/>My days have passed in a roar, and my heartstrings were broken.<verse eid="JOB 17:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 17:12"/><verse eid="JOB 17:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 17:13"/>For if I last, Hades is my house, and my bed lies spread in gloom.<verse eid="JOB 17:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 17:14"/>I called on death to be my father and decay to be my mother and sister.<verse eid="JOB 17:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 17:15"/>Where then is yet my hope? Shall I see my goods?<verse eid="JOB 17:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 17:16"/>Will they go down with me to Hades?"<verse eid="JOB 17:16"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:1"/>Now Baldad the Sauchite said in reply:<verse eid="JOB 18:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:2"/>"How long before you stop? Hold back, so that we too can speak.<verse eid="JOB 18:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:3"/>Why have we, like quadrupeds, been silent before you?<verse eid="JOB 18:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:4"/>Anger has used you. What? If you die, will what is under heaven be uninhabited? Or will mountains be overthrown from their foundations?<verse eid="JOB 18:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:5"/>"Yes, the light of the impious will be put out, and their flame will not do well.<verse eid="JOB 18:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:6"/>His light is darkness in his dwelling, and his lamp will be put out on him.<verse eid="JOB 18:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:7"/>May those of least account chase down his possessions, and may his counsel trip him up.<verse eid="JOB 18:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:8"/>But his foot has been thrust into a snare; may he be entangled in a net,<verse eid="JOB 18:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:9"/>and may snares come upon him!<verse eid="JOB 18:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:10"/><verse eid="JOB 18:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:11"/>May pains destroy him on every side, and may many beset him in severe famine.<verse eid="JOB 18:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:12"/>But an extraordinary fall has been prepared for him--<verse eid="JOB 18:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:13"/>may the digits of his feet be devoured, and death will consume his maturity.<verse eid="JOB 18:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:14"/>And may healing be torn from his dwelling, and may duress take hold of him by royal charge.<verse eid="JOB 18:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:15"/><verse eid="JOB 18:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:16"/><verse eid="JOB 18:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:17"/>May mention of him perish from earth;<verse eid="JOB 18:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:18"/>may he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">18:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the Lord'</char></note> drive him away from light into darkness.<verse eid="JOB 18:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:19"/>He will no longer be known among his people, nor will his house be preserved on what is under heaven; rather, others will live in what is his.<verse eid="JOB 18:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:20"/>The last groaned over him, and wonder seized the first.<verse eid="JOB 18:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 18:21"/>These are the houses of the unjust, and this is the place of those that do not know the Lord."<verse eid="JOB 18:21"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:1"/>Now Iob said in reply:<verse eid="JOB 19:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:2"/>"How long will you make my soul weary and destroy me with words?<verse eid="JOB 19:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:3"/>Know only that the Lord treated me this way; you speak against me; shamelessly you press upon me.<verse eid="JOB 19:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:4"/>Yes indeed, I have truly erred, and error lodges with me-- to have spoken a word that was not fitting, and my words err and are inappropriate.<verse eid="JOB 19:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:5"/>But alas, it is because you magnify yourselves against me and jump at me with reproach.<verse eid="JOB 19:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:6"/>Know then that it is the Lord who troubles me, and he raised up his stronghold against me.<verse eid="JOB 19:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:7"/>Look, I laugh at reproach, and I will not speak; I will cry out, and nowhere is there judgment.<verse eid="JOB 19:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:8"/>I am hemmed in all around and cannot get out; he has placed darkness upon my face.<verse eid="JOB 19:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:9"/>And he has stripped my glory from me and taken the crown from my head.<verse eid="JOB 19:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:10"/>He totally isolated me, and I was gone, and he has cut down my hope like a tree.<verse eid="JOB 19:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:11"/>And he has dealt with me terribly in anger and has counted me as an enemy.<verse eid="JOB 19:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:12"/>And with one accord his gangs of brigands came against me; they encircled me on my paths, lying in ambush.<verse eid="JOB 19:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:13"/>"And my brothers turned away from me; they recognized strangers rather than me. And friends of mine became merciless.<verse eid="JOB 19:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:14"/>My nearest kin disowned me, and those who knew my name forgot me.<verse eid="JOB 19:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:15"/>As for neighbors next door and my servant girls-- I became an alien to them.<verse eid="JOB 19:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:16"/>I called my attendant, and he did not respond; yet my mouth kept pleading.<verse eid="JOB 19:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:17"/>I also repeatedly implored my wife, and, using flattery, I kept summoning sons of my concubines,<verse eid="JOB 19:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:18"/>but they rejected me for all time; when I rise, they talk against me.<verse eid="JOB 19:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:19"/>My acquaintances abhorred me, and those I had loved rose up against me.<verse eid="JOB 19:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:20"/>My flesh rotted under my skin, and my bones are held in my teeth.<verse eid="JOB 19:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:21"/>Pity me; pity me, O my friends, for it is the Lord's hand that has touched me.<verse eid="JOB 19:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:22"/>But why do you pursue me just as the Lord does, and why are you not satisfied with my flesh?<verse eid="JOB 19:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:23"/>"For who would grant that my words be written and that they be put in a book forever<verse eid="JOB 19:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:24"/>or be carved in rock?<verse eid="JOB 19:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:25"/>To be sure, I know that he who is about to undo me on earth is everlasting.<verse eid="JOB 19:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:26"/>May my skin, which patiently endures these things, rise up; for these things have been accomplished on me by the Lord--<verse eid="JOB 19:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:27"/>things I am conscious of in myself, things my eye has seen and no other, and all of them have come to an end for me in my bosom.<verse eid="JOB 19:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:28"/>But even if you say, 'What shall we say before him?'<verse eid="JOB 19:28"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 19:29"/>Do as well be afraid of a cover-up, for wrath will come upon the lawless, and then they will find out where their substance is."<verse eid="JOB 19:29"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:1"/>Now Sophar the Minite said in reply:<verse eid="JOB 20:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:2"/>"I did not suppose that you would counter these things so, and surely the rest of you have gained no better understanding than I--<verse eid="JOB 20:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:3"/><verse eid="JOB 20:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:4"/>not since mortals were placed on the earth!<verse eid="JOB 20:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:5"/>For the merriment of the impious ends in an extraordinary fall, and the enjoyment of transgressors in destruction,<verse eid="JOB 20:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:6"/>even if his gifts go up to heaven and his sacrifices touch the clouds.<verse eid="JOB 20:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:7"/>For just when he thinks he is firmly established, at that point he will be utterly destroyed, and those who saw him will say, 'Where is he?'<verse eid="JOB 20:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:8"/>Like a dream that has taken to flight, he shall not be found, but he has flown away like a nocturnal apparition!<verse eid="JOB 20:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:9"/><verse eid="JOB 20:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:10"/>"May his inferiors do away with his sons, and his hands kindle pains.<verse eid="JOB 20:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:11"/><verse eid="JOB 20:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:12"/><verse eid="JOB 20:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:13"/><verse eid="JOB 20:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:14"/>And he shall not be able to help himself.<verse eid="JOB 20:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:15"/>"Wealth being gathered unjustly will be disgorged; a messenger will drag it out of his house.<verse eid="JOB 20:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:16"/>And may he suck the wrath of dragons, and may a snake's tongue kill him.<verse eid="JOB 20:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:17"/>May he not see the milk of pastures nor pasturage of honey and butter.<verse eid="JOB 20:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:18"/>Vainly and foolishly he has toiled for wealth of which he will not taste; it will be like something tough, unchewable, impossible to swallow.<verse eid="JOB 20:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:19"/>For he has broken down the houses of many who are powerless, and he has seized a dwelling, though he did not build it.<verse eid="JOB 20:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:20"/>"His possessions hold no security for him;<verse eid="JOB 20:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:21"/>therefore his goods will not flourish.<verse eid="JOB 20:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:22"/>But just when he thinks he has fully satisfied himself, he will be afflicted, and every distress will come upon him.<verse eid="JOB 20:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:23"/>May he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">20:23</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'God'</char></note> send on him fierce wrath; may he wash pains on him.<verse eid="JOB 20:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:24"/>And he shall not escape a blade's power; may a bronze bow wound him.<verse eid="JOB 20:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:25"/>Yes, may an arrow pass through his body, and may lightning bolts strut about in his dwellings.<verse eid="JOB 20:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:26"/>Then may utter darkness await him; unquenchable fire will devour him-- and may a stranger afflict his house.<verse eid="JOB 20:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:27"/>And may heaven uncover his acts of lawlessness and earth rise up against him.<verse eid="JOB 20:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:28"/>May destruction drag his house to an end; may a day of anger come upon him.<verse eid="JOB 20:28"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 20:29"/>This is the portion of an impious person from the Lord, and possession of his things is from the Overseer."<verse eid="JOB 20:29"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:1"/>Now Iob said in reply:<verse eid="JOB 21:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:2"/>" Listen, listen to my words, lest this be your consolation for me.<verse eid="JOB 21:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:3"/>Lift me up, and I will speak; then you will not laugh me to scorn.<verse eid="JOB 21:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:4"/>What? My argument is not with a mortal, is it? Or, why should I not be angry?<verse eid="JOB 21:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:5"/>Look at me, and marvel, laying your hand on your cheek.<verse eid="JOB 21:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:6"/>For even when I remember, I am in haste, and pains seize my flesh.<verse eid="JOB 21:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:7"/>Why do the impious live on and grow old, even in wealth?<verse eid="JOB 21:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:8"/>Their progeny are according to their pleasure, and their children in their sight.<verse eid="JOB 21:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:9"/>Their houses prosper without any fear, and no scourge from the Lord is upon them.<verse eid="JOB 21:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:10"/>Their cow did not miscarry, and their pregnant one came through safely and did not falter.<verse eid="JOB 21:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:11"/>And they remain as ageless sheep, and their children play about<verse eid="JOB 21:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:12"/>when they take up the harp and lyre and make merry to the sound of a melody.<verse eid="JOB 21:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:13"/>And they finished their life in prosperity and lay down in the repose of Hades.<verse eid="JOB 21:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:14"/>But he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">21:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the impious'</char></note> says to the Lord, 'Stay away from me; I do not wish to know your ways.'<verse eid="JOB 21:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:15"/><verse eid="JOB 21:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:16"/>For their good things were in their hands, but he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">21:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the Lord'</char></note> does not regard the works of the impious.<verse eid="JOB 21:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:17"/>"Nonetheless, the lamp of the impious shall also be put out, and destruction shall come upon them, and sharp pains shall seize them, because of anger.<verse eid="JOB 21:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:18"/>And they shall be as chaff before the wind or as dust that the whirlwind has sucked up.<verse eid="JOB 21:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:19"/>May his possessions fail his sons.<verse eid="JOB 21:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:20"/>May his eyes see his own slaughter, and may he not escape from the Lord.<verse eid="JOB 21:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:21"/><verse eid="JOB 21:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:22"/>Is it not the Lord who teaches understanding and knowledge? But he will discerningly judge murders.<verse eid="JOB 21:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:23"/><verse eid="JOB 21:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:24"/>And his inwards are full of fat<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">21:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'his inwards are full of fat':  Ziegler = 'as for his inwards, he is full of fat'</char></note>, and his marrow is being dispersed.<verse eid="JOB 21:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:25"/>And he dies of bitterness of soul, not eating anything good.<verse eid="JOB 21:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:26"/>But one and all, they lay down on the ground, and decay covered them.<verse eid="JOB 21:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:27"/>"So I know you, that you daringly attack me.<verse eid="JOB 21:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:28"/><verse eid="JOB 21:28"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:29"/><verse eid="JOB 21:29"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:30"/><verse eid="JOB 21:30"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:31"/><verse eid="JOB 21:31"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:32"/><verse eid="JOB 21:32"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:33"/><verse eid="JOB 21:33"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 21:34"/>How then will you comfort me with emptiness? And I have no rest at all from you."<verse eid="JOB 21:34"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:1"/>Now Eliphaz<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">22:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = 'Eliphas'</char></note> the Thaimanite said in reply:<verse eid="JOB 22:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:2"/>"Is it not the Lord who teaches understanding and knowledge?<verse eid="JOB 22:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:3"/>For what does it matter to the Lord if you were blameless in your actions?<verse eid="JOB 22:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:4"/>Though he makes an account of you, will he reprove you, and will he go to trial with you?<verse eid="JOB 22:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:5"/>Is your evil not abundant, and are your sins not without number?<verse eid="JOB 22:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:6"/>Yes, you used to take your brothers in pledge for no reason and took away the clothing of the naked.<verse eid="JOB 22:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:7"/>Nor did you give water to the thirsty to drink but withheld a morsel from the hungry.<verse eid="JOB 22:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:8"/>And you made favorites of some and settled them on the land,<verse eid="JOB 22:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:9"/>but you sent away widows empty and mistreated orphans.<verse eid="JOB 22:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:10"/>Therefore snares have encircled you, and an extraordinary conflict has hurried you.<verse eid="JOB 22:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:11"/>The light has proved to be darkness for you, and water has covered you while you slept.<verse eid="JOB 22:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:12"/>"Does not he who dwells on high observe, and has he not humbled those borne along by pride?<verse eid="JOB 22:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:13"/><verse eid="JOB 22:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:14"/><verse eid="JOB 22:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:15"/><verse eid="JOB 22:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:16"/><verse eid="JOB 22:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:17"/>Those who say, 'What will the Lord do to us?' or, 'What will the Almighty bring against us?'--<verse eid="JOB 22:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:18"/>yet he it was who filled their houses with good things, though the counsel of the impious is far from him.<verse eid="JOB 22:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:19"/>Those in the right laughed when they saw it, and the blameless mocked.<verse eid="JOB 22:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:20"/><verse eid="JOB 22:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:21"/>"Do be unyielding, if you would endure; then your fruit will prosper.<verse eid="JOB 22:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:22"/>And accept an utterance from his mouth, and take up his words in your heart.<verse eid="JOB 22:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:23"/>And if you turn and humble yourself before the Lord, you have put what is unjust far from your dwelling.<verse eid="JOB 22:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:24"/><verse eid="JOB 22:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:25"/>Therefore the Almighty will be your help from enemies, and he will render you pure as silver tried by fire.<verse eid="JOB 22:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:26"/>Then you will speak frankly before the Lord, looking up to heaven cheerfully.<verse eid="JOB 22:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:27"/>And when you pray to him, he will listen to you and give to you to pay your vows.<verse eid="JOB 22:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 22:28"/>Yes, he will restore to you a righteous way of life, and there will be light on your ways."<verse eid="JOB 22:28"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:1"/>Iob said in reply:<verse eid="JOB 23:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:2"/>"Yes, I do know that argumentation is out of my reach, and his hand has become heavy on my groaning.<verse eid="JOB 23:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:3"/>But who would then know that I might find him and come to a resolution?<verse eid="JOB 23:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:4"/>But oh that I could state my case before him and fill my mouth with arguments.<verse eid="JOB 23:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:5"/>Then I would know the words that he would say to me and perceive what he would declare to me.<verse eid="JOB 23:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:6"/>Even if he comes upon me with great strength, then he will not treat me with a threat;<verse eid="JOB 23:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:7"/>for truth and reproof are from him-- but oh that he would bring my case to an end!<verse eid="JOB 23:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:8"/>"For I will go first and be no more, and what do I know about things at the end?<verse eid="JOB 23:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:9"/><verse eid="JOB 23:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:10"/>For he already knows my way and has discerningly judged me like gold.<verse eid="JOB 23:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:11"/>But I will go forth when he commands, for I have kept his ways and I will never turn aside.<verse eid="JOB 23:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:12"/>Nor shall I go away from what he commands, but I have treasured his words in my bosom.<verse eid="JOB 23:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:13"/>But if even he has so judged, who is there to contradict him? For what he has wanted he also has done.<verse eid="JOB 23:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:14"/><verse eid="JOB 23:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:15"/>Therefore I am in haste about him, and when I was admonished, I gave heed to him.<verse eid="JOB 23:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:16"/>But the Lord enfeebled my heart, and the Almighty hurried me.<verse eid="JOB 23:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 23:17"/>For I did not know that darkness would come upon me, but gloom has fallen as a covering before my face.<verse eid="JOB 23:17"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:1"/>"But why did times escape the notice of the Lord,<verse eid="JOB 24:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:2"/>and the impious overstepped the limit, when they seized flock with shepherd?<verse eid="JOB 24:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:3"/>They led away the orphans' beast of burden and took the widow's ox in pledge.<verse eid="JOB 24:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:4"/>They turned aside the powerless from the righteous way.<verse eid="JOB 24:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:5"/>And they proved to be like donkeys in a field, because of me doing their own thing.<verse eid="JOB 24:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:6"/>They reaped a field not their own before its time, but the powerless worked vineyards of the impious without pay or food.<verse eid="JOB 24:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:7"/>They made many go to sleep naked, without clothes, and took away the covering from their person.<verse eid="JOB 24:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:8"/>Because they had no shelter, they surrounded themselves with rock.<verse eid="JOB 24:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:9"/>"They snatched the orphan from the breast and humiliated one that had fallen.<verse eid="JOB 24:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:10"/>And they had the naked sleep, unjustly, and took away the morsel of the hungry.<verse eid="JOB 24:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:11"/>They unjustly laid in wait in narrow places and did not know the righteous way.<verse eid="JOB 24:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:12"/>Those who cast them<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">24:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the powerless'</char></note> out of the city and their own houses, though the soul of the young groaned loudly-- and he, why has he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">24:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the Lord'</char></note> not paid these a visit?<verse eid="JOB 24:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:13"/>"While they were on earth, they did not even notice them, and they did not know the way of righteousness, nor did they travel its pathways.<verse eid="JOB 24:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:14"/>But when he knew their deeds, he handed them over to darkness.<verse eid="JOB 24:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:15"/><verse eid="JOB 24:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:16"/><verse eid="JOB 24:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:17"/><verse eid="JOB 24:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:18"/>"May their earthly portion be cursed,<verse eid="JOB 24:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:19"/>and may their plants on earth appear withered, for they seized the orphans' armful.<verse eid="JOB 24:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:20"/>Then his sin was remembered<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">24:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'his sin was remembered':  Or 'sin remembered him'</char></note>, and he disappeared like a dewy mist, but may what he did be paid back to him, and may every unjust person be crushed like an incurable tree!<verse eid="JOB 24:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:21"/>"For he did not treat well the barren woman and had no pity on the weak woman.<verse eid="JOB 24:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:22"/>And in wrath he overthrew the powerless. Therefore, when he has risen up, he will not feel secure about his own life.<verse eid="JOB 24:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:23"/>When he is sickly, let him not hope to regain health; rather, he will fall by disease.<verse eid="JOB 24:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:24"/>For his loftiness harmed many, but he shriveled away like a mallow in the heat or as an ear of corn, fallen off the stalk of itself.<verse eid="JOB 24:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 24:25"/>But if it is not so, who is there to say that I speak what is false?"<verse eid="JOB 24:25"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 25:1"/>Now Baldad the Sauchite said in reply:<verse eid="JOB 25:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 25:2"/>"Why, what preamble or fear is there with him, he who on high keeps making the entire earth?<verse eid="JOB 25:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 25:3"/>For would there be anyone who thinks there is respite for brigands? And upon whom will not come ambushes from him?<verse eid="JOB 25:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 25:4"/>For how can a mortal be right before the Lord? Or who, born of woman, could purify himself?<verse eid="JOB 25:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 25:5"/>If he instructs the moon, then it does not shine, and the stars are not pure before him.<verse eid="JOB 25:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 25:6"/>But alas, a human being is rot!"<verse eid="JOB 25:6"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 26:1"/>Now Iob said in reply:<verse eid="JOB 26:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 26:2"/>"To whom are you devoted, or to whom are you about to provide help? Is it not to him who has much strength and a strong arm?<verse eid="JOB 26:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 26:3"/>With whom have you taken counsel? Is it not with him who has all wisdom? Or whom will you follow? Is it not he who has the greatest power?<verse eid="JOB 26:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 26:4"/>To whom did you utter words? And whose breath is it that comes forth from you?<verse eid="JOB 26:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 26:5"/><verse eid="JOB 26:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 26:6"/><verse eid="JOB 26:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 26:7"/><verse eid="JOB 26:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 26:8"/><verse eid="JOB 26:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 26:9"/><verse eid="JOB 26:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 26:10"/><verse eid="JOB 26:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 26:11"/><verse eid="JOB 26:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 26:12"/>By force he calmed the sea, and by knowledge he struck down the sea-monster,<verse eid="JOB 26:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 26:13"/>and heaven's bars fear him, and by decree he put to death the rebellious dragon.<verse eid="JOB 26:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 26:14"/>And the force of his thunder-- who knows when it will act?"<verse eid="JOB 26:14"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:1"/>Now Iob, yet further to his preamble, said:<verse eid="JOB 27:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:2"/>"The Lord lives, who has judged me so, and the Almighty, who has embittered my soul--<verse eid="JOB 27:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:3"/>indeed, while my breath is still within me and a divine puff of air is what remains in my nostrils,<verse eid="JOB 27:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:4"/>my lips will not speak lawless things, nor will my soul ponder injustices.<verse eid="JOB 27:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:5"/>Far be it from me to declare that you are right, until I die, for I will not relinquish my innocence.<verse eid="JOB 27:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:6"/>But holding fast to righteousness, I will never let it go, for I am not conscious within myself of having done anything amiss.<verse eid="JOB 27:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:7"/>"Nonetheless, may my enemies be like the ruin of the impious, and those who rise up against me like the destruction of the transgressors.<verse eid="JOB 27:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:8"/>To be sure, what hope does the impious have that he hangs on? When he trusts in the Lord, will he be saved?<verse eid="JOB 27:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:9"/>Will the Lord listen to his petition? Or when distress comes upon him,<verse eid="JOB 27:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:10"/>does he have any confidence before him? Or as he calls upon him, will he listen to him?<verse eid="JOB 27:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:11"/>Well then, I will declare to you what is in the Lord's hand; what is with the Almighty, I will not falsify.<verse eid="JOB 27:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:12"/>Look here, all of you know that you are piling nothing upon nothing.<verse eid="JOB 27:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:13"/>"This is the portion of an impious person from the Lord, and the possession of the powerful will come from the Almighty upon them.<verse eid="JOB 27:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:14"/>Now if his sons be many, they shall be for slaughter, and if perchance they reach manhood, they shall be beggars.<verse eid="JOB 27:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:15"/>And those of his who survive will end in death, and no one will pity their widows.<verse eid="JOB 27:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:16"/>If he gathers silver like dirt and prepares gold like clay,<verse eid="JOB 27:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:17"/>all these the righteous will gain, and his money the truthful will possess.<verse eid="JOB 27:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:18"/>And his house turned out like moths and like a spider's web.<verse eid="JOB 27:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:19"/>Though he lies down rich, he will not in fact add to it.<verse eid="JOB 27:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 27:20"/>Pain came upon him like water, and gloom carried him off by night.<verse eid="JOB 27:20"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 28"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:1"/>"For silver has a place from which it comes, and gold a place from where it is sifted.<verse eid="JOB 28:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:2"/>For whereas iron comes out of the earth, copper is quarried like stone.<verse eid="JOB 28:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:3"/>He imposed order on darkness,<verse eid="JOB 28:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:4"/>and those of mortals who kept forgetting the righteous way became weak.<verse eid="JOB 28:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:5"/><verse eid="JOB 28:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:6"/><verse eid="JOB 28:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:7"/><verse eid="JOB 28:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:8"/><verse eid="JOB 28:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:9"/>And he overturned mountains from their roots<verse eid="JOB 28:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:10"/>and broke whirlpools of rivers-- and my eye saw every precious thing.<verse eid="JOB 28:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:11"/>And he uncovered rivers' depths and showed his own power to the light.<verse eid="JOB 28:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:12"/>"But wisdom-- where was it found? And of what sort is the place of knowledge?<verse eid="JOB 28:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:13"/>No mortal knows its way, nor will it ever be discovered among human beings.<verse eid="JOB 28:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:14"/><verse eid="JOB 28:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:15"/><verse eid="JOB 28:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:16"/><verse eid="JOB 28:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:17"/><verse eid="JOB 28:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:18"/><verse eid="JOB 28:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:19"/><verse eid="JOB 28:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:20"/>"But wisdom-- where was it found? And of what sort is the place of knowledge?<verse eid="JOB 28:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:21"/>It has escaped notice by any human,<verse eid="JOB 28:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:22"/>but we have heard of its renown.<verse eid="JOB 28:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:23"/>"God has established well its way, and he himself knows its place,<verse eid="JOB 28:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:24"/>for he observes all that is under heaven, since he knows all the earth contains, that which he made--<verse eid="JOB 28:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:25"/>the weight of winds and the measures of water!<verse eid="JOB 28:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:26"/>When he had done so, he looked and<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">28:26</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'he looked and':  Ziegler = 'rain'</char></note> made a count;<verse eid="JOB 28:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:27"/>since he prepared them, he kept track of them.<verse eid="JOB 28:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 28:28"/>And he said to humankind, 'Look, the worship of God is wisdom, and to stay away from evil is knowledge.' "<verse eid="JOB 28:28"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 29"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:1"/>Now Iob, yet further to his preamble, said:<verse eid="JOB 29:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:2"/>"Who might put me in a month of former days, when God watched over me,<verse eid="JOB 29:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:3"/>as when his lamp would shine over my head, when by his light I strode in darkness,<verse eid="JOB 29:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:4"/>when I was pressing on my ways, when God would pay a visit to my house,<verse eid="JOB 29:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:5"/>when I was very much a person of substance and my children were around me,<verse eid="JOB 29:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:6"/>when my roads were flowing with butter and my hills flowed with milk!--<verse eid="JOB 29:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:7"/>when I would go out early in the city and my seat was placed in the squares.<verse eid="JOB 29:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:8"/>When young men saw me, they hid, and the aged, all of them stood,<verse eid="JOB 29:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:9"/>and prominent men stopped talking, putting a finger to their mouth.<verse eid="JOB 29:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:10"/>And those who heard counted me happy,<verse eid="JOB 29:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:11"/>and the eye that saw me averted its glance,<verse eid="JOB 29:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:12"/>for I delivered the poor from the hand of the powerful, and the orphan, who had no helper, I helped,<verse eid="JOB 29:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:13"/>and the widow's mouth blessed me.<verse eid="JOB 29:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:14"/>Yes, I put on righteousness and was clothed with justice like a cloak.<verse eid="JOB 29:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:15"/>I was the eye of the blind and the foot of the lame.<verse eid="JOB 29:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:16"/>It was I that was a father to the powerless, and a case I did not know I investigated.<verse eid="JOB 29:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:17"/>And I broke the molars of the unjust and tore prey from between their teeth.<verse eid="JOB 29:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:18"/>And I said, 'My manhood will see old age; I shall live a long while, like the trunk of a palm tree.'<verse eid="JOB 29:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:19"/><verse eid="JOB 29:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:20"/><verse eid="JOB 29:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:21"/>"When they heard me, they took heed and fell silent at my counsel.<verse eid="JOB 29:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:22"/>And they did not add to what I said but became overjoyed whenever I spoke to them.<verse eid="JOB 29:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:23"/>As thirsty earth welcomes the rain, so these welcomed what I said.<verse eid="JOB 29:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 29:24"/>If I smiled toward them, they would not believe it.<verse eid="JOB 29:24"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 30"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:1"/>"But now they have laughed me to scorn; now the least of them reprove me in turn-- whom I did not deem worthy of my shepherd dogs!<verse eid="JOB 30:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:2"/><verse eid="JOB 30:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:3"/><verse eid="JOB 30:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:4"/>Who indeed! Saltwort was their food, and they were without honor and disparaged, in want of everything good, who also chewed on tree roots out of great hunger.<verse eid="JOB 30:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:5"/>Thieves have risen up against me,<verse eid="JOB 30:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:6"/>whose houses were caves in the rocks,<verse eid="JOB 30:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:7"/>who spent their lives under wild bushes--<verse eid="JOB 30:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:8"/>sons of fools and of people dishonored in name, and a reputation quenched from earth.<verse eid="JOB 30:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:9"/>"But now I am their lyre, and they have me as a byword;<verse eid="JOB 30:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:10"/>yes, they abhorred me, standing afar off, and they did not spare my face their spit.<verse eid="JOB 30:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:11"/>For he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">30:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'God'</char></note> opened his quiver and harmed me,<verse eid="JOB 30:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:12"/><verse eid="JOB 30:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:13"/>for he took off my robe.<verse eid="JOB 30:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:14"/>He shot me down with his arrows; he has treated me as he wishes; I am a jumble of pain.<verse eid="JOB 30:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:15"/>My pains are returning; my hope has gone away like a puff of air, and my safety like a cloud.<verse eid="JOB 30:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:16"/>"And days of pain seize me,<verse eid="JOB 30:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:17"/>while at night my bones are inflamed, and my sinews are dissolved.<verse eid="JOB 30:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:18"/>With great force he took hold of my robe.<verse eid="JOB 30:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:19"/>"And you have treated me like clay, my lot is in dust and ashes.<verse eid="JOB 30:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:20"/>But I have cried to you, and you do not listen to me.<verse eid="JOB 30:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:21"/>Yes, you fell upon me without mercy; with a strong hand you have scourged me,<verse eid="JOB 30:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:22"/>and you arrayed me in pains.<verse eid="JOB 30:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:23"/>You see, I know that death will crush me, for earth is home to every mortal.<verse eid="JOB 30:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:24"/>"Oh that I might be able to lay hands on myself or, at least, entreat another, and he will do this for me.<verse eid="JOB 30:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:25"/>But I, I wept over every powerless person, and I groaned when I saw a man in dire straits.<verse eid="JOB 30:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:26"/>But I, when I was intent on good, look, days of evil met me all the more.<verse eid="JOB 30:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:27"/><verse eid="JOB 30:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:28"/>I have gone about, groaning without restraint, and I have stood in the assembly, crying out.<verse eid="JOB 30:28"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:29"/>I have become a brother of sirens and a companion of ostriches.<verse eid="JOB 30:29"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:30"/>As well, my skin has blackened greatly, and my bones, from heat.<verse eid="JOB 30:30"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 30:31"/>Yes, my lyre has been turned into mourning, and my melody into weeping for me.<verse eid="JOB 30:31"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 31"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:1"/><verse eid="JOB 31:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:2"/><verse eid="JOB 31:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:3"/><verse eid="JOB 31:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:4"/><verse eid="JOB 31:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:5"/>"But if I had walked with jesters and if too my foot hurried to deceit,<verse eid="JOB 31:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:6"/>then may he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">31:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'it', i.e. my foot</char></note> place me in a just balance-- but the Lord knows my innocence.<verse eid="JOB 31:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:7"/>If my foot has turned aside from the way and if too my heart followed my eye and if too I touched gifts with my hands,<verse eid="JOB 31:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:8"/>then may I sow and others eat, and may I become without root on earth.<verse eid="JOB 31:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:9"/>"If my heart followed another man's wife, if in fact I lay in wait at her doors,<verse eid="JOB 31:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:10"/>then may my wife too be pleasing to another, and may my children be humiliated.<verse eid="JOB 31:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:11"/>For a fit of passion is uncontrollable, namely, the defiling of a man's wife;<verse eid="JOB 31:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:12"/>for a fire is set burning in all parts, and wherever it has gone, it has destroyed root and branch.<verse eid="JOB 31:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:13"/>"And if too I have disparaged the case of my male or female attendant when they bring a complaint against me,<verse eid="JOB 31:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:14"/>what then shall I do, if the Lord puts me under scrutiny? And if too he pays a visit, what answer shall I give?<verse eid="JOB 31:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:15"/>Just as I was conceived in the belly, were not they also? Yes, we were conceived in the same cavity.<verse eid="JOB 31:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:16"/>"But as for the powerless, what need they had-- I did not miss it, and the eye of the widow I did not let waste away.<verse eid="JOB 31:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:17"/>And if too I ate my morsel alone and did not share with the orphan,<verse eid="JOB 31:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:18"/><verse eid="JOB 31:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:19"/>and if too I overlooked a naked person, perishing, and did not clothe him,<verse eid="JOB 31:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:20"/>and as for the powerless, if they did not bless me-- yet their shoulders were warmed with the fleece of my lambs--<verse eid="JOB 31:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:21"/>if I raised a hand against an orphan, confident that I have much help at my disposal,<verse eid="JOB 31:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:22"/>then may my shoulder separate from its socket and my arm be crushed from the elbow.<verse eid="JOB 31:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:23"/>To be sure, fear of the Lord controlled me.<verse eid="JOB 31:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:24"/>"And if too I trusted in a precious stone<verse eid="JOB 31:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:25"/>and if too I rejoiced when much wealth accrued to me and if too I placed my hand on things without number--<verse eid="JOB 31:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:26"/>indeed do I not see the shining sun setting, and the moon waning? For they do not have it in them.<verse eid="JOB 31:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:27"/>And if too I placed my hand on my mouth and kissed it,<verse eid="JOB 31:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:28"/>then may this too be reckoned to me as the greatest lawlessness, because I played false before the Lord Most High.<verse eid="JOB 31:28"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:29"/>"And if too I was gratified at my enemies' fall, and my heart said, 'Good!'--<verse eid="JOB 31:29"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:30"/>then may my ear hear a curse against me; yes, then may I be gossiped about by my people as one afflicted.<verse eid="JOB 31:30"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:31"/>And if too my female attendants often said, 'Who might grant us to be filled with his flesh?' though I was very kind--<verse eid="JOB 31:31"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:32"/>and no stranger would lodge outside, but my door stood open to everyone that came,<verse eid="JOB 31:32"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:33"/>and if too, having sinned haplessly, I hid my sin--<verse eid="JOB 31:33"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:34"/>for I was not deterred by the populous multitude from speaking out before them-- and if too I permitted the powerless to leave my door with empty pockets,<verse eid="JOB 31:34"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:35"/>and if I had not feared the hand of the Lord, then the writ that I had against someone<verse eid="JOB 31:35"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:36"/>I would have placed on my shoulders as a chaplet and read it aloud,<verse eid="JOB 31:36"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:37"/>and if I did not tear it up and hand it back, having taken nothing from the debtor--<verse eid="JOB 31:37"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:38"/>"if at any time the land groaned over me and if too its furrows wept with one accord<verse eid="JOB 31:38"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:39"/>and if too I ate its strength alone, without payment, and if too I, in throwing it away, grieved the soul of the land's owner<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">31:39</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'lord'</char></note>,<verse eid="JOB 31:39"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 31:40"/>then may nettles come forth to me instead of wheat, and a bramble instead of barley." And Iob ceased speaking.<verse eid="JOB 31:40"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 32"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:1"/>Now too, his three friends gave up taking issue with Iob any longer, for Iob was righteous before them.<verse eid="JOB 32:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:2"/>But Elious the son of Barachiel, the Bouzite, of the kinfolk of Ram in the region of Ausitis, became angry, but he was very angry with Iob, because he declared himself in the right before the Lord.<verse eid="JOB 32:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:3"/>But he was very angry also with the three friends, because they were unable to give Iob counter-argument, and they made him out to be impious.<verse eid="JOB 32:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:4"/>Yet Elious waited to give an answer to Iob.<verse eid="JOB 32:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:5"/><verse eid="JOB 32:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:6"/>Now Elious the son of Barachiel, the Bouzite, stated in reply: "I am rather young in age, but you are older; so I held my peace, being reticent to declare my own learning to you.<verse eid="JOB 32:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:7"/>But I said, 'It is not time that speaks, and with many years they do not know wisdom.'<verse eid="JOB 32:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:8"/>Rather, there is a spirit in mortals, and it is a breath of the Almighty that teaches.<verse eid="JOB 32:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:9"/>It is not the long-lived that are wise, nor do the aged know discernment.<verse eid="JOB 32:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:10"/>So I said, 'Hear me, and I will declare to you what I know.'<verse eid="JOB 32:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:11"/>"Give ear to my words, for I will speak, while you hear,<verse eid="JOB 32:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:12"/><verse eid="JOB 32:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:13"/>lest you say, 'We discovered wisdom and contributed it to the Lord,'<verse eid="JOB 32:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:14"/>but you gave a person<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">32:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'Iob'</char></note> the occasion to utter such words!"<verse eid="JOB 32:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:15"/><verse eid="JOB 32:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:16"/><verse eid="JOB 32:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:17"/>And Elious resumed and said:<verse eid="JOB 32:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:18"/>"I will speak again, for I am full of words; for my gastral spirit is killing me<verse eid="JOB 32:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:19"/>and my belly is like a bound wineskin of new wine in ferment or like a burst bellows of a blacksmith.<verse eid="JOB 32:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:20"/>I will speak, that I may find relief when I open my lips,<verse eid="JOB 32:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:21"/>for I will not be in awe of a human being; to the contrary, I will have no regard for any mortal,<verse eid="JOB 32:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 32:22"/>for I do not know how to show respect; if that is not so, moths will also eat me!<verse eid="JOB 32:22"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 33"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:1"/>"Nonetheless, O Iob, hear my words, and give ear to what I say.<verse eid="JOB 33:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:2"/>For look, I have opened my mouth, and my tongue has spoken.<verse eid="JOB 33:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:3"/>My heart will be seen pure by my words, and the thought of my lips pure by my interpretation.<verse eid="JOB 33:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:4"/>It is the divine spirit that has made me and the Almighty's breath that teaches me.<verse eid="JOB 33:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:5"/>Give me an answer to these things, if you can; wait, take a stand against me, and I against you.<verse eid="JOB 33:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:6"/>You have been fashioned from clay, even as I am; we have been fashioned from the same thing.<verse eid="JOB 33:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:7"/>No fear of me will send you spinning, nor will my hand be heavy on you.<verse eid="JOB 33:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:8"/>"I have heard the sound of your words,<verse eid="JOB 33:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:9"/>that you say, 'I am pure, since I have done no wrong, and I am blameless, for I did not act lawlessly.<verse eid="JOB 33:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:10"/>But he found a basis for complaint against me and has reckoned me as an adversary,<verse eid="JOB 33:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:11"/>and he put my foot in the stocks and watched all my paths.'<verse eid="JOB 33:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:12"/>"How then do you say, 'I am righteous, and he has paid no heed to me?' for he that is above mortals is everlasting.<verse eid="JOB 33:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:13"/>But you say, 'Why has he not heeded one word of my case?'<verse eid="JOB 33:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:14"/>For may the Lord speak just this once, and the second time, through a dream<verse eid="JOB 33:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:15"/>or during reflection by night-- as when a fearful dread falls on people, while they slumber on their bed.<verse eid="JOB 33:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:16"/>Then he lays bare the human mind; he frightened them with such scary apparitions,<verse eid="JOB 33:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:17"/>to turn a person from injustice, and he saved his body from a fall.<verse eid="JOB 33:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:18"/>And he has spared his soul from death and from his falling in battle.<verse eid="JOB 33:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:19"/>Then again, he reproved him with sickness upon his bed,<verse eid="JOB 33:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:20"/>and he shall not be able to take any edible bit of food<verse eid="JOB 33:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:21"/>until his flesh rots and he shows his bones to be bare.<verse eid="JOB 33:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:22"/>Yes, his soul drew near to death, and his life was in Hades.<verse eid="JOB 33:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:23"/>If there be a thousand death-bearing angels, not one of them shall wound him; if he purpose with his heart to turn to the Lord and declare to a person his own fault and reveal his folly,<verse eid="JOB 33:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:24"/>he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">33:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the Lord'</char></note> will provide support so that he does not fall into death and renew his body like paint does a wall and fill his bones with marrow<verse eid="JOB 33:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:25"/>and will make his flesh soft like an infant's and restore him full-grown among people.<verse eid="JOB 33:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:26"/>And when he makes vows to the Lord, they will also be acceptable to him, and he will enter with a pure look, with a declaration, and he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">33:26</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the Lord'</char></note> will repay people with righteousness.<verse eid="JOB 33:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:27"/>After that, the same person will chastise himself, saying: 'Given the kinds of things I was doing, he has not even tried me commensurate with my sin!<verse eid="JOB 33:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:28"/><verse eid="JOB 33:28"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:29"/><verse eid="JOB 33:29"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:30"/>Rather, he delivered my soul from death, that my life may praise him in the light.'<verse eid="JOB 33:30"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 33:31"/>Give ear, O Iob, and keep hearing me."<verse eid="JOB 33:31"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 34"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:1"/>Now Elious resumed and said:<verse eid="JOB 34:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:2"/>"Hear me, you wise men; O you who know, give ear to what is good<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">34:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'to what is good':  Ziegler = Omit</char></note>--<verse eid="JOB 34:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:3"/><verse eid="JOB 34:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:4"/><verse eid="JOB 34:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:5"/>because Iob has said, 'I am righteous; the Lord dismissed my case<verse eid="JOB 34:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:6"/>and played false in my judgment,<verse eid="JOB 34:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:7"/><verse eid="JOB 34:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:8"/>seeing that I have not sinned or acted impiously or shared a way with doers of lawless acts, to walk with the impious.'<verse eid="JOB 34:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:9"/>For do not say, 'There will be no visitation of a man'-- when there is visitation to him from the Lord!<verse eid="JOB 34:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:10"/>"Therefore, you intelligent of heart, hear me: far be it from me to act impiously before the Lord and before the Almighty, to pervert what is right.<verse eid="JOB 34:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:11"/>Rather, he repays a person according to what each of them does.<verse eid="JOB 34:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:12"/>Now, do you think the Lord will do what is amiss? Or will the Almighty pervert justice,<verse eid="JOB 34:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:13"/>he who created the earth? And who is it that sustains what is under heaven and all it contains?<verse eid="JOB 34:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:14"/>For if he should wish to confine and to keep his spirit with himself,<verse eid="JOB 34:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:15"/>all flesh will die together, and every mortal return to dust, whence too he was formed.<verse eid="JOB 34:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:16"/>"But lest he rebuke you, hear these things; give ear to the sound of my words.<verse eid="JOB 34:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:17"/>Look then at him that hates lawless acts and destroys the wicked, since he is forever just.<verse eid="JOB 34:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:18"/>Impious is he who says to a king, 'You are acting lawlessly,'--<verse eid="JOB 34:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:19"/>he who felt no reticence before a person of worth nor knows how to accord honor to the prominent so that their persons be respected.<verse eid="JOB 34:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:20"/>But crying out and begging, a man will prove to be of no use to them, for they used people lawlessly, when the powerless were being turned aside.<verse eid="JOB 34:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:21"/>"For he is one that views human deeds, and nothing of what they do has escaped him,<verse eid="JOB 34:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:22"/>nor will there be a place to hide for those that do lawless acts.<verse eid="JOB 34:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:23"/>For the Lord observes all people--<verse eid="JOB 34:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:24"/>he who comprehends inscrutable things, things both glorious and extraordinary, without number,<verse eid="JOB 34:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:25"/>he who reveals their deeds<verse eid="JOB 34:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:26"/>and has extinguished the impious-- yes, they were in plain view before him,<verse eid="JOB 34:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:27"/>because they turned aside from God's law and did not recognize his requirements.<verse eid="JOB 34:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:28"/><verse eid="JOB 34:28"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:29"/><verse eid="JOB 34:29"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:30"/><verse eid="JOB 34:30"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:31"/><verse eid="JOB 34:31"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:32"/><verse eid="JOB 34:32"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:33"/><verse eid="JOB 34:33"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:34"/>"So, the intelligent of heart will say these things, and a wise man will have grasped what I said.<verse eid="JOB 34:34"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:35"/>But Iob did not speak with intelligence, and his words were without knowledge.<verse eid="JOB 34:35"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:36"/>Nonetheless, learn O Iob! No longer give a response as fools do,<verse eid="JOB 34:36"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 34:37"/>lest we add to our sins and lawlessness be reckoned against us, while speaking many words before the Lord."<verse eid="JOB 34:37"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 35"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 35:1"/>Now Elious resumed and said:<verse eid="JOB 35:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 35:2"/>"What is this you thought to be in dispute? Who are you that you said, 'I am in the right before the Lord?'<verse eid="JOB 35:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 35:3"/>Or will you say, 'What am I to do, if I sinned?'<verse eid="JOB 35:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 35:4"/>I will give an answer to you, as well as to your three friends.<verse eid="JOB 35:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 35:5"/>Look up to the sky, and see, and take a close look at the clouds, how high they are beyond you.<verse eid="JOB 35:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 35:6"/>If you sinned, what will you do? And if too you broke the law many times, what can you do? Now then, inasmuch as you are righteous, what will you concede to him<verse eid="JOB 35:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 35:7"/><verse eid="JOB 35:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 35:8"/><verse eid="JOB 35:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 35:9"/><verse eid="JOB 35:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 35:10"/>He it is that appoints the watches of the night;<verse eid="JOB 35:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 35:11"/>he it is that sets me apart from earth's four- footed animals and from the birds of the air<verse eid="JOB 35:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 35:12"/>and from the insolence of the wicked.<verse eid="JOB 35:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 35:13"/>For the Lord does not wish to see wrongs, for he, the Almighty, is one that views<verse eid="JOB 35:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 35:14"/>those who perform lawless acts, and he will save me! But submit to judgment before him, if you can approve of him as he is."<verse eid="JOB 35:14"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 36"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:1"/>Now Elious added still more and said:<verse eid="JOB 36:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:2"/>"Wait for me a little longer so that I may teach you, for there is still more speech in me.<verse eid="JOB 36:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:3"/>Having fetched my knowledge from afar, yes, in my efforts I will speak what is just,<verse eid="JOB 36:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:4"/>in truth, and not unjust words; you understand wrongly!<verse eid="JOB 36:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:5"/>"But know that the Lord will not reject the innocent;<verse eid="JOB 36:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:6"/><verse eid="JOB 36:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:7"/><verse eid="JOB 36:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:8"/><verse eid="JOB 36:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:9"/><verse eid="JOB 36:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:10"/>rather, he will listen to the righteous.<verse eid="JOB 36:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:11"/><verse eid="JOB 36:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:12"/>But the impious he does not deliver, because they do not wish to know the Lord and because, when they were being admonished, they were unreceptive.<verse eid="JOB 36:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:13"/><verse eid="JOB 36:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:14"/>"Well then, may their soul die in youth, and their life, being wounded by messengers<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">36:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'angels'</char></note>,<verse eid="JOB 36:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:15"/>because they afflicted the weak and powerless, but he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">36:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the Lord'</char></note> will expose judgment against the meek.<verse eid="JOB 36:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:16"/><verse eid="JOB 36:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:17"/>"Yes, justice will not be wanting for those in the right,<verse eid="JOB 36:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:18"/>but wrath will fall on the impious on account of the impiety of gifts they would receive for injustices.<verse eid="JOB 36:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:19"/>Let not your mind purposely turn you aside from the petition of the powerless when they are in distress.<verse eid="JOB 36:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:20"/><verse eid="JOB 36:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:21"/>Rather, be careful that you do no wrongs;<verse eid="JOB 36:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:22"/>for who is a mighty one like him?<verse eid="JOB 36:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:23"/>And who is it that examines his works, or who is it that states, 'He has done injustice'?<verse eid="JOB 36:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:24"/>"Remember that his works are great,<verse eid="JOB 36:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:25"/>however many mortals are being wounded.<verse eid="JOB 36:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:26"/><verse eid="JOB 36:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:27"/>But to him raindrops are numbered,<verse eid="JOB 36:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 36:28"/>and clouds cast a shadow on untold mortals. He appointed a time for cattle, and they know their schedule for rest. Is your mind not amazed at all these things, and does your heart not take leave of your body?<verse eid="JOB 36:28"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 37"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:1"/><verse eid="JOB 37:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:2"/><verse eid="JOB 37:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:3"/><verse eid="JOB 37:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:4"/><verse eid="JOB 37:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:5"/>For he did great things that we did not know,<verse eid="JOB 37:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:6"/>instructing the snow, 'Come upon the earth!'<verse eid="JOB 37:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:7"/>so that every human being may know his own weakness.<verse eid="JOB 37:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:8"/>But the wild animals came in under shelter and were quiet upon their lair.<verse eid="JOB 37:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:9"/>From their chambers whirlwinds come, and cold from the peaks.<verse eid="JOB 37:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:10"/>And he steers the water as he wishes--<verse eid="JOB 37:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:11"/><verse eid="JOB 37:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:12"/>these things have been instructed by him on the earth.<verse eid="JOB 37:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:13"/><verse eid="JOB 37:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:14"/>"Give ear to these things, O Iob; stand still, be warned of the Lord's power.<verse eid="JOB 37:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:15"/>We know that God ordained his works, when he made light out of darkness.<verse eid="JOB 37:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:16"/>And he understands the division of the clouds and the extraordinary falls of the wicked.<verse eid="JOB 37:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:17"/>But your cloak is hot; yet there is quiet on the earth.<verse eid="JOB 37:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:18"/><verse eid="JOB 37:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:19"/>Why? Teach me what we shall say to him, and let us cease talking so much.<verse eid="JOB 37:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:20"/>Is book or scribe in attendance on me, that I stand and put a person to silence?<verse eid="JOB 37:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:21"/>But the light is not visible to all, just as the light from him is upon the clouds.<verse eid="JOB 37:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:22"/>From the north are clouds shining like gold; on these is great the glory and honor of the Almighty.<verse eid="JOB 37:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:23"/>And we do not find another like him in strength. As for him that judges rightly, do you not think he pays heed?<verse eid="JOB 37:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 37:24"/>Therefore humans will fear him; yes, the wise in heart too will fear him."<verse eid="JOB 37:24"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 38"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:1"/>Now after Elious stopped his speech, the Lord said to Iob through a whirlwind and clouds:<verse eid="JOB 38:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:2"/>"Who is this that hides counsel from me but confines words in his heart and thinks to hide them from me?<verse eid="JOB 38:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:3"/>Gird up your loins like a man, and I will question you, but as for you, just answer me!<verse eid="JOB 38:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:4"/>"Where were you when I was laying the earth's foundation? Now tell me, if you are endowed with understanding.<verse eid="JOB 38:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:5"/>Who determined its measures, if you know? Or who was it that stretched a line upon it?<verse eid="JOB 38:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:6"/>On what have its rings been fastened? And who is he that cast a cornerstone upon it?<verse eid="JOB 38:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:7"/>When the stars were born, all my angels praised me with a loud voice.<verse eid="JOB 38:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:8"/>"Again, I shut up the sea with gates, when it quivered with eagerness, as it issued from its mother's womb,<verse eid="JOB 38:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:9"/>and I made the cloud its clothing, and with mist I swaddled it;<verse eid="JOB 38:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:10"/>yes, I prescribed bounds for it, setting bars and gates around it.<verse eid="JOB 38:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:11"/>And I said to it, 'Thus far you shall come, and you shall not go beyond; rather, your waves shall be broken up within you!'<verse eid="JOB 38:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:12"/>"Indeed, was it in your time that I instructed the morning light and that the morning star saw its post,<verse eid="JOB 38:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:13"/>to take hold of earth's wings, to shake the impious off it?<verse eid="JOB 38:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:14"/>Indeed, was it you that took clay soil and formed a living creature, and, able to talk, set him on earth?<verse eid="JOB 38:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:15"/>Again, did you remove the light from the impious and crush the arm of the proud?<verse eid="JOB 38:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:16"/>"And did you go to the source of the sea and walk in the tracks of the deep?<verse eid="JOB 38:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:17"/>Again, do the gates of death open to you out of fear, and did the porters of Hades cower when they saw you?<verse eid="JOB 38:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:18"/>Again, have you been advised of the breadth of what is under heaven? Do tell me how much it is.<verse eid="JOB 38:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:19"/>"As well, in what kind of land does the light dwell, and of what kind is the place of darkness?<verse eid="JOB 38:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:20"/>Might you perhaps lead me to their borders? And perhaps too you know their paths?<verse eid="JOB 38:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:21"/>Thereby I know that you were born then, and the number of your years is great!<verse eid="JOB 38:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:22"/>"And have you gone to the storehouses of the snow, and have you seen the storehouses of the hail?<verse eid="JOB 38:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:23"/>But it is at your disposal for a time of enemies, for a day of war and battle.<verse eid="JOB 38:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:24"/>And from where does the hoarfrost come, or from where is the south wind dispersed to what is under heaven?<verse eid="JOB 38:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:25"/>"And who prepared a course for the driving rain and a way for the tumults?<verse eid="JOB 38:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:26"/><verse eid="JOB 38:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:27"/><verse eid="JOB 38:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:28"/>"Who is the rain's father? And who is it that has given birth to the dew's nuggets?<verse eid="JOB 38:28"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:29"/>And from whose womb does the ice come forth? And who has given birth to freezing rain in the sky<verse eid="JOB 38:29"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:30"/>that descends like flowing water? And who froze the face of the deep?<verse eid="JOB 38:30"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:31"/>"And did you understand the bond of Pleiades, and did you open the barrier of Orion?<verse eid="JOB 38:31"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:32"/><verse eid="JOB 38:32"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:33"/>And do you know heaven's changes or the corresponding events under heaven?<verse eid="JOB 38:33"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:34"/>"And will you summon a cloud by voice, and will it obey you with a violent burst of water?<verse eid="JOB 38:34"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:35"/>And will you send out thunderbolts-- and will they go? And will they say to you, 'What is it?'<verse eid="JOB 38:35"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:36"/>And who gave to women skill in weaving or knowledge of embroidery?<verse eid="JOB 38:36"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:37"/>And who is he that numbers the clouds in wisdom and inclined the sky to the earth?<verse eid="JOB 38:37"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:38"/>And dust has been poured out like soil, but I have cemented it, like a block to a stone.<verse eid="JOB 38:38"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:39"/>"And will you hunt prey for the lions and satisfy the appetite of dragons?<verse eid="JOB 38:39"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:40"/>For they are in a state of fear in their lairs, and they crouch in the woods, lying in wait.<verse eid="JOB 38:40"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 38:41"/>And who prepared food for the raven? For its young have cried to the Lord as they wander about, searching for food.<verse eid="JOB 38:41"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 39"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:1"/>(1) "And did you protect the birth pangs of the deer?<verse eid="JOB 39:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:2"/>And did you check off their months full of pregnancy, and did you relieve their birth pangs?<verse eid="JOB 39:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:3"/>And did you rear their young without fear?<verse eid="JOB 39:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:4"/><verse eid="JOB 39:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:5"/>"And who is he that let the wild ass go free, and its bonds-- who loosed them?<verse eid="JOB 39:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:6"/>Yes, I made its home the wilderness,<verse eid="JOB 39:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:7"/>while it laughs to scorn the city's crowds and hears not the chiding of the tax- gatherer.<verse eid="JOB 39:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:8"/><verse eid="JOB 39:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:9"/>"And will the unicorn be willing to be your slave or to lie down at your manger?<verse eid="JOB 39:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:10"/>And will you bind its yoke with straps, or will it draw your furrows in the plain?<verse eid="JOB 39:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:11"/>Again, do you trust it, because its strength is great, and will you discharge to it your work?<verse eid="JOB 39:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:12"/>And will you believe that it will return your seed to you and bring it to your threshing floor?<verse eid="JOB 39:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:13"/><verse eid="JOB 39:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:14"/><verse eid="JOB 39:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:15"/><verse eid="JOB 39:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:16"/><verse eid="JOB 39:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:17"/><verse eid="JOB 39:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:18"/><verse eid="JOB 39:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:19"/>"Indeed, was it you that endowed the horse with power and clothed its neck with terror?<verse eid="JOB 39:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:20"/>And did you endow it with full armor and the majesty of its breast with courage?<verse eid="JOB 39:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:21"/>Pawing at the plain, it bears itself proudly, and it goes forth into the plain in strength.<verse eid="JOB 39:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:22"/>Meeting up with an arrow, it laughs in scorn and will never turn back from a blade.<verse eid="JOB 39:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:23"/>Upon it exult the bow and dagger,<verse eid="JOB 39:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:24"/>and in rage it will stamp out the ground and will not steady itself until the trumpet sounds.<verse eid="JOB 39:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:25"/>But when the trumpet sounds, it says, 'Good!' and from afar it scents battle with leap and cry.<verse eid="JOB 39:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:26"/>"And is it by your understanding that the hawk stops still, having spread its wings, motionless, eyeing what lies to the south?<verse eid="JOB 39:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:27"/>And is it at your decree that the eagle rises up and the vulture lodges, sitting on its brood?<verse eid="JOB 39:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:28"/><verse eid="JOB 39:28"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:29"/>From there it searches for food,<verse eid="JOB 39:29"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 39:30"/>and its young are drenched in blood, and, wherever there are carcasses, at once they are found."<verse eid="JOB 39:30"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 40"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:1"/><verse eid="JOB 40:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:2"/><verse eid="JOB 40:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:3"/>Now Iob said in reply to the Lord:<verse eid="JOB 40:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:4"/>"Why do I yet contend-- being rebuked even while confuting the Lord, hearing such things-- when I am nothing? And I, what answer shall I give to these things? I will lay my hand on my mouth.<verse eid="JOB 40:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:5"/>I have spoken once, but I will not add to a second time."<verse eid="JOB 40:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:6"/>Now yet again the Lord said in reply to Iob from the mass of cloud:<verse eid="JOB 40:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:7"/>"No, but gird up your loins like a man, and I will question you, but as for you, just answer me!<verse eid="JOB 40:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:8"/>Do not shrug off my judgment. And do you think I have dealt with you in any other way than that you might appear to be right?<verse eid="JOB 40:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:9"/>Do you have an arm like the Lord, or do you thunder with a voice like his?<verse eid="JOB 40:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:10"/>"Go ahead take on loftiness and power, and put on glory and honor.<verse eid="JOB 40:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:11"/>And send forth messengers in wrath and every insolent person humble.<verse eid="JOB 40:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:12"/>Yes, extinguish the proud, and at once make putrid the impious.<verse eid="JOB 40:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:13"/>And hide them outside together in the earth, and fill their faces with dishonor;<verse eid="JOB 40:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:14"/>then I will acknowledge that your right hand can save.<verse eid="JOB 40:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:15"/>"But look now, you are familiar with 'monsters'; they eat grass like cows.<verse eid="JOB 40:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:16"/>Look now, its strength is in its loins, and its power in its belly's navel.<verse eid="JOB 40:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:17"/>It stood up its tail like a cypress, and its sinews have been interwoven.<verse eid="JOB 40:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:18"/>Its flanks are flanks of copper, and its spine is cast iron.<verse eid="JOB 40:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:19"/>"This is the chief of what the Lord created, made to be mocked at by his angels.<verse eid="JOB 40:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:20"/>But when it went up on a steep mountain, it brought gladness to the quadrupeds in Tartarus<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">40:20</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the nether world'</char></note>.<verse eid="JOB 40:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:21"/>Under trees of every kind it lies down, by the papyrus and reed and sedge.<verse eid="JOB 40:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:22"/>And tall trees find themselves in its shade, with limbs, as do the chaste-tree's branches.<verse eid="JOB 40:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:23"/>If there is a flood, it will never notice.<verse eid="JOB 40:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:24"/><verse eid="JOB 40:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:25"/>(41.1) "And will you catch a dragon with a fish hook and put a halter around its nose?<verse eid="JOB 40:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:26"/>And will you pierce its lip with a ring?<verse eid="JOB 40:26"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:27"/>And will it address you with a petition, with a supplication, softly?<verse eid="JOB 40:27"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:28"/>And will it make a covenant with you, and will you take it as your perpetual slave?<verse eid="JOB 40:28"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:29"/>And will you play with it as with a bird, or tie it up like a sparrow for a child?<verse eid="JOB 40:29"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:30"/>And do nations feed on it, and do the Phoenician races divvy it up?<verse eid="JOB 40:30"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:31"/>And a whole fleet, gathered, cannot carry the mere skin of its tail.<verse eid="JOB 40:31"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 40:32"/>But you will lay a hand on it, though you remember the battle that is waging in its body, and let it happen no more!<verse eid="JOB 40:32"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 41"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:1"/>(9) "Have you not seen it, and have you not marveled at what is said?<verse eid="JOB 41:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:2"/>Do you not fear because it has been prepared for me? For who is it that withstands me?<verse eid="JOB 41:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:3"/>Or who will withstand me and survive, if the entire earth beneath the sky is mine?<verse eid="JOB 41:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:4"/><verse eid="JOB 41:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:5"/>"Who will uncover the front of what it is wearing? And who could enter the plate of its cuirass?<verse eid="JOB 41:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:6"/>Who will open the gates of its face? Fear is all around its teeth.<verse eid="JOB 41:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:7"/>Its inwards are bronze shields, and its ligament is like emery stone--<verse eid="JOB 41:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:8"/>and no puff of air will ever pass through it!<verse eid="JOB 41:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:9"/><verse eid="JOB 41:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:10"/>Light shines forth at its sneezing, and its eyes have the look of the morning star.<verse eid="JOB 41:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:11"/>From its mouth proceed flaming torches, and fiery braziers are being cast forth.<verse eid="JOB 41:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:12"/>From its nostrils proceeds smoke of a furnace burning with the fire of coals.<verse eid="JOB 41:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:13"/>Its soul is coals, and a flame proceeds from its mouth.<verse eid="JOB 41:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:14"/>And in its neck lodges power; destruction runs before it.<verse eid="JOB 41:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:15"/>And the flesh of its body cleaves together.<verse eid="JOB 41:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:16"/>Its heart is solid like stone, and it stands like an unyielding anvil.<verse eid="JOB 41:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:17"/>And when it turns, fear takes hold of the quadrupeds jumping upon the earth.<verse eid="JOB 41:17"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:18"/>If spears meet it, they will do nothing,<verse eid="JOB 41:18"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:19"/>for it regards iron as chaff and bronze as rotten wood.<verse eid="JOB 41:19"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:20"/>A bronze bow will never wound it; it regards a catapult as grass<verse eid="JOB 41:20"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:21"/>and laughs to scorn the waving of a firebrand.<verse eid="JOB 41:21"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:22"/>Its bed is sharp points, and all the sea's gold under it is like untold clay.<verse eid="JOB 41:22"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:23"/>It makes the deep boil like a caldron and regards the sea as a pot of ointment<verse eid="JOB 41:23"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:24"/>and Tartarus<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">41:24</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the nether world'</char></note> of the deep as a captive.<verse eid="JOB 41:24"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:25"/>There is nothing on earth like it, made to be mocked at by my angels.<verse eid="JOB 41:25"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 41:26"/>Everything high it sees, and it is king over all that are in the waters."<verse eid="JOB 41:26"/>



  <chapter sid="JOB 42"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:1"/>Now Iob said in reply to the Lord:<verse eid="JOB 42:1"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:2"/>" I know that you can do anything, and nothing is impossible for you.<verse eid="JOB 42:2"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:3"/>For who is it that hides counsel from you, and being sparing with words thinks to hide them from you as well? But who will tell me what I did not know, great and marvelous things that I did not understand?<verse eid="JOB 42:3"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:4"/>Now hear me, Lord, that I too may speak; then I will question you, and you, teach me!<verse eid="JOB 42:4"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:5"/>Whereas before I would hear an aural report of you, now, however, my eye has seen you;<verse eid="JOB 42:5"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:6"/>therefore I disparaged myself and wasted away, and I regard myself as dust and ashes."<verse eid="JOB 42:6"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:7"/>Now it happened, after the Lord spoke all these words to Iob, that the Lord said to Eliphaz<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">42:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = 'Eliphas'</char></note> the Thaimanite: "You have sinned, and your two friends, for you have spoken nothing true in my presence, as has my attendant Iob.<verse eid="JOB 42:7"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:8"/>Now then, take seven calves and seven rams, and go to my attendant Iob, and he will make offerings for you, and Iob, my attendant, will pray for you, for, if not for him, I would have destroyed you; for what you spoke against my attendant Iob is not true."<verse eid="JOB 42:8"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:9"/>Then Eliphaz<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">42:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = 'Eliphas'</char></note> the Thaimanite went, and Baldad the Sauchite and Sophar the Minite, and they did as the Lord instructed them, and he absolved them of their sin on Iob's account.<verse eid="JOB 42:9"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:10"/>And the Lord gave Iob increase, and when he also prayed for the friends, he forgave them their sin, and the Lord gave Iob twice as much as he had before so that he had double.<verse eid="JOB 42:10"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:11"/>Now all his brothers and his sisters heard about all that had happened to him, and they came to him, and all, as many as had known him from the first. Now when they ate and drank with him, they comforted him and wondered at all that the Lord had brought upon him, and each gave him a lamb and a four-drachma weight of gold bullion.<verse eid="JOB 42:11"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:12"/>Yes, the Lord blessed the last years of Iob more than the ones before, and his livestock was: fourteen thousand sheep, six thousand camels, a thousand yoke of oxen, a thousand female donkeys at pasture.<verse eid="JOB 42:12"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:13"/>And there were born to him seven sons and three daughters,<verse eid="JOB 42:13"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:14"/>and he called the first Day and the second Cassia and the third Horn of Amaltheia.<verse eid="JOB 42:14"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:15"/>And there were not found women more excellent than Iob's daughters beneath heaven, and their father gave them an inheritance along with their brothers.<verse eid="JOB 42:15"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:16"/>Now Iob lived after his calamity one hundred and seventy years, (16b) and all the years he lived were two hundred and forty-eight years.<verse eid="JOB 42:16"/>
    <verse sid="JOB 42:17"/>And it is written that he will rise again with those the Lord raises up. (17b) This man is interpreted from the Syriac book as living in the land of Ausitis, on the borders of Idumea and Arabia, and previously his name was Iobab; (17c) now he took an Arabian wife and fathered a son, whose name was Ennon, and he in turn had as father Zare, a son of the sons of Esau, and as mother Bosorra, so that he was the fifth from Abraam. (17d) And these are the kings who reigned in Edom, which country he too ruled: first Balak the son of Beor, and the name of his city was Dennaba, and after Balak, Iobab, who is called Iob, and after him Hasom, who was a leader from the Thaimanite country, and after him Hadad son of Barad, who cut down Madiam in the plain of Moab, and the name of his city was Geththaim. (17e) Now the friends who came to him were: Eliphaz<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">42:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Ziegler = 'Eliphas'</char></note>, of the sons of Esau, king of the Thaimanites, Baldad, the tyrant of the Sauchites, Sophar, the king of the Minites.<verse eid="JOB 42:17"/>
</usx>
