<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- SourceFormat: VL.  Converted to USX by the STEP project: 2023-08-18 -->
<usx version="2.0">
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <book code="NAM"/>



  <chapter sid="NAM 1"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 1:1"/>An issue for Nineue. A book of vision of Naoum the Elkesite.<verse eid="NAM 1:1"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 1:2"/>A jealous and avenging god is the Lord, the Lord avenging with wrath, the Lord taking vengeance on his adversaries and removing his enemies.<verse eid="NAM 1:2"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 1:3"/>The Lord is slow to anger, and his strength is great, and holding guiltless, the Lord will not hold guiltless. His way is in consummation and seismic upheaval<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:3</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'seismic upheaval':  Possibly 'earthquake and hurricane'</char></note>, and clouds are dust for his feet,<verse eid="NAM 1:3"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 1:4"/>threatening<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the Lord'</char></note> the sea and making it dry and making all the rivers desolate; Basanitis and Carmel were diminished, and the vegetation of Lebanon has died out.<verse eid="NAM 1:4"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 1:5"/>The mountains quaked because of him, and the hills were shaken, and the earth was removed from his presence, the whole of it and all who live in it.<verse eid="NAM 1:5"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 1:6"/>Who shall endure before his wrath? And who shall withstand the heat of his anger? His anger causes domains to melt, and by him the rocks were broken in pieces.<verse eid="NAM 1:6"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 1:7"/>The Lord is kind to those who await him in a day of trouble and familiar with those who reverence him.<verse eid="NAM 1:7"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 1:8"/>And by the flooding of a passage, he will make an end to those who arise, and darkness will pursue his enemies.<verse eid="NAM 1:8"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 1:9"/>Why do you calculate against the Lord? It is he that will make an end. He will not avenge twice added together with affliction!<verse eid="NAM 1:9"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 1:10"/>Because he shall be left dry down to their foundation, and he shall be consumed like a twisted yew tree and like straw fully dried.<verse eid="NAM 1:10"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 1:11"/>From you a calculation shall go forth against the Lord, counseling evil things, contrary things.<verse eid="NAM 1:11"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 1:12"/>This is what the Lord says, who rules over many waters, "And thus they shall be dispersed, and your fame shall no longer be heard.<verse eid="NAM 1:12"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 1:13"/>And now I will break off his rod from you, and I will shatter your bonds."<verse eid="NAM 1:13"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 1:14"/>And the Lord will command concerning you: "Part of your name will no longer be scattered. I will utterly destroy the carved and molten images from the house of your God. I will make your grave, because they are fleeting."<verse eid="NAM 1:14"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 1:15"/>Behold, on the mountains are the feet of one who brings good tidings and who announces peace. Celebrate your feasts, O Ioudas; pay your vows, for they shall not add any longer to pass on to becoming old.<verse eid="NAM 1:15"/>



  <chapter sid="NAM 2"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 2:1"/>(1.15) It is finished; it has been removed.<verse eid="NAM 2:1"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 2:2"/>(1) Delivered from trouble, he rose up, breathing in your face. Watch the road; grasp your loins; be very manly in strength!<verse eid="NAM 2:2"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 2:3"/>(2) For the Lord has turned aside the pride of Iakob, as he did the pride of Israel, for shaking they shook them off and their branches.<verse eid="NAM 2:3"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 2:4"/>(3) They destroyed their weapons of dominance from men, mighty men<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'mighty men' = 'weapons of dominance'</char></note> sporting with fire. The reins of their chariots, in the day of his preparation, and the horsemen will be thrown into confusion<verse eid="NAM 2:4"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 2:5"/>(4) in the roads. And the chariots will be in confusion and jammed together in the streets. Their appearance will be like torches of fire and like flashing lightnings.<verse eid="NAM 2:5"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 2:6"/>(5) And their nobles shall remember and flee by day, and they shall become weak in their journey and hasten to the walls and prepare their outposts.<verse eid="NAM 2:6"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 2:7"/>(6) The river gates have been opened, and the royal palace has collapsed,<verse eid="NAM 2:7"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 2:8"/>(7) and the substructure has been uncovered, and this<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'substructure'</char></note> kept coming up, and its slave women were being led away, moaning in their hearts like doves.<verse eid="NAM 2:8"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 2:9"/>(8) And as for Nineue, her water is like a swimming pool of water, and they, when they were fleeing, did not stop, and there was no one who looked on.<verse eid="NAM 2:9"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 2:10"/>(9) They were plundering the silver; they were plundering the gold, and there was no end of her adornment. They have been laden with all her desirable vessels.<verse eid="NAM 2:10"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 2:11"/>(10) Shaking and quaking and trembling and shattering of heart and loosening of knees and pains in every loin, and the face of all like burnt earthenware!<verse eid="NAM 2:11"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 2:12"/>(11) Where is the abode of the lions and the feeding ground that exists for whelps, where the lion went to enter there, a lion's whelp, and there was none to scare it away?<verse eid="NAM 2:12"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 2:13"/>(12) A lion has snatched enough for its whelps and has strangled for its lions, and it has filled its lair with game and its abode with prey.<verse eid="NAM 2:13"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 2:14"/>(13) Behold, I am against you, says the Lord Almighty, and I will burn your abundance in smoke, and a sword shall devour your lions, and I will utterly destroy your prey from the earth, and your works shall be heard of no more.<verse eid="NAM 2:14"/>



  <chapter sid="NAM 3"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:1"/>Ah city of bloodshed, utterly deceitful, full of injustice, prey shall not be groped for!<verse eid="NAM 3:1"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:2"/>A noise of whips and a noise of the rumble of wheels, of pursuing horse and bounding chariot<verse eid="NAM 3:2"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:3"/>and of mounting horsemen and glittering sword and of flashing arms and a multitude of wounded and of heavy falling. And there was no end to her nations, and they shall become weak in their bodies, because of a multitude of whoredom.<verse eid="NAM 3:3"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:4"/>Beautiful and gratifying prostitute, manipulator of potions, she who barters nations through her whoredom and tribes through her potions.<verse eid="NAM 3:4"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:5"/>Behold, I am against you, says the Lord God the Almighty, and I will uncover your behind to your face, and I will show your shame to nations and your dishonor to kingdoms.<verse eid="NAM 3:5"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:6"/>And I will throw filth at you, even your own uncleanness, and I will set you as an example.<verse eid="NAM 3:6"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:7"/>And it shall be, everyone who sees you will go down from you and say, "Wretched Nineue, who will bemoan her? From where shall I seek comfort for her?"<verse eid="NAM 3:7"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:8"/>Tune a chord; prepare a portion, O Amon who dwells in rivers<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'streams'</char></note>; water is around her, whose dominion is the sea, and her walls are water,<verse eid="NAM 3:8"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:9"/>and her strength is Ethiopia and Egypt -- and there is no end to flight! Even the Libyans have become her helpers.<verse eid="NAM 3:9"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:10"/>She too shall go into migration a captive, and they shall dash her infants to the ground at the heads of all her streets. And they shall cast lots for all her glorious things, and all her nobles shall be bound in handcuffs.<verse eid="NAM 3:10"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:11"/>You too will be drunken, and you will be despised; as well you will seek a position for yourself from your enemies.<verse eid="NAM 3:11"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:12"/>All your fortresses are fig trees with guards; if shaken, they will then fall into the mouth of the eater.<verse eid="NAM 3:12"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:13"/>Behold, your people are like women in your midst. The gates of your land, when opened, shall be opened to your foes; fire shall devour your bars.<verse eid="NAM 3:13"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:14"/>Draw yourself water for a siege; strengthen your forts; trample the clay, and let it be trodden in the chaff; make it stronger than brick.<verse eid="NAM 3:14"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:15"/>There a fire will devour you; a sword will utterly destroy you. It will devour you like the grasshopper, and you shall be weighed down like the locust larva.<verse eid="NAM 3:15"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:16"/>You increased your merchandise beyond the stars of the sky. The locust larva rushed in and spread.<verse eid="NAM 3:16"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:17"/>Your commingled one hopped off like a locust, like a grasshopper having landed on a fence in the days of frost: the sun rose, and it jumped off and knew not its place. Woe to them!<verse eid="NAM 3:17"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:18"/>Your shepherds dozed; the Assyrian king put your mighty men to sleep. Your people have departed for the mountains, and there has been none to receive them.<verse eid="NAM 3:18"/>
    <verse sid="NAM 3:19"/>There is no healing for your ruin; your blow swelled up. All who hear the news about you will clap their hands over you. For against whom has your endless wickedness not come?<verse eid="NAM 3:19"/>
</usx>
