<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- SourceFormat: VL.  Converted to USX by the STEP project: 2023-08-18 -->
<usx version="2.0">
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <book code="PSS"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 1:1"/>I cried to the Lord when I was completely distressed, to God when sinners attacked.<verse eid="PSS 1:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 1:2"/>Suddenly the cry of war was heard before me: he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Rahlfs = preceded by 'I said'</char></note> will listen to me, for I was full of righteousness.<verse eid="PSS 1:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 1:3"/>I thought in my heart that I was full of righteousness, when I prospered and had become rich in children.<verse eid="PSS 1:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 1:4"/>Their wealth was spread over the whole earth, and their glory to the end of the earth.<verse eid="PSS 1:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 1:5"/>They were exalted to the stars; they said they would not fall.<verse eid="PSS 1:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 1:6"/>But they became insolent in their prosperity, and they did not bring.<verse eid="PSS 1:6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 1:7"/>Their sins were in secret, and I had no knowledge of them.<verse eid="PSS 1:7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 1:8"/>Their acts lawlessness surpassed those of the nations before them; they profaned with profanity the sanctuary of the Lord.<verse eid="PSS 1:8"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:1"/>A Psalm. Pertaining to Salomon. Concerning Ierousalem. When the sinner became proud, he struck down fortified walls with a battering-ram, and you did not prevent him.<verse eid="PSS 2:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:2"/>Foreign nations went up to your altar; in pride they trampled it with their sandals,<verse eid="PSS 2:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:3"/>because the sons of Ierousalem had defiled the sanctuary of the Lord, had profaned the gifts of God with acts of lawlessness.<verse eid="PSS 2:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:4"/>Because of these things he said, "Cast them<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'gifts'</char></note> far from me; I take no pleasure in them."<verse eid="PSS 2:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:5"/>The beauty of her glory was despised before God; it was completely dishonored.<verse eid="PSS 2:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:6"/>The sons and daughters were in harsh captivity, their neck in a seal, with a mark among the nations.<verse eid="PSS 2:6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:7"/>According to their sins he dealt with them, for he abandoned them into the hands of those who prevail.<verse eid="PSS 2:7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:8"/>He<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Rahlfs = preceded by 'for'</char></note> turned away his face from pitying them, young and old and their children once again, for they did evil once again in not listening.<verse eid="PSS 2:8"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:9"/>And heaven was weighed down, and the earth detested them, because no person upon it had done what they did.<verse eid="PSS 2:9"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:10"/>And the earth shall know all your righteous judgments, O God.<verse eid="PSS 2:10"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:11"/>They set the sons of Ierousalem to be mocked because of the prostitutes in her; everyone passing by would enter before the sun.<verse eid="PSS 2:11"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:12"/>They used to mock with their acts of lawlessness, as they themselves used to do; before the sun they paraded their injustices.<verse eid="PSS 2:12"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:13"/>And the daughters of Ierousalem were profane according to your judgment, because they had defiled themselves with a confusion of mingling<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'unnatural intercourse'</char></note>.<verse eid="PSS 2:13"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:14"/>I am troubled in my entrails and my inward parts over these things.<verse eid="PSS 2:14"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:15"/>I will justify you, O God, in uprightness of heart, for in your judgments is your righteousness, O God.<verse eid="PSS 2:15"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:16"/>For you have repaid the sinners according to their works, and according to their sins, which were very wicked.<verse eid="PSS 2:16"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:17"/>You have exposed their sins, that your judgment might be evident; you have wiped out their memorial from the earth.<verse eid="PSS 2:17"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:18"/>God is a righteous judge, and he will not marvel at a person.<verse eid="PSS 2:18"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:19"/>For the nations reviled Ierousalem, trampling her down; he dragged down her beauty from the throne of glory.<verse eid="PSS 2:19"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:20"/>She put on sackcloth instead of beautiful clothing, a rope around her head instead of a crown.<verse eid="PSS 2:20"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:21"/>She removed the headdress of glory, which God had set upon her; in dishonor her beauty was cast upon the ground.<verse eid="PSS 2:21"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:22"/>And I saw and entreated the face of the Lord and said: Long enough, Lord, has your hand been heavy on Ierousalem in bringing the nations upon her.<verse eid="PSS 2:22"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:23"/>For they mocked and spared not, in wrath and fierce anger, and they will be brought to an end, unless you, Lord, rebuke them in your wrath.<verse eid="PSS 2:23"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:24"/>For it was not out of zeal that they acted, but out of the desire of the soul, so as to pour out their wrath upon us in plunder.<verse eid="PSS 2:24"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:25"/>Do not delay, O God, to repay them on their heads, to declare<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:25</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'to say'</char></note> in dishonor the arrogance of the dragon.<verse eid="PSS 2:25"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:26"/>And I did not wait long until God showed me his insolence, pierced, on the mountains of Egypt, more than the least despised on land and sea.<verse eid="PSS 2:26"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:27"/>His body, carried about on the waves in great insolence, and there was no one to bury, for he had rejected him in dishonor.<verse eid="PSS 2:27"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:28"/>He did not consider that he was a human, nor did he consider the hereafter.<verse eid="PSS 2:28"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:29"/>He said, "I will be lord of earth and sea," and he did not recognize that God is great, mighty in his great strength.<verse eid="PSS 2:29"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:30"/>He is king over the heavens, also judging kings and authorities.<verse eid="PSS 2:30"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:31"/>It is he who raises me up to glory and puts the arrogant to sleep for everlasting destruction in dishonor, because they did not know him.<verse eid="PSS 2:31"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:32"/>And now see, the nobles of the earth, the judgment of the Lord; for he is a great and righteous king; judging what is under heaven.<verse eid="PSS 2:32"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:33"/>Bless God, you who fear the Lord with understanding, for the pity of the Lord is upon those who fear him with judgment,<verse eid="PSS 2:33"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:34"/>to separate between righteous and sinner, to repay the sinners forever according to their works<verse eid="PSS 2:34"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:35"/>and to have pity on the righteous, from the humiliation of the sinner<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:35</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'from the humiliation of the sinner':  Or 'delivering him from the humiliation of the sinner'</char></note>, and to repay the sinner for what he has done to the righteous.<verse eid="PSS 2:35"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:36"/>For the Lord is kind to those who call on him with endurance, treating his devout according to his pity, setting them continuously before him in strength.<verse eid="PSS 2:36"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 2:37"/>Blessed is the Lord forever before his slaves.<verse eid="PSS 2:37"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 3:1"/>A Psalm. Pertaining to Salomon. Concerning the righteous. Why do you sleep, soul, and do not bless the Lord? Play a new hymn to God, who is worthy to be praised.<verse eid="PSS 3:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 3:2"/>Play, and be fully awake in wakefulness<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'vigilance'</char></note> for him, for a good melody to God is from a good heart.<verse eid="PSS 3:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 3:3"/>The righteous remember the Lord at all times, with confession and justification, the Lord's judgments.<verse eid="PSS 3:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 3:4"/>The righteous does not despise being disciplined by the Lord; his good will is always before the Lord.<verse eid="PSS 3:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 3:5"/>The righteous stumbled and justified the Lord; he fell and watches what God will do for him; he eagerly watches whence his salvation will come.<verse eid="PSS 3:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 3:6"/>The truth of the righteous is from their divine savior; in the house of the righteous sin upon sin does not lodge<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'find a home'</char></note>.<verse eid="PSS 3:6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 3:7"/>The righteous always searches his house, to remove his injustice in transgression.<verse eid="PSS 3:7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 3:8"/>He made atonement for sins of ignorance by fasting and humiliation of his soul, and the Lord cleanses every devout man and his house.<verse eid="PSS 3:8"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 3:9"/>The sinner stumbled, and he curses his life, the day of his birth and his mother's birth pangs.<verse eid="PSS 3:9"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 3:10"/>He has added sin upon sin in his lifetime; he fell, because his fall is evil, and he shall not rise up.<verse eid="PSS 3:10"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 3:11"/>The destruction of the sinner is forever, and he will not be remembered, when he visits the righteous.<verse eid="PSS 3:11"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 3:12"/>This is the portion of sinners forever, but those who fear the Lord shall rise to everlasting life, and their life is in the light of the Lord and shall never end.<verse eid="PSS 3:12"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:1"/>Discourse of Salomon. Pertaining to the men-pleasers. Why do you sit, profaner, in the council of the devout, and your heart is far removed from the Lord, provoking with transgressions of the law the God of Israel?<verse eid="PSS 4:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:2"/>Extravagant in speech, extravagant in appearance above everyone, the person harsh in speech in condemning sinners in judgment.<verse eid="PSS 4:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:3"/>And his hand is the first upon him as if in zeal, and he himself is guilty of various sins and self-indulgence.<verse eid="PSS 4:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:4"/>His eyes are upon every woman without distinction; his tongue is false when he makes a contract with an oath.<verse eid="PSS 4:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:5"/>At night and in secret he sins as though unseen; with his eyes he speaks to every woman in evil assignation<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:5</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'in evil assignation':  Possibly 'about illicit affairs'</char></note>; he is quick to enter every house cheerfully as though innocent.<verse eid="PSS 4:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:6"/>May God remove those who live in hypocrisy with the devout, with corruption of his flesh and his life with poverty.<verse eid="PSS 4:6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:7"/>May God reveal the works of men, of menpleasers, his works with derision and contempt.<verse eid="PSS 4:7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:8"/>And may the devout justify the judgment of their God, when sinners are removed from the presence of the righteous, the man-pleaser who speaks the law with deceit.<verse eid="PSS 4:8"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:9"/>And their eyes are upon a stable house of a man<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'stable house of a man':  Or 'a peaceful man's house'</char></note>, as a serpent to destroy each other's wisdom with words of those who transgress the law.<verse eid="PSS 4:9"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:10"/>His words are deceptions to accomplish his desire for injustice; he did not cease until he had succeeded in scattering them as orphans.<verse eid="PSS 4:10"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:11"/>He devastated a house on account of his desire for transgressing the law; he deceived with words, because there is no one who sees and judges.<verse eid="PSS 4:11"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:12"/>At this<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Antecedent unclear; possibly 'desire'</char></note> he was filled with transgressing the law, and his eyes are upon another house, to destroy it with clamorous words.<verse eid="PSS 4:12"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:13"/>His soul, like Hades, is not satisfied with all these things.<verse eid="PSS 4:13"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:14"/>May his portion, O Lord, be dishonored before you; may his going out be with groaning, and his coming in with a curse.<verse eid="PSS 4:14"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:15"/>May his life be in anguish and poverty and anxiety, O Lord; may his sleep be with grief, and his waking with anxiety.<verse eid="PSS 4:15"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:16"/>May sleep be taken from his temples at night; may he fail dishonorably in all the work of his hands.<verse eid="PSS 4:16"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:17"/>May he enter his house empty-handed, and may his house lack everything with which he might satisfy his soul.<verse eid="PSS 4:17"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:18"/>May his old age be spent in loneliness without children right up to his being taken up.<verse eid="PSS 4:18"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:19"/>May the flesh of the men-pleasers be scattered by wild beasts, and may the bones of the transgressors of the law lie before the sun in dishonor.<verse eid="PSS 4:19"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:20"/>May ravens peck out the eyes of hypocrites, for they have devastated many houses of men in dishonor, and they scattered them in desire.<verse eid="PSS 4:20"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:21"/>And they have not remembered God, and they did not fear God in all these things, and they provoked and angered God.<verse eid="PSS 4:21"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:22"/>May he remove them from the earth, because with pretense they have deceived the souls of the innocent.<verse eid="PSS 4:22"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:23"/>Happy are those who fear the Lord in their innocence; the Lord will save them from deceitful men and sinners, and he will save us from every stumbling block of the transgressor of the law.<verse eid="PSS 4:23"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:24"/>May God remove those who arrogantly do all injustice; for the Lord our God is a great and mighty judge in righteousness.<verse eid="PSS 4:24"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 4:25"/>May your pity, O Lord, be upon all those who love you.<verse eid="PSS 4:25"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:1"/>A Psalm. Pertaining to Salomon. O Lord God, I will praise your name with joy in the midst of those who have knowledge of your righteous judgments.<verse eid="PSS 5:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:2"/>For you are kind and merciful, the refuge of the poor; when I cry out to you, do not pass me by in silence.<verse eid="PSS 5:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:3"/>For no one will take booty from a strong man, and who shall take of all that you have made, unless you give it?<verse eid="PSS 5:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:4"/>For man and his portion are before you in the balance; he cannot increase it beyond your judgment<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'your judgment':  Perhaps 'what you have prescribed'</char></note>, O God.<verse eid="PSS 5:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:5"/>When we are distressed we will call upon you for help, and you will not turn back our petition, because you are our God.<verse eid="PSS 5:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:6"/>Make not your hand heavy upon us, lest, from distress, we sin.<verse eid="PSS 5:6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:7"/>And if you do not return us, we will not stay away, but we will come to you.<verse eid="PSS 5:7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:8"/>For if I hunger, I will cry to you, O God, and you will give to me.<verse eid="PSS 5:8"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:9"/>You feed the birds and the fish, when you give rain to wildernesses that green grass may spring up.<verse eid="PSS 5:9"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:10"/>You have provided fodder in the wilderness for every living thing, and if they hunger, they will lift their face to you.<verse eid="PSS 5:10"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:11"/>You feed kings and rulers and peoples, O God, and who is the hope of the poor and needy, unless it be you, O Lord?<verse eid="PSS 5:11"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:12"/>And you will listen-- for who is kind and forgiving but you?-- making glad the soul of the humble by opening your hand in pity.<verse eid="PSS 5:12"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:13"/>Man's kindness is grudgingly, and tomorrow, and if he repeat it without complaining, you would even marvel at this.<verse eid="PSS 5:13"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:14"/>But your gift is great in kindness, and rich, and he whose hope is in you will not be sparing with a gift<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:14</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'not be sparing with a gift':  Perhaps 'give generously'</char></note>.<verse eid="PSS 5:14"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:15"/>Your pity, O Lord, is upon the whole earth in kindness.<verse eid="PSS 5:15"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:16"/>Happy is the man whom God remembers in due proportion to sufficiency<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">5:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'in due proportion to sufficiency':  Perhaps 'and provides for his needs in moderation'</char></note>; if man has too much, he sins.<verse eid="PSS 5:16"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:17"/>Sufficient is a moderate provision with righteousness, and in this is the blessing of the Lord for abundance with righteousness.<verse eid="PSS 5:17"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:18"/>May those who fear the Lord rejoice in good things, and your kindness be upon Israel in your kingdom.<verse eid="PSS 5:18"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 5:19"/>Blessed is the glory of the Lord, for he is our king.<verse eid="PSS 5:19"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 6:1"/>In hope. Pertaining to Salomon. Happy is the man whose heart is prepared to call on the name of the Lord; when he remembers the name of the Lord, he will be saved.<verse eid="PSS 6:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 6:2"/>His ways are directed by the Lord, and the works of his hands are protected by the Lord, his God.<verse eid="PSS 6:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 6:3"/>His soul will not be disturbed with the sight of evil dreams; when he crosses rivers and when the seas swell, he will not be terrified.<verse eid="PSS 6:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 6:4"/>He arose from his sleep and blessed the name of the Lord. In firmness of heart he sang a hymn to the name of his God.<verse eid="PSS 6:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 6:5"/>And he entreated the face of the Lord for his entire household, and the Lord listened to the prayer of everyone in fear of God.<verse eid="PSS 6:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 6:6"/>And the Lord fulfills every request of the soul that hopes in him. Blessed is the Lord who works pity for those who love him in truth.<verse eid="PSS 6:6"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 7:1"/>Pertaining to Salomon. Of returning. Remove not your dwelling from us, O God, lest they attack us, those who hated us without cause.<verse eid="PSS 7:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 7:2"/>For you have rejected them, O God; let their foot not trample upon the inheritance of your holy precinct.<verse eid="PSS 7:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 7:3"/>Discipline us by your will, and do not give us to the nations.<verse eid="PSS 7:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 7:4"/>For if you send death, you will command it concerning us.<verse eid="PSS 7:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 7:5"/>For you are full of pity, and you will not be angry enough to destroy us completely.<verse eid="PSS 7:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 7:6"/>While your name dwells in our midst, we shall find pity, and no nation will prevail against us.<verse eid="PSS 7:6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 7:7"/>For you are our protector, and we shall call upon you, and you will hearken to us;<verse eid="PSS 7:7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 7:8"/>For you will have compassion upon the race of Israel forever, and you will not reject it,<verse eid="PSS 7:8"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 7:9"/>and we are under your yoke forever, and the whip of your discipline.<verse eid="PSS 7:9"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 7:10"/>And you will direct us in the time of your help, showing pity to the house of Iakob on the day you promised them.<verse eid="PSS 7:10"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 8"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:1"/>Pertaining to Salomon. Regarding victory. My ear heard distress and the sound of war, the sound of a trumpet announcing slaughter and destruction.<verse eid="PSS 8:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:2"/>The sound of many people is like that of an exceedingly great wind, like a hurricane with mighty fire sweeping through the wilderness.<verse eid="PSS 8:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:3"/>And I said in my heart, "Where, then, will God judge him?"<verse eid="PSS 8:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:4"/>I heard a sound in Ierousalem, city of a holy precinct.<verse eid="PSS 8:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:5"/>My lower back was crushed from the report; my knees weakened; my heart was afraid; my bones were shaken like flax.<verse eid="PSS 8:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:6"/>I said, "They will direct their ways in righteousness."<verse eid="PSS 8:6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:7"/>I considered the judgments of God since the creation of heaven and earth; I justified God in his judgments from eternity.<verse eid="PSS 8:7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:8"/>God exposed their sins before the sun; all the earth knew the righteous judgments of God.<verse eid="PSS 8:8"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:9"/>In secret places under the earth were their transgressions of the law in provocation<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'in provocation':  Possibly 'committed in provocation'</char></note>; they committed incest, son with mother and father with daughter.<verse eid="PSS 8:9"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:10"/>They committed adultery, every man with his neighbor's wife. They concluded compacts by oath with one another concerning these things.<verse eid="PSS 8:10"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:11"/>They would plunder the sanctuary of God, as though there was no heir who redeems.<verse eid="PSS 8:11"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:12"/>They would trample the altar of the Lord because<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">8:12</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'as a result'</char></note> of all kinds of uncleanness, and with menstrual blood they defiled the sacrifices as if they were profane meat.<verse eid="PSS 8:12"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:13"/>They left no sin, which they did not do more than the nations.<verse eid="PSS 8:13"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:14"/>Therefore God mixed for them a spirit of confusion; he gave them a cup of undiluted wine to drink, that they might become drunk.<verse eid="PSS 8:14"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:15"/>He brought him from the end of the earth, who strikes mightily; he declared war against Ierousalem and her land.<verse eid="PSS 8:15"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:16"/>The rulers of the land met him with joy; they said to him, "Welcome is your way; come, enter in peace."<verse eid="PSS 8:16"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:17"/>They leveled the rough roads before his entry; they opened the gates to Ierousalem; they crowned her walls.<verse eid="PSS 8:17"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:18"/>He entered, as a father the house of his sons, with peace; he set down his feet with great security.<verse eid="PSS 8:18"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:19"/>He captured her towered strongholds and the wall of Ierousalem, for God led him with security while they went astray.<verse eid="PSS 8:19"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:20"/>He killed their rulers and everyone wise in counsel; he poured out the blood of the inhabitants of Ierousalem like the water of uncleanness.<verse eid="PSS 8:20"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:21"/>He led away their sons and daughters whom they had begotten in defilement.<verse eid="PSS 8:21"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:22"/>They did according to their uncleanness, just as their fathers; they defiled Ierousalem and the things that had been sanctified to the name of God.<verse eid="PSS 8:22"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:23"/>God was justified in his judgments among the nations of the earth, and the devout of God are like lambs innocent in their midst.<verse eid="PSS 8:23"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:24"/>Worthy to be praised is the Lord who judges all the earth in his righteousness.<verse eid="PSS 8:24"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:25"/>See, O God, you have shown us your judgment in your righteousness; our eyes have seen your judgments, O God.<verse eid="PSS 8:25"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:26"/>We have justified your name that is honored forever, for you are the God of righteousness, judging Israel with discipline.<verse eid="PSS 8:26"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:27"/>Turn, O God, your pity upon us, and have compassion upon us.<verse eid="PSS 8:27"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:28"/>Gather together the dispersion of Israel with pity and kindness, for your faithfulness is with us.<verse eid="PSS 8:28"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:29"/>And we stiffened our neck, and you are the one who disciplines us.<verse eid="PSS 8:29"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:30"/>Overlook us not, our God, lest the nations swallow us up, as though there were no redeemer.<verse eid="PSS 8:30"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:31"/>And you are our God from the beginning, and upon you is our hope, O Lord.<verse eid="PSS 8:31"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:32"/>And we shall not depart from you, for your judgments upon us are kind.<verse eid="PSS 8:32"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:33"/>Upon us and our children is your good will forever; O Lord, our savior, we shall never more be shaken.<verse eid="PSS 8:33"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 8:34"/>Worthy to be praised is the Lord for his judgments by the mouth of devout ones, and blessed is Israel by the Lord forever.<verse eid="PSS 8:34"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 9"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 9:1"/>Pertaining to Salomon. Regarding rebuke. When Israel was led away in exile to a foreign land, when they fell away from the Lord who redeemed them, they were expelled from the inheritance, which the Lord had given them.<verse eid="PSS 9:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 9:2"/>The dispersion of Israel was among every nation, according to the word of God, that you may be justified, O God, in your righteousness by reason of our acts of lawlessness; for you are a righteous judge over all the peoples of the earth.<verse eid="PSS 9:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 9:3"/>For none that does injustice shall be hidden from your knowledge, and the righteous acts of your devout are before you, O Lord, and where shall a human being hide himself from your knowledge, O God?<verse eid="PSS 9:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 9:4"/>Our works are in the choosing and power of our soul, to do righteousness or injustice in the works of our hands, and in your righteousness you visit human beings.<verse eid="PSS 9:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 9:5"/>The one who practices righteousness stores up life for himself with the Lord, and the one who practices injustice is responsible for the destruction of his own soul, for the judgments of the Lord are in righteousness for each man and household.<verse eid="PSS 9:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 9:6"/>To whom will you show kindness, O God, if not to them that call upon the Lord? You will cleanse a soul from sins when he will confess, when he acknowledges<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'when he will confess, when he acknowledges':  Possibly 'when confession and acknowledgment is made'</char></note>; for shame is upon us and our faces on account of all these things.<verse eid="PSS 9:6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 9:7"/>And to whom will you forgive sins, except to those who have sinned? You shall bless the righteous and not straighten them for the sins they have committed<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">9:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'straighten them for the sins they have committed':  Possibly 'guide them in situations when they have sinned'</char></note>, and your kindness is upon sinners in repentance.<verse eid="PSS 9:7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 9:8"/>And now, you are our God, and we are the people whom you have loved. Look, and be compassionate, O God of Israel, for we are yours, and remove not your pity from us, lest they attack us.<verse eid="PSS 9:8"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 9:9"/>And you chose the offspring of Abraam above all the nations, and you placed your name upon us, O Lord, and you will not reject us forever.<verse eid="PSS 9:9"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 9:10"/>You made a covenant with our fathers concerning us, and we shall hope in you when we return our souls toward you.<verse eid="PSS 9:10"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 9:11"/>The mercy of the Lord is upon the house of Israel forever and ever.<verse eid="PSS 9:11"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 10"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 10:1"/>Among hymns. Pertaining to Salomon. Happy is the man whom the Lord remembers with reproving and who is fenced<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">10:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'restrained'</char></note> from the evil road by a whip, that he may be cleansed from sin, that it may not increase.<verse eid="PSS 10:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 10:2"/>He who prepares his back for lashes shall be cleansed, for the Lord is kind to those who endure discipline.<verse eid="PSS 10:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 10:3"/>For he will straighten the ways of the righteous and will not turn them aside by discipline, and the pity of the Lord is upon those who love him in truth.<verse eid="PSS 10:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 10:4"/>And the Lord will remember his slaves in pity, for the testimony is in the law of the everlasting covenant, the testimony of the Lord for the ways of humankind at his visitation.<verse eid="PSS 10:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 10:5"/>Our Lord is righteous and devout in his judgments forever, and Israel shall praise the name of the Lord with joy.<verse eid="PSS 10:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 10:6"/>And the devout shall acknowledge in the assembly of the people, and God will show pity upon the poor to the joy of Israel.<verse eid="PSS 10:6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 10:7"/>For God is kind and full of pity forever, and the congregations of Israel shall glorify the name of the Lord.<verse eid="PSS 10:7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 10:8"/>The salvation of the Lord is upon the house of Israel for everlasting joy.<verse eid="PSS 10:8"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 11"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 11:1"/>Pertaining to Salomon. Regarding expectation. Trumpet in Sion with a signal trumpet to summon the holy ones; proclaim in Ierousalem the voice of one who brings good news; for the God of Israel has shown pity in his visitation of them.<verse eid="PSS 11:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 11:2"/>Stand upon a high place, O Ierousalem, and behold your children, from the east and the west, gathered together once again by the Lord.<verse eid="PSS 11:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 11:3"/>From the north they come in the joy of their God; from the islands far away God has gathered them.<verse eid="PSS 11:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 11:4"/>He has leveled high mountains into level ground for them; the hills fled at their approach.<verse eid="PSS 11:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 11:5"/>The woods shaded them as they passed by; God caused every tree of fragrance to spring up for them,<verse eid="PSS 11:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 11:6"/>that Israel might pass by at the visitation of their God's glory.<verse eid="PSS 11:6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 11:7"/>Put on, O Ierousalem, the garments of your glory; prepare the robe of your sanctity<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">11:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'holy precinct'</char></note>, for God has spoken good concerning Israel forever and ever.<verse eid="PSS 11:7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 11:8"/>May the Lord do what he has spoken concerning Israel and Ierousalem; may the Lord raise up Israel by his glorious name.<verse eid="PSS 11:8"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 11:9"/>The pity of the Lord is upon Israel forever and ever.<verse eid="PSS 11:9"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 12"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 12:1"/>Pertaining to Salomon. Against the tongue of the transgressors of the law. O Lord, deliver my soul from the man who is a transgressor of the law and wicked, from the tongue that transgresses the law and is slanderous and that speaks lies and deceits.<verse eid="PSS 12:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 12:2"/>The words of the tongue of the wicked man are twisted in many ways, like fire among a people which burns up its beauty.<verse eid="PSS 12:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 12:3"/>His sojourn-- to set on fire households with a lying tongue-- to cut down trees of joy that sets the transgressors of the law on fire, to confound households in warfare by means of slanderous lips.<verse eid="PSS 12:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 12:4"/>May God remove far from the innocent the lips of the transgressors of the law with anxiety, and may the bones of slanderers be scattered far from those who fear the Lord; may the slanderous tongue perish in flaming fire far from the devout.<verse eid="PSS 12:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 12:5"/>May the Lord preserve the quiet soul that hates the unjust, and may the Lord direct the man who makes peace at home.<verse eid="PSS 12:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 12:6"/>The salvation of the Lord is upon Israel his servant forever, and may the sinners perish altogether from the presence of the Lord, and may the devout of the Lord inherit the promises of the Lord.<verse eid="PSS 12:6"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 13"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 13:1"/>A Psalm. Pertaining to Salomon. Comfort for the righteous. The right hand of the Lord covered me; the right hand of the Lord spared us.<verse eid="PSS 13:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 13:2"/>The arm of the Lord saved us from the sword that passes through, from famine and the death of sinners.<verse eid="PSS 13:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 13:3"/>Evil wild animals rushed upon them; with their teeth they tore their flesh, and with their molars they crushed their bones.<verse eid="PSS 13:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 13:4"/>But from all these things the Lord delivered us.<verse eid="PSS 13:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 13:5"/>The pious man was troubled on account of his transgressions, lest he should be taken away along with the sinners.<verse eid="PSS 13:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 13:6"/>For the destruction of the sinner is terrible, but not one of all these things shall touch the righteous.<verse eid="PSS 13:6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 13:7"/>For not the same is the discipline of the righteous in ignorance and the destruction of the sinners.<verse eid="PSS 13:7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 13:8"/>The righteous is disciplined with distinctness so that the sinner may not rejoice over the righteous.<verse eid="PSS 13:8"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 13:9"/>For he will admonish the righteous as a beloved son, and his discipline is as that of a firstborn.<verse eid="PSS 13:9"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 13:10"/>For the Lord will spare his devout and will wipe away their transgressions with discipline.<verse eid="PSS 13:10"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 13:11"/>For the life of the righteous is forever, but sinners shall be taken away into destruction, and their memorial shall never be found.<verse eid="PSS 13:11"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 13:12"/>But the pity of the Lord is upon the devout, and his pity is upon those who fear him.<verse eid="PSS 13:12"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 14"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 14:1"/>A Hymn. Pertaining to Salomon. Faithful is the Lord to those who love him in truth, to those who endure his discipline,<verse eid="PSS 14:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 14:2"/>to those who walk in the righteousness of his ordinances, in the law which he commanded us that we might live.<verse eid="PSS 14:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 14:3"/>The devout of the Lord shall live by it forever; the orchard of the Lord, the trees of life, are his devout.<verse eid="PSS 14:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 14:4"/>Their planting is rooted forever; they shall not be pulled up all the days of heaven;<verse eid="PSS 14:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 14:5"/>for the portion and the inheritance of God is Israel.<verse eid="PSS 14:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 14:6"/>But not so are the sinners and transgressors of the law, who loved a day in the companionship of their sin.<verse eid="PSS 14:6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 14:7"/>Their desire was for the briefness of corruption, and they have not remembered God.<verse eid="PSS 14:7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 14:8"/>For the ways of human beings are known before him at all times, and he knows the storerooms<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">14:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'secret rooms'</char></note> of the heart before they come to pass.<verse eid="PSS 14:8"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 14:9"/>Therefore their inheritance is Hades and darkness and destruction, and they shall not be found in the day when the righteous obtain pity.<verse eid="PSS 14:9"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 14:10"/>But the devout of the Lord shall inherit life with joy.<verse eid="PSS 14:10"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 15"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 15:1"/>A Psalm. Pertaining to Salomon. With an Ode. When I was in distress, I called upon the name of the Lord; I hoped for the help of the God of Iakob and was saved, for you are the hope and the refuge of the poor, O God.<verse eid="PSS 15:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 15:2"/>For who, O God, is strong except to confess to you in truth? And wherein is a person mighty except in confessing to your name?<verse eid="PSS 15:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 15:3"/>A new melody with an ode in gladness of heart, the fruit of the lips with the tuned instrument of the tongue, the first fruit of the lips from a devout and righteous heart--<verse eid="PSS 15:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 15:4"/>he who does these things shall never be shaken by evil; the flame of fire and the wrath against the unrighteous shall not touch him,<verse eid="PSS 15:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 15:5"/>when it goes forth from the face of the Lord against sinners, to destroy all the substance of sinners;<verse eid="PSS 15:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 15:6"/>For the mark of God is upon the righteous for salvation.<verse eid="PSS 15:6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 15:7"/>Famine and sword and death shall be far from the righteous; for they shall flee from the devout as those pursued by war,<verse eid="PSS 15:7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 15:8"/>but they shall pursue sinners and overtake them, and those who do lawlessness shall not escape the judgment of the Lord;<verse eid="PSS 15:8"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 15:9"/>they shall be overtaken by those experienced in war, for the mark of destruction is upon their forehead.<verse eid="PSS 15:9"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 15:10"/>And the inheritance of sinners is destruction and darkness, and their acts of lawlessness shall pursue them to Hades below.<verse eid="PSS 15:10"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 15:11"/>Their inheritance shall not be found for their children, for sins shall lay waste the houses of sinners.<verse eid="PSS 15:11"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 15:12"/>And sinners shall perish forever in the day of the Lord's judgment, when God visits the earth with his judgment.<verse eid="PSS 15:12"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 15:13"/>But those who fear the Lord shall find mercy on it<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">15:13</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the earth'</char></note>, and they shall live by the mercy of their God, but sinners shall perish forever and anon.<verse eid="PSS 15:13"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 16"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 16:1"/>A Hymn. Pertaining to Salomon. Regarding help for the devout. When my soul slumbered, away from the Lord, I slipped for a short time, in the lethargy of those that sleep far from God.<verse eid="PSS 16:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 16:2"/>For a short time my soul was poured out to death, close to the gates of Hades with the sinner,<verse eid="PSS 16:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 16:3"/>when my soul separated from the Lord, God of Israel, except that the Lord helped me with his pity forever.<verse eid="PSS 16:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 16:4"/>He pricked me, like a goad for a horse, that I might awaken unto him; my savior and protector at all times saved me.<verse eid="PSS 16:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 16:5"/>I will acknowledge [to] you, O God, for you helped me to salvation, and you did not count me with sinners for destruction.<verse eid="PSS 16:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 16:6"/>Remove not your pity from me, O God, nor your remembrance from my heart until death.<verse eid="PSS 16:6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 16:7"/>Rule over me<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">16:7</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Perhaps 'hold me back'</char></note>, O God, from wicked sin and from every evil woman who causes the foolish to stumble.<verse eid="PSS 16:7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 16:8"/>And let not the beauty of a woman who transgresses the law deceive me, nor of anything that is subject to useless sin.<verse eid="PSS 16:8"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 16:9"/>Direct the works of my hands in your place, and guard my steps in your remembrance.<verse eid="PSS 16:9"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 16:10"/>Protect my tongue and my lips with words of truth; anger and unreasoning wrath put far from me.<verse eid="PSS 16:10"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 16:11"/>Grumbling and faint-heartedness in affliction keep far from me, when, if I sin, you discipline me to return me.<verse eid="PSS 16:11"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 16:12"/>Support my soul with goodwill and cheerfulness; when you strengthen my soul, what is given will be sufficient for me.<verse eid="PSS 16:12"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 16:13"/>For if you do not give strength, who will endure discipline in poverty?<verse eid="PSS 16:13"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 16:14"/>When a soul is rebuked in the hand of his corruption, your testing is in his flesh and in the affliction of poverty.<verse eid="PSS 16:14"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 16:15"/>If the righteous endures in all these, he shall receive pity from the Lord.<verse eid="PSS 16:15"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 17"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:1"/>A Psalm. Pertaining to Salomon. With an Ode. Pertaining to the king. O Lord, you are our king forever and ever, for in you, O God, shall our soul boast.<verse eid="PSS 17:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:2"/>And how long is the time of a person's life upon the earth? According to his time and his hope upon him.<verse eid="PSS 17:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:3"/>But we will hope in God our savior; for the might of our God is forever with pity, and the kingdom of our God is forever over the nations in judgment.<verse eid="PSS 17:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:4"/>You, O Lord, you chose Dauid king over Israel, and you swore to him concerning his offspring forever, that his palace would never fail before you.<verse eid="PSS 17:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:5"/>And, because of our sins, sinners rose up against us; they attacked us and thrust us out, to whom you did not promise; they took possession by force, and they did not glorify your honorable name.<verse eid="PSS 17:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:6"/>They set up in glory a palace corresponding to their loftiness; they laid waste the throne of Dauid in arrogance leading to change.<verse eid="PSS 17:6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:7"/>But you, O God, will overthrow them and will remove their offspring from the earth, when there rises up against them a person that is foreign to our race.<verse eid="PSS 17:7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:8"/>According to their sins you will repay them, O God, that it may befall them according to their works.<verse eid="PSS 17:8"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:9"/>God showed them no pity; he has sought out their offspring and let not one of them go free.<verse eid="PSS 17:9"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:10"/>Faithful is the Lord in all his judgments, which he performs on the earth.<verse eid="PSS 17:10"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:11"/>The lawless one laid waste our land so that no one inhabited it; they destroyed young and old and their children together.<verse eid="PSS 17:11"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:12"/>In the wrath of his beauty he expelled them to the west, and the rulers of the land to derision, and did not spare them.<verse eid="PSS 17:12"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:13"/>Being an alien the enemy acted arrogantly, and his heart was estranged from our God.<verse eid="PSS 17:13"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:14"/>And all things that he did in Ierousalem were just as the nations do in their strong cities.<verse eid="PSS 17:14"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:15"/>And the sons of the covenant surpassed them in the midst of motley nations; there was no one among them who practiced pity and truth in Ierousalem.<verse eid="PSS 17:15"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:16"/>Those who loved the congregations of the devout fled from them, as sparrows were scattered from their nest.<verse eid="PSS 17:16"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:17"/>They wandered in wildernesses that their souls be saved from evil, and their saved soul was precious in the eyes of those who sojourned abroad.<verse eid="PSS 17:17"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:18"/>They were scattered over the whole earth by lawless men, for heaven withheld the rain from falling on the earth.<verse eid="PSS 17:18"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:19"/>Everlasting springs out of abysses were held back from high mountains, for there was none among them who did righteousness and justice.<verse eid="PSS 17:19"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:20"/>From their ruler and the lowest of the people they were in every sin; the king was in transgression of the law, and the judge in disobedience, and the people in sin.<verse eid="PSS 17:20"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:21"/>See, O Lord, and raise up for them their king, the son of Dauid, at the time which you chose, O God, to rule over Israel your servant.<verse eid="PSS 17:21"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:22"/>And gird him with strength to shatter in pieces unrighteous rulers, to purify Ierousalem from nations that trample her down in destruction,<verse eid="PSS 17:22"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:23"/>in wisdom of righteousness, to drive out sinners from the inheritance, to smash the arrogance of the sinner like a potter's vessel,<verse eid="PSS 17:23"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:24"/>to shatter all their substance with an iron rod, to destroy the lawless nations by the word of his mouth,<verse eid="PSS 17:24"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:25"/>that, by his threat, nations flee from his presence, and to reprove sinners with the thought of their hearts.<verse eid="PSS 17:25"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:26"/>And he shall gather a holy people whom he shall lead in righteousness, and he shall judge the tribes of the people that has been sanctified by the Lord, his God.<verse eid="PSS 17:26"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:27"/>And he shall not allow injustice to lodge in their midst any longer, nor shall there dwell with them any person who knows evil; for he shall know them, that all are their God's sons.<verse eid="PSS 17:27"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:28"/>And he shall distribute them according to their tribes upon the land, and no resident alien and alien shall sojourn among them any longer.<verse eid="PSS 17:28"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:29"/>He shall judge peoples and nations in the wisdom of his righteousness. Interlude on strings<verse eid="PSS 17:29"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:30"/>And he shall have the peoples of the nations to be subject to him under his yoke, and he shall glorify the Lord in the mark<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">17:30</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Perhaps 'sight'</char></note> of all the earth, and he shall purify Ierousalem in holiness as it was at the beginning<verse eid="PSS 17:30"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:31"/>so that nations may come from the end of the earth to see his glory, bringing as gifts her sons who are exhausted, and to see the glory of the Lord with which God has glorified her.<verse eid="PSS 17:31"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:32"/>And he shall be a righteous king, taught by God, over them, and there shall be no injustice in his days in their midst, for all shall be holy, and their king the anointed of the Lord.<verse eid="PSS 17:32"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:33"/>For he shall not put his hope in horse and rider and bow, nor shall he multiply for himself gold and silver for war, nor shall he gather hopes from a multitude of people for the day of war.<verse eid="PSS 17:33"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:34"/>The Lord himself is his king, the hope of him who is strong through hope in God, and he shall have pity on all the nations before him in fear.<verse eid="PSS 17:34"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:35"/>For he shall strike the earth with the word of his mouth forever; he shall bless the people of the Lord in wisdom with joy.<verse eid="PSS 17:35"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:36"/>And he himself shall be pure from sin so that he may rule a great people, that he may rebuke rulers and remove sinners by the strength of his word.<verse eid="PSS 17:36"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:37"/>And he shall not weaken in his days, relying<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">17:37</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> on his God; for God has made him strong in the holy spirit and wise in the counsel of understanding with strength and righteousness.<verse eid="PSS 17:37"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:38"/>And the blessing of the Lord shall be with him in strength, and he shall not weaken.<verse eid="PSS 17:38"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:39"/>His hope shall be in the Lord, and who can prevail against him?<verse eid="PSS 17:39"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:40"/>He shall be strong in his works and mighty in fear of God, shepherding the flock of the Lord faithfully and righteously, and he shall not let any among them become weak in their pasture.<verse eid="PSS 17:40"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:41"/>And he shall lead all of them in equity, and there shall be no arrogance among them, that any one of them should be oppressed.<verse eid="PSS 17:41"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:42"/>This is the majesty of the king of Israel, which God knew, to raise him up over the house of Israel to discipline it.<verse eid="PSS 17:42"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:43"/>His words will be more refined than costly gold, the finest. In the congregations he will discerningly judge the tribes of a sanctified people; his words are as words of the holy in the midst of sanctified peoples.<verse eid="PSS 17:43"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:44"/>Happy are those who shall live in those days, to see the good things of Israel that God shall accomplish in the congregation of the tribes.<verse eid="PSS 17:44"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:45"/>May God hasten his pity upon Israel; may he deliver us from the uncleanness of profane enemies.<verse eid="PSS 17:45"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 17:46"/>The Lord himself is our king forever and ever.<verse eid="PSS 17:46"/>



  <chapter sid="PSS 18"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 18:1"/>A Psalm. Pertaining to Salomon. Again of the anointed of the Lord. O Lord, your pity is over the works of your hands forever; your goodness is over Israel with a rich gift.<verse eid="PSS 18:1"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 18:2"/>When your eyes gaze upon them, then none of them shall be in want; your ears listen to the hopeful petition of the poor.<verse eid="PSS 18:2"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 18:3"/>Your judgments are over the whole earth with pity, and your love is upon the offspring of Abraam, the sons of Israel.<verse eid="PSS 18:3"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 18:4"/>Your discipline is upon us as on a firstborn, an only son, to turn back the obedient soul from ignorant stupidity.<verse eid="PSS 18:4"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 18:5"/>May God cleanse Israel for the day of pity with blessing, for the day of election when he brings up his anointed one.<verse eid="PSS 18:5"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 18:6"/>Happy are those who shall live in those days, to see the good things of the Lord, which he will perform for the coming generation.<verse eid="PSS 18:6"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 18:7"/>Under the rod of discipline of the Lord's anointed in fear of his God, in wisdom of spirit and of righteousness and strength,<verse eid="PSS 18:7"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 18:8"/>to direct a man in works of righteousness in fear of God, to establish them all before the Lord--<verse eid="PSS 18:8"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 18:9"/>a good generation in fear of God in the days of pity. Interlude on strings<verse eid="PSS 18:9"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 18:10"/>Great is our God, and glorious, dwelling in the highest, who appointed the lights in their course for the determining of seasons from day to day, and they did not turn aside from the path you commanded them.<verse eid="PSS 18:10"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 18:11"/>Their path each day is in the fear of God, from the day God created them and forever.<verse eid="PSS 18:11"/>
    <verse sid="PSS 18:12"/>And they have not wandered since the day he created them; since the generations of old they have not turned aside from their paths, except when God commanded them through the injunction of his slaves.<verse eid="PSS 18:12"/>
</usx>
