<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- SourceFormat: VL.  Converted to USX by the STEP project: 2023-08-18 -->
<usx version="2.0">
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <book code="RUT"/>



  <chapter sid="RUT 1"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:1"/>It was when the judges were judging, and there was a famine in the land, and a man went from Baithleem in Iouda to sojourn in the countryside of Moab, he and his wife and his sons.<verse eid="RUT 1:1"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:2"/>The name of the man was Abimelech, and the name of his wife, Noemin, and the name of his two sons, Maalon and Chelaion, Ephrathites from Baithleem in Iouda. They went into the countryside of Moab and remained there.<verse eid="RUT 1:2"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:3"/>And Abimelech, the husband of Noemin, died, and she was left, she and her two sons.<verse eid="RUT 1:3"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:4"/>They took for themselves Moabite wives; the name of the one was Orpha, and the name of the second, Routh. And they lived there about ten years,<verse eid="RUT 1:4"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:5"/>and both Maalon and Chelaion also died, and the woman was left, apart from her husband and apart from her two sons.<verse eid="RUT 1:5"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:6"/>And she set out, she and her two daughters-in-law, and they came back from the countryside of Moab, for they had heard in the countryside of Moab that the Lord had looked upon<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'looked upon':  Or 'visited'</char></note> his people, giving<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:6</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'to give'</char></note> them bread.<verse eid="RUT 1:6"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:7"/>And she went out from the place, there where she had been, and her two daughters-in-law with her, and they were going on their way to return to the land of Iouda,<verse eid="RUT 1:7"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:8"/>and Noemin said to her daughters-in-law, "Go now, go back, each to her mother's house. May the Lord do mercy with you, as you have done with the dead and with me.<verse eid="RUT 1:8"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:9"/>May the Lord give to you, and may you find rest, each in the house of her husband." And she kissed them, and they lifted up their voice and wept.<verse eid="RUT 1:9"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:10"/>They said to her, "We are returning with you to your people."<verse eid="RUT 1:10"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:11"/>And Noemin said, "Turn back now, my daughters! Now why are you going with me? Do I still have sons in my womb, and will they become husbands for you?<verse eid="RUT 1:11"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:12"/>Turn back now, my daughters, for I am too old for a husband to have me. For if I said, 'I have confidence that a man will marry me and I will bear sons,'<verse eid="RUT 1:12"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:13"/>you would not wait for them until they mature, would you? Or would you, on their account, refrain from getting married? Don't, my daughters, for it has been more bitter for me than for you, because the hand of the Lord has gone forth against me."<verse eid="RUT 1:13"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:14"/>And they lifted up their voice and wept further. Orpha kissed her mother-in-law and returned to her people, but Routh followed her.<verse eid="RUT 1:14"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:15"/>And Noemin said to Routh, "See, your sister-in-law has turned back to her people and to her gods; now turn back, you too, after your sister-in-law."<verse eid="RUT 1:15"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:16"/>But Routh said, "Do not oppose me, to make me abandon you or turn back<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'Do not oppose me, to make me abandon you or turn back':  Rahlfs = 'May it not befall me to abandon you or to turn back'</char></note> from after you. For wherever you go, I will go, and wherever you lodge, I will lodge; your people shall be my people, and your God my God.<verse eid="RUT 1:16"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:17"/>And wherever you die, I will die-- there will I be buried. Thus and so may the Lord do to me, and thus and so may he add-- for death alone<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Rahlfs = 'May it not befall me to abandon you or to turn back'</char></note> shall part me from you!"<verse eid="RUT 1:17"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:18"/>Then when Noemin saw that she was determined to go with her, she ceased speaking to her further.<verse eid="RUT 1:18"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:19"/>So the two of them went on until they came to Baithleem. And the whole city was abuzz because of them, and they<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">1:19</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'the women'</char></note> said, "Is this Noemin?"<verse eid="RUT 1:19"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:20"/>She said to them, "Call me no longer Noemin; call me Bitter, for the Sufficient One was greatly embittered against me.<verse eid="RUT 1:20"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:21"/>I went away full, and the Lord has brought me back empty. Why do you call me Noemin when the Lord has abased me and the Sufficient One has maltreated me?"<verse eid="RUT 1:21"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 1:22"/>And Noemin returned, and Routh the Moabite, her daughter-in-law, returning from the countryside of Moab. Now they came to Baithleem at the beginning of the barley harvest.<verse eid="RUT 1:22"/>



  <chapter sid="RUT 2"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:1"/>And with regard to Noemin there was a man, an acquaintance of her husband, and the man was powerful, of the kin of Abimelech, and his name was Boos.<verse eid="RUT 2:1"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:2"/>And Routh the Moabite said to Noemin, "Let me go now to the field and gather among the ears of grain, behind anyone in whose eyes I may find favor." And she said to her, "Go, daughter."<verse eid="RUT 2:2"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:3"/>And she went and gleaned in the field behind the reapers. And by happenstance she happened upon the part of the field belonging to Boos, who was of the kin of Abimelech.<verse eid="RUT 2:3"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:4"/>And there, from Baithleem, came Boos! He said to the reapers, "The Lord be with you." They said to him, "The Lord bless you."<verse eid="RUT 2:4"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:5"/>And Boos said to his servant who was in charge of the reapers, "To whom does this young woman belong?"<verse eid="RUT 2:5"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:6"/>The servant who was in charge of the reapers answered and said, "She is the Moabite lass, the one who came back with Noemin from the countryside of Moab.<verse eid="RUT 2:6"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:7"/>She said, 'Let me glean now and gather among the sheaves behind the reapers.' And she came, and she stood from morning until evening. She did not rest a bit in the field."<verse eid="RUT 2:7"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:8"/>And Boos said to Routh, "Did you not hear, daughter<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:8</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'Did you not hear, daughter':  I.e. 'Listen, daughter'</char></note>? Do not go to glean in another field, and you should not go from this one. Stick close to my girls here.<verse eid="RUT 2:8"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:9"/>Keep<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> your eyes on the field, wherever they are reaping, and walk behind them. See, I have commanded the young men not to touch you. If you want anything to drink, go to the vessels, and drink from what the young men draw."<verse eid="RUT 2:9"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:10"/>And she fell upon her face and did obeisance on the ground and said to him, "Why is it that I have found favor in your eyes, that you should take notice of me? And I am a foreigner!"<verse eid="RUT 2:10"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:11"/>And Boos answered and said to her, "All that you have done together with your mother-in-law since the death of your husband has been fully told me, and how you left your father and your mother and your native land and came to a people that you did not know yesterday or the day before.<verse eid="RUT 2:11"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:12"/>May the Lord repay you for your work, and may your recompense be full from the Lord, God of Israel, to whom you came, to put your trust under his wings!"<verse eid="RUT 2:12"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:13"/>Then she said, "May I find favor in your eyes, sir, because you have comforted me and because you have spoken to the heart of your slave, and see, I shall be like one of your maidservants."<verse eid="RUT 2:13"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:14"/>And Boos said to her, "It is already time to eat. Come here, and eat some of the bread, and dip your morsel in the wine vinegar." And Routh sat by the side of the reapers, and Boos heaped up barley groats for her. She ate and was satisfied and had some left over.<verse eid="RUT 2:14"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:15"/>And she got up to glean, and Boos commanded his young men, saying, "Let her glean even among the standing sheaves, and do not dishonor her.<verse eid="RUT 2:15"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:16"/>By all means carry for her, and even throw aside something for her from the bundles, and leave it, and she will glean, and do not rebuke her."<verse eid="RUT 2:16"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:17"/>And she gleaned in the field until evening and beat out what she had gleaned, and it was about an oiphi<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:17</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Hebrew 1 ephah = 22 liters</char></note> of barley.<verse eid="RUT 2:17"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:18"/>She picked it up and came into the city, and her mother-in-law saw what she had gleaned. And taking it out, Routh gave her what she had left over after she had been satisfied.<verse eid="RUT 2:18"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:19"/>Her mother-in-law said to her, "Where did you glean today? And where did you work? Blessed be the man who took notice of you." And Routh told her mother-in-law where she worked and said, "The name of the man with whom I worked today is Boos."<verse eid="RUT 2:19"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:20"/>And Noemin said to her daughter-in-law, "He is blessed by the Lord, because he has not forsaken his compassion for the living and for the dead." And Noemin said to her, "The man is near to us; he is one of our next-of-kin."<verse eid="RUT 2:20"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:21"/>And Routh said to her mother-in-law, "He even said to me, 'Stick with my servants<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:21</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'young men'</char></note> until they have finished all the harvest that belongs to me.' "<verse eid="RUT 2:21"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:22"/>Noemin said to Routh, her daughter-in-law, "It is good, daughter, that you go with his girls, and they<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:22</char><char closed="false" style="ft">I.e. 'people'</char></note> will not confront you in another field."<verse eid="RUT 2:22"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 2:23"/>And Routh stayed close to the girls of Boos, gleaning<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">2:23</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'in order to glean'</char></note> until he completed the reaping of the barley and the wheat, and she lived with her mother-in-law.<verse eid="RUT 2:23"/>



  <chapter sid="RUT 3"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:1"/>But Noemin her mother-in-law said to her, "Daughter, shall I not seek rest for you so that it may be well with you?<verse eid="RUT 3:1"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:2"/>Now, is not Boos our acquaintance, whose girls you were with? Look, he is winnowing the threshing floor of the barley<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:2</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Possibly 'barley on the threshing floor'</char></note> this very night.<verse eid="RUT 3:2"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:3"/>Now bathe, and apply oil, and put your clothing on yourself, and go up onto the threshing floor. Do not make yourself known to the man until he has finished drinking and eating.<verse eid="RUT 3:3"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:4"/>And it shall be, when he lies down, that you shall observe the place there where he is lying, and you shall go and uncover the place at his feet and lie down, and he will tell you what you shall do."<verse eid="RUT 3:4"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:5"/>Then Routh said to her, "Everything that you say I will do."<verse eid="RUT 3:5"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:6"/>And she went down to the threshing floor and did according to everything that her mother-in-law had commanded her.<verse eid="RUT 3:6"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:7"/>And Boos ate, and his heart was content, and he went to lie down on part of the heap of grain. Then she came stealthily and uncovered the place at his feet.<verse eid="RUT 3:7"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:8"/>Now it was at midnight, and the man was startled and troubled, and there, lying at his feet, was a woman!<verse eid="RUT 3:8"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:9"/>So he said, "Who are you?" Then she answered, "I am Routh, your slave; spread your wing<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:9</char><char closed="false" style="ft">f I.e. part of the cloak</char></note> over your bondwoman, for you are a next-of-kin."<verse eid="RUT 3:9"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:10"/>Boos said, "May you be blessed by the Lord God, daughter, for your last instance of compassion is better than the first, that you have not gone after young men, whether poor or rich.<verse eid="RUT 3:10"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:11"/>And now, daughter, do not be afraid. Everything that you say I will do for you, for the whole clan of my people knows that you are a strong woman<verse eid="RUT 3:11"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:12"/>and that I am, truly, a near kinsman, yet there is even a nearer kinsman than I.<verse eid="RUT 3:12"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:13"/>Spend the night, and it shall be in the morning, if he will act as next-of-kin for you, good; let him do it. But if he is not willing to act as next-of-kin for you, the Lord lives, I myself will act as next-of-kin for you. Lie down until morning."<verse eid="RUT 3:13"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:14"/>And she lay at his feet until morning but got up before a man could recognize his neighbor. And Boos said, "It must not be known that a woman came to the threshing floor."<verse eid="RUT 3:14"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:15"/>And he said to her, "Bring the apron that you have on." And she held it, and he measured out six measures of barley and put it upon her, and he<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:15</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'she'</char></note> went into the city.<verse eid="RUT 3:15"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:16"/>And Routh came in to her mother-in-law, and she said, "Who are you, daughter?" And she told her all that the man had done for her,<verse eid="RUT 3:16"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:17"/>and she said to her, "He gave me these six measures of barley, for he said to me, 'Do not go in empty-handed to your mother-in-law.' "<verse eid="RUT 3:17"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 3:18"/>Then she replied, "Sit, daughter, until you observe how not a word will fail<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Or 'fall short'</char></note>, for certainly the man will not rest until he settles the matter<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">3:18</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'settles the matter':  Possibly 'fulfills his word'</char></note> today."<verse eid="RUT 3:18"/>



  <chapter sid="RUT 4"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:1"/>And Boos went up to the gate and sat down there, and right there, passing by, was the next-of-kin of whom Boos had spoken. And Boos said to him, "Come over; sit down here, Hidden One<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:1</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'Hidden One':  I.e. apparently 'Name Withheld'</char></note>." And he went over and sat down.<verse eid="RUT 4:1"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:2"/>And Boos took ten men of the elders of the city and said, "Sit down here," and they sat down.<verse eid="RUT 4:2"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:3"/>And Boos said to the next-of-kin, "Concerning the portion of the field that belongs to our brother Abimelech, which has been given to Noemin, who returned from the countryside of Moab;<verse eid="RUT 4:3"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:4"/>I said, I will uncover your ear<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:4</char><char closed="false" style="ft">'uncover your ear':  I.e. 'bring it to your attention'</char></note>, saying: Buy it in the presence of those sitting here and in the presence of the elders of my people. If you are acting as next-of-kin, act as next-ofkin, but if you are not acting as next-of-kin, tell me, and I shall know, for there is no one except you to act as next-of-kin, and I come after you." So he said, "I am the one; I will act as next-of-kin."<verse eid="RUT 4:4"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:5"/>And Boos said, "The day you acquire the field from the hand of Noemin and from Routh the Moabite, the wife of the deceased, it is necessary for you to acquire her also in order to raise up the name of the deceased on his inheritance."<verse eid="RUT 4:5"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:6"/>And the next-of-kin said, "I will not be able to perform the kinsman's function for myself without ruining my inheritance. Take for yourself my right of inheritance, for I will not be able to act as next-of-kin."<verse eid="RUT 4:6"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:7"/>And this was the statute in former times in Israel concerning the right of inheritance and concerning exchange: to confirm every agreement, a man would take off his sandal and give it to his neighbor who was acquiring the right of inheritance. This was an attestation in Israel.<verse eid="RUT 4:7"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:8"/>And the next-of-kin said to Boos, "Acquire for yourself my right of inheritance," and he took off his sandal and gave it to him.<verse eid="RUT 4:8"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:9"/>And Boos said to the elders and all the people, "Today you are witnesses that I have acquired everything of Abimelech's and all that belongs to Chelaion and Maalon from the hand of Noemin.<verse eid="RUT 4:9"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:10"/>I have also acquired Routh the Moabite, the wife of Maalon, for myself as a wife, to raise up the name of the deceased on his inheritance, and the name of the deceased shall not be extirpated from his brothers and from the clan of his people. Today you are witnesses."<verse eid="RUT 4:10"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:11"/>And all the people who were at the gate said, "We are<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:11</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Lacking in Greek</char></note> witnesses." And the elders said, "May the Lord make your wife who is coming into your house like Rachel and like Leia, who built up, both of them, the house of Israel and produced might in Ephratha, and there shall be a name in Baithleem.<verse eid="RUT 4:11"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:12"/>And, through the offspring that the Lord will give you from this maidservant, may your house be like the house of Phares whom Thamar bore to Iouda."<verse eid="RUT 4:12"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:13"/>And Boos took Routh, and she became a wife to him. And he went in to her, and the Lord granted her conception, and she bore a son.<verse eid="RUT 4:13"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:14"/>And the women said to Noemin, "Blessed be the Lord, who did not bring your next-of-kin to an end this day! And may he call your name in Israel!<verse eid="RUT 4:14"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:15"/>He shall be to you a restorer of life and shall sustain your gray head. For your daughter-in-law, who loves you, who is better to you than seven sons, has borne him."<verse eid="RUT 4:15"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:16"/>And Noemin took the child and laid him in her bosom and became a nanny<note caller="▼" style="f"><char closed="false" style="fr">4:16</char><char closed="false" style="ft">Perhaps 'foster mother'</char></note> to him.<verse eid="RUT 4:16"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:17"/>The women of the neighborhood gave him a name, saying, "A son has been born to Noemin." They named him Obed. This was the father of Iessai, the father of Dauid.<verse eid="RUT 4:17"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:18"/>And these are the generations of Phares: Phares became the father of Hesron,<verse eid="RUT 4:18"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:19"/>then Hesron became the father of Arran, and Arran became the father of Aminadab;<verse eid="RUT 4:19"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:20"/>Aminadab became the father of Naasson; Naasson became the father of Salman;<verse eid="RUT 4:20"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:21"/>Salman became the father of Boos; Boos became the father of Obed;<verse eid="RUT 4:21"/>
    <verse sid="RUT 4:22"/>Obed became the father of Iessai, and Iessai became the father of Dauid.<verse eid="RUT 4:22"/>
</usx>
