<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="1JN" style="id">- God’s Word Bible</book>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="rem">© 1995, 2003, 2013, 2014, 2019, 2020 by God’s Word to the Nations Mission Society. All rights reserved.</para>
  <para style="rem">Converted from InDesign files to USFM-3 by Elbert Boot (Digital Bible Library Customer Service Team, Miami [USA])</para>
  <para style="rem">Language: English</para>
  <para style="rem">This project has 9 poetry levels, and Paratext only supports up to 4 levels. To upload the text to DBL, we have created a dblChanges file and added q5 to q9 to a custom.sty to obtain the desired design in Paratext.</para>
  <para style="h">1 JOHN</para>
  <para style="toc1">1 John</para>
  <para style="toc2">1 John</para>
  <para style="toc3">1 John</para>
  <para style="mt1">1 John</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="1JN 1" />
  <para style="s1">John’s Reason for Writing</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1JN 1:1" />The Word of life existed from the beginning. We have heard it. We have seen it. We observed and touched it. <verse eid="1JN 1:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1JN 1:2" />This life was revealed to us. We have seen it, and we testify about it. We are reporting to you about this eternal life that was in the presence of the Father and was revealed to us. <verse eid="1JN 1:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1JN 1:3" />This is the life we have seen and heard. We are reporting about it to you also so that you, too, can have a relationship with us. Our relationship is with the Father and with his Son Jesus Christ. <verse eid="1JN 1:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1JN 1:4" />We are writing this so that we can be completely filled with joy.<verse eid="1JN 1:4" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Through Jesus We Have a Relationship with God</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1JN 1:5" />This is the message we heard from Christ and are reporting to you: God is light, and there isn’t any darkness in him. <verse eid="1JN 1:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1JN 1:6" />If we say, “We have a relationship with God” and yet live in the dark, we’re lying. We aren’t being truthful.<verse eid="1JN 1:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1JN 1:7" />But if we live in the light in the same way that God is in the light, we have a relationship with each other. And the blood of his Son Jesus cleanses us from every sin. <verse eid="1JN 1:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1JN 1:8" />If we say, “We aren’t sinful” we are deceiving ourselves, and the truth is not in us. <verse eid="1JN 1:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1JN 1:9" />God is faithful and reliable. If we confess our sins, he forgives them and cleanses us from everything we’ve done wrong. <verse eid="1JN 1:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1JN 1:10" />If we say, “We have never sinned,” we turn God into a liar and his Word is not in us.<verse eid="1JN 1:10" /></para>
  <chapter eid="1JN 1" />
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="1JN 2" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1JN 2:1" />My dear children, I’m writing this to you so that you will not sin. Yet, if anyone does sin, we have Jesus Christ, who has God’s full approval. He speaks on our behalf when we come into the presence of the Father. <verse eid="1JN 2:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1JN 2:2" />He is the payment for our sins, and not only for our sins, but also for the sins of the whole world.<verse eid="1JN 2:2" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Those Who Know Christ Obey His Commandments</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1JN 2:3" />We are sure that we know Christ if we obey his commandments. <verse eid="1JN 2:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1JN 2:4" />The person who says, “I know him,” but doesn’t obey his commandments is a liar. The truth isn’t in that person. <verse eid="1JN 2:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1JN 2:5" />But whoever obeys what Christ says is the kind of person in whom God’s love is perfected. That’s how we know we are in Christ. <verse eid="1JN 2:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1JN 2:6" />Those who say that they live in him must live the same way he lived.<verse eid="1JN 2:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1JN 2:7" />Dear friends, it’s not as though I’m writing to give you a new commandment. Rather, I’m giving you an old commandment that you’ve had from the beginning. It’s the old commandment you’ve already heard. <verse eid="1JN 2:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1JN 2:8" />On the other hand, I’m writing to give you a new commandment. It’s a truth that exists in Christ and in you: The darkness is fading, and the true light is already shining.<verse eid="1JN 2:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1JN 2:9" />Those who say that they are in the light but hate other believers are still in the dark. <verse eid="1JN 2:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1JN 2:10" />Those who love other believers live in the light. Nothing will destroy the faith of those who live in the light. <verse eid="1JN 2:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1JN 2:11" />Those who hate other believers are in the dark and live in the dark. They don’t know where they’re going, because they can’t see in the dark.<verse eid="1JN 2:11" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Don’t Love the World</para>
  <para style="li">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1JN 2:12" />I’m writing to you, dear children, because your sins are forgiven through Christ.<verse eid="1JN 2:12" /></para>
  <para style="li">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1JN 2:13" />I’m writing to you, fathers, because you know Christ who has existed from the beginning.</para>
  <para style="li" vid="1JN 2:13">I’m writing to you, young people, because you have won the victory over the evil one.<verse eid="1JN 2:13" /></para>
  <para style="li">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1JN 2:14" />I’ve written to you, children, because you know the Father.</para>
  <para style="li" vid="1JN 2:14">I’ve written to you, fathers, because you know Christ, who has existed from the beginning.</para>
  <para style="li" vid="1JN 2:14">I’ve written to you, young people, because you are strong and God’s word lives in you. You have won the victory over the evil one.<verse eid="1JN 2:14" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1JN 2:15" />Don’t love the world and what it offers. Those who love the world don’t have the Father’s love in them. <verse eid="1JN 2:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1JN 2:16" />Not everything that the world offers—physical gratification, greed, and extravagant lifestyles—comes from the Father. It comes from the world, and <verse eid="1JN 2:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1JN 2:17" />the world and its evil desires are passing away. But the person who does what God wants lives forever.<verse eid="1JN 2:17" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Live in Christ</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1JN 2:18" />Children, it’s the end of time. You’ve heard that an antichrist is coming. Certainly, many antichrists are already here. That’s how we know it’s the end of time. <verse eid="1JN 2:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1JN 2:19" />They left us. However, they were never really part of us. If they had been, they would have stayed with us. But by leaving they made it clear that none of them were part of us.<verse eid="1JN 2:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1JN 2:20" />The Holy One has anointed you, so all of you have knowledge. <verse eid="1JN 2:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1JN 2:21" />I’m writing to you because you know the truth, not because you don’t know the truth. You know that no lie ever comes from the truth.<verse eid="1JN 2:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1JN 2:22" />Who is a liar? Who else but the person who rejects Jesus as the Messiah? The person who rejects the Father and the Son is an antichrist. <verse eid="1JN 2:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1JN 2:23" />Everyone who rejects the Son doesn’t have the Father either. The person who acknowledges the Son also has the Father. <verse eid="1JN 2:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1JN 2:24" />Make sure that the message you heard from the beginning lives in you. If that message lives in you, you will also live in the Son and in the Father. <verse eid="1JN 2:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1JN 2:25" />Christ has given us the promise of eternal life.<verse eid="1JN 2:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1JN 2:26" />I’m writing to you about those who are trying to deceive you. <verse eid="1JN 2:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1JN 2:27" />The anointing you received from Christ lives in you. You don’t need anyone to teach you something else. Instead, Christ’s anointing teaches you about everything. His anointing is true and contains no lie. So live in Christ as he taught you to do.<verse eid="1JN 2:27" /></para>
  <para style="s1">We Are God’s Children</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1JN 2:28" />Now, dear children, live in Christ. Then, when he appears we will have confidence, and when he comes we won’t turn from him in shame. <verse eid="1JN 2:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1JN 2:29" />If you know that Christ has God’s approval, you also know that everyone who does what God approves of has been born from God.<verse eid="1JN 2:29" /></para>
  <chapter eid="1JN 2" />
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="1JN 3" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1JN 3:1" />Consider this: The Father has given us his love. He loves us so much that we are actually called God’s dear children. And that’s what we are. For this reason the world doesn’t recognize us, and it didn’t recognize him either. <verse eid="1JN 3:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1JN 3:2" />Dear friends, now we are God’s children. What we will be isn’t completely clear yet. We do know that when Christ appears we will be like him because we will see him as he is. <verse eid="1JN 3:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1JN 3:3" />So all people who have this confidence in Christ keep themselves pure, as Christ is pure.<verse eid="1JN 3:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1JN 3:4" />Those who live sinful lives are disobeying God. Sin is disobedience. <verse eid="1JN 3:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1JN 3:5" />You know that Christ appeared in order to take away our sins. He isn’t sinful. <verse eid="1JN 3:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1JN 3:6" />Those who live in Christ don’t go on sinning. Those who go on sinning haven’t seen or known Christ.<verse eid="1JN 3:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1JN 3:7" />Dear children, don’t let anyone deceive you. Whoever does what God approves of has God’s approval as Christ has God’s approval. <verse eid="1JN 3:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1JN 3:8" />The person who lives a sinful life belongs to the devil, because the devil has been committing sin since the beginning. The reason that the Son of God appeared was to destroy what the devil does. <verse eid="1JN 3:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1JN 3:9" />Those who have been born from God don’t live sinful lives. What God has said lives in them, and they can’t live sinful lives. They have been born from God. <verse eid="1JN 3:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1JN 3:10" />This is the way God’s children are distinguished from the devil’s children. Everyone who doesn’t do what is right or love other believers isn’t God’s child.<verse eid="1JN 3:10" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Love One Another</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1JN 3:11" />The message that you have heard from the beginning is to love each other. <verse eid="1JN 3:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1JN 3:12" />Don’t be like Cain. He was a child of the evil one and murdered his brother. And why did Cain murder his brother? Because the things Cain did were evil and the things his brother did had God’s approval. <verse eid="1JN 3:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1JN 3:13" />Brothers and sisters, don’t be surprised if the world hates you.<verse eid="1JN 3:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1JN 3:14" />We know that we have passed from death to life, because we love other believers. The person who doesn’t grow in love remains in death. <verse eid="1JN 3:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1JN 3:15" />Everyone who hates another believer is a murderer, and you know that a murderer doesn’t have eternal life.<verse eid="1JN 3:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1JN 3:16" />We understand what love is when we realize that Christ gave his life for us. That means we must give our lives for other believers. <verse eid="1JN 3:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1JN 3:17" />Now, suppose a person has enough to live on and notices another believer in need. How can God’s love be in that person if he doesn’t bother to help the other believer? <verse eid="1JN 3:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1JN 3:18" />Dear children, we must show love through actions that are sincere, not through empty words.<verse eid="1JN 3:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1JN 3:19" />This is how we will know that we belong to the truth and how we will be reassured in his presence. <verse eid="1JN 3:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1JN 3:20" />Whenever our conscience condemns us, we will be reassured that God is greater than our conscience and knows everything. <verse eid="1JN 3:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1JN 3:21" />Dear friends, if our conscience doesn’t condemn us, we can boldly look to God <verse eid="1JN 3:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1JN 3:22" />and receive from him anything we ask. We receive it because we obey his commandments and do what pleases him. <verse eid="1JN 3:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1JN 3:23" />This is his commandment: to believe in his Son, the one named Jesus Christ, and to love each other as he commanded us. <verse eid="1JN 3:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1JN 3:24" />Those who obey Christ’s commandments live in God, and God lives in them. We know that he lives in us because he has given us the Spirit.<verse eid="1JN 3:24" /></para>
  <chapter eid="1JN 3" />
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="1JN 4" />
  <para style="s1">Test People Who Say They Have God’s Spirit</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1JN 4:1" />Dear friends, don’t believe all people who say that they have the Spirit. Instead, test them. See whether the spirit they have is from God, because there are many false prophets in the world. <verse eid="1JN 4:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1JN 4:2" />This is how you can recognize God’s Spirit: Every person who declares that Jesus Christ has come as a human has the Spirit that is from God. <verse eid="1JN 4:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1JN 4:3" />But every person who doesn’t declare that Jesus Christ has come as a human has a spirit that isn’t from God. This is the spirit of the antichrist that you have heard is coming. That spirit is already in the world.<verse eid="1JN 4:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1JN 4:4" />Dear children, you belong to God. So you have won the victory over these people, because the one who is in you is greater than the one who is in the world. <verse eid="1JN 4:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1JN 4:5" />These people belong to the world. That’s why they speak the thoughts of the world, and the world listens to them. <verse eid="1JN 4:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1JN 4:6" />We belong to God. The person who knows God listens to us. Whoever doesn’t belong to God doesn’t listen to us. That’s how we can tell the Spirit of truth from the spirit of lies.<verse eid="1JN 4:6" /></para>
  <para style="s1">God’s Love Lives in His People</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1JN 4:7" />Dear friends, we must love each other because love comes from God. Everyone who loves has been born from God and knows God. <verse eid="1JN 4:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1JN 4:8" />The person who doesn’t love doesn’t know God, because God is love. <verse eid="1JN 4:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1JN 4:9" />God has shown us his love by sending his only Son into the world so that we could have life through him. <verse eid="1JN 4:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1JN 4:10" />This is love: not that we have loved God, but that he loved us and sent his Son to be the payment for our sins. <verse eid="1JN 4:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1JN 4:11" />Dear friends, if this is the way God loved us, we must also love each other. <verse eid="1JN 4:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1JN 4:12" />No one has ever seen God. If we love each other, God lives in us, and his love is perfected in us. <verse eid="1JN 4:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1JN 4:13" />We know that we live in him and he lives in us because he has given us his Spirit.<verse eid="1JN 4:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1JN 4:14" />We have seen and testify to the fact that the Father sent his Son as the Savior of the world. <verse eid="1JN 4:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1JN 4:15" />God lives in those who declare that Jesus is the Son of God, and they live in God. <verse eid="1JN 4:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1JN 4:16" />We have known and believed that God loves us. God is love. Those who live in God’s love live in God, and God lives in them.<verse eid="1JN 4:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1JN 4:17" />God’s love has reached its goal in us. So we look ahead with confidence to the day of judgment. While we are in this world, we are exactly like him <char style="add">⌞with regard to love⌟</char>. <verse eid="1JN 4:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1JN 4:18" />No fear exists where his love is. Rather, perfect love gets rid of fear, because fear involves punishment. The person who lives in fear doesn’t have perfect love.<verse eid="1JN 4:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1JN 4:19" />We love because God loved us first. <verse eid="1JN 4:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1JN 4:20" />Whoever says, “I love God,” but hates another believer is a liar. People who don’t love other believers, whom they have seen, can’t love God, whom they have not seen. <verse eid="1JN 4:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1JN 4:21" />Christ has given us this commandment: The person who loves God must also love other believers.<verse eid="1JN 4:21" /></para>
  <chapter eid="1JN 4" />
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="1JN 5" />
  <para style="s1">Those Who Believe in Jesus Are God’s Children</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1JN 5:1" />Everyone who believes that Jesus is the Messiah has been born from God. Everyone who loves the Father also loves his children. <verse eid="1JN 5:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1JN 5:2" />We know that we love God’s children when we love God by obeying his commandments. <verse eid="1JN 5:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1JN 5:3" />To love God means that we obey his commandments. Obeying his commandments isn’t difficult <verse eid="1JN 5:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1JN 5:4" />because everyone who has been born from God has won the victory over the world. Our faith is what wins the victory over the world. <verse eid="1JN 5:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1JN 5:5" />Who wins the victory over the world? Isn’t it the person who believes that Jesus is the Son of God?<verse eid="1JN 5:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1JN 5:6" />This Son of God is Jesus Christ, who came by water and blood. He didn’t come with water only, but with water and with blood. The Spirit is the one who verifies this, because the Spirit is the truth. <verse eid="1JN 5:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1JN 5:7" />There are three witnesses: <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Four very late manuscripts add verses 7b–8a: </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“in heaven: the Father, the Word, and the Holy Spirit. These three witnesses agree. And there are three witnesses on earth:”</char></note> <verse eid="1JN 5:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1JN 5:8" />the Spirit, the water, and the blood. These three witnesses agree.<verse eid="1JN 5:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1JN 5:9" />We accept human testimony. God’s testimony is greater because it is the testimony that he has given about his Son. <verse eid="1JN 5:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1JN 5:10" />Those who believe in the Son of God have the testimony of God in them. Those who don’t believe God have made God a liar. They haven’t believed the testimony that God has given about his Son.<verse eid="1JN 5:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1JN 5:11" />This is the testimony: God has given us eternal life, and this life is found in his Son. <verse eid="1JN 5:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1JN 5:12" />The person who has the Son has this life. The person who doesn’t have the Son of God doesn’t have this life.<verse eid="1JN 5:12" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Conclusion</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1JN 5:13" />I’ve written this to those who believe in the Son of God so that they will know that they have eternal life.<verse eid="1JN 5:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1JN 5:14" />We are confident that God listens to us if we ask for anything that has his approval. <verse eid="1JN 5:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1JN 5:15" />We know that he listens to our requests. So we know that we already have what we ask him for.<verse eid="1JN 5:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1JN 5:16" />If you see another believer committing a sin that doesn’t lead to death, you should pray that God would give that person life. This is true for those who commit sins that don’t lead to death. There is a sin that leads to death. I’m not telling you to pray about that. <verse eid="1JN 5:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1JN 5:17" />Every kind of wrongdoing is sin, yet there are sins that don’t lead to death.<verse eid="1JN 5:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1JN 5:18" />We know that those who have been born from God don’t go on sinning. Rather, the Son of God protects them, and the evil one can’t harm them.<verse eid="1JN 5:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1JN 5:19" />We know that we are from God, and that the whole world is under the control of the evil one.<verse eid="1JN 5:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1JN 5:20" />We know that the Son of God has come and has given us understanding so that we know the real God. We are in the one who is real, his Son Jesus Christ. This Jesus Christ is the real God and eternal life.<verse eid="1JN 5:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1JN 5:21" />Dear children, guard yourselves from false gods.<verse eid="1JN 5:21" /></para>
  <chapter eid="1JN 5" />
</usx>