<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="1TH" style="id">- God’s Word Bible</book>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="rem">© 1995, 2003, 2013, 2014, 2019, 2020 by God’s Word to the Nations Mission Society. All rights reserved.</para>
  <para style="rem">Converted from InDesign files to USFM-3 by Elbert Boot (Digital Bible Library Customer Service Team, Miami [USA])</para>
  <para style="rem">Language: English</para>
  <para style="rem">This project has 9 poetry levels, and Paratext only supports up to 4 levels. To upload the text to DBL, we have created a dblChanges file and added q5 to q9 to a custom.sty to obtain the desired design in Paratext.</para>
  <para style="h">1 THESSALONIANS</para>
  <para style="toc1">1 Thessalonians</para>
  <para style="toc2">1 Thessalonians</para>
  <para style="toc3">1 Thessalonians</para>
  <para style="mt1">1 Thessalonians</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="1TH 1" />
  <para style="s1">Greeting</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1TH 1:1" />From Paul, Silas, and Timothy. To the church at Thessalonica united with God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1TH 1:1">Good will <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“Grace.”</char></note> and peace are yours!<verse eid="1TH 1:1" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul’s Prayer for the Thessalonians</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1TH 1:2" />We always thank God for all of you as we remember you in our prayers. <verse eid="1TH 1:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1TH 1:3" />In the presence of our God and Father, we never forget that your faith is active, your love is working hard, and your confidence in our Lord Jesus Christ is enduring. <verse eid="1TH 1:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1TH 1:4" />Brothers and sisters, we never forget this because we know that God loves you and has chosen you. <verse eid="1TH 1:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1TH 1:5" />We know this because the Good News we brought came to you not only with words but also with power, with the Holy Spirit, and with complete certainty. In the same way you know what kind of people we were while we were with you and the good things we did for you.<verse eid="1TH 1:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1TH 1:6" />You imitated us and the Lord. In spite of a lot of suffering, you welcomed God’s word with the kind of joy that the Holy Spirit gives. <verse eid="1TH 1:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1TH 1:7" />This way, you became a model for all the believers in the province of Macedonia and Greece. <verse eid="1TH 1:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1TH 1:8" />From you the Lord’s word has spread out not only through the province of Macedonia and Greece but also to people everywhere who have heard about your faith in God. We don’t need to say a thing about it. <verse eid="1TH 1:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1TH 1:9" />They talk about how you welcomed us when we arrived. They even report how you turned away from false gods to serve the real, living God <verse eid="1TH 1:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1TH 1:10" />and to wait for his Son to come from heaven. His Son is Jesus, whom he brought back to life. Jesus is the one who rescues us from <char style="add">⌞God’s⌟</char> coming anger.<verse eid="1TH 1:10" /></para>
  <chapter eid="1TH 1" />
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="1TH 2" />
  <para style="s1">Paul Remembers When He Was with the Thessalonians</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1TH 2:1" />You know, brothers and sisters, that our time with you was not wasted. <verse eid="1TH 2:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1TH 2:2" />As you know, we suffered rough and insulting treatment in Philippi. But our God gave us the courage to tell you his Good News in spite of strong opposition.<verse eid="1TH 2:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1TH 2:3" />When we encouraged you, we didn’t use unethical schemes, corrupt practices, or deception. <verse eid="1TH 2:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1TH 2:4" />Rather, we are always spreading the Good News. God trusts us to do this because we passed his test. We don’t try to please people but God, who tests our motives. <verse eid="1TH 2:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1TH 2:5" />As you know, we never used flattery or schemes to make money. God is our witness! <verse eid="1TH 2:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1TH 2:6" />We didn’t seek praise from people, from you or from anyone else, <verse eid="1TH 2:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1TH 2:7" />although as apostles of Christ we had the right to do this.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1TH 2:7">Instead, we were gentle when we were with you, like a mother taking care of her children. <verse eid="1TH 2:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1TH 2:8" />We felt so strongly about you that we were determined to share with you not only the Good News of God but also our lives. That’s how dear you were to us! <verse eid="1TH 2:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1TH 2:9" />You remember, brothers and sisters, our work and what we did to earn a living. We worked night and day so that we could bring you the Good News of God without being a burden to any of you. <verse eid="1TH 2:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1TH 2:10" />You and God are witnesses of how pure, honest, and blameless we were in our dealings with you believers. <verse eid="1TH 2:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1TH 2:11" />You know very well that we treated each of you the way a father treats his children. We comforted you and encouraged you. Yet, we insisted that <verse eid="1TH 2:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1TH 2:12" />you should live in a way that proves you belong to the God who calls you into his kingdom and glory.<verse eid="1TH 2:12" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Remembers How the Thessalonians Received God’s Word</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1TH 2:13" />Here is another reason why we never stop thanking God: When you received God’s word from us, you realized it wasn’t human words. Instead, you accepted it for what it really is—God’s word. This word is at work in you believers.<verse eid="1TH 2:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1TH 2:14" />You, brothers and sisters, were like the churches of God in Judea that are united with Christ Jesus. You suffered the same persecutions from the people of your own country as those churches did from the Jews <verse eid="1TH 2:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1TH 2:15" />who killed the Lord Jesus and the prophets and who have persecuted us severely. They are displeasing to God. They are enemies of the whole human race <verse eid="1TH 2:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1TH 2:16" />because they try to keep us from telling people who are not Jewish how they can be saved. The result is that those Jews always commit as many sins as possible. So at last they are receiving <char style="add">⌞God’s⌟</char> anger.<verse eid="1TH 2:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1TH 2:17" />Brothers and sisters, we have been separated from you for a little while. Although we may not be able to see you, you’re always in our thoughts. We have made every possible effort to fulfill our desire to see you. <verse eid="1TH 2:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1TH 2:18" />We wanted to visit you. I, Paul, wanted to visit you twice already, but Satan made that impossible.<verse eid="1TH 2:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1TH 2:19" />Who is our hope, joy, or prize that we can brag about in the presence of our Lord Jesus when he comes? Isn’t it you? <verse eid="1TH 2:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1TH 2:20" />You are our glory and joy!<verse eid="1TH 2:20" /></para>
  <chapter eid="1TH 2" />
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="1TH 3" />
  <para style="s1">Timothy’s Report to Paul</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1TH 3:1" />We thought it best to remain in Athens by ourselves. But, because we couldn’t wait any longer <char style="add">⌞for news about you⌟</char>, <verse eid="1TH 3:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1TH 3:2" />we sent our brother Timothy to you. He serves God by spreading the Good News about Christ. His mission was to strengthen and encourage you in your faith <verse eid="1TH 3:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1TH 3:3" />so that these troubles don’t disturb any of you. You know that we’re destined to suffer persecution. <verse eid="1TH 3:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1TH 3:4" />In fact, when we were with you, we told you ahead of time that we were going to suffer persecution. And as you know, that’s what happened. <verse eid="1TH 3:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1TH 3:5" />But when I couldn’t wait any longer, I sent <char style="add">⌞Timothy⌟</char> to find out about your faith. I wanted to see whether the tempter had in some way tempted you, making our work meaningless.<verse eid="1TH 3:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1TH 3:6" />But Timothy has just now come back to us from you and has told us the good news about your faith and love. He also told us that you always have fond memories of us and want to see us, as we want to see you. <verse eid="1TH 3:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1TH 3:7" />So brothers and sisters, your faith has encouraged us in all our distress and trouble. <verse eid="1TH 3:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1TH 3:8" />Now we can go on living as long as you keep your relationship with the Lord firm.<verse eid="1TH 3:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1TH 3:9" />We can never thank God enough for all the joy you give us as we rejoice in God’s presence. <verse eid="1TH 3:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1TH 3:10" />We pray very hard night and day that we may see you again so that we can supply whatever you still need for your faith. <verse eid="1TH 3:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1TH 3:11" />We pray that God our Father and the Lord Jesus will guide us to you. <verse eid="1TH 3:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1TH 3:12" />We also pray that the Lord will greatly increase your love for each other and for everyone else, just as we love you. <verse eid="1TH 3:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1TH 3:13" />Then he will strengthen you to be holy. Then you will be blameless in the presence of our God and Father when our Lord Jesus comes with all God’s holy people.<verse eid="1TH 3:13" /></para>
  <chapter eid="1TH 3" />
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="1TH 4" />
  <para style="s1">Instructions on the Way Christians Should Live</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1TH 4:1" />Now then, brothers and sisters, because of the Lord Jesus we ask and encourage you to excel in living a God-pleasing life even more than you already do. Do this the way we taught you. <verse eid="1TH 4:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1TH 4:2" />You know what orders we gave you through the Lord Jesus. <verse eid="1TH 4:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1TH 4:3" />It is God’s will that you keep away from sexual sin as a mark of your devotion to him. <verse eid="1TH 4:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1TH 4:4" />Each of you should know that finding a husband or wife for yourself is to be done in a holy and honorable way, <verse eid="1TH 4:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1TH 4:5" />not in the passionate, lustful way of people who don’t know God. <verse eid="1TH 4:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1TH 4:6" />No one should take advantage of or exploit other believers that way. The Lord is the one who punishes people for all these things. We’ve already told you and warned you about this. <verse eid="1TH 4:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1TH 4:7" />God didn’t call us to be sexually immoral but to be holy. <verse eid="1TH 4:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1TH 4:8" />Therefore, whoever rejects this <char style="add">⌞order⌟</char> is not rejecting human authority but God, who gives you his Holy Spirit.<verse eid="1TH 4:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1TH 4:9" />You don’t need anyone to write to you about the way Christians should love each other. God has taught you to love each other. <verse eid="1TH 4:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1TH 4:10" />In fact, you are showing love to all the Christians throughout the province of Macedonia. We encourage you as believers to excel in love even more. <verse eid="1TH 4:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1TH 4:11" />Also, make it your goal to live quietly, do your work, and earn your own living, as we ordered you. <verse eid="1TH 4:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1TH 4:12" />Then your way of life will win respect from those outside <char style="add">⌞the church⌟</char>, and you won’t have to depend on anyone else for what you need.<verse eid="1TH 4:12" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Comfort about Christians Who Have Died</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1TH 4:13" />Brothers and sisters, we don’t want you to be ignorant about those who have died. We don’t want you to grieve like other people who have no hope. <verse eid="1TH 4:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1TH 4:14" />We believe that Jesus died and came back to life. We also believe that, through Jesus, God will bring back those who have died. They will come back with Jesus. <verse eid="1TH 4:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1TH 4:15" />We are telling you what the Lord taught. We who are still alive when the Lord comes will not go <char style="add">⌞into his kingdom⌟</char> ahead of those who have already died. <verse eid="1TH 4:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1TH 4:16" />The Lord will come from heaven with a command, with the voice of the archangel, and with the trumpet <char style="add">⌞call⌟</char> of God. First, the dead who believed in Christ will come back to life. <verse eid="1TH 4:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1TH 4:17" />Then, together with them, we who are still alive will be taken in the clouds to meet the Lord in the air. In this way we will always be with the Lord. <verse eid="1TH 4:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1TH 4:18" />So then, comfort each other with these words!<verse eid="1TH 4:18" /></para>
  <chapter eid="1TH 4" />
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="1TH 5" />
  <para style="s1">Be Ready for the Day of the Lord</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1TH 5:1" />Brothers and sisters, you don’t need anyone to write to you about times and dates. <verse eid="1TH 5:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1TH 5:2" />You know very well that the day of the Lord will come like a thief in the night. <verse eid="1TH 5:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1TH 5:3" />When people say, “Everything is safe and sound!” destruction will suddenly strike them. It will be as sudden as labor pains come to a pregnant woman. They won’t be able to escape. <verse eid="1TH 5:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1TH 5:4" />But, brothers and sisters, you don’t live in the dark. That day won’t take you by surprise as a thief would. <verse eid="1TH 5:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1TH 5:5" />You belong to the day and the light not to the night and the dark. <verse eid="1TH 5:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1TH 5:6" />Therefore, we must not fall asleep like other people, but we must stay awake and be sober. <verse eid="1TH 5:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1TH 5:7" />People who sleep, sleep at night; people who get drunk, get drunk at night. <verse eid="1TH 5:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1TH 5:8" />Since we belong to the day, we must be sober. We must put on faith and love as a breastplate and the hope of salvation as a helmet. <verse eid="1TH 5:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1TH 5:9" />It was not God’s intention that we experience his anger but that we obtain salvation through our Lord Jesus Christ. <verse eid="1TH 5:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1TH 5:10" />He died for us so that, whether we are awake in this life or asleep in death, we will live together with him. <verse eid="1TH 5:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1TH 5:11" />Therefore, encourage each other and strengthen one another as you are doing.<verse eid="1TH 5:11" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul Encourages the Thessalonians</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1TH 5:12" />Brothers and sisters, we ask you to show your appreciation for those leaders who work among you and instruct you. <verse eid="1TH 5:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1TH 5:13" />We ask you to love them and think very highly of them because of the work they are doing. Live in peace with each other.<verse eid="1TH 5:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1TH 5:14" />We encourage you, brothers and sisters, to instruct those who are not living right, cheer up those who are discouraged, help the weak, and be patient with everyone. <verse eid="1TH 5:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1TH 5:15" />Make sure that no one ever pays back one wrong with another wrong. Instead, always try to do what is good for each other and everyone else.<verse eid="1TH 5:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1TH 5:16" />Always be joyful. <verse eid="1TH 5:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1TH 5:17" />Never stop praying. <verse eid="1TH 5:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1TH 5:18" />Whatever happens, give thanks, because it is God’s will in Christ Jesus that you do this.<verse eid="1TH 5:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1TH 5:19" />Don’t put out the Spirit’s fire. <verse eid="1TH 5:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1TH 5:20" />Don’t despise what God has revealed. <verse eid="1TH 5:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1TH 5:21" />Instead, test everything. Hold on to what is good. <verse eid="1TH 5:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1TH 5:22" />Keep away from every kind of evil.<verse eid="1TH 5:22" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Farewell</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1TH 5:23" />May the God who gives peace make you holy in every way. May he keep your whole being—spirit, soul, and body—blameless when our Lord Jesus Christ comes. <verse eid="1TH 5:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1TH 5:24" />The one who calls you is faithful, and he will do this.<verse eid="1TH 5:24" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1TH 5:25" />Brothers and sisters, pray for us.<verse eid="1TH 5:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1TH 5:26" />Greet all the brothers and sisters with a holy kiss.<verse eid="1TH 5:26" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1TH 5:27" />In the Lord’s name, I order you to read this letter to all the brothers and sisters.<verse eid="1TH 5:27" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1TH 5:28" />The good will <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:28 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“grace.”</char></note> of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you.<verse eid="1TH 5:28" /></para>
  <chapter eid="1TH 5" />
</usx>