<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="3JN" style="id">- God’s Word Bible</book>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="rem">© 1995, 2003, 2013, 2014, 2019, 2020 by God’s Word to the Nations Mission Society. All rights reserved.</para>
  <para style="rem">Converted from InDesign files to USFM-3 by Elbert Boot (Digital Bible Library Customer Service Team, Miami [USA])</para>
  <para style="rem">Language: English</para>
  <para style="rem">This project has 9 poetry levels, and Paratext only supports up to 4 levels. To upload the text to DBL, we have created a dblChanges file and added q5 to q9 to a custom.sty to obtain the desired design in Paratext.</para>
  <para style="h">3 JOHN</para>
  <para style="toc1">3 John</para>
  <para style="toc2">3 John</para>
  <para style="toc3">3 John</para>
  <para style="mt1">3 John</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="3JN 1" />
  <para style="s1">Greeting</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="3JN 1:1" />From the church leader.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“pastor,” </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“elder.”</char></note></para>
  <para style="p" vid="3JN 1:1">To my dear friend Gaius, whom I love because we share the truth.<verse eid="3JN 1:1" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Encouragement for Gaius</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="3JN 1:2" />Dear friend, I know that you are spiritually well. I pray that you’re doing well in every other way and that you’re healthy. <verse eid="3JN 1:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="3JN 1:3" />I was very happy when some believers came and told us that you are living according to the truth. <verse eid="3JN 1:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="3JN 1:4" />Nothing makes me happier than to hear that my children are living according to the truth.<verse eid="3JN 1:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="3JN 1:5" />Dear friend, you are showing your faith in whatever you do for other believers, especially when they’re your guests. <verse eid="3JN 1:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="3JN 1:6" />These believers have told the congregation about your love. You will do well to support them on their trip in a way that proves you belong to God. <verse eid="3JN 1:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="3JN 1:7" />After all, they went on their trip to serve the one named Christ, and they didn’t accept any help from the people to whom they went. <verse eid="3JN 1:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="3JN 1:8" />We must support believers who go on trips like this so that we can work together with them in spreading the truth.<verse eid="3JN 1:8" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Criticism of Diotrephes</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="3JN 1:9" />I wrote a letter to the congregation. But Diotrephes, who loves to be in charge, won’t accept us. <verse eid="3JN 1:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="3JN 1:10" />For this reason, when I come I will bring up what he’s doing. He’s not satisfied with saying malicious things about us. He also refuses to accept the believers <char style="add">⌞we send⌟</char> as guests. He even tries to stop others who want to accept them and attempts to throw those people out of the congregation.<verse eid="3JN 1:10" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Praise for Demetrius</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="3JN 1:11" />Dear friend, never imitate evil, but imitate good. The person who does good is from God. The person who does evil has never seen God.<verse eid="3JN 1:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="3JN 1:12" />Everyone, including the truth itself, says good things about Demetrius. We also say good things about him, and you know that what we say is true.<verse eid="3JN 1:12" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Farewell</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="3JN 1:13" />I have a lot to write to you. However, I would rather not write. <verse eid="3JN 1:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="3JN 1:14" />I hope to visit you very soon. Then we can talk things over personally.<verse eid="3JN 1:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="3JN 1:15" />Peace be with you! Your friends here send you their greetings. Greet each of our friends by name.<verse eid="3JN 1:15" /></para>
  <chapter eid="3JN 1" />
</usx>