<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="JAS" style="id">- God’s Word Bible</book>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="rem">© 1995, 2003, 2013, 2014, 2019, 2020 by God’s Word to the Nations Mission Society. All rights reserved.</para>
  <para style="rem">Converted from InDesign files to USFM-3 by Elbert Boot (Digital Bible Library Customer Service Team, Miami [USA])</para>
  <para style="rem">Language: English</para>
  <para style="rem">This project has 9 poetry levels, and Paratext only supports up to 4 levels. To upload the text to DBL, we have created a dblChanges file and added q5 to q9 to a custom.sty to obtain the desired design in Paratext.</para>
  <para style="h">JAMES</para>
  <para style="toc1">James</para>
  <para style="toc2">James</para>
  <para style="toc3">James</para>
  <para style="mt1">James</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="JAS 1" />
  <para style="s1">Greeting</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JAS 1:1" />From James, a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JAS 1:1">To God’s faithful people <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“to the twelve tribes.”</char></note> who have been scattered.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JAS 1:1">Greetings.<verse eid="JAS 1:1" /></para>
  <para style="s1">When You Are Tested, Turn to God</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JAS 1:2" />My brothers and sisters, be very happy when you are tested in different ways. <verse eid="JAS 1:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JAS 1:3" />You know that such testing of your faith produces endurance. <verse eid="JAS 1:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JAS 1:4" />Endure until your testing is over. Then you will be mature and complete, and you won’t need anything.<verse eid="JAS 1:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JAS 1:5" />If any of you needs wisdom to know what you should do, you should ask God, and he will give it to you. God is generous to everyone and doesn’t find fault with them. <verse eid="JAS 1:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JAS 1:6" />When you ask for something, don’t have any doubts. A person who has doubts is like a wave that is blown by the wind and tossed by the sea. <verse eid="JAS 1:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JAS 1:7" />A person who has doubts shouldn’t expect to receive anything from the Lord. <verse eid="JAS 1:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JAS 1:8" />A person who has doubts is thinking about two different things at the same time and can’t make up his mind about anything.<verse eid="JAS 1:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JAS 1:9" />Humble believers should be proud because being humble makes them important. <verse eid="JAS 1:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JAS 1:10" />Rich believers should be proud because being rich should make them humble. Rich people will wither like flowers. <verse eid="JAS 1:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JAS 1:11" />The sun rises with its scorching heat and dries up plants. The flowers drop off, and the beauty is gone. The same thing will happen to rich people. While they are busy, they will die.<verse eid="JAS 1:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JAS 1:12" />Blessed are those who endure when they are tested. When they pass the test, they will receive the crown of life that God has promised to those who love him. <verse eid="JAS 1:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JAS 1:13" />When someone is tempted, he shouldn’t say that God is tempting him. God can’t be tempted by evil, and God doesn’t tempt anyone. <verse eid="JAS 1:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JAS 1:14" />Everyone is tempted by his own desires as they lure him away and trap him. <verse eid="JAS 1:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JAS 1:15" />Then desire becomes pregnant and gives birth to sin. When sin grows up, it gives birth to death.<verse eid="JAS 1:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JAS 1:16" />My dear brothers and sisters, don’t be fooled. <verse eid="JAS 1:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JAS 1:17" />Every good present and every perfect gift comes from above, from the Father who made the sun, moon, and stars. The Father doesn’t change like the shifting shadows produced by the sun and the moon.<verse eid="JAS 1:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JAS 1:18" />God decided to give us life through the word of truth to make us his most important creatures.<verse eid="JAS 1:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JAS 1:19" />Remember this, my dear brothers and sisters: Everyone should be quick to listen, slow to speak, and should not get angry easily. <verse eid="JAS 1:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JAS 1:20" />An angry person doesn’t do what God approves of. <verse eid="JAS 1:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JAS 1:21" />So get rid of all immoral behavior and all the wicked things you do. Humbly accept the word that God has placed in you. This word can save you.<verse eid="JAS 1:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JAS 1:22" />Do what God’s word says. Don’t merely listen to it, or you will fool yourselves. <verse eid="JAS 1:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JAS 1:23" />If someone listens to God’s word but doesn’t do what it says, he is like a person who looks at his face in a mirror, <verse eid="JAS 1:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JAS 1:24" />studies his features, goes away, and immediately forgets what he looks like. <verse eid="JAS 1:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JAS 1:25" />However, the person who continues to study God’s perfect laws that make people free and who remains committed to them will be blessed. People like that don’t merely listen and forget; they actually do what God’s laws say.<verse eid="JAS 1:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JAS 1:26" />If a person thinks that he is religious but can’t control his tongue, he is fooling himself. That person’s religion is worthless. <verse eid="JAS 1:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JAS 1:27" />Pure, unstained religion, according to God our Father, is to take care of orphans and widows when they suffer and to remain uncorrupted by this world.<verse eid="JAS 1:27" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JAS 1" />
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="JAS 2" />
  <para style="s1">Don’t Favor Rich People over Poor People</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JAS 2:1" />My brothers and sisters, practice your faith in our glorious Lord Jesus Christ by not favoring one person over another. <verse eid="JAS 2:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JAS 2:2" />For example, two men come to your worship service. One man is wearing gold rings and fine clothes; the other man, who is poor, is wearing shabby clothes. <verse eid="JAS 2:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JAS 2:3" />Suppose you give special attention to the man wearing fine clothes and say to him, “Please have a seat.” But you say to the poor man, “Stand over there,” or “Sit on the floor at my feet.” <verse eid="JAS 2:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JAS 2:4" />Aren’t you discriminating against people and using a corrupt standard to make judgments?<verse eid="JAS 2:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JAS 2:5" />Listen, my dear brothers and sisters! Didn’t God choose poor people in the world to become rich in faith and to receive the kingdom that he promised to those who love him? <verse eid="JAS 2:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JAS 2:6" />Yet, you show no respect to poor people. Don’t rich people oppress you and drag you into court? <verse eid="JAS 2:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JAS 2:7" />Don’t they curse the good name <char style="add">⌞of Jesus⌟</char>, the name that was used to bless you?<verse eid="JAS 2:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JAS 2:8" />You are doing right if you obey this law from the highest authority: “Love your neighbor as you love yourself.” <verse eid="JAS 2:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JAS 2:9" />If you favor one person over another, you’re sinning, and this law convicts you of being disobedient. <verse eid="JAS 2:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JAS 2:10" />If someone obeys all of God’s laws except one, that person is guilty of breaking all of them. <verse eid="JAS 2:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JAS 2:11" />After all, the one who said, “Never commit adultery,” is the same one who said, “Never murder.” If you do not commit adultery but you murder, you become a person who disobeys God’s laws.<verse eid="JAS 2:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JAS 2:12" />Talk and act as people who are going to be judged by laws that bring freedom. <verse eid="JAS 2:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JAS 2:13" />No mercy will be shown to those who show no mercy to others. Mercy triumphs over judgment.<verse eid="JAS 2:13" /></para>
  <para style="s1">We Show Our Faith by What We Do</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JAS 2:14" />My brothers and sisters, what good does it do if someone claims to have faith but doesn’t do any good things? Can this kind of faith save him? <verse eid="JAS 2:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JAS 2:15" />Suppose a believer, whether a man or a woman, needs clothes or food <verse eid="JAS 2:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JAS 2:16" />and one of you tells that person, “God be with you! Stay warm, and make sure you eat enough.” If you don’t provide for that person’s physical needs, what good does it do? <verse eid="JAS 2:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JAS 2:17" />In the same way, faith by itself is dead if it doesn’t cause you to do any good things.<verse eid="JAS 2:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JAS 2:18" />Another person might say, “You have faith, but I do good things.” Show me your faith apart from the good things you do. I will show you my faith by the good things I do. <verse eid="JAS 2:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JAS 2:19" />You believe that there is one God. That’s fine! The demons also believe that, and they tremble with fear.<verse eid="JAS 2:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JAS 2:20" />You fool! Do you have to be shown that faith which does nothing is useless? <verse eid="JAS 2:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JAS 2:21" />Didn’t our ancestor Abraham receive God’s approval as a result of what he did when he offered his son Isaac as a sacrifice on the altar? <verse eid="JAS 2:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JAS 2:22" />You see that Abraham’s faith and what he did worked together. His faith was shown to be genuine by what he did. <verse eid="JAS 2:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JAS 2:23" />The Scripture passage came true. It says, “Abraham believed God, and that faith was regarded as the basis of Abraham’s approval by God.” So Abraham was called God’s friend. <verse eid="JAS 2:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JAS 2:24" />You see that a person receives God’s approval because of what he does, not only because of what he believes. <verse eid="JAS 2:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JAS 2:25" />The same is true of the prostitute Rahab who welcomed the spies and sent them away on another road. She received God’s approval because of what she did.<verse eid="JAS 2:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JAS 2:26" />A body that doesn’t breathe <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“A body without a spirit.”</char></note> is dead. In the same way faith that does nothing is dead.<verse eid="JAS 2:26" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JAS 2" />
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="JAS 3" />
  <para style="s1">Speak Wisely</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JAS 3:1" />Brothers and sisters, not many of you should become teachers. You know that we who teach will be judged more severely.<verse eid="JAS 3:1" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JAS 3:2" />All of us make a lot of mistakes. If someone doesn’t make any mistakes when he speaks, he would be perfect. He would be able to control everything he does. <verse eid="JAS 3:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JAS 3:3" />We put bits in the mouths of horses to make them obey us, and we have control over everything they do. <verse eid="JAS 3:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JAS 3:4" />The same thing is true for ships. They are very big and are driven by strong winds. Yet, by using small rudders, pilots steer ships wherever they want them to go. <verse eid="JAS 3:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JAS 3:5" />In the same way the tongue is a small part of the body, but it can brag about doing important things.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JAS 3:5">A large forest can be set on fire by a little flame. <verse eid="JAS 3:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JAS 3:6" />The tongue is that kind of flame. It is a world of evil among the parts of our bodies, and it completely contaminates our bodies. The tongue sets our lives on fire, and is itself set on fire from hell. <verse eid="JAS 3:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JAS 3:7" />People have tamed all kinds of animals, birds, reptiles, and sea creatures. <verse eid="JAS 3:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JAS 3:8" />Yet, no one can tame the tongue. It is an uncontrollable evil filled with deadly poison.<verse eid="JAS 3:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JAS 3:9" />With our tongues we praise our Lord and Father. Yet, with the same tongues we curse people, who were created in God’s likeness. <verse eid="JAS 3:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JAS 3:10" />Praise and curses come from the same mouth. My brothers and sisters, this should not happen! <verse eid="JAS 3:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JAS 3:11" />Do clean and polluted water flow out of the same spring? <verse eid="JAS 3:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JAS 3:12" />My brothers and sisters, can a fig tree produce olives? Can a grapevine produce figs? In the same way, a pool of salt water can’t produce fresh water.<verse eid="JAS 3:12" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Live Wisely</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JAS 3:13" />Do any of you have wisdom and insight? Show this by living the right way with the humility that comes from wisdom. <verse eid="JAS 3:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JAS 3:14" />But if you are bitterly jealous and filled with self-centered ambition, don’t brag. Don’t say that you are wise when it isn’t true. <verse eid="JAS 3:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JAS 3:15" />That kind of wisdom doesn’t come from above. It belongs to this world. It is self-centered and demonic. <verse eid="JAS 3:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JAS 3:16" />Wherever there is jealousy and rivalry, there is disorder and every kind of evil.<verse eid="JAS 3:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JAS 3:17" />However, the wisdom that comes from above is first of all pure. Then it is peaceful, gentle, obedient, filled with mercy and good deeds, impartial, and sincere. <verse eid="JAS 3:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JAS 3:18" />A harvest that has God’s approval comes from the peace planted by peacemakers.<verse eid="JAS 3:18" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JAS 3" />
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="JAS 4" />
  <para style="s1">Stop Fighting with Each Other</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JAS 4:1" />What causes fights and quarrels among you? Aren’t they caused by the selfish desires that fight to control you? <verse eid="JAS 4:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JAS 4:2" />You want what you don’t have, so you commit murder. You’re determined to have things, but you can’t get what you want. You quarrel and fight. You don’t have the things you want, because you don’t pray for them. <verse eid="JAS 4:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JAS 4:3" />When you pray for things, you don’t get them because you want them for the wrong reason—for your own pleasure.<verse eid="JAS 4:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JAS 4:4" />You unfaithful people! Don’t you know that love for this <char style="add">⌞evil⌟</char> world is hatred toward God? Whoever wants to be a friend of this world is an enemy of God. <verse eid="JAS 4:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JAS 4:5" />Do you think this passage means nothing? It says, “The Spirit that lives in us wants us to be his own.”<verse eid="JAS 4:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JAS 4:6" />But God shows us even more kindness.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“grace.”</char></note> Scripture says,</para>
  <para style="b" vid="JAS 4:6" />
  <para style="q1" vid="JAS 4:6">“God opposes arrogant people,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JAS 4:6">but he is kind to humble people.”<verse eid="JAS 4:6" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JAS 4:7" />So place yourselves under God’s authority. Resist the devil, and he will run away from you. <verse eid="JAS 4:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JAS 4:8" />Come close to God, and he will come close to you. Clean up your lives, you sinners, and clear your minds, you doubters. <verse eid="JAS 4:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JAS 4:9" />Be miserable, mourn, and cry. Turn your laughter into mourning and your joy into gloom. <verse eid="JAS 4:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JAS 4:10" />Humble yourselves in the Lord’s presence. Then he will give you a high position.<verse eid="JAS 4:10" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Stop Slandering Each Other</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JAS 4:11" />Brothers and sisters, stop slandering each other. Those who slander and judge other believers slander and judge God’s laws. If you judge God’s teachings, you are no longer following them. Instead, you are judging them. <verse eid="JAS 4:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JAS 4:12" />There is only one who creates laws and judges on the basis of them. He is able to save or destroy you. So who are you to judge your neighbor?<verse eid="JAS 4:12" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Don’t Brag about Your Plans for the Future</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JAS 4:13" />Pay attention to this! You’re saying, “Today or tomorrow we will go into some city, stay there a year, conduct business, and make money.” <verse eid="JAS 4:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JAS 4:14" />You don’t know what will happen tomorrow. What is life? You are a mist that is seen for a moment and then disappears. <verse eid="JAS 4:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JAS 4:15" />Instead, you should say, “If the Lord wants us to, we will live and carry out our plans.” <verse eid="JAS 4:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JAS 4:16" />However, you brag because you’re arrogant. All such bragging is evil.<verse eid="JAS 4:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JAS 4:17" />Whoever knows what is right but doesn’t do it is sinning.<verse eid="JAS 4:17" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JAS 4" />
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="JAS 5" />
  <para style="s1">Advice to Rich People</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JAS 5:1" />Pay attention to this if you’re rich. Cry and moan about the misery that is coming to you. <verse eid="JAS 5:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JAS 5:2" />Your riches have decayed, and your clothes have been eaten by moths. <verse eid="JAS 5:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JAS 5:3" />Your gold and silver are corroded, and their corrosion will be used as evidence against you. Like fire, it will destroy your body.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JAS 5:3">You have stored up riches in these last days. <verse eid="JAS 5:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JAS 5:4" />The wages you refused to pay the people who harvested your fields shout <char style="add">⌞to God⌟</char> against you. The Lord of Armies has heard the cries of those who gather the crops. <verse eid="JAS 5:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JAS 5:5" />You have lived in luxury and pleasure here on earth. You have fattened yourselves for the day of slaughter. <verse eid="JAS 5:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JAS 5:6" />You have condemned and murdered people who have God’s approval, even though they didn’t resist you.<verse eid="JAS 5:6" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Be Patient</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JAS 5:7" />Brothers and sisters, be patient until the Lord comes again. See how farmers wait for their precious crops to grow. They wait patiently for fall and spring rains. <verse eid="JAS 5:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JAS 5:8" />You, too, must be patient. Don’t give up hope. The Lord will soon be here. <verse eid="JAS 5:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JAS 5:9" />Brothers and sisters, stop complaining about each other, or you will be condemned. Realize that the judge is standing at the door.<verse eid="JAS 5:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JAS 5:10" />Brothers and sisters, follow the example of the prophets who spoke in the name of the Lord. They were patient when they suffered unjustly. <verse eid="JAS 5:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JAS 5:11" />We consider those who endure to be blessed. You have heard about Job’s endurance. You saw that the Lord ended Job’s suffering because the Lord is compassionate and merciful.<verse eid="JAS 5:11" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Don’t Take Oaths</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JAS 5:12" />Above all things, my brothers and sisters, do not take an oath on anything in heaven or on earth. Do not take any oath. If you mean yes, say yes. If you mean no, say no. Do this so that you won’t be condemned.<verse eid="JAS 5:12" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Prayer Is Powerful</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JAS 5:13" />If any of you are having trouble, pray. If you are happy, sing psalms. <verse eid="JAS 5:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JAS 5:14" />If you are sick, call for the church leaders. Have them pray for you and anoint you with olive oil <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">People in ancient times used </char><char style="fq" closed="false">olive oil </char><char style="ft" closed="false">for healing.</char></note> in the name of the Lord. <verse eid="JAS 5:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JAS 5:15" />(Prayers offered in faith will save those who are sick, and the Lord will cure them.) If you have sinned, you will be forgiven. <verse eid="JAS 5:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JAS 5:16" />So admit your sins to each other, and pray for each other so that you will be healed.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JAS 5:16">Prayers offered by those who have God’s approval are effective. <verse eid="JAS 5:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JAS 5:17" />Elijah was human like us. Yet, when he prayed that it wouldn’t rain, no rain fell on the ground for three-and-a-half years. <verse eid="JAS 5:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JAS 5:18" />Then he prayed again. It rained, and the ground produced crops.<verse eid="JAS 5:18" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Help Those Who Have Wandered Away from the Truth</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JAS 5:19" />My brothers and sisters, if one of you wanders from the truth, someone can bring that person back. <verse eid="JAS 5:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JAS 5:20" />Realize that whoever brings a sinner back from the error of his ways will save him from death, and many sins will be forgiven.<verse eid="JAS 5:20" /></para>
  <chapter eid="JAS 5" />
</usx>