<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="LEV" style="id">- God’s Word Bible</book>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="rem">© 1995, 2003, 2013, 2014, 2019, 2020 by God’s Word to the Nations Mission Society. All rights reserved.</para>
  <para style="rem">Converted from InDesign files to USFM-3 by Elbert Boot (Digital Bible Library Customer Service Team, Miami [USA])</para>
  <para style="rem">Language: English</para>
  <para style="rem">This project has 9 poetry levels, and Paratext only supports up to 4 levels. To upload the text to DBL, we have created a dblChanges file and added q5 to q9 to a custom.sty to obtain the desired design in Paratext.</para>
  <para style="h">LEVITICUS</para>
  <para style="toc1">Leviticus</para>
  <para style="toc2">Leviticus</para>
  <para style="toc3">Leviticus</para>
  <para style="mt1">Leviticus</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="LEV 1" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 1:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> called Moses and spoke to him from the tent of meeting. He said, <verse eid="LEV 1:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 1:2" />“Tell the Israelites: If any of you bring a sacrifice to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, you must offer an animal from your cattle, sheep, or goats.<verse eid="LEV 1:2" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Burnt Offerings of Cattle</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 1:3" />“If you bring a burnt offering from your cattle, you must offer a male that has no defects. Offer it at the entrance to the tent of meeting so that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will accept you. <verse eid="LEV 1:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 1:4" />Place your hand on the animal’s head. The burnt offering will be accepted to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 1:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 1:5" />Then slaughter the bull in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence. Aaron’s sons, the priests, will offer the blood. They will throw it against all sides of the altar that is at the entrance to the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 1:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 1:6" />Skin the burnt offering, and cut it into pieces. <verse eid="LEV 1:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 1:7" />Then the sons of the priest Aaron will start a fire on the altar and lay the wood on the fire. <verse eid="LEV 1:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 1:8" />Aaron’s sons, the priests, will also lay the pieces, the head, and the fat on top of the wood burning on the altar. <verse eid="LEV 1:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 1:9" />Wash the internal organs and legs. Then the priest will burn all of it on the altar. It is a burnt offering, an offering by fire, a soothing aroma to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 1:9" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Burnt Offerings of Sheep or Goats</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 1:10" />“If your offering is a sheep or goat, you must bring a male that has no defects. <verse eid="LEV 1:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 1:11" />Slaughter it in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence on the north side of the altar. Aaron’s sons, the priests, will throw the blood against the altar on all sides. <verse eid="LEV 1:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 1:12" />Then cut it into pieces. The priest will lay the head and the fat on the wood burning on the altar. <verse eid="LEV 1:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 1:13" />Wash the internal organs and legs. Then the priest will burn all of it on the altar. It is a burnt offering, an offering by fire, a soothing aroma to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 1:13" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Burnt Offerings of Birds</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 1:14" />“If your offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is a bird, you must sacrifice a mourning dove or pigeon. <verse eid="LEV 1:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 1:15" />The priest must bring it to the altar. He will break its neck and burn the bird on the altar. First, he will drain the blood against the side of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 1:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 1:16" />Remove the gizzard with its filth and throw it on the east side of the altar on the place for the ashes. <verse eid="LEV 1:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 1:17" />Then pull on the bird’s wings to tear the bird open, but don’t pull the wings off. Then the priest will lay the bird on the wood burning on the altar. It is a burnt offering, an offering by fire, a soothing aroma to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.”<verse eid="LEV 1:17" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 1" />
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="LEV 2" />
  <para style="s1">Uncooked Grain Offerings</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 2:1" />
    <char style="add">⌞The <char style="nd">Lord</char> continued,⌟</char> “Now, if any of you bring a grain offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, your offering must be flour. Pour olive oil on it, and put incense on it. <verse eid="LEV 2:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 2:2" />Then bring it to Aaron’s sons, the priests. Take from this a handful of flour with olive oil, and all the incense. The priest will burn it on the altar as a reminder. It is an offering by fire, a soothing aroma to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 2:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 2:3" />The rest of the grain offering will belong to Aaron and his sons. It is very holy, set apart from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s offering by fire.<verse eid="LEV 2:3" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Cooked Grain Offerings</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 2:4" />“If you bring a grain offering which has been baked in an oven, it must be rings of unleavened bread made of flour mixed with olive oil or wafers of unleavened bread brushed with olive oil. <verse eid="LEV 2:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 2:5" />If your grain offering is prepared in a frying pan, it, too, will be unleavened bread made of flour mixed with olive oil. <verse eid="LEV 2:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 2:6" />Break it into pieces and pour olive oil over it. It is a grain offering. <verse eid="LEV 2:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 2:7" />If your grain offering is prepared in a skillet, it will be made of flour with olive oil.<verse eid="LEV 2:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 2:8" />“Bring the <char style="nd">Lord</char> the grain offering prepared in any of these ways. Offer it to the priest who will bring it to the altar. <verse eid="LEV 2:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 2:9" />The priest will remove part of the grain offering and burn it as a reminder on the altar. It is an offering by fire, a soothing aroma to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 2:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 2:10" />The rest of the grain offering belongs to Aaron and his sons. It is very holy, set apart from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s offering by fire.<verse eid="LEV 2:10" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Other Ingredients</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 2:11" />“Every grain offering that you bring to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> must be prepared without yeast. Never burn yeast or honey as an offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 2:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 2:12" />You may bring them to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as offerings of your first products. But they must never be placed on the altar to make a soothing aroma. <verse eid="LEV 2:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 2:13" />Also put salt on each of your grain offerings. The salt of God’s promise <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“covenant.”</char></note> must never be left out of your grain offerings. Put salt on all your offerings.<verse eid="LEV 2:13" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Offering the First Grain Harvested</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 2:14" />“If you bring a grain offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> from the first grain you harvest, roast the cracked grain over fire. <verse eid="LEV 2:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 2:15" />Put olive oil on it, and place incense on it. It is a grain offering. <verse eid="LEV 2:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 2:16" />The priest will burn the flour, olive oil, and all the incense as a reminder. It is an offering by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.”<verse eid="LEV 2:16" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 2" />
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="LEV 3" />
  <para style="s1">Fellowship Offerings of Cattle</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 3:1" />
    <char style="add">⌞The <char style="nd">Lord</char> continued,⌟</char> “If your sacrifice is a fellowship offering of cattle in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence, it must be a male or female animal that has no defects. <verse eid="LEV 3:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 3:2" />Place your hand on the animal’s head. Then slaughter it at the entrance to the tent of meeting. Then Aaron’s sons, the priests, will throw the blood against the altar on all sides. <verse eid="LEV 3:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 3:3" />From your offering remove the fat that covers the internal organs <verse eid="LEV 3:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 3:4" />and the two kidneys with the fat on them and offer them by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Also cut off the lobe of the liver along with the kidneys. <verse eid="LEV 3:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 3:5" />Then Aaron’s sons will lay them on top of the burnt offering on the burning wood. It is an offering by fire, a soothing aroma to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 3:5" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Fellowship Offerings of Sheep</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 3:6" />“If your sacrifice is a fellowship offering of sheep to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, you must bring a male or female animal that has no defects. <verse eid="LEV 3:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 3:7" />If your offering is a lamb, you must bring it to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 3:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 3:8" />Place your hand on the animal’s head. Slaughter it in front of the tent of meeting. Then Aaron’s sons will throw the blood against the altar on all sides. <verse eid="LEV 3:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 3:9" />Then take the fat from the fellowship offering and offer it by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Remove all the fat from the tail and the fat that covers the internal organs. <verse eid="LEV 3:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 3:10" />Also remove the two kidneys with the fat on them along with the lobe of the liver. <verse eid="LEV 3:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 3:11" />Then the priest will burn the fellowship offering on the altar. It is food, an offering by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 3:11" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Fellowship Offerings of Goats</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 3:12" />“If your offering is a goat, you must bring it to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 3:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 3:13" />Place your hand on its head. Slaughter it in front of the tent of meeting. Then Aaron’s sons will throw the blood against the altar on all sides. <verse eid="LEV 3:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 3:14" />Then bring the fat that covers the internal organs <verse eid="LEV 3:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 3:15" />and the two kidneys with the fat on them as an offering by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Also remove the lobe of the liver along with the kidneys. <verse eid="LEV 3:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 3:16" />Then the priest will burn them on the altar. It is food, an offering by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It is a soothing aroma. All the fat belongs to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 3:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 3:17" />This is a permanent law for generations to come wherever you live: Never eat any fat or blood.”<verse eid="LEV 3:17" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 3" />
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="LEV 4" />
  <para style="s1">Offerings for Unintentional Wrongdoing</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 4:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 4:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 4:2" />“Tell the Israelites: If a person unintentionally does something wrong—even one thing that is forbidden by any of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s commands—this is what he must do.<verse eid="LEV 4:2" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Offerings for Wrongdoing by the Chief Priest</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 4:3" />“If the anointed priest does something wrong and brings guilt on the people, he must bring a bull that has no defects as an offering for sin to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 4:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 4:4" />He must bring the bull into the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence at the entrance to the tent of meeting. He will place his hand on the bull’s head. He will then slaughter the bull in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence. <verse eid="LEV 4:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 4:5" />Then the anointed priest will take some of the bull’s blood and bring it into the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 4:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 4:6" />The priest will dip his finger in it and sprinkle some of the blood seven times in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence facing the canopy in the holy place. <verse eid="LEV 4:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 4:7" />Then the priest will put some of the blood on the horns of the altar for sweet-smelling incense in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence in the tent of meeting. He will pour the rest of the bull’s blood at the bottom of the altar for burnt offerings at the entrance to the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 4:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 4:8" />He will remove all of the fat from the bull that is the offering for sin, the fat that covers the internal organs, <verse eid="LEV 4:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 4:9" />and the two kidneys with the fat on them. He will also remove the lobe of the liver and the kidneys <verse eid="LEV 4:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 4:10" />the same way they were removed from the bull used for the fellowship offering. The priest will lay them on the altar for burnt offerings. <verse eid="LEV 4:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 4:11" />Then he will take the entire bull (the skin, meat, head, legs, internal organs, and excrement) <verse eid="LEV 4:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 4:12" />to a clean <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">“</char><char style="fk" closed="false">Clean</char><char style="ft" closed="false">” refers to anything that is presentable to God.</char></note> place outside the camp where the ashes are dumped. He will burn it there on a wood fire.<verse eid="LEV 4:12" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Offerings for Wrongdoing by the Whole Congregation</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 4:13" />“If the whole congregation of Israel unintentionally does something wrong, without the assembly being aware of it, if they do even one thing that is forbidden by any of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s commands, they will be guilty. <verse eid="LEV 4:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 4:14" />When the wrong they have done becomes known, the congregation must sacrifice a bull as an offering for sin. They must bring it in front of the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 4:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 4:15" />The leaders of the congregation will place their hands on the bull’s head in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence. One of them will slaughter it in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence. <verse eid="LEV 4:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 4:16" />Then the anointed priest will bring some of the bull’s blood into the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 4:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 4:17" />The priest will dip his finger in some of the blood and sprinkle it seven times in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence facing the canopy. <verse eid="LEV 4:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 4:18" />He will also put some blood on the horns of the altar in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence in the tent of meeting. He will pour the rest of the blood at the bottom of the altar for burnt offerings at the entrance to the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 4:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 4:19" />He will remove all the fat and burn it on the altar. <verse eid="LEV 4:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 4:20" />He will do the same thing with this bull that he did with the bull used as the offering for sin. So the priest will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for the people, and they will be forgiven. <verse eid="LEV 4:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 4:21" />Then he will take the bull outside the camp and will burn it the same way he burned the first bull. It is an offering for sin for the community.<verse eid="LEV 4:21" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Offerings for Wrongdoing by a Leader</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 4:22" />“When a leader unintentionally does something wrong—even one thing that is forbidden by any of the commands of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> his God—he will be guilty. <verse eid="LEV 4:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 4:23" />When he is told about what he has done wrong, he must bring a male goat that has no defects as his offering. <verse eid="LEV 4:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 4:24" />He will place his hand on the goat’s head and slaughter it in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence where he slaughters animals for burnt offerings. It is an offering for sin. <verse eid="LEV 4:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 4:25" />Then the priest will take some of the blood of the offering for sin with his finger and put it on the horns of the altar for burnt offerings. He will pour the rest of the blood at the bottom of the altar for burnt offerings. <verse eid="LEV 4:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 4:26" />He will burn all the fat on the altar the same way the fat of the fellowship offering is burned. So the priest will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for what the leader did wrong, and the leader will be forgiven.<verse eid="LEV 4:26" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Offerings for Wrongdoing by a Common Person—Goats</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 4:27" />“If a common person unintentionally does something wrong—even one thing forbidden by the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s commands—he will be guilty. <verse eid="LEV 4:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 4:28" />When he is told about what he has done wrong, he must bring a female goat that has no defects as his offering for what he has done wrong. <verse eid="LEV 4:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 4:29" />He will place his hand on the animal’s head and slaughter it where animals for burnt offerings are slaughtered. <verse eid="LEV 4:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 4:30" />The priest will take some of the blood with his finger and put it on the horns of the altar for burnt offerings. He will pour the rest of the blood at the bottom of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 4:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 4:31" />He will remove all the fat the same way it is removed from the fellowship offering. The priest will burn it on the altar for a soothing aroma to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. So the priest will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for that person, and that person will be forgiven.<verse eid="LEV 4:31" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Offerings for Wrongdoing by a Common Person—Lambs</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 4:32" />“If someone brings a lamb as his offering for sin, he must bring a female that has no defects. <verse eid="LEV 4:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 4:33" />He will place his hand on the animal’s head and slaughter it where he slaughters animals for burnt offerings. <verse eid="LEV 4:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 4:34" />Then the priest will take some of the blood from the offering for sin with his finger and put it on the horns of the altar for burnt offerings. He will pour the rest of the blood at the bottom of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 4:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 4:35" />He will remove all the fat the same way the fat of the lamb is removed from the fellowship offerings. Then the priest will burn it on the altar with the offering by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. So the priest will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for what that person did wrong, and that person will be forgiven.”<verse eid="LEV 4:35" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 4" />
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="LEV 5" />
  <para style="s1">Sins Which Require an Offering for Sin</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 5:1" />
    <char style="add">⌞The <char style="nd">Lord</char> continued,⌟</char> “Now, if you are a witness under oath and won’t tell what you saw or what you know, you are sinning and will be punished.<verse eid="LEV 5:1" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 5:2" />“If you touch anything unclean <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">“</char><char style="fk" closed="false">Unclean</char><char style="ft" closed="false">” refers to anything that is not presentable to God.</char></note>—the unclean dead body of a wild or tame animal or the body of an unclean, swarming creature—and then ignore what you did, you are unclean and will be guilty.<verse eid="LEV 5:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 5:3" />“If you become unclean by touching human uncleanness of any kind and then ignore it (although you know what you did), you will be guilty.<verse eid="LEV 5:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 5:4" />“If you hastily take a vow about what you will or will not do (as some people do) and then ignore it (although you know what you said), you will be guilty.<verse eid="LEV 5:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 5:5" />“So if you are guilty of any of these sins, you must confess it. <verse eid="LEV 5:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 5:6" />Bring your guilt offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for the sin you committed. It must be a female sheep or goat as an offering for sin. Then the priest will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for what you did wrong.<verse eid="LEV 5:6" /></para>
  <para style="s1">If You Cannot Afford a Sheep</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 5:7" />“Now, if you cannot afford a sheep, you must bring to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> two mourning doves or two pigeons as a guilt offering for the sin you committed. One will be an offering for sin, the other a burnt offering. <verse eid="LEV 5:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 5:8" />Bring them to the priest, and he will sacrifice the offering for sin first. He will break the bird’s neck without pulling its head off. <verse eid="LEV 5:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 5:9" />He will sprinkle some of the blood from the offering for sin on the side of the altar, and the rest of the blood will be drained at the bottom of the altar. It is an offering for sin. <verse eid="LEV 5:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 5:10" />Then, following the proper procedures, he will sacrifice the second bird as a burnt offering. So the priest will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for what you did wrong.<verse eid="LEV 5:10" /></para>
  <para style="s1">If You Cannot Afford Two Mourning Doves</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 5:11" />“But if you cannot afford two mourning doves or two pigeons, then bring eight cups of flour as an offering for the sin you committed. Never put olive oil on it or add incense to it, because it is an offering for sin. <verse eid="LEV 5:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 5:12" />Bring it to the priest. The priest will take a handful of it. He will burn it as a reminder on top of the offering by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> on the altar. It is an offering for sin. <verse eid="LEV 5:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 5:13" />So the priest will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for what you did wrong, and you will be forgiven. The offering will belong to the priest like the grain offering.”<verse eid="LEV 5:13" /></para>
  <para style="s1">For Unintentional Wrongdoing against the <char style="nd">LORD</char>’s Property</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 5:14" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 5:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 5:15" />“If any of you fail to do your duty by unintentionally doing something wrong with any of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s holy things, bring a guilt offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It must be a ram that has no defects or its value in silver weighed according to the official standards of the holy place. <verse eid="LEV 5:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 5:16" />Pay for whatever holy things you used plus one-fifth more. Give it to the priest. So the priest will use the ram sacrificed for the guilt offering to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for what you did wrong, and you will be forgiven.<verse eid="LEV 5:16" /></para>
  <para style="s1">For Unintentionally Disobeying the <char style="nd">LORD</char>’s Commands</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 5:17" />“If any of you do wrong—even one thing forbidden by any of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s commands, but you didn’t know it—when you realize your guilt, you must be punished. <verse eid="LEV 5:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 5:18" />You must bring the priest a ram that has no defects from the flock or its value in money for a guilt offering. The priest will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for the wrong you did unintentionally (although you didn’t know what you did), and you will be forgiven. <verse eid="LEV 5:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 5:19" />It is a guilt offering because you are certainly guilty as far as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> is concerned.”<verse eid="LEV 5:19" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 5" />
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="LEV 6" />
  <para style="s1">For Sins against the <char style="nd">LORD</char>’s People</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 6:1" />
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">6:1 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">
        <char style="xt">
          <ref loc="LEV 6:1-30">Leviticus 6:1–30</ref>
        </char> in English Bibles is Leviticus 5:20–6:23 in the Hebrew Bible.</char>
    </note>The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 6:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 6:2" />“If any of you sin against the <char style="nd">Lord </char> by failing to do your duty, if you lie to your neighbor about something you were supposed to take care of or if you lie about something stolen or seized from your neighbor, you are sinning and will be guilty. <verse eid="LEV 6:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 6:3" />If you find something that someone lost and lie about it under oath, or commit any other sin like this, <verse eid="LEV 6:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 6:4" />you are sinning and will be guilty. Return what you stole or seized, what you were supposed to take care of, the lost item you found, <verse eid="LEV 6:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 6:5" />or whatever it was that you swore falsely about. Pay it back in full plus one-fifth more. Give it back to its owner on the day you bring your guilt offering. <verse eid="LEV 6:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 6:6" />Then bring the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your guilt offering, a ram that has no defects or its value in money. Bring it to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 6:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 6:7" />So the priest will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Then you will be forgiven for whatever you did that made you guilty.”<verse eid="LEV 6:7" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Instructions for Taking Care of the Fire</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 6:8" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 6:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 6:9" />“Command Aaron and his sons: These are the instructions for the burnt offering that stays on the altar overnight while the altar fire is kept burning.<verse eid="LEV 6:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 6:10" />“The priest must put on his linen clothes, including his linen undergarments. Then he will remove the ashes left on the altar from the fire that consumed the burnt offering and will put them next to the altar. <verse eid="LEV 6:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 6:11" />Then he will take off these clothes and put on some others. He will take the ashes to a clean place outside the camp. <verse eid="LEV 6:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 6:12" />The fire must always be burning on the altar. It must never go out. The priest will burn wood on it every morning. He will lay the burnt offering on the fire and burn the fat of the fellowship offering. <verse eid="LEV 6:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 6:13" />The fire must always be burning on the altar. It must never go out.<verse eid="LEV 6:13" /></para>
  <para style="s1">The Grain Offering from the People</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 6:14" />“These are the instructions for the grain offering. Aaron’s sons must bring it into the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence in front of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 6:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 6:15" />One of them will remove a handful of flour from the grain offering, together with the olive oil and all the incense. He will burn it on the altar as a reminder. It is a soothing aroma to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 6:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 6:16" />Aaron and his sons will eat the rest of it. They will eat unleavened bread in a holy place, in the courtyard of the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 6:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 6:17" />Don’t use yeast in baking the bread. I have given it to them as their share from the offerings by fire made to me. It is very holy like the offering for sin and the guilt offering. <verse eid="LEV 6:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 6:18" />Every male descendant of Aaron may eat it. It is a permanent law for generations to come regarding the offering by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Everyone who touches it will become holy.”<verse eid="LEV 6:18" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Special Grain Offerings from the Priests</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 6:19" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 6:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 6:20" />“This is the offering that Aaron and his sons must bring to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> on the day he is anointed—eight cups of flour. They must do this every day. He must offer half of it in the morning and half in the evening. <verse eid="LEV 6:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 6:21" />Prepare it in a frying pan with olive oil, mixing it well. Offer baked pieces of the grain offering as a soothing aroma to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 6:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 6:22" />Aaron’s son who is anointed to take his place as priest will prepare it. This is a permanent law of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>: It must be completely burned. <verse eid="LEV 6:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 6:23" />Every grain offering made by a priest must be completely burned. It must not be eaten.”<verse eid="LEV 6:23" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Instructions for the Offering for Sin</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 6:24" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 6:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 6:25" />“Tell Aaron and his sons: These are the instructions for the offering for sin. The offering for sin must be slaughtered in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence in the same place where the burnt offering is slaughtered. It is very holy. <verse eid="LEV 6:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 6:26" />The priest who makes the offering for sin will eat it in a holy place, in the courtyard of the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 6:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 6:27" />Anything that touches its meat will be holy. If blood gets on someone’s clothes, he must wash them in a holy place. <verse eid="LEV 6:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 6:28" />Any piece of pottery in which the offering for sin is cooked must be broken into pieces. Any copper kettle in which the offering for sin is cooked must be scoured and rinsed with water. <verse eid="LEV 6:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 6:29" />Any male among the priests may eat the offering for sin. It is very holy. <verse eid="LEV 6:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 6:30" />Any offering for sin must not be eaten if some of the blood was brought into the holy place in the tent of meeting to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It must be burned.”<verse eid="LEV 6:30" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 6" />
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="LEV 7" />
  <para style="s1">Instructions for the Guilt Offering</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 7:1" />
    <char style="add">⌞The <char style="nd">Lord</char> continued,⌟</char> “These are the instructions for the guilt offering. It is very holy. <verse eid="LEV 7:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 7:2" />It must be slaughtered in the same place where the burnt offering is slaughtered. <char style="add">⌞A priest⌟</char> will throw the blood against the altar on all sides. <verse eid="LEV 7:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 7:3" />He will offer all the fat, the fat from the tail, the fat covering the internal organs, <verse eid="LEV 7:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 7:4" />and the two kidneys with the fat on them. He will also remove the lobe of the liver along with the kidneys. <verse eid="LEV 7:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 7:5" />The priest will burn them on the altar. It is a guilt offering by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 7:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 7:6" />Any male among the priests may eat it. It will be eaten in a holy place. It is very holy.<verse eid="LEV 7:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 7:7" />“The same instructions apply to the offering for sin and the guilt offering. Both offerings belong to the priest to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 7:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 7:8" />The skin of the burnt offering belongs to the priest who sacrifices it. <verse eid="LEV 7:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 7:9" />Every grain offering, whether baked in an oven or prepared in a skillet or a frying pan, belongs to the priest who offers it. <verse eid="LEV 7:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 7:10" />Every grain offering, whether mixed with olive oil or dry, will be shared equally by all of Aaron’s sons.<verse eid="LEV 7:10" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Instructions for the Fellowship Offering of Thanksgiving</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 7:11" />“These are the instructions for the fellowship offering that you must bring to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 7:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 7:12" />If you offer it as a thank offering, you must also bring rings of unleavened bread mixed with olive oil, wafers of unleavened bread brushed with olive oil, and loaves made from flour mixed well with olive oil. <verse eid="LEV 7:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 7:13" />In addition to these rings of bread, you must bring bread with yeast along with your fellowship offering of thanksgiving. <verse eid="LEV 7:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 7:14" />From every offering you must bring one loaf to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as a <char style="add">⌞special⌟</char> contribution. It will belong to the priest who throws the blood of the fellowship offering.<verse eid="LEV 7:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 7:15" />“The meat from your fellowship offering of thanksgiving must be eaten on the day it is offered. Never leave any of it until morning.<verse eid="LEV 7:15" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Instructions for Other Fellowship Offerings</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 7:16" />“If your sacrificial offering is something you vowed or a freewill offering, it must be eaten the day you offer it or the next day. <verse eid="LEV 7:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 7:17" />However, on the third day any meat left over from the sacrifice must be burned. <verse eid="LEV 7:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 7:18" />You will not be accepted if any meat from the fellowship offering is eaten on the third day. You will not receive credit for it. It is repulsive to God. The person who eats any of it must be punished.<verse eid="LEV 7:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 7:19" />“Meat that touches anything unclean must not be eaten. It must be burned. Anyone who is clean may eat from these sacrifices. <verse eid="LEV 7:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 7:20" />Those who eat meat from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s fellowship offering while unclean must be excluded from the people. <verse eid="LEV 7:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 7:21" />Those who touch anything unclean, human or animal, or any other disgusting uncleanness and still eat the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s fellowship offering must be excluded from the people.”<verse eid="LEV 7:21" /></para>
  <para style="s1">No Fat or Blood May Be Eaten</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 7:22" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 7:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 7:23" />“Tell the Israelites: Never eat any fat from bulls, sheep, or goats. <verse eid="LEV 7:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 7:24" />The fat from an animal that dies naturally or is killed by wild animals you may use for any other purpose, but you must never eat it. <verse eid="LEV 7:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 7:25" />Those who eat the fat from an animal which they sacrificed by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> must be excluded from the people.<verse eid="LEV 7:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 7:26" />“Never eat the blood of any bird or animal no matter where you live. <verse eid="LEV 7:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 7:27" />Those who eat any blood must be excluded from the people.”<verse eid="LEV 7:27" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Dividing the Fellowship Offering between the People and the Priests</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 7:28" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 7:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 7:29" />“Tell the Israelites: Anyone who offers the <char style="nd">Lord</char> a fellowship offering must bring a part of that sacrifice as a gift to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 7:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 7:30" />Bring the sacrifices by fire made to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> yourself. Bring the fat with the breast. Take the breast and present it to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 7:30" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 7:31" />“The priest will burn the fat on the altar. However, the breast will belong to Aaron and his sons. <verse eid="LEV 7:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 7:32" />You will also give the priest the right thigh as a contribution. <verse eid="LEV 7:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 7:33" />When any of Aaron’s sons offer the blood and fat of the fellowship offering, the right thigh will belong to him as his share. <verse eid="LEV 7:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 7:34" />From the fellowship offerings of the Israelites, I have taken the breast that was presented <char style="add">⌞to me⌟</char> and the thigh from the contribution offering. I have given them to the priest Aaron and his sons. This is a permanent law for generations to come.<verse eid="LEV 7:34" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 7:35" />“This is the share for Aaron and his sons from the sacrifices by fire made to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It was given to them on the day Moses ordained them to serve the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as priests. <verse eid="LEV 7:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 7:36" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded the Israelites to give it to them on the day he anointed them. This is a permanent law for generations to come.”<verse eid="LEV 7:36" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Summary of Offerings</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 7:37" />These are the instructions for the burnt offering, the grain offering, the offering for sin, the guilt offering, the ordination offering, and the fellowship offering. <verse eid="LEV 7:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 7:38" />On Mount Sinai the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave Moses commands about these offerings at the same time that he commanded the Israelites to bring their offerings to him in the Sinai Desert.<verse eid="LEV 7:38" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 7" />
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="LEV 8" />
  <para style="s1">Aaron and His Sons Made Priests</para>
  <para style="r">(<ref loc="EXO 29:1-45">Exodus 29:1–45</ref>)</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 8:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 8:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 8:2" />“Take Aaron and his sons, the priests’ clothes, the anointing oil, the bull that will be the offering for sin, the two rams, and the basket of unleavened bread. <verse eid="LEV 8:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 8:3" />Gather the whole congregation at the entrance to the tent of meeting.”<verse eid="LEV 8:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 8:4" />Moses did as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded him, and the congregation gathered at the entrance to the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 8:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 8:5" />Moses told the congregation, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has commanded that this is what you must do.”<verse eid="LEV 8:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 8:6" />Moses had Aaron and his sons come forward, and he washed them. <verse eid="LEV 8:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 8:7" />He put the linen robe on Aaron and fastened the belt around him. He also dressed him in the robe that is worn with the ephod.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:7 </char><char style="fk" closed="false">Ephod </char><char style="ft" closed="false">is a technical term for part of the priest’s clothes. Its exact usage and shape are unknown.</char></note> He fastened the ephod to it. <verse eid="LEV 8:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 8:8" />Then he put the breastplate on him, and into it he placed the Urim and Thummim.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:8 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">The Urim and Thummim </char><char style="ft" closed="false">were used by the chief priest to determine God’s answer to questions.</char></note> <verse eid="LEV 8:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 8:9" />He put the turban on him and fastened the gold medallion (the holy crown) to the front of the turban as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded Moses.<verse eid="LEV 8:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 8:10" />Moses took the anointing oil to anoint the tent and everything in it and dedicate them. <verse eid="LEV 8:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 8:11" />He sprinkled some of the oil on the altar seven times and anointed the altar, all the utensils, and the basin with its stand to dedicate them.<verse eid="LEV 8:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 8:12" />He also poured some of the anointing oil on Aaron’s head and anointed him to set him apart for his holy duties.<verse eid="LEV 8:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 8:13" />Moses had Aaron’s sons come forward. He put linen robes on them, fastened their belts around them, and put turbans on them as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded Moses.<verse eid="LEV 8:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 8:14" />He brought the bull that was the offering for sin. Aaron and his sons placed their hands on its head. <verse eid="LEV 8:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 8:15" />When it was slaughtered, Moses took the blood and put it on the horns of the altar all around with his finger and cleansed the altar from sins. He poured the rest of the blood at the bottom of the altar and declared it holy so that priests could use it to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 8:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 8:16" />Moses took all the fat that was on the internal organs, the lobe of the liver, and the two kidneys with their fat, and he burned them on the altar. <verse eid="LEV 8:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 8:17" />He burned the rest of the bull, its skin, meat, and excrement outside the camp, as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded him.<verse eid="LEV 8:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 8:18" />He brought forward the ram for the burnt offering. Aaron and his sons placed their hands on the ram’s head. <verse eid="LEV 8:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 8:19" />Moses slaughtered it and threw the blood against the altar on all sides. <verse eid="LEV 8:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 8:20" />When the ram was cut into pieces, Moses burned the head with the other pieces and the fat. <verse eid="LEV 8:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 8:21" />He washed the internal organs and the legs. Then Moses burned the whole ram on the altar as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded him. It was a burnt offering, a soothing aroma, an offering by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 8:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 8:22" />He brought forward the second ram for the ordination offering. Aaron and his sons placed their hands on the ram’s head. <verse eid="LEV 8:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 8:23" />Moses slaughtered it, took some of the blood, and put it on Aaron’s right ear lobe, on his right thumb, and on the big toe of his right foot. <verse eid="LEV 8:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 8:24" />Moses also brought Aaron’s sons forward. He put some of the blood on their right ear lobes, on their right thumbs, and on the big toes of their right feet. Moses threw the rest of the blood against all the sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 8:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 8:25" />He took the fat, the fat from the tail, all the fat on the internal organs, the lobe of the liver, the two kidneys with their fat, and the right thigh. <verse eid="LEV 8:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 8:26" />He took a loaf of unleavened bread, a ring of bread made with olive oil, and a wafer from the basket of unleavened bread which was in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence. He put them on the fat and the right thigh. <verse eid="LEV 8:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 8:27" />Then he placed all these things in the hands of Aaron and his sons. Moses presented all these things to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as an offering. <verse eid="LEV 8:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 8:28" />Then he took them from their hands and burned them on top of the burnt offering on the altar. These were ordination offerings, offerings by fire, a soothing aroma to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 8:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 8:29" />Moses also took the breast from the ram of the ordination offering and presented it to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It was Moses’ share, as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded.<verse eid="LEV 8:29" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 8:30" />Moses took some of the anointing oil and some of the blood that was on the altar, sprinkled it on Aaron and his clothes and on his sons and their clothes. In this way he dedicated Aaron, his clothes, his sons, and their clothes.<verse eid="LEV 8:30" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 8:31" />Moses told Aaron and his sons: “Cook the meat at the entrance to the tent of meeting. Take the meat and the bread in the basket of the ordination offering. Eat them there as I commanded when I said, ‘Aaron and his sons will eat it.’ <verse eid="LEV 8:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 8:32" />You must burn any meat or bread that is left over. <verse eid="LEV 8:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 8:33" />You will not leave the entrance to the tent of meeting for seven days, not until the last day of your ordination is over. It will take seven days to ordain you. <verse eid="LEV 8:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 8:34" />I did today what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded me to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for you. <verse eid="LEV 8:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 8:35" />You will stay at the entrance to the tent of meeting day and night for seven days and serve as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> tells you. Then you will not die. This is what I was commanded.”<verse eid="LEV 8:35" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 8:36" />So Aaron and his sons did everything the <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded through Moses.<verse eid="LEV 8:36" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 8" />
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="LEV 9" />
  <para style="s1">Aaron’s First Sacrifices</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 9:1" />On the eighth day Moses summoned Aaron and his sons and the leaders of Israel. <verse eid="LEV 9:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 9:2" />He told Aaron, “Take a calf that has no defects for yourself as an offering for sin and a ram that has no defects as a burnt offering. Sacrifice them in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence. <verse eid="LEV 9:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 9:3" />Also tell the Israelites: ‘Take a male goat as an offering for sin, a calf and a lamb (each one year old and without defects) as a burnt offering, <verse eid="LEV 9:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 9:4" />a bull and a ram as a fellowship offering, and a grain offering mixed with olive oil to sacrifice in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence. The <char style="nd">Lord</char> will appear to you today.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 9:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 9:5" />So they took the things Moses commanded and brought them in front of the tent of meeting. The whole congregation came and stood in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence.<verse eid="LEV 9:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 9:6" />Moses said, “The <char style="nd">Lord</char> has commanded you to offer these sacrifices so that you may see the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s glory.”<verse eid="LEV 9:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 9:7" />Moses told Aaron, “Come to the altar and sacrifice an offering for sin and a burnt offering to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for your sins and the sins of the people. Also make an offering for the people, to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for them as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded.”<verse eid="LEV 9:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 9:8" />Aaron came to the altar and slaughtered the calf as his own offering for sin. <verse eid="LEV 9:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 9:9" />Aaron’s sons brought him the blood. He dipped his finger in the blood and put it on the horns of the altar. Then he poured out the blood at the bottom of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 9:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 9:10" />On the altar he burned the fat, kidneys, and lobe of the liver from the offering for sin as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded Moses. <verse eid="LEV 9:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 9:11" />He burned the meat and the skin outside the camp.<verse eid="LEV 9:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 9:12" />He slaughtered the animal for the burnt offering. Aaron’s sons gave him the blood, and he threw it against the altar on all sides. <verse eid="LEV 9:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 9:13" />They also gave him the burnt offering, which was cut in pieces and included the head. He burned it on the altar. <verse eid="LEV 9:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 9:14" />He washed the internal organs and the legs and laid them on top of the burnt offering on the altar.<verse eid="LEV 9:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 9:15" />He brought the people’s offerings. He took the male goat for the people’s offering for sin and slaughtered it. He sacrificed it to take away sins as he had done before. <verse eid="LEV 9:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 9:16" />Following the proper procedures, he brought forward the burnt offering and sacrificed it. <verse eid="LEV 9:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 9:17" />He also brought the grain offering. He took a handful of grain and burned it on the altar in addition to the morning burnt offering. <verse eid="LEV 9:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 9:18" />He slaughtered the bull and the ram for the people’s fellowship offering. Aaron’s sons gave him the blood, which he threw against the altar on all sides. <verse eid="LEV 9:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 9:19" />However, the fat from the bull and the ram (the fat from the tail, the layer of fat, the kidneys, and the lobe of the liver) <verse eid="LEV 9:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 9:20" />they placed on the breasts. Aaron burned them all on the altar. <verse eid="LEV 9:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 9:21" />However, he first took the breasts and the right thighs and presented them to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as Moses commanded.<verse eid="LEV 9:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 9:22" />Then Aaron raised his hands toward the people and blessed them. He sacrificed the offering for sin, the burnt offering, and the fellowship offering. Then he came down <char style="add">⌞from the altar⌟</char>. <verse eid="LEV 9:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 9:23" />Moses and Aaron went into the tent of meeting. When they came out, they blessed the people. Then the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s glory appeared to all the people. <verse eid="LEV 9:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 9:24" />Fire came out from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence and consumed the burnt offering and the pieces of fat on the altar. When all the people saw this, they shouted and bowed with their faces touching the ground.<verse eid="LEV 9:24" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 9" />
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="LEV 10" />
  <para style="s1">Improper Conduct for Priests</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 10:1" />Aaron’s sons Nadab and Abihu each took an incense burner and put burning coals and incense in it. Then in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence they offered this unauthorized fire. <verse eid="LEV 10:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 10:2" />A fire flashed from the <char style="nd">Lord</char> and burned them, and they died in the presence of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 10:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 10:3" />Moses said to Aaron, “This is exactly what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> said:</para>
  <para style="b" vid="LEV 10:3" />
  <para style="q1" vid="LEV 10:3">‘I will show my holiness among those who come to me.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LEV 10:3">I will show my glory to all the people.’ ”</para>
  <para style="b" vid="LEV 10:3" />
  <para style="m" vid="LEV 10:3">Aaron was speechless.<verse eid="LEV 10:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 10:4" />Moses called Mishael and Elzaphan, the sons of Aaron’s uncle, Uzziel. He told them, “Come and take your relatives away from in front of the holy place. Take them outside the camp.” <verse eid="LEV 10:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 10:5" />So they came and took them away to a place outside the camp, as Moses told them. The dead men were still in their linen robes.<verse eid="LEV 10:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 10:6" />Moses told Aaron and his sons Eleazar and Ithamar: “Do not mourn by leaving your hair uncombed or tearing your clothes. If you do, you will die and the <char style="nd">Lord</char> will become angry with the whole congregation. All the other Israelites may cry over the fire the <char style="nd">Lord</char> sent, but you may not. <verse eid="LEV 10:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 10:7" />You must not leave the entrance to the tent of meeting or else you, too, will die, because the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has anointed you with his oil.” They obeyed Moses.<verse eid="LEV 10:7" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Proper Conduct for Priests</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 10:8" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Aaron, <verse eid="LEV 10:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 10:9" />“You and your sons must not drink any wine or liquor when you go into the tent of meeting, or you will die. This is a permanent law for generations to come. <verse eid="LEV 10:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 10:10" />Teach them the difference between what is holy and what is unholy, what is clean and what is unclean.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10:10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">“</char><char style="fk" closed="false">Clean</char><char style="ft" closed="false">” refers to anything that is presentable to God. “</char><char style="fk" closed="false">Unclean</char><char style="ft" closed="false">” refers to anything that is not presentable to God.</char></note> <verse eid="LEV 10:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 10:11" />Also teach the Israelites all the laws that I gave them through Moses.”<verse eid="LEV 10:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 10:12" />Moses told Aaron and his surviving sons Eleazar and Ithamar, “Take the grain offering left over from the offering by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Make unleavened bread, and eat it next to the altar because it is very holy. <verse eid="LEV 10:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 10:13" />Eat it in a holy place because it is the part of the offering by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> that belongs to you and your children. That is the command I received. <verse eid="LEV 10:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 10:14" />Also eat the breast presented <char style="add">⌞to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>⌟</char> and the thigh that was given as a contribution. You and your sons and daughters may eat them in a clean place because they are your part of the fellowship offerings from the Israelites. <verse eid="LEV 10:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 10:15" />They will bring the thigh given as a contribution, the breast presented <char style="add">⌞to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>⌟</char>, and the fat that is to be burned and present them to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. These parts will belong to you and your children. This will be a permanent law, as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has commanded.”<verse eid="LEV 10:15" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Eleazar and Ithamar Sacrifice the Offering for Sin</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 10:16" />Moses tried to find out what had happened to the male goat that was supposed to be the offering for sin. To his surprise, it had already been burned. So he became angry with Eleazar and Ithamar, Aaron’s surviving sons. <verse eid="LEV 10:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 10:17" />He asked them, “Why didn’t you eat the offering for sin in the holy place? It is very holy and was given to you to take away the sins of the congregation and to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for them. <verse eid="LEV 10:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 10:18" />Since its blood was not brought inside the holy place, you certainly should have eaten it there, as I commanded.”<verse eid="LEV 10:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 10:19" />Aaron answered Moses, “Today they sacrificed their offering for sin and their burnt offering in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence, and look what happened to me. If I had eaten the offering for sin today, would the <char style="nd">Lord</char> have approved?”<verse eid="LEV 10:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 10:20" />When Moses heard this, he was satisfied.<verse eid="LEV 10:20" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 10" />
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="LEV 11" />
  <para style="s1">Laws about Animals the Israelites May and May Not Eat</para>
  <para style="r">(<ref loc="DEU 14:3-20">Deuteronomy 14:3–20</ref>)</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 11:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses and Aaron, <verse eid="LEV 11:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 11:2" />“Tell the Israelites: Here are the kinds of land animals you may eat: <verse eid="LEV 11:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 11:3" />all animals that have completely divided hoofs and that also chew their cud. <verse eid="LEV 11:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 11:4" />However, from those that either chew their cud or have divided hoofs, these are the kinds you must never eat: You must never eat camels. (Camels are unclean because they chew their cud but do not have divided hoofs.) <verse eid="LEV 11:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 11:5" />You must never eat rock badgers. (Rock badgers are unclean because they chew their cud but do not have divided hoofs.) <verse eid="LEV 11:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 11:6" />You must never eat rabbits. (Rabbits are unclean because they chew their cud but do not have divided hoofs.) <verse eid="LEV 11:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 11:7" />You must never eat pigs. (Because pigs have completely divided hoofs but do not chew their cud, they are also unclean.) <verse eid="LEV 11:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 11:8" />Never eat the meat of these animals or touch their dead bodies. They are unclean for you.<verse eid="LEV 11:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 11:9" />“Here are the kinds of creatures that live in the water which you may eat—anything in the seas and streams that has fins and scales. <verse eid="LEV 11:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 11:10" />However, you must consider all swarming creatures living in the seas or the streams that have no fins or scales disgusting. <verse eid="LEV 11:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 11:11" />They must remain disgusting to you. Never eat their meat. Consider their dead bodies disgusting. <verse eid="LEV 11:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 11:12" />Every creature in the water without fins or scales is disgusting to you.<verse eid="LEV 11:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 11:13" />“Here are the kinds of birds you must consider disgusting and must not eat. They are eagles, bearded vultures, black vultures, <verse eid="LEV 11:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 11:14" />kites, all types of buzzards, <verse eid="LEV 11:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 11:15" />all types of crows, <verse eid="LEV 11:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 11:16" />ostriches, nighthawks, seagulls, all types of falcons, <verse eid="LEV 11:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 11:17" />little owls, cormorants, great owls, <verse eid="LEV 11:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 11:18" />barn owls, pelicans, ospreys, <verse eid="LEV 11:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 11:19" />storks, all types of herons, hoopoes, and bats.<verse eid="LEV 11:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 11:20" />“Every swarming, winged insect that walks across the ground like a four-legged animal is disgusting to you. <verse eid="LEV 11:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 11:21" />However, you may eat winged insects that swarm if they use their legs to hop on the ground. <verse eid="LEV 11:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 11:22" />You may eat any kind of locust, cricket, katydid, or grasshopper. <verse eid="LEV 11:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 11:23" />Every kind of winged insect that walks across the ground like a four-legged animal is disgusting to you.<verse eid="LEV 11:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 11:24" />“Regarding the creatures mentioned above, this is how you would become unclean: Whoever touches their dead bodies will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 11:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 11:25" />Whoever carries any part of their dead bodies must wash his clothes. He will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 11:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 11:26" />All animals whose hoofs are not completely divided or that don’t chew their cud are unclean for you. Whoever touches them is unclean. <verse eid="LEV 11:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 11:27" />All four-legged animals that walk on their paws are unclean for you. Whoever touches their dead bodies will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 11:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 11:28" />Those who carry the dead body of any of these animals must wash their clothes and will be unclean until evening. These animals are unclean for you.<verse eid="LEV 11:28" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 11:29" />“The following swarming creatures that move on the ground are unclean for you—moles, mice, and all types of lizards: <verse eid="LEV 11:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 11:30" />geckos, monitors, lizards, skinks, and chameleons. <verse eid="LEV 11:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 11:31" />Among all the swarming creatures that move on the ground, these are unclean for you. Whoever touches their dead bodies will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 11:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 11:32" />When the dead body of one of these creatures falls on something, that thing will be unclean. It may be a wooden article, clothing, leather, a sack, or anything used for any purpose. It should be put in water and will be unclean until evening. Then it will be clean <char style="add">⌞again⌟</char>.<verse eid="LEV 11:32" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 11:33" />“If any of these creatures falls into a piece of pottery, break the pottery because everything in it is unclean. <verse eid="LEV 11:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 11:34" />If water <char style="add">⌞from that pottery⌟</char> touches any food, the food is unclean. Any liquid that you drink from that pottery is unclean. <verse eid="LEV 11:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 11:35" />Anything on which their dead bodies fall is unclean. If it is an oven or a stove, smash it. It is unclean and will remain unclean for you. <verse eid="LEV 11:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 11:36" />However, a spring or a cistern holding water will remain clean. But anyone who touches their dead bodies will be unclean. <verse eid="LEV 11:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 11:37" />If their dead bodies fall on seed that is to be planted, the seed is clean. <verse eid="LEV 11:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 11:38" />But if water is poured on the seed and their dead bodies fall on it, the seed is unclean for you.<verse eid="LEV 11:38" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 11:39" />“When any animal that you are allowed to eat dies, whoever touches its dead body will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 11:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LEV 11:40" />Those who eat any of its dead body must wash their clothes and will be unclean until evening. Those who carry its dead body away will wash their clothes and will be unclean until evening.<verse eid="LEV 11:40" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="LEV 11:41" />“Any creature that swarms on the ground is disgusting and must not be eaten. <verse eid="LEV 11:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 11:42" />Don’t eat any creature with many legs that goes on its belly or on the ground like a four-legged animal, or any creature that swarms on the ground. Consider them disgusting. <verse eid="LEV 11:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 11:43" />Don’t become disgusting by eating anything that swarms on the ground. Never allow yourselves to become unclean because of them.<verse eid="LEV 11:43" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 11:44" />“Here is the reason: I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. You must live holy lives. Be holy because I am holy. Never become unclean by touching anything that swarms or crawls on the ground. <verse eid="LEV 11:44" /><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LEV 11:45" />Here is the reason <char style="add">⌞again⌟</char>: I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. I brought you out of Egypt to be your God. Be holy because I am holy.<verse eid="LEV 11:45" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="LEV 11:46" />“These are the instructions about animals, birds, and every living creature that swims in the water and every creature that swarms on the ground. <verse eid="LEV 11:46" /><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LEV 11:47" />These instructions help you distinguish between clean and unclean, the animals you may eat and those you may not eat.”<verse eid="LEV 11:47" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 11" />
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="LEV 12" />
  <para style="s1">Instructions for Women after Childbirth</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 12:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 12:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 12:2" />“Tell the Israelites: When a woman gives birth to a boy, she will be unclean for seven days. This is the same number of days she is unclean for her monthly period. <verse eid="LEV 12:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 12:3" />The boy must be circumcised when he is eight days old. <verse eid="LEV 12:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 12:4" />Then she must stay at home for 33 days in order to be made clean from her bleeding. She must not touch anything holy or go into the holy place until the days needed to make her clean are over.<verse eid="LEV 12:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 12:5" />“When a woman gives birth to a girl, she will be unclean as in her monthly period. However, she will be unclean for two weeks. Then she must stay at home for 66 days in order to be made clean from her bleeding.<verse eid="LEV 12:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 12:6" />“When the days needed to make her clean are over, she must bring a one-year-old lamb for a burnt offering and a pigeon or a mourning dove as an offering for sin. She must bring them to the priest at the entrance to the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 12:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 12:7" />The priest will offer them in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for her. Then she will be clean from her flow of blood.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 12:7">“These are the instructions for the woman who gives birth to a boy or a girl. <verse eid="LEV 12:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 12:8" />If she cannot afford a lamb, she must use two mourning doves or two pigeons. One will be the burnt offering and the other the offering for sin. So the priest will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for her, and she will be clean.”<verse eid="LEV 12:8" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 12" />
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="LEV 13" />
  <para style="s1">Skin Diseases</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 13:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses and Aaron, <verse eid="LEV 13:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 13:2" />“If anyone has a sore, a rash, or an irritated area on his skin that turns into an infectious skin disease, he must be taken to the priest Aaron or to one of his sons who are also priests. <verse eid="LEV 13:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 13:3" />The priest will examine the disease. If the hair in the diseased area has turned white, and the diseased area looks deeper than the rest of his skin, it is an infectious skin disease. When the priest has examined him, he must declare him unclean. <verse eid="LEV 13:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 13:4" />But if the irritated area is white and does not look deeper than the rest of the skin, and the hair has not turned white, the priest must put him in isolation for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 13:5" />On the seventh day the priest will examine him again. If the disease looks the same and has not spread, the priest must put him in isolation for another seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 13:6" />On the seventh day the priest will examine him again. If the diseased area has faded and not spread, the priest must declare him clean. It is only a rash. The person must wash his clothes and will be clean. <verse eid="LEV 13:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 13:7" />But if the rash has spread after he has shown himself to the priest to be declared clean, he must show himself to the priest again. <verse eid="LEV 13:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 13:8" />The priest will examine him one more time, and if the rash has spread, the priest must declare him unclean. It is an infectious skin disease.<verse eid="LEV 13:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 13:9" />“If anyone has an infectious skin disease, he must be taken to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 13:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 13:10" />The priest will examine him. If there is a white sore that has turned the hair white, and if there is raw flesh in the sore, <verse eid="LEV 13:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 13:11" />he has a chronic skin disease. Without putting him in isolation, the priest must declare him unclean because he is unclean. <verse eid="LEV 13:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 13:12" />If skin disease develops and covers the whole person from head to foot (so far as the priest can see), <verse eid="LEV 13:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 13:13" />the priest will examine him. If the disease does cover his whole body, the priest must declare the diseased person clean. His body has turned white. The person is clean. <verse eid="LEV 13:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 13:14" />But if raw flesh appears, he will be unclean. <verse eid="LEV 13:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 13:15" />The priest will examine the raw flesh and declare him unclean. The raw flesh is unclean. It is an infectious skin disease. <verse eid="LEV 13:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 13:16" />But if the raw flesh turns white again, he must go to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 13:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 13:17" />The priest will examine him again, and if the diseased area has turned white, the priest must declare the diseased person clean. He is clean.<verse eid="LEV 13:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 13:18" />“If a boil on the skin has healed <verse eid="LEV 13:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 13:19" />and in its place there is a white sore or a pink area, it must be shown to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 13:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 13:20" />The priest will examine it. If it looks deeper than the rest of the skin and its hair has turned white, the priest must declare the person unclean. An infectious skin disease has developed in the boil. <verse eid="LEV 13:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 13:21" />But if the priest examines the affected area and the hair in it is not white or the affected area is not deeper than the rest of the skin but has faded, the priest must put him in isolation for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 13:22" />If the area has spread, the priest must declare him unclean. It is a skin disease. <verse eid="LEV 13:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 13:23" />But if the irritated area has not spread, it is a scar caused by the boil. The priest must declare him clean.<verse eid="LEV 13:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 13:24" />“If anyone has a burn on his skin and the raw flesh of the burn turns into a pink or bright white area, <verse eid="LEV 13:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 13:25" />the priest will examine it. If the hair on the affected area has turned white and the affected area looks deeper than the rest of the skin, an infectious skin disease has developed in the burn. The priest must declare him unclean. It is an infectious skin disease. <verse eid="LEV 13:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 13:26" />But if the priest examines it and the hair in it is not white and the affected area is not deeper than the rest of the skin but has faded, the priest must put him in isolation for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 13:27" />On the seventh day the priest will examine him again. If the area has spread, the priest must declare him unclean. It is an infectious skin disease. <verse eid="LEV 13:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 13:28" />If the irritated area does not spread but has faded, it is only a sore caused by the burn. The priest must declare him clean, because it is a scar caused by the burn.<verse eid="LEV 13:28" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 13:29" />“If a man or a woman has some disease on the head or chin, <verse eid="LEV 13:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 13:30" />the priest will examine the disease. If it looks deeper than the rest of the skin and there is thin yellow hair on it, the priest must declare the person unclean. It is a scab, a disease on the head or the chin. <verse eid="LEV 13:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 13:31" />But if the priest examines the scabby disease and it does not look deeper than the rest of the skin and there is no black hair in it, the priest must put the person with the scabby disease in isolation for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 13:32" />On the seventh day the priest will examine the disease. If the scab has not spread, there is no yellow hair on it, and the scab does not look deeper than the rest of the skin, <verse eid="LEV 13:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 13:33" />the person will shave everything except the scab. The priest will put the person with the scab in isolation for another seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 13:34" />On the seventh day the priest will examine the scab again. If the scab has not spread on the skin and does not look deeper than the rest of the skin, the priest must declare him clean. When he has washed his clothes, he will be clean. <verse eid="LEV 13:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 13:35" />But if the scab spreads after the person has been declared clean, <verse eid="LEV 13:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 13:36" />the priest will make another examination. If the scab has spread on the skin, the priest does not have to look for yellow hair. The person is unclean. <verse eid="LEV 13:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 13:37" />But if he sees that the scab hasn’t spread and black hair grows on it, the scab is healed. The person is clean, so the priest must declare him clean.<verse eid="LEV 13:37" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 13:38" />“If a man or a woman has white irritated areas of skin, <verse eid="LEV 13:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 13:39" />the priest will make an examination. If the irritated areas on the skin are pale white, a rash has developed on the skin. The person is clean.<verse eid="LEV 13:39" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="LEV 13:40" />“If a man loses his hair, he is clean, even though he is bald. <verse eid="LEV 13:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LEV 13:41" />If he loses the hair on the front of his head, he is clean, even though he is bald on the forehead. <verse eid="LEV 13:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 13:42" />But if there is a pink patch on the bald places in back or in front, a skin disease is developing in those places. <verse eid="LEV 13:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 13:43" />The priest will examine him. If the sore from the disease in the bald places in back or in front is pink like a skin disease somewhere else on the body, <verse eid="LEV 13:43" /><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 13:44" />the man has come down with an infectious skin disease. He is unclean. The priest must declare him unclean because of the skin disease on his head.<verse eid="LEV 13:44" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="LEV 13:45" />“People who come down with a skin disease must wear torn clothes and leave their hair uncombed. They must cover their upper lips and call out, ‘Unclean, unclean!’ <verse eid="LEV 13:45" /><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LEV 13:46" />As long as they have the skin disease, they are unclean. They must live outside the camp.<verse eid="LEV 13:46" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Mildew in Clothing or Leather Articles</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="LEV 13:47" />“Now about clothing—if there is a green or red area on a piece of clothing <verse eid="LEV 13:47" /><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LEV 13:48" />that is woven or knitted from linen or wool or on any leather article, <verse eid="LEV 13:48" /><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LEV 13:49" />it is mildew. It must be shown to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 13:49" /><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LEV 13:50" />The priest will examine the mildew and will put the clothing in a separate place for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:50" /><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LEV 13:51" />On the seventh day he will examine the area again. If the spot is spreading, it is unclean. <verse eid="LEV 13:51" /><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LEV 13:52" />He must burn the piece of clothing or the leather article because the mildew is growing. <verse eid="LEV 13:52" /><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LEV 13:53" />But if the priest sees that the area has not spread, <verse eid="LEV 13:53" /><verse number="54" style="v" sid="LEV 13:54" />he must order the area to be washed and put the clothing in a separate place for seven more days. <verse eid="LEV 13:54" /><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LEV 13:55" />The priest will examine the area again after it is washed. If it doesn’t look any different and the mildew has not spread, it is still unclean. It must be burned, whether the area is on the outside or the inside. <verse eid="LEV 13:55" /><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LEV 13:56" />If the priest sees that the area is pale after washing, he will tear it out of the clothing or the leather. <verse eid="LEV 13:56" /><verse number="57" style="v" sid="LEV 13:57" />However, if it shows up again, you must burn the clothing or the leather article. <verse eid="LEV 13:57" /><verse number="58" style="v" sid="LEV 13:58" />But if the area disappears from the woven or knitted clothing or any leather article when it is washed, wash it again, and it will be clean.<verse eid="LEV 13:58" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="59" style="v" sid="LEV 13:59" />“These are the instructions for deciding whether mildew in clothing that is woven or knitted from linen or wool or in any leather article is clean or unclean.”<verse eid="LEV 13:59" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 13" />
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="LEV 14" />
  <para style="s1">Cleansing after Skin Diseases</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 14:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 14:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 14:2" />“These are the instructions for making a person clean after a skin disease. He must be taken to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 14:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 14:3" />The priest will go outside the camp and examine him. If the person is healed, <verse eid="LEV 14:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 14:4" />the priest will order someone to get two living, clean birds, some cedar wood, red yarn, and a hyssop sprig to use for the cleansing. <verse eid="LEV 14:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 14:5" />Then the priest will order someone to kill one bird over a clay bowl containing fresh water. <verse eid="LEV 14:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 14:6" />The priest will take the living bird, the cedar wood, the red yarn, and the hyssop sprig and dip them and the living bird in the blood of the bird that was killed over the fresh water. <verse eid="LEV 14:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 14:7" />He will sprinkle the blood seven times on the one to be cleansed and will declare that person clean. Then he will let the living bird fly away into the open country.<verse eid="LEV 14:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 14:8" />“The one to be cleansed must wash his clothes, shave off all his hair, and wash. Then he will be clean. After that he may go into the camp. However, for seven days he will live outside his tent. <verse eid="LEV 14:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 14:9" />On the seventh day he must shave off all the hair on his head, his beard, and his eyebrows, and he must wash his clothes and body. Then he will be clean.<verse eid="LEV 14:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 14:10" />“On the eighth day he must take two male lambs that have no defects and a one-year-old female lamb that has no defects. He must also take eight cups of flour mixed with olive oil for a grain offering along with a quart of olive oil. <verse eid="LEV 14:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 14:11" />The priest who will declare him clean must bring the person and his offerings into the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence at the entrance to the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 14:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 14:12" />The priest will take one of the male lambs and the quart of olive oil and present them to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as a guilt offering. <verse eid="LEV 14:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 14:13" />He will slaughter the lamb in the holy place where he slaughters the offering for sin and the burnt offering. He will do this because the guilt offering, like the offering for sin, belongs to the priest. It is very holy. <verse eid="LEV 14:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 14:14" />Then the priest will take some of the blood from the guilt offering and put it on the right ear lobe, on the right thumb, and on the big toe of the right foot of the one to be cleansed. <verse eid="LEV 14:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 14:15" />The priest will also take some of the olive oil and pour it into his own left hand. <verse eid="LEV 14:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 14:16" />He will dip his right finger in the oil in his left hand, and with his finger sprinkle some of the oil seven times in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence. <verse eid="LEV 14:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 14:17" />The priest will put some of the oil that is still in his hand on the right ear lobe, on the right thumb, and on the big toe of the right foot of the one to be cleansed. These are the same places he had put the blood of the guilt offering. <verse eid="LEV 14:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 14:18" />The priest will put the rest of the oil in his hand on the head of the one to be cleansed. So he will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for that person in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence. <verse eid="LEV 14:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 14:19" />The priest will also sacrifice the offering for sin to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for the one who is being cleansed from his impurity. After that, he will slaughter the burnt offering. <verse eid="LEV 14:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 14:20" />The priest will sacrifice the burnt offering and the grain offering on the altar. So the priest will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for that person, and the person who had the skin disease will be clean.<verse eid="LEV 14:20" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Cleansing for a Poor Person after a Skin Disease</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 14:21" />“But if the one to be cleansed is poor and cannot afford that much, he must take one male lamb, present it to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for himself, and use it for his guilt offering. He will take only eight cups of flour mixed with olive oil as a grain offering, a quart of olive oil, <verse eid="LEV 14:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 14:22" />and two mourning doves or two pigeons (whatever he can afford). The one will be an offering for sin and the other a burnt offering. <verse eid="LEV 14:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 14:23" />On the eighth day he will take them to the priest for his cleansing at the entrance to the tent of meeting in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence. <verse eid="LEV 14:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 14:24" />The priest will take the lamb for the guilt offering and the quart of olive oil and present them to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 14:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 14:25" />He will slaughter the lamb as a guilt offering. Then the priest will take some of the blood of the guilt offering and put it on the right ear lobe, on the right thumb, and on the big toe of the right foot of the one to be cleansed. <verse eid="LEV 14:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 14:26" />The priest will pour some of the olive oil into his own left hand. <verse eid="LEV 14:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 14:27" />With his right finger he will sprinkle some of the oil seven times in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence. <verse eid="LEV 14:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 14:28" />The priest will put some of the oil that is in his hand on the right ear lobe, on the right thumb, and on the big toe of the right foot of the one to be cleansed. These are the same places he had put the blood of the guilt offering. <verse eid="LEV 14:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 14:29" />In the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence, the priest will pour the rest of the oil in his hand on the head of the one to be cleansed in order to make a payment for him. <verse eid="LEV 14:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 14:30" />Then the one to be cleansed must take one of the mourning doves or pigeons (whichever he can afford),<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14:30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Greek, Syriac; Masoretic Text repeats “whichever he can afford.”</char></note> <verse eid="LEV 14:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 14:31" />and sacrifice it as an offering for sin. He will take the other and sacrifice it as a burnt offering together with the grain offering. So in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence the priest will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for the one who is being cleansed. <verse eid="LEV 14:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 14:32" />These are the instructions for one who has an infectious skin disease but cannot afford what is needed for his cleansing.”<verse eid="LEV 14:32" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Mildew in Houses</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 14:33" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses and Aaron, <verse eid="LEV 14:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 14:34" />“When you come to Canaan that I am going to give to you, mildew may appear in a house. <verse eid="LEV 14:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 14:35" />The owner of that house must come and tell the priest that there is something that looks like mildew in his house.<verse eid="LEV 14:35" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 14:36" />“Before the priest examines the house, he will order everything taken out of it so that nothing in the house will become unclean. Then the priest will go inside to examine the house. <verse eid="LEV 14:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 14:37" />He will examine the mildew area on the walls. If it is green and red in sunken areas that are deeper than the rest of the wall, <verse eid="LEV 14:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 14:38" />the priest will go out to the door of the house and close up the house for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 14:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 14:39" />On the seventh day the priest will go back and examine it again. If the mildew in the walls of the house has spread, <verse eid="LEV 14:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LEV 14:40" />the priest must order the stones that have the mildew to be torn out and thrown outside the city in an unclean place. <verse eid="LEV 14:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LEV 14:41" />He must have the entire inside of the house scraped. The plaster dust scraped off the walls must be dumped in an unclean place outside the city. <verse eid="LEV 14:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 14:42" />The stones must be replaced, and the house must be plastered again. <verse eid="LEV 14:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 14:43" />If the mildew develops again in the house after all this, <verse eid="LEV 14:43" /><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 14:44" />the priest will examine it one more time. If it is a spreading type of mildew, the house is unclean. <verse eid="LEV 14:44" /><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LEV 14:45" />The house—stones, wood, and all the plaster—must be torn down and taken to an unclean place outside the city. <verse eid="LEV 14:45" /><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LEV 14:46" />Whoever goes into the house any time it is closed up will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 14:46" /><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LEV 14:47" />Whoever sleeps or eats in the house must wash his clothes. <verse eid="LEV 14:47" /><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LEV 14:48" />But if the priest comes and makes an examination and the mildew has not spread in the house after it is plastered again, the priest must declare the house clean. The mildew is gone.<verse eid="LEV 14:48" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="LEV 14:49" />“The priest must take two birds, cedar wood, red yarn, and a hyssop sprig and use them to make the house clean. <verse eid="LEV 14:49" /><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LEV 14:50" />He must kill the one bird over a clay bowl containing fresh water. <verse eid="LEV 14:50" /><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LEV 14:51" />He must take the cedar wood, the hyssop sprig, the red yarn, and the living bird and dip them in the fresh water containing the blood of the bird that was killed. He must sprinkle the house seven times. <verse eid="LEV 14:51" /><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LEV 14:52" />So he must use the bird’s blood, the fresh water, the living bird, the cedar wood, the hyssop, and the red yarn to make the house clean. <verse eid="LEV 14:52" /><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LEV 14:53" />Then he will let the living bird fly from the city into the open country. He will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for the house, and it will be clean.<verse eid="LEV 14:53" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="LEV 14:54" />“These are the instructions for any kind of mildew or fungus <verse eid="LEV 14:54" /><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LEV 14:55" />that infects clothing or houses <verse eid="LEV 14:55" /><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LEV 14:56" />and for skin diseases where there is a sore, a rash, or an irritated area. <verse eid="LEV 14:56" /><verse number="57" style="v" sid="LEV 14:57" />These instructions for skin diseases and mildew help you distinguish between what is clean and what is unclean.”<verse eid="LEV 14:57" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 14" />
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="LEV 15" />
  <para style="s1">Bodily Discharges from Men</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 15:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses and Aaron, <verse eid="LEV 15:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 15:2" />“Tell the Israelites: If a man has a discharge from his penis, his discharge is unclean. <verse eid="LEV 15:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 15:3" />He is unclean because of the discharge from his penis. Whether it is chronic or not makes no difference; he is still unclean.<verse eid="LEV 15:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 15:4" />“The man who has a discharge makes everything he lies on or sits on unclean. <verse eid="LEV 15:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 15:5" />Those who touch his bed must wash their clothes and their bodies. They will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 15:6" />Those who sit on anything he sat on must wash their clothes and their bodies. They will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 15:7" />Those who touch a man who has a discharge must wash their clothes and their bodies. They will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 15:8" />If a man who has a discharge spits on anyone who is clean, the person he spits on must wash his clothes and his body. He will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 15:9" />When a man who has a discharge sits on a saddle, it becomes unclean. <verse eid="LEV 15:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 15:10" />Those who carry such things must wash their clothes and their bodies. They will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 15:11" />If a man who has a discharge touches anyone without first rinsing his hands, the person he touched must wash his clothes and his body. He will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 15:12" />When a man who has a discharge touches pottery, it must be broken, and any wooden bucket he touches must be rinsed.<verse eid="LEV 15:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 15:13" />“When a man’s discharge stops, he must wait seven days to be cleansed. He must wash his clothes and his body in fresh water. Then he will be clean. <verse eid="LEV 15:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 15:14" />On the eighth day he must take two mourning doves or two pigeons and come into the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence at the entrance to the tent of meeting. He will give these birds to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 15:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 15:15" />The priest will sacrifice one as an offering for sin and the other as a burnt offering. So in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence, the priest will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for the man who had a discharge.<verse eid="LEV 15:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 15:16" />“If a man has an emission of semen, he must bathe his whole body. He will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 15:17" />Any clothes or any leather with semen on it must be washed. It will be unclean until evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 15:18" />“When a man has sexual intercourse with a woman and has an emission of semen, they must wash themselves. They will be unclean until evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:18" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Bodily Discharges from Women</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 15:19" />“When a woman has her monthly period, she will be unclean for seven days. Those who touch her will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 15:20" />Everything she lies on or sits on during her period will be unclean. <verse eid="LEV 15:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 15:21" />Those who touch her bed must wash their clothes and their bodies. They will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 15:22" />Those who touch anything she sits on must wash their clothes and their bodies. They will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 15:23" />If her blood touches anything on the bed or anything she sits on, it will be unclean until evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 15:24" />If a man has sexual intercourse with her while she has her period, he will be unclean for seven days. Any bed he lies on will become unclean.<verse eid="LEV 15:24" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 15:25" />“If a woman has a discharge of blood for many days other than her monthly period, she is unclean. If her period lasts longer than usual, she will be unclean as long as she has a discharge. It is like her period. <verse eid="LEV 15:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 15:26" />As long as she has a discharge, any bed she lies on or anything she sits on is unclean. It is like her period. <verse eid="LEV 15:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 15:27" />Those who touch these things are unclean and must wash their clothes and their bodies. They will be unclean until evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:27" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 15:28" />“When her discharge stops, she must wait seven days. After that, she will be clean. <verse eid="LEV 15:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 15:29" />On the eighth day she must take two mourning doves or two pigeons and bring them to the priest at the entrance to the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 15:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 15:30" />The priest will offer one as an offering for sin and the other as a burnt offering. So in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence the priest will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for the woman who had an unclean discharge.<verse eid="LEV 15:30" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 15:31" />“You must separate the Israelites from anything that keeps them from being presentable to me. Otherwise, they will die because they make my tent, which is among them, unclean.<verse eid="LEV 15:31" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 15:32" />“These are the instructions for any man who has a discharge or an emission of semen that makes him unclean, <verse eid="LEV 15:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 15:33" />for any woman who has her period, for any man or woman who has a discharge, or for any man who has sexual intercourse with a woman when she is unclean.”<verse eid="LEV 15:33" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 15" />
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="LEV 16" />
  <para style="s1">The Day for Making Peace with the <char style="nd">LORD</char></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 16:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses after Aaron’s two sons had come into the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence and died. <verse eid="LEV 16:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 16:2" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> said, “Tell your brother Aaron that he cannot go into the holy place whenever he wants to. If he goes up to the canopy and stands in front of the throne of mercy on the ark, he will die, because I appear in the smoke above the throne of mercy.<verse eid="LEV 16:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 16:3" />“This is what Aaron must do in order to come into the holy place: He must take a bull as an offering for sin and a ram as a burnt offering. <verse eid="LEV 16:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 16:4" />He must put on a holy linen robe and wear linen undergarments. He must wear a linen belt and turban. These are holy clothes. He must wash his body and put them on. <verse eid="LEV 16:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 16:5" />He will take two male goats from the congregation of Israel as an offering for sin and a ram as a burnt offering.<verse eid="LEV 16:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 16:6" />“Aaron must sacrifice the bull as his own offering for sin. By doing this, he will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for himself and his family. <verse eid="LEV 16:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 16:7" />He must take the two male goats and bring them into the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence at the entrance to the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 16:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 16:8" />Then Aaron must throw lots for the two goats. One lot will be for the <char style="nd">Lord</char> and the other for Azazel.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16:8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Unknown Hebrew term.</char></note> <verse eid="LEV 16:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 16:9" />Aaron must sacrifice the goat chosen by lot for the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as an offering for sin. <verse eid="LEV 16:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 16:10" />But he must bring the goat chosen by lot for Azazel into the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence. He will release it in the desert to Azazel in order to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for himself and his family.<verse eid="LEV 16:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 16:11" />“Aaron will bring the bull. He will then slaughter it as his own offering for sin. By doing this he will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for himself and his family. <verse eid="LEV 16:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 16:12" />He will take an incense burner full of burning coals from the altar, which is in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence, and two handfuls of finely ground, sweet-smelling incense. He will bring them up to the canopy. <verse eid="LEV 16:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 16:13" />Then he will put the incense on the fire in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence. The cloud of incense will cover the throne of mercy, which is over the words of God’s promise, so that he will not die. <verse eid="LEV 16:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 16:14" />He will take some of the bull’s blood and sprinkle it with his finger on the east side of the throne of mercy. Then he will sprinkle some of the blood with his finger seven times in front of the throne of mercy.<verse eid="LEV 16:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 16:15" />“Next, Aaron will slaughter the goat for the people’s offering for sin. He will take the blood inside, go up to the canopy, and sprinkle it on the throne of mercy and in front of it, as he did with the bull’s blood. <verse eid="LEV 16:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 16:16" />So he will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for all the sins the Israelites committed against the holy place. These sins happened because the Israelites were unclean and because they committed rebellious acts. He will do the same for the tent of meeting which is among an unclean people. <verse eid="LEV 16:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 16:17" />No one may be in the tent of meeting from the time Aaron enters the holy place to do this until he comes out. Aaron will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for his own sins, his family’s sins, and the sins of the entire assembly of Israel. <verse eid="LEV 16:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 16:18" />Then he will go out to the altar that is in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence and make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> there for the sins committed. He will take some of the blood from the bull and some of the goat’s blood and put it all around the horns of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 16:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 16:19" />With his finger he will sprinkle some of the blood on it seven times. Because the Israelites made it unclean, he will cleanse it and declare it holy.<verse eid="LEV 16:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 16:20" />“When he finishes making peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> at the holy place, the tent of meeting, and the altar, he will bring the living goat forward. <verse eid="LEV 16:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 16:21" />Aaron will place both hands on its head. He will confess over it all the sins, all the rebellious acts, and all the things the Israelites did wrong. He will transfer them to the goat’s head. A man will be appointed to release the goat in the desert. <verse eid="LEV 16:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 16:22" />The goat will take all their sins away to a deserted place. The man must release the goat in the desert.<verse eid="LEV 16:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 16:23" />“Then Aaron will go to the tent of meeting, take off the linen clothes he had put on to go into the holy place, and leave them there. <verse eid="LEV 16:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 16:24" />He will wash his body in the holy place and put on his other clothes. Then he will come out and sacrifice the burnt offering for himself and for the people to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for his own sins and the sins of the people. <verse eid="LEV 16:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 16:25" />He will burn the fat of the offering for sin on the altar.<verse eid="LEV 16:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 16:26" />“The man who released the goat to Azazel must wash his clothes and his body. Then he may return to the camp. <verse eid="LEV 16:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 16:27" />He must take the bull and the goat outside the camp. These animals were the offering for sin whose blood was brought into the holy place to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for sins. The skin, meat, and excrement from the animals must be burned. <verse eid="LEV 16:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 16:28" />Whoever burns them must wash his clothes and his body. Then he may return to the camp.<verse eid="LEV 16:28" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 16:29" />“This will be a permanent law for you: On the tenth day of the seventh month both native Israelites and foreigners must humble themselves. They must do no work. <verse eid="LEV 16:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 16:30" />On this day Aaron will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> to make you clean. Then you will be clean from all your sins in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence. <verse eid="LEV 16:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 16:31" />This is the most important worship festival there is for you. You will humble yourselves. It is a permanent law. <verse eid="LEV 16:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 16:32" />The priest who is anointed and ordained to serve as chief priest in his father’s place will pay for sins. He will put on the holy linen clothes <verse eid="LEV 16:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 16:33" />and will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> at the holy place, the tent of meeting, and the altar. He will make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for the priests and all the worshipers.<verse eid="LEV 16:33" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 16:34" />“This permanent law tells you how to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> once a year for all the sins the Israelites committed.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 16:34">Aaron did as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> had commanded Moses.<verse eid="LEV 16:34" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 16" />
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="LEV 17" />
  <para style="s1">Eating Sacrifices</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 17:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 17:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 17:2" />“Tell Aaron, his sons, and all the Israelites that this is what the <char style="nd">Lord</char> has commanded: <verse eid="LEV 17:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 17:3" />Any Israelite who slaughters a bull, sheep, or goat inside or outside the camp <verse eid="LEV 17:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 17:4" />is guilty of bloodshed. He has shed blood and must be excluded from the people. Bring the animal to the entrance of the tent of meeting. Offer it to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> in front of the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s tent. <verse eid="LEV 17:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 17:5" /><char style="add">⌞This means⌟</char> that the people of Israel must take the sacrifices they have been making in the open fields and bring them to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They must bring them to the priest at the entrance to the tent of meeting. The people will sacrifice them as fellowship offerings to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 17:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 17:6" />The priest will pour the blood against the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s altar at the entrance to the tent of meeting. He will burn the fat as a soothing aroma to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 17:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 17:7" />The people must stop sacrificing to goat idols and chasing after them as though they were prostitutes. This is a permanent law for the people and for future generations.<verse eid="LEV 17:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 17:8" />“Tell them: If Israelites or foreigners make burnt offerings or sacrifices <verse eid="LEV 17:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 17:9" />but do not bring them to the entrance of the tent of meeting to offer them to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, they must be excluded from the people.<verse eid="LEV 17:9" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Eating Blood</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 17:10" />“If Israelites or foreigners eat any blood, I will condemn them and exclude them from the people, <verse eid="LEV 17:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 17:11" />because blood contains life. I have given this blood to you to make peace with me on the altar. Blood is needed to make peace with me. <verse eid="LEV 17:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 17:12" />That is why I have said to the people of Israel: Neither you nor foreigners should ever eat blood.<verse eid="LEV 17:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 17:13" />“If Israelites or foreigners hunt any animal or bird that may be eaten, they must pour out the animal’s blood and cover it with dirt. <verse eid="LEV 17:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 17:14" />This is because the life of any creature is in its blood. So I have said to the people of Israel: Never eat any blood, because the life of any creature is in its blood. Whoever eats blood must be excluded <char style="add">⌞from the people⌟</char>.<verse eid="LEV 17:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 17:15" />“Native Israelites or foreigners who eat the body of an animal that dies naturally or is killed by another animal must wash their clothes and their bodies. They will be unclean until evening. Then they will be clean. <verse eid="LEV 17:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 17:16" />If they don’t wash their clothes and their bodies, they will be guilty of sin.”<verse eid="LEV 17:16" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 17" />
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="LEV 18" />
  <para style="s1">Forbidden Sexual Practices</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 18:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 18:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 18:2" />“Tell the Israelites: I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="LEV 18:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 18:3" />You used to live in Egypt. Don’t live the way the Egyptians do. I am bringing you to Canaan. Don’t live the way the Canaanites do. Never live by their standards. <verse eid="LEV 18:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 18:4" />Follow my rules, and live by my standards. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="LEV 18:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 18:5" />Live by my standards, and obey my rules. You will have life through them. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 18:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 18:6" />“Never have sexual intercourse with anyone related to you by blood. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 18:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 18:7" />“Never have sexual intercourse with your mother. She is your own mother. Never have sexual intercourse with her. <verse eid="LEV 18:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 18:8" />Never have sexual intercourse with your stepmother. She is related to you through your father. <verse eid="LEV 18:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 18:9" />Never have sexual intercourse with your stepsister, whether she is your father’s daughter or your mother’s daughter. It makes no difference whether or not she was born in your house. <verse eid="LEV 18:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 18:10" />Never have sexual intercourse with your granddaughter, whether she is your son’s daughter or your daughter’s daughter, because she is related to you. <verse eid="LEV 18:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 18:11" />Never have sexual intercourse with a daughter of your father and his wife. She is your own sister. <verse eid="LEV 18:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 18:12" />Never have sexual intercourse with your father’s sister. She is your paternal aunt. <verse eid="LEV 18:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 18:13" />Never have sexual intercourse with your mother’s sister. She is your maternal aunt. <verse eid="LEV 18:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 18:14" />Never have sexual intercourse with the wife of your father’s brother. She, too, is your aunt. <verse eid="LEV 18:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 18:15" />Never have sexual intercourse with your daughter-in-law. She is your son’s wife. Never have sexual intercourse with her. <verse eid="LEV 18:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 18:16" />Never have sexual intercourse with your sister-in-law. She is your brother’s wife. <verse eid="LEV 18:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 18:17" />Never have sexual intercourse with a woman and her daughter or a woman and her granddaughter. They are related. Doing this is perverted. <verse eid="LEV 18:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 18:18" />While your wife is living, never marry her sister as a rival wife and have sexual intercourse with her.<verse eid="LEV 18:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 18:19" />“Never have sexual intercourse with a woman while she is unclean during her monthly period. <verse eid="LEV 18:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 18:20" />Never have sexual intercourse with your neighbor’s wife and become unclean with her. <verse eid="LEV 18:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 18:21" />Never give your children as sacrifices to the god Molech <char style="add">⌞by burning them alive⌟</char>. If you do, you are dishonoring the name of your God. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 18:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 18:22" />Never have sexual intercourse with a man as with a woman. It is disgusting. <verse eid="LEV 18:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 18:23" />Never have sexual intercourse with any animal and become unclean with it. A woman must never offer herself to an animal for sexual intercourse. It is unnatural.<verse eid="LEV 18:23" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Punishment for Sexual Sins</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 18:24" />“Do not become unclean in any of these ways. By these practices all the nations which I am forcing out of your way have become unclean. <verse eid="LEV 18:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 18:25" />The land has become unclean. I will punish it for its sins. The land will vomit out those who live in it. <verse eid="LEV 18:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 18:26" />Live by my standards, and obey my rules. Neither you nor any foreigner should ever do any of these disgusting things. <verse eid="LEV 18:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 18:27" />The people of the land who were there before you did all these disgusting things. As a result, the land has become unclean. <verse eid="LEV 18:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 18:28" />If you make the land unclean, it will vomit you out as it has vomited out the people who were there before you. <verse eid="LEV 18:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 18:29" />Whoever does any of these disgusting things must be excluded from the people. <verse eid="LEV 18:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 18:30" />So you must follow my instructions. Don’t live by the standards of the people who lived there before you. What they do is disgusting. Never become unclean that way. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.”<verse eid="LEV 18:30" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 18" />
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="LEV 19" />
  <para style="s1">Duties of the People Toward God</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 19:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 19:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 19:2" />“Tell the whole congregation of Israel: Be holy because I, the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God, am holy.<verse eid="LEV 19:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 19:3" />“Respect your mother and father. Observe my days of rest as holy days. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 19:4" />“Don’t turn to worthless gods or cast metal idols. Never make any gods for yourselves. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 19:5" />“When you bring a fellowship offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, sacrifice it <char style="add">⌞properly⌟</char> so that you will be accepted. <verse eid="LEV 19:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 19:6" />Eat your sacrifice on the day you bring it and on the next day. On the third day burn whatever is left over. <verse eid="LEV 19:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 19:7" />If you eat any of it on the third day, it is repulsive and will not be accepted. <verse eid="LEV 19:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 19:8" />Those who eat it will be punished because they have dishonored what is holy to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. They must be excluded from the people.<verse eid="LEV 19:8" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Duties of the People Toward Each Other</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 19:9" />“When you harvest the grain in your land, don’t harvest the grain in the corners of your fields or gather what is left after you’re finished. <verse eid="LEV 19:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 19:10" />Don’t harvest your vineyard a second time or pick up fallen grapes. Leave them for poor people and foreigners. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 19:11" />“Never steal, lie, or deceive your neighbor.<verse eid="LEV 19:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 19:12" />“Never swear by my name in order to deceive anyone. This dishonors the name of your God. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 19:13" />“Never oppress or rob your neighbor. Never keep the pay you owe a hired worker overnight. <verse eid="LEV 19:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 19:14" />Never curse deaf people or put anything in the way of blind people to make them stumble. Instead, fear your God. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 19:15" />“Don’t be corrupt when administering justice. Never give special favors to poor people, and never show preference to important people. Judge your neighbor fairly. <verse eid="LEV 19:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 19:16" />Never gossip. Never endanger your neighbor’s life. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 19:17" />“Never hate another Israelite. Be sure to correct your neighbor so that you will not be guilty of sinning along with him. <verse eid="LEV 19:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 19:18" />Never get revenge. Never hold a grudge against any of your people. Instead, love your neighbor as you love yourself. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:18" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Other Duties</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 19:19" />“Obey my laws. Never crossbreed different kinds of animals. Never plant two kinds of crops in your field. Never wear clothes made from two kinds of material.<verse eid="LEV 19:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 19:20" />“If a man has sexual intercourse with a female slave who is engaged to another man and if her freedom was never bought or given to her, they should not be put to death. He will only pay a fine because she is a slave. <verse eid="LEV 19:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 19:21" />He must bring a ram for his guilt offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> at the entrance to the tent of meeting. <verse eid="LEV 19:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 19:22" />In the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence the priest will use them to make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for this sin. The man will be forgiven for this sin.<verse eid="LEV 19:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 19:23" />“When you come into the land and plant all kinds of fruit trees, you must not eat the fruit for <char style="add">⌞the first⌟</char> three years. <verse eid="LEV 19:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 19:24" />In the fourth year all the fruit will be a holy offering of praise to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 19:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 19:25" />In the fifth year you may eat the fruit. Do this to make the trees produce more for you. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 19:26" />“Never eat any meat with blood still in it.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:26">“Never cast evil spells, and never consult fortunetellers.<verse eid="LEV 19:26" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 19:27" />“Never shave the hair on your foreheads, and never cut the edges of your beard. <verse eid="LEV 19:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 19:28" />Never slash your body to mourn the dead, and never get a tattoo. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:28" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 19:29" />“Never dishonor your daughter by making her a prostitute, or the country will turn to prostitution and be filled with people who are perverted.<verse eid="LEV 19:29" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 19:30" />“Observe my days of rest as holy days and respect my holy tent. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:30" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 19:31" />“Don’t turn to psychics or mediums to get help. That will make you unclean. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:31" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 19:32" />“Show respect to the elderly, and honor older people. In this way you show respect for your God. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:32" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 19:33" />“Never mistreat a foreigner living in your land. <verse eid="LEV 19:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 19:34" />Foreigners living among you will be like your own people. Love them as you love yourself, because you were foreigners living in Egypt. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:34" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 19:35" />“Don’t be corrupt when administering justice concerning length, weight, or measuring liquid. <verse eid="LEV 19:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 19:36" />Use honest scales, honest weights, and honest measures. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God who brought you out of Egypt.<verse eid="LEV 19:36" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 19:37" />“Obey all my laws and all my rules, and live by them. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.”<verse eid="LEV 19:37" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 19" />
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="LEV 20" />
  <para style="s1">Punishment for Serious Crimes</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 20:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 20:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 20:2" />“Tell the Israelites: If Israelites or foreigners living among you give one of their children as a sacrifice to <char style="add">⌞the god⌟</char> Molech, they must be put to death. The common people must stone them to death. <verse eid="LEV 20:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 20:3" />I will condemn them and exclude them from the people. They gave one of their children to Molech, made my holy tent unclean, and dishonored my holy name. <verse eid="LEV 20:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 20:4" />If the common people ignore those who give their children to Molech and do not put them to death, <verse eid="LEV 20:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 20:5" />I will condemn them and their families. I will exclude them from the people. I will exclude from the people everyone who chases after Molech as if he were a prostitute.<verse eid="LEV 20:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 20:6" />“I will condemn people who turn to mediums and psychics and chase after them as though they were prostitutes. I will exclude them from the people.<verse eid="LEV 20:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 20:7" />“Live holy lives. Be holy because I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="LEV 20:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 20:8" />Obey my laws, and live by them. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> who sets you apart as holy.<verse eid="LEV 20:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 20:9" />“Whoever curses his father or mother must be put to death. He has cursed his father or mother and deserves to die.<verse eid="LEV 20:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 20:10" />“If a man commits adultery with another man’s wife or with his neighbor’s wife, both he and the woman must be put to death for their adultery. <verse eid="LEV 20:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 20:11" />Whoever has sexual intercourse with his father’s wife has violated his father’s marriage. Both he and his father’s wife must be put to death. They deserve to die. <verse eid="LEV 20:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 20:12" />If a man has sexual intercourse with his daughter-in-law, both of them must be put to death. They have done a disgusting thing and deserve to die. <verse eid="LEV 20:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 20:13" />When a man has sexual intercourse with another man as with a woman, both men are doing something disgusting and must be put to death. They deserve to die. <verse eid="LEV 20:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 20:14" />When a man marries a woman and her mother, they have done a perverted thing. The man and the two women must be burned. Never do this perverted thing. <verse eid="LEV 20:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 20:15" />A man who has sexual intercourse with an animal must be put to death. You must kill the animal, too. <verse eid="LEV 20:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 20:16" />When a woman offers herself sexually to any animal, you must kill both the woman and the animal. They must be put to death. They deserve to die. <verse eid="LEV 20:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 20:17" />Whoever takes his sister, his father’s daughter or his mother’s daughter, and has sexual intercourse does a shameful thing. They both must be publicly excluded from the people. He has had sexual intercourse with his sister and must be punished. <verse eid="LEV 20:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 20:18" />If a man has sexual intercourse with a woman while she has her monthly period, both of them have had sexual intercourse in blood. They must be excluded from the people. <verse eid="LEV 20:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 20:19" />Never have sexual intercourse with your mother’s sister or your father’s sister. Whoever has sexual intercourse with a close relative must be punished. <verse eid="LEV 20:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 20:20" />Whoever has sexual intercourse with his uncle’s wife violates his uncle’s marriage. That man and woman are guilty of sin. They will die without children. <verse eid="LEV 20:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 20:21" />Whoever marries his brother’s wife violates his brother’s marriage and does an unclean thing. That man and woman will have no children.<verse eid="LEV 20:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 20:22" />“If you carefully obey all my laws and my rules, the land I am bringing you to live in will not vomit you out. <verse eid="LEV 20:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 20:23" />Never follow the practices of the people I am forcing out of your way. I cannot stand them because they did all these things. <verse eid="LEV 20:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 20:24" />I have told you that you will take their land. I will give it to you as your own. It is a land flowing with milk and honey. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God who separated you from other people. <verse eid="LEV 20:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 20:25" />Separate clean and unclean <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20:25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">“</char><char style="fk" closed="false">Clean</char><char style="ft" closed="false">” refers to anything that is presentable to God. “</char><char style="fk" closed="false">Unclean</char><char style="ft" closed="false">” refers to anything that is not presentable to God.</char></note> animals and birds. Never become disgusting by eating any animal or bird or anything that crawls on the ground. I have separated you from every unclean thing. <verse eid="LEV 20:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 20:26" />Be my holy people because I, the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, am holy. I have separated you from other people to be my very own.<verse eid="LEV 20:26" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 20:27" />“Every man or woman who is a medium or a psychic must be put to death. They must be stoned to death because they deserve to die.”<verse eid="LEV 20:27" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 20" />
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="LEV 21" />
  <para style="s1">Holiness for All the Priests</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 21:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, “Tell the priests, Aaron’s sons: None of you should become unclean by touching one of your relatives who has died. <verse eid="LEV 21:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 21:2" />However, you are allowed to become unclean when one of your nearest relatives dies. These relatives include your mother, father, son, daughter, or brother, <verse eid="LEV 21:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 21:3" />and especially an unmarried virgin sister who is still close to you. <verse eid="LEV 21:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 21:4" />As the head of your people, you should never become unclean. That would make you unholy.<verse eid="LEV 21:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 21:5" />“You should never mourn by shaving bald spots on your heads, shaving the edges of your beards, or slashing your bodies.<verse eid="LEV 21:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 21:6" />“Be God’s holy men, and don’t dishonor the name of your God. Be holy because you bring sacrifices by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It is the food of your God. <verse eid="LEV 21:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 21:7" />You should never marry prostitutes, those who have lost their virginity, or divorced women because a priest is God’s holy man. <verse eid="LEV 21:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 21:8" />Be holy because you offer the food of your God. Be holy because I, the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, am holy. I set you apart as holy. <verse eid="LEV 21:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 21:9" />When a priest’s daughter dishonors herself by becoming a prostitute, she dishonors her father. She must be burned.<verse eid="LEV 21:9" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Holiness for the Chief Priest</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 21:10" />“The priest who is anointed with oil and wears the chief priest’s clothes is chief over his brothers. He must never mourn by leaving his hair uncombed or by tearing his clothes. <verse eid="LEV 21:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 21:11" />He must never go near any dead bodies or become unclean, even for his father or mother. <verse eid="LEV 21:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 21:12" />He must not leave the holy tent of his God. If he does, he will be dishonoring it, because he is dedicated with the anointing oil of his God. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 21:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 21:13" />“The anointed priest must marry a virgin. <verse eid="LEV 21:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 21:14" />He must never marry a widow, a divorced woman, a woman who has lost her virginity, or a prostitute. He may only marry a virgin from his own people. <verse eid="LEV 21:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 21:15" />He must not dishonor his children among his people because I, the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, set him apart as holy.”<verse eid="LEV 21:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 21:16" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 21:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 21:17" />“Tell Aaron: If any of your descendants (now or in future generations) has a physical defect, he must never bring food to offer to God. <verse eid="LEV 21:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 21:18" />Indeed, no one who has a physical defect may ever come near <char style="add">⌞the altar⌟</char>. That means anyone who is blind or lame, who has a disfigured face, a deformity, <verse eid="LEV 21:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 21:19" />or a crippled hand or foot, <verse eid="LEV 21:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 21:20" />who is a hunchback or dwarf, who has defective sight, skin diseases, or crushed testicles. <verse eid="LEV 21:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 21:21" />If a descendant of the priest Aaron has a physical defect, he must never bring sacrifices by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. He has a defect. He must never bring food to offer to God. <verse eid="LEV 21:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 21:22" />He may eat the food of his God—what is holy and what is very holy. <verse eid="LEV 21:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 21:23" />However, he must never come up to the canopy or to the altar, since he has a physical defect. He must never dishonor the holy places because I, the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, set them apart as holy.”<verse eid="LEV 21:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 21:24" />So Moses spoke to Aaron and his sons and to all the Israelites.<verse eid="LEV 21:24" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 21" />
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="LEV 22" />
  <para style="s1">Eating the Priests’ Share of the Sacrifice</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 22:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 22:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 22:2" />“Tell Aaron and his sons that they must respect the holy offerings which the Israelites set apart for me. In this way they will not dishonor my holy name. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 22:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 22:3" />“Tell them: In future generations if any of your descendants, while unclean, comes near the holy offerings the Israelites set apart for the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, that person must be excluded from my presence. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 22:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 22:4" />“No descendant of Aaron who has a skin disease or a discharge may eat any of the holy offerings until he is clean. Any person who has an emission of semen or touches a dead body, <verse eid="LEV 22:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 22:5" />an unclean swarming creature or an unclean person <verse eid="LEV 22:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 22:6" />will be unclean until evening. He must not eat any of the holy offerings unless he has washed himself. <verse eid="LEV 22:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 22:7" />When the sun has set, he will be clean. Then he may eat the holy offerings because they are his food. <verse eid="LEV 22:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 22:8" />He must never eat the meat of an animal that dies naturally or is killed by wild animals. It will make him unclean. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 22:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 22:9" />The priests must do what I order, or their sin will bring them death because they dishonored a holy offering. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, who sets them apart as holy.<verse eid="LEV 22:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 22:10" />“Laypeople must never eat any holy offering, even if they are visiting a priest or are working for him. <verse eid="LEV 22:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 22:11" />But if a priest buys a slave, the slave and anyone born in his household may eat the priest’s food. <verse eid="LEV 22:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 22:12" />However, if a priest’s daughter marries a layman, she must never eat the food taken from the holy contributions. <verse eid="LEV 22:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 22:13" />If a priest’s daughter is widowed or divorced, doesn’t have any children, and comes back to live in her father’s home, she may eat her father’s food. But a layperson must never eat it.<verse eid="LEV 22:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 22:14" />“Those who eat a holy offering by mistake must give another holy offering to the priest and add one-fifth more to it. <verse eid="LEV 22:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 22:15" />Priests must not dishonor the holy offerings that the Israelites contribute to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 22:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 22:16" />They must make those people pay the penalty for their guilt because they have eaten the priests’ holy offerings. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, who sets them apart as holy.”<verse eid="LEV 22:16" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Animals Accepted for Sacrifice</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 22:17" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 22:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 22:18" />“Tell Aaron, his sons, and all the Israelites: Israelites or foreigners may bring burnt offerings to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for anything they vowed or as freewill offerings. <verse eid="LEV 22:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 22:19" />The offering must be a male that has no defects from your cattle, sheep, or goats in order to be accepted. <verse eid="LEV 22:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 22:20" />Never bring any animal with a physical defect, because it will not be accepted on your behalf. <verse eid="LEV 22:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 22:21" />A person may bring the <char style="nd">Lord</char> a fellowship offering to fulfill a vow or for a freewill offering. Whether it is from the cattle, sheep, or goats, it must be an animal that has no defects in order to be accepted. It must never be an animal that has defects. <verse eid="LEV 22:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 22:22" />Never bring the <char style="nd">Lord</char> an animal that is blind, has broken bones, cuts, warts, scabs, or ringworm. Never give the <char style="nd">Lord</char> any of these in a sacrifice by fire on the altar. <verse eid="LEV 22:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 22:23" />You may use a bull or a sheep with a deformity or one that is stunted in growth as a freewill offering. However, it will not be accepted for a vow. <verse eid="LEV 22:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 22:24" />Never bring the <char style="nd">Lord</char> an animal that has bruised, crushed, torn out, or cut out testicles. Never do any of these things to an animal in your land. <verse eid="LEV 22:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 22:25" />Never bring any kind of castrated animal received from a foreigner as a food offering for your God. A castrated animal will not be accepted on your behalf because castration is a physical defect.”<verse eid="LEV 22:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 22:26" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 22:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 22:27" />“When a calf, a lamb, or a goat is born, it must stay with its mother for seven days. From the eighth day on it may be accepted as a sacrifice by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 22:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 22:28" />Never slaughter a cow or a sheep and its young the same day.<verse eid="LEV 22:28" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 22:29" />“When you sacrifice a thank offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, do it in the proper way. <verse eid="LEV 22:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 22:30" />Eat it the same day. Never leave any of it until morning. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 22:30" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 22:31" />“Carefully obey my commands. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 22:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 22:32" />Never dishonor my holy name. I will show my holiness among the Israelites. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, who sets you apart as holy. <verse eid="LEV 22:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 22:33" />I brought you out of Egypt to be your God. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.”<verse eid="LEV 22:33" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 22" />
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="LEV 23" />
  <para style="s1">The Day of Rest and Other Holy Assemblies</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 23:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 23:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 23:2" />“Tell the Israelites: These are the appointed festivals with the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, which you must announce as holy assemblies. <verse eid="LEV 23:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 23:3" />You may work for six days. But the seventh day is a day of rest, a day when you don’t work, a holy assembly. Don’t do any work. It is the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s day of rest—a holy day wherever you live.<verse eid="LEV 23:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 23:4" />“The following are the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s appointed festivals with holy assemblies, which you must announce at their appointed times.<verse eid="LEV 23:4" /></para>
  <para style="s1">The Spring Festivals</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 23:5" />“The fourteenth day of the first month, in the evening, is the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s Passover. <verse eid="LEV 23:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 23:6" />The fifteenth day of this same month is the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s Festival of Unleavened Bread. For seven days you must eat unleavened bread. <verse eid="LEV 23:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 23:7" />On the first day there will be a holy assembly. Don’t do any regular work. <verse eid="LEV 23:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 23:8" />Bring the <char style="nd">Lord</char> a sacrifice by fire for seven days. On the seventh day there will be a holy assembly. Don’t do any regular work.”<verse eid="LEV 23:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 23:9" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 23:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 23:10" />“Tell the Israelites: When you come to the land I am going to give you and you harvest grain, bring the priest a bundle of the first grain you harvest. <verse eid="LEV 23:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 23:11" />He will present it to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> so that you will be accepted. He will present it on the day after Passover. <verse eid="LEV 23:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 23:12" />On the day you present the bundle, you must sacrifice a one-year-old male lamb that has no defects as a burnt offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 23:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 23:13" />Bring a grain offering of four quarts of flour mixed with olive oil with it. This will be a sacrifice by fire made to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, a soothing aroma. Use one quart of wine for the wine offering. <verse eid="LEV 23:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 23:14" />Don’t eat bread, roasted grain, or fresh grain until this same day, when you bring the offering to your God. It is a permanent law for generations to come wherever you live.<verse eid="LEV 23:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 23:15" />“Count seven full weeks from the day after Passover (the day you bring the bundle of grain as an offering presented to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>) <verse eid="LEV 23:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 23:16" />until the day after the seventh week. This is a total of fifty days. Then bring a new grain offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 23:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 23:17" />Bring two loaves of bread from your homes to present to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Bake them with four quarts of flour. They are the first harvested grain for the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 23:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 23:18" />With the bread bring seven one-year-old lambs that have no defects, one bull, and two rams. They will be a burnt offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. With these offerings also bring grain and wine offerings. They will be a sacrifice by fire, a soothing aroma to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 23:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 23:19" />Also sacrifice one male goat as an offering for sin and two one-year-old lambs as a fellowship offering. <verse eid="LEV 23:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 23:20" />The priest must present them along with the bread of the first harvested grain as an offering to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. All this, along with the two lambs, will be holy and will belong to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s priests. <verse eid="LEV 23:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 23:21" />Make an announcement that there will be a holy assembly on that same day. Don’t do any regular work. It is a permanent law for generations to come wherever you live.<verse eid="LEV 23:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 23:22" />“When you harvest the grain in your land, don’t harvest the grain in the corners of your fields or gather what is left after you’re finished. Leave it for poor people and foreigners. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.”<verse eid="LEV 23:22" /></para>
  <para style="s1">The Fall Festivals</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 23:23" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 23:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 23:24" />“Tell the Israelites: On the first day of the seventh month hold a worship festival. It will be a memorial day, a holy assembly announced by the blowing of rams’ horns. <verse eid="LEV 23:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 23:25" />Don’t do any regular work. Bring a sacrifice by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.”<verse eid="LEV 23:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 23:26" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 23:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 23:27" />“In addition, the tenth day of this seventh month is a special day for the payment for sins. There will be a holy assembly. Humble yourselves, and bring the <char style="nd">Lord</char> a sacrifice by fire. <verse eid="LEV 23:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 23:28" />Don’t do any work that day. It is a special day for the payment for sins. It is a time when you make peace with the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="LEV 23:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 23:29" />Those who do not humble themselves on that day will be excluded from the people. <verse eid="LEV 23:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 23:30" />I will kill those who do any work on that day. <verse eid="LEV 23:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 23:31" />Don’t do any work. It is a permanent law for generations to come wherever you live. <verse eid="LEV 23:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 23:32" />It is a day of rest, a day when you don’t work. Humble yourselves starting on the evening of the ninth day of the month. From that evening to the next, observe the day of rest as a holy day.”<verse eid="LEV 23:32" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 23:33" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 23:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 23:34" />“Tell the Israelites: The fifteenth day of this seventh month is the Festival of Booths to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It will last seven days. <verse eid="LEV 23:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 23:35" />On the first day there will be a holy assembly. Don’t do any regular work. <verse eid="LEV 23:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 23:36" />For seven consecutive days bring a sacrifice by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. On the eighth day there will be a holy assembly. Bring the <char style="nd">Lord</char> a sacrifice by fire. This is the last festival of the year. Don’t do any regular work.<verse eid="LEV 23:36" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 23:37" />“These are the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s appointed festivals. Announce them as holy assemblies for bringing sacrifices by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Bring burnt offerings, grain offerings, other sacrifices, and wine offerings—each one on its special day. <verse eid="LEV 23:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 23:38" />These offerings are in addition to those for the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s holy days of rest, as well as your gifts, all your vows, and your freewill offerings to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 23:38" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 23:39" />“However, on the fifteenth day of the seventh month, when you have gathered what the land produces, celebrate the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s festival for seven days. The first and the eighth days will be worship festivals. <verse eid="LEV 23:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LEV 23:40" />On the first day take the best fruits, palm branches, the branches of leafy trees and poplars, and celebrate in the presence of the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 23:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LEV 23:41" />It is the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s festival. Celebrate it for seven days each year. This is a permanent law for generations to come. Celebrate this festival in the seventh month. <verse eid="LEV 23:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 23:42" />Live in booths for seven days. Everyone born in Israel must live in booths <verse eid="LEV 23:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 23:43" />so that generations to come may learn how I made the people of Israel live in booths when I brought them out of Egypt. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.”<verse eid="LEV 23:43" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 23:44" />So Moses told the Israelites about the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s appointed festivals.<verse eid="LEV 23:44" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 23" />
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="LEV 24" />
  <para style="s1">Duties in the Tent of Meeting</para>
  <para style="r">(<ref loc="EXO 27:20-21">Exodus 27:20–21</ref>)</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 24:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 24:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 24:2" />“Command the Israelites to bring you pure, virgin olive oil for the lamp stand so that the lamps won’t go out. <verse eid="LEV 24:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 24:3" />In the tent of meeting, outside the canopy where the words of my promise are, Aaron must keep the lamps lit in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence from evening until morning. It is a permanent law for generations to come. <verse eid="LEV 24:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 24:4" />Aaron must keep the lamps on the pure gold lamp stand lit in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence.<verse eid="LEV 24:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 24:5" />“Also take flour and bake twelve rings of bread. Each ring will contain four quarts of flour. <verse eid="LEV 24:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 24:6" />Put them in two stacks of six each on the gold table in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence. <verse eid="LEV 24:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 24:7" />Lay pure incense on top of each stack. The incense on the bread will be a reminder, an offering by fire to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 24:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 24:8" />Every day of rest is a holy day when the <char style="add">⌞priest⌟</char> must arrange the bread in the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s presence. It is a continual reminder of my promise <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24:8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“covenant.”</char></note> to the Israelites. <verse eid="LEV 24:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 24:9" />The bread will belong to Aaron and his sons. They will eat it in a holy place. It is very holy, set apart from the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s offering by fire. This is a permanent law.”<verse eid="LEV 24:9" /></para>
  <para style="s1">The Man Who Cursed the <char style="nd">LORD</char>’s Name</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 24:10" />A man, whose mother was Shelomith (daughter of Dibri, from the tribe of Dan in Israel) and whose father was from Egypt, got into a quarrel with an Israelite in the camp. <verse eid="LEV 24:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 24:11" />The Israelite woman’s son began cursing the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s name and treating it with contempt. So they brought him to Moses.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24:11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Part of verse 11 (in Hebrew) has been placed in verse 10 to express the complex Hebrew paragraph structure more clearly in English.</char></note> <verse eid="LEV 24:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 24:12" />They kept him in custody until the <char style="nd">Lord</char> told them what to do.<verse eid="LEV 24:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 24:13" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 24:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 24:14" />“The man who cursed <char style="add">⌞my name⌟</char> must be taken outside the camp. All who heard him curse <char style="add">⌞my name⌟</char> must lay their hands on his head. Then the whole congregation must stone him to death.<verse eid="LEV 24:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 24:15" />“Also tell the Israelites: Those who treat their God with contempt will be punished for their sin. <verse eid="LEV 24:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 24:16" />But those who curse the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s name must be put to death. The whole congregation must stone them to death. It makes no difference whether they are Israelites or foreigners. Whoever curses the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s name must die.<verse eid="LEV 24:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 24:17" />“Whoever kills another person must be put to death. <verse eid="LEV 24:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 24:18" />Whoever kills an animal must replace it, life for life. <verse eid="LEV 24:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 24:19" />Whoever injures a neighbor must receive the same injury in return— <verse eid="LEV 24:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 24:20" />a broken bone for a broken bone, an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth. Whoever injures another person must receive the same injury in return. <verse eid="LEV 24:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 24:21" />Whoever kills an animal must replace it. Whoever kills a person must be put to death. <verse eid="LEV 24:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 24:22" />The same rule applies to every one of you. It makes no difference whether you are a foreigner or an Israelite, because I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.”<verse eid="LEV 24:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 24:23" />Moses spoke to the people of Israel. So the man who had cursed the <char style="nd">Lord</char>’s name was taken outside the camp. There they stoned him to death as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded Moses. The Israelites did as the <char style="nd">Lord</char> commanded Moses.<verse eid="LEV 24:23" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 24" />
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="LEV 25" />
  <para style="s1">The Year to Honor the <char style="nd">LORD</char></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 25:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses on Mount Sinai, <verse eid="LEV 25:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 25:2" />“Tell the Israelites: When you come into the land I’m giving you, the land will celebrate a year to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 25:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 25:3" />Then, for six years you may plant crops in your fields, prune your vineyards, and gather what they produce. <verse eid="LEV 25:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 25:4" />However, the seventh year will be a festival year for the land. It will be a year to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. Don’t plant crops in your fields or prune your vineyards. <verse eid="LEV 25:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 25:5" />Don’t harvest what grows by itself or harvest grapes from your vines. That year will be a festival for the land. <verse eid="LEV 25:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 25:6" />Whatever the land produces during that year is for all of you to eat—for you, your male and female slaves, your hired workers, foreigners among you, <verse eid="LEV 25:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 25:7" />your animals and the wild animals in your land. Everything the land produces will be yours to eat.<verse eid="LEV 25:7" /></para>
  <para style="s1">The Jubilee for the Land</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 25:8" />“Count seven of these years seven times for a total of 49 years. <verse eid="LEV 25:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 25:9" />On the tenth day of the seventh month, the special day for the payment for sin, sound rams’ horns throughout the country. <verse eid="LEV 25:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 25:10" />Set apart the fiftieth year as holy, and proclaim liberty to everyone living in the land. This is your jubilee year. Every slave will be freed in order to return to his property and to his family. <verse eid="LEV 25:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 25:11" />That fiftieth year will be your jubilee year. Don’t plant or harvest what grows by itself or pick grapes from the vines in the land. <verse eid="LEV 25:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 25:12" />The jubilee <char style="add">⌞year⌟</char> will be holy to you. You will eat what the field itself produces.<verse eid="LEV 25:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 25:13" />“In this jubilee year every slave will be freed in order to return to his property. <verse eid="LEV 25:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 25:14" />If you sell anything to your neighbor or buy anything from him, don’t take advantage of him. <verse eid="LEV 25:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 25:15" />When you buy property from your neighbor, take into account the number of years since the jubilee. Your neighbor must sell it to you taking into account the number of crops <char style="add">⌞until the next jubilee⌟</char>. <verse eid="LEV 25:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 25:16" />If there are still many years <char style="add">⌞until the jubilee⌟</char>, you will pay more for it. If there are only a few years <char style="add">⌞until the jubilee⌟</char>, you will pay less for it because he is selling you only the number of crops. <verse eid="LEV 25:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 25:17" />Never take advantage of each other. Fear your God, because I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="LEV 25:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 25:18" />“Obey my laws, and carefully follow my rules. Then you will live securely in the land. <verse eid="LEV 25:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 25:19" />The land will give you its products, and you will eat all you want and live there securely. <verse eid="LEV 25:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 25:20" />You may ask, ‘What will we eat in the seventh year if we do not plant or bring in our crops?’ <verse eid="LEV 25:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 25:21" />I will give you my blessing in the sixth year so that the land will produce enough for three years. <verse eid="LEV 25:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 25:22" />You will plant <char style="add">⌞again⌟</char> in the eighth year but live on what the land already produced. You will eat it, even in the ninth year, until the land produces more.<verse eid="LEV 25:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 25:23" />“Land must never be sold permanently, because the land is mine. To me you are strangers without permanent homes. <verse eid="LEV 25:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 25:24" />People must always have the right to buy their property back. <verse eid="LEV 25:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 25:25" />If your brother becomes poor and sells some of his property, then the one who can assume responsibility, his nearest relative, must buy back what he sold. <verse eid="LEV 25:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 25:26" />If a man doesn’t have anyone to buy it back for him, but if he prospers and earns enough to buy it back himself, <verse eid="LEV 25:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 25:27" />he must count the years from its sale. Then he will pay what is left to the man to whom he sold it, and it will be his property again. <verse eid="LEV 25:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 25:28" />However, if he cannot earn enough to buy it back, what he sold stays in the hands of the buyer until the year of jubilee. In the jubilee it will be released, and he will own it again.<verse eid="LEV 25:28" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 25:29" />“If anyone sells a home in a walled city, for one year after selling it he has the right to buy it back. He may buy it back only within that time. <verse eid="LEV 25:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 25:30" />If he does not buy it back during that year, the house in the city belongs to the buyer for generations to come. It will not be released in the jubilee. <verse eid="LEV 25:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 25:31" />However, houses in villages without walls are regarded as belonging to the fields of the land. They can be bought back. They will be released in the jubilee.<verse eid="LEV 25:31" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 25:32" />“The Levites always have the right to buy back their property in the cities they own. <verse eid="LEV 25:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 25:33" />If any Levite buys back <char style="add">⌞a house⌟</char>, in the jubilee the purchased house in the city will be released, because the houses in the Levite cities are their property among the Israelites. <verse eid="LEV 25:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 25:34" />But a field that belongs to their cities must not be sold, because it is their permanent property.<verse eid="LEV 25:34" /></para>
  <para style="s1">The Jubilee for the People</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 25:35" />“If an Israelite becomes poor and cannot support himself, help him. He must live with you as a stranger without a permanent home. <verse eid="LEV 25:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 25:36" />Don’t collect interest or make any profit from him. Fear your God by respecting other Israelites’ lives. <verse eid="LEV 25:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 25:37" />Never collect any kind of interest on your money or on the food you give them. <verse eid="LEV 25:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 25:38" />I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God, who brought you out of Egypt to give you Canaan and to be your God.<verse eid="LEV 25:38" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 25:39" />“If an Israelite becomes poor and sells himself to you, don’t work him like a slave. <verse eid="LEV 25:39" /><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LEV 25:40" />He will be like a hired worker or a visitor to you. He may work with you until the year of jubilee. <verse eid="LEV 25:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LEV 25:41" />Then you will release him and his children to go back to their family and the property of their ancestors. <verse eid="LEV 25:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 25:42" />They are my servants. I brought them out of Egypt. They must never be sold as slaves. <verse eid="LEV 25:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 25:43" />Do not treat them harshly. Fear your God.<verse eid="LEV 25:43" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 25:44" />“You may have male and female slaves, but buy them from the nations around you. <verse eid="LEV 25:44" /><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LEV 25:45" />You may also buy them from the foreigners living among you and from their families born in your country. They will be your property. <verse eid="LEV 25:45" /><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LEV 25:46" />You may acquire them for yourselves and for your descendants as permanent property. You may work them as slaves. However, do not treat the Israelites harshly. They are your relatives.<verse eid="LEV 25:46" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="LEV 25:47" />“Someone who is a foreigner without a permanent home among you may become rich, and your relative living with him may be poor. The poor Israelite may sell himself to that foreigner or a member of his family. <verse eid="LEV 25:47" /><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LEV 25:48" />After he has sold himself, he has the right to be bought back. One of his brothers may buy him back. <verse eid="LEV 25:48" /><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LEV 25:49" />His uncle, his cousin, or some other relative could also buy him back. If he becomes rich, he could buy his own freedom. <verse eid="LEV 25:49" /><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LEV 25:50" />Then he and his buyer must take into account the number of years from the year he was bought until the year of jubilee. His sale price will be adjusted based on the number of years he was with his buyer, like the wages of a hired worker. <verse eid="LEV 25:50" /><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LEV 25:51" />If there are many years left, he must refund from his purchase price an amount equal <char style="add">⌞to those years⌟</char>. <verse eid="LEV 25:51" /><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LEV 25:52" />If there are only a few years left until the year of jubilee, he must take them into account. He must refund from his purchase price an amount equal to those years. <verse eid="LEV 25:52" /><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LEV 25:53" />During those years he should serve his buyer as a hired worker. His buyer should not treat him harshly. <verse eid="LEV 25:53" /><verse number="54" style="v" sid="LEV 25:54" />If he cannot buy his freedom in these ways, he and his children will be released in the year of jubilee.<verse eid="LEV 25:54" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="55" style="v" sid="LEV 25:55" />“The Israelites belong to me as servants. They are my servants. I brought them out of Egypt. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God.”<verse eid="LEV 25:55" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 25" />
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="LEV 26" />
  <para style="s1">God’s Promises for Those Who Keep His Laws</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 26:1" />
    <char style="add">⌞The <char style="nd">Lord</char> continued,⌟</char> “Never make worthless idols or set up a carved statue or a sacred stone for yourselves. Never cut figures in stone to worship them in your country, because I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="LEV 26:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 26:2" />Observe my days of rest as holy days and respect my holy tent. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.<verse eid="LEV 26:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 26:3" />“This is what I will do if you will live by my laws and carefully obey my commands:<verse eid="LEV 26:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 26:4" />“I will give you rain at the right time. The land will produce its crops, and the trees in the field will produce their fruit. <verse eid="LEV 26:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 26:5" />Threshing <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26:5 </char><char style="fk" closed="false">Threshing </char><char style="ft" closed="false">is the process of beating stalks to separate them from the grain.</char></note> time will last until grape gathering, and grape gathering will last until planting. You will eat all you want and live securely in your land.<verse eid="LEV 26:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 26:6" />“I will bring peace to your land. You will lie down with no one to scare you. I will remove dangerous animals, and there will be no war in your land. <verse eid="LEV 26:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 26:7" />You will chase your enemies, and you will defeat them. <verse eid="LEV 26:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 26:8" />Five of you will chase a hundred of them, and a hundred of you will chase ten thousand of them. You will defeat your enemies, <verse eid="LEV 26:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 26:9" />and I will be pleased with you. Your families will be large, and I will keep my promise <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26:9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“covenant.”</char></note> to you. <verse eid="LEV 26:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 26:10" />You will clear out old food supplies to make room for new ones.<verse eid="LEV 26:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 26:11" />“I will put my tent among you, and I will never look at you with disgust. <verse eid="LEV 26:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 26:12" />So I will live among you and be your God, and you will be my people. <verse eid="LEV 26:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 26:13" />I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> your God. I brought you out of Egypt so that you are no longer slaves of the Egyptians. I have broken their power over you and made you live as a free people.<verse eid="LEV 26:13" /></para>
  <para style="s1">God’s Curses for Those Who Break His Laws</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 26:14" />“If you will not listen to me and obey all these commands, <verse eid="LEV 26:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 26:15" />if you reject my laws and look at my rules with disgust, if you reject my promise by disobeying my commands, <verse eid="LEV 26:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 26:16" />then this is what I will do to you: I will terrorize you with disease and fever. You will suffer from eye problems and depression. You will plant your crops and get nothing because your enemies will eat them. <verse eid="LEV 26:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 26:17" />I will condemn you so that you will go down in defeat in front of your enemies. Those who hate you will be your rulers. You will run away even when no one is chasing you.<verse eid="LEV 26:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 26:18" />“If you still will not listen to me, I will discipline you seven times for your sins. <verse eid="LEV 26:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 26:19" />I will crush your arrogance. You will have no rain, and your land will be as hard as cement. <verse eid="LEV 26:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 26:20" />You will work hard for nothing because your land will produce no crops and the trees will produce no fruit.<verse eid="LEV 26:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 26:21" />“If you resist and don’t listen to me, I will increase the punishment for your sins seven times. <verse eid="LEV 26:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 26:22" />I will send wild animals among you. They will rob you of your children, destroy your cattle, and make you so few that your roads will be deserted.<verse eid="LEV 26:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 26:23" />“If this discipline does not help and you still resist, <verse eid="LEV 26:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 26:24" />then I, too, will resist you. I will punish you seven times for your sins. <verse eid="LEV 26:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 26:25" />I will bring war on you to get revenge for my promise <char style="add">⌞that you rejected⌟</char>. When you gather in your cities, I will send plagues on you and you will fall under the control of your enemy. <verse eid="LEV 26:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 26:26" />I will destroy your food supply. Ten women will need only one oven to prepare your food. You will eat and go away hungry.<verse eid="LEV 26:26" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 26:27" />“If in spite of this you do not listen to me and still resist me, <verse eid="LEV 26:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 26:28" />I will fiercely resist you. I will discipline you seven times for your sins. <verse eid="LEV 26:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 26:29" />You will eat the bodies of your sons and daughters. <verse eid="LEV 26:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 26:30" />I will destroy your worship sites, cut down your incense altars, and pile your dead bodies on top of your dead idols. I will look at you with disgust. <verse eid="LEV 26:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 26:31" />I will make your cities deserted and ruin your sacred places. I will no longer accept the soothing aroma from your sacrifices. <verse eid="LEV 26:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 26:32" />I will make your land so deserted that your enemies will be shocked as they settle in it. <verse eid="LEV 26:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 26:33" />I will scatter you among the nations. War will follow you. Your country will be in ruins. Your cities will be deserted.<verse eid="LEV 26:33" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 26:34" />“Then the land will enjoy its time <char style="add">⌞to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char>⌟</char> while it lies deserted and you are in your enemies’ land. Then the land will joyfully celebrate its time <char style="add">⌞to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char>⌟</char>. <verse eid="LEV 26:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 26:35" />All the days it lies deserted, it will celebrate the time <char style="add">⌞to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char>⌟</char> it never celebrated while you lived there. <verse eid="LEV 26:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 26:36" />I will fill with despair those who are left in the land of their enemies. The sound of a windblown leaf will make them run. They will run away and fall, but no one will be chasing them. <verse eid="LEV 26:36" /><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 26:37" />They will stumble over each other, but no one will be after them. They will not be able to stand up to their enemies. <verse eid="LEV 26:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 26:38" />They will be destroyed among the nations. The land of their enemies will devour them. <verse eid="LEV 26:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 26:39" />Those who are left will waste away in the lands of their enemies because of their sins and the sins of their ancestors.<verse eid="LEV 26:39" /></para>
  <para style="s1">God Will Remember His Promise</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="LEV 26:40" />“But if they confess their sins and the sins of their ancestors—the treacherous things they did to oppose me— <verse eid="LEV 26:40" /><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LEV 26:41" />I will oppose them and bring them into the lands of their enemies. Then, if they humble their uncircumcised hearts and accept their guilt, <verse eid="LEV 26:41" /><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 26:42" />I will remember my promise to Jacob, Isaac, and Abraham. I will also remember the land. <verse eid="LEV 26:42" /><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 26:43" />The land, abandoned by them, will enjoy its time to honor the <char style="nd">Lord</char> while it lies deserted without them. They must accept their guilt because they rejected my rules and looked at my laws with disgust. <verse eid="LEV 26:43" /><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 26:44" />Even when they are in the land of their enemies, I will not reject them or look at them with disgust. I will not reject or cancel my promise to them, because I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char> their God. <verse eid="LEV 26:44" /><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LEV 26:45" />But for their sake, I will remember the promise to their ancestors. I brought them out of Egypt to be their God while nations looked on. I am the <char style="nd">Lord</char>.”<verse eid="LEV 26:45" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="LEV 26:46" />These are the laws, rules, and instructions that the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave to the Israelites through Moses on Mount Sinai.<verse eid="LEV 26:46" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 26" />
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="LEV 27" />
  <para style="s1">Special Vows</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 27:1" />The <char style="nd">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, <verse eid="LEV 27:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 27:2" />“Tell the Israelites: If any of you makes a special vow <char style="add">⌞to give a person⌟</char> to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, you may give money instead of the person. <verse eid="LEV 27:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 27:3" />The amount you must give for a man from 20 to 60 years old is 20 ounces of silver. Use the standard weight of the holy place. <verse eid="LEV 27:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 27:4" />If it is a woman, give 12 ounces. <verse eid="LEV 27:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 27:5" />For a boy from 5 to 20 years old, give 8 ounces and for a girl give 4 ounces. <verse eid="LEV 27:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 27:6" />For a boy from one month to five years old, give 2 ounces of silver and for a girl give about one ounce. <verse eid="LEV 27:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 27:7" />For a man 60 years or over, give 6 ounces and for a woman give 4 ounces. <verse eid="LEV 27:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 27:8" />But the person who is too poor to pay the required amount must stand in front of the priest. The priest will determine the amount based on what the person can afford.<verse eid="LEV 27:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 27:9" />“If <char style="add">⌞the vow⌟</char> is to give the kind of animal that people offer to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>, it will be considered holy. <verse eid="LEV 27:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 27:10" />Don’t exchange or substitute animals, a good one for a bad one or a bad one for a good one. If you do exchange one animal for another, then both animals will be holy. <verse eid="LEV 27:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 27:11" />If it is an unclean animal that cannot be brought to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as an offering, bring it in front of the priest. <verse eid="LEV 27:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 27:12" />The priest will determine what its value is. The value will be whatever the priest decides. <verse eid="LEV 27:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 27:13" />If you want to buy it back, you must pay its full value plus one-fifth more.<verse eid="LEV 27:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 27:14" />“If you give your house to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as something holy, the priest will determine what its value is. The value will be whatever the priest decides. <verse eid="LEV 27:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 27:15" />If you want to buy it back, you must pay its full value plus one-fifth more.<verse eid="LEV 27:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 27:16" />“If a person gives part of a field to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as something holy, its value will be based on the seed planted on it. Ground planted with 2 quarts of barley will be worth 20 ounces of silver. <verse eid="LEV 27:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 27:17" />If you give your field in the jubilee year, it will have its full value. <verse eid="LEV 27:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 27:18" />But if you give the field after the jubilee year, the priest will estimate its value based on the number of years left until the next jubilee year. <verse eid="LEV 27:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 27:19" />If you want to buy it back, you must pay its full value plus one-fifth more. <verse eid="LEV 27:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 27:20" />But if you don’t buy it back and it is sold to someone else, you cannot buy it back. <verse eid="LEV 27:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 27:21" />When the field is released in the jubilee year, it will be holy like a field claimed by the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. It will become the property of the priest. <verse eid="LEV 27:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 27:22" />You may give a field you bought (not one that was a part of your family property) to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> as something holy. <verse eid="LEV 27:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 27:23" />The priest must figure out the field’s value until the jubilee year. You will pay its value on that day as something holy, belonging to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 27:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 27:24" />In the jubilee year the field will go back to the person from whom it was bought, to whom it belongs as family property.<verse eid="LEV 27:24" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 27:25" />“All values will be set using the standard weight of the holy place.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">27:25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew adds “There are 20 gerahs to the standard shekel.”</char></note><verse eid="LEV 27:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 27:26" />“A firstborn animal already belongs to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> because it was born first. Therefore, it cannot be set apart as holy. Whether it is a bull or a sheep, it belongs to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 27:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 27:27" />But if it is an unclean animal, it must be bought back. The payment will be its full value plus one-fifth more. If it is not bought back, it must be sold at the value given it.<verse eid="LEV 27:27" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 27:28" />“However, everything dedicated to the <char style="nd">Lord</char> for destruction—a person, an animal, or a field that belongs to you—must not be sold or bought back. Everything dedicated in that way is very holy. It belongs to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 27:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 27:29" />People dedicated this way cannot be bought back. They must be put to death.<verse eid="LEV 27:29" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 27:30" />“One-tenth of what comes from the land, whether grain or fruit, is holy and belongs to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 27:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 27:31" />If you buy back any part of it, you must add one-fifth more to it. <verse eid="LEV 27:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 27:32" />Every tenth head of cattle or sheep that you counted is holy and belongs to the <char style="nd">Lord</char>. <verse eid="LEV 27:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 27:33" />You must not look to see if it is good or bad or exchange it. But if you do exchange it, both the first animal and its substitute will be holy. They cannot be bought back.”<verse eid="LEV 27:33" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 27:34" />These are the commands the <char style="nd">Lord</char> gave Moses on Mount Sinai for the Israelites.<verse eid="LEV 27:34" /></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 27" />
</usx>