<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="ROM" style="id">- God’s Word Bible</book>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="rem">© 1995, 2003, 2013, 2014, 2019, 2020 by God’s Word to the Nations Mission Society. All rights reserved.</para>
  <para style="rem">Converted from InDesign files to USFM-3 by Elbert Boot (Digital Bible Library Customer Service Team, Miami [USA])</para>
  <para style="rem">Language: English</para>
  <para style="rem">This project has 9 poetry levels, and Paratext only supports up to 4 levels. To upload the text to DBL, we have created a dblChanges file and added q5 to q9 to a custom.sty to obtain the desired design in Paratext.</para>
  <para style="h">ROMANS</para>
  <para style="toc1">Romans</para>
  <para style="toc2">Romans</para>
  <para style="toc3">Romans</para>
  <para style="mt1">Romans</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="ROM 1" />
  <para style="s1">Greeting</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 1:1" />From Paul, a servant of Jesus Christ, called to be an apostle and appointed to spread the Good News of God.<verse eid="ROM 1:1" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 1:2" />(God had already promised this Good News through his prophets in the Holy Scriptures. <verse eid="ROM 1:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 1:3" />This Good News is about his Son, our Lord Jesus Christ.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">“</char><char style="fq" closed="false">Our Lord Jesus Christ</char><char style="ft" closed="false">” from verse 4 (in Greek) has been placed in verse 3 to express the complex Greek sentence structure more clearly in English.</char></note> In his human nature he was a descendant of David. <verse eid="ROM 1:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 1:4" />In his spiritual, holy nature he was declared the Son of God. This was shown in a powerful way when he came back to life. <verse eid="ROM 1:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 1:5" />Through him we have received God’s kindness <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“grace.”</char></note> and the privilege of being apostles who bring people from every nation to the obedience that is associated with faith. This is for the honor of his name. <verse eid="ROM 1:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 1:6" />You are among those who have been called to belong to Jesus Christ.)<verse eid="ROM 1:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 1:7" />To everyone in Rome whom God loves and has called to be his holy people.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ROM 1:7">Good will <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“grace.”</char></note> and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ are yours!<verse eid="ROM 1:7" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul’s Prayer and Desire to Visit Rome</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 1:8" />First, I thank my God through Jesus Christ for every one of you because the news of your faith is spreading throughout the whole world. <verse eid="ROM 1:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 1:9" />I serve God by spreading the Good News about his Son. God is my witness that I always mention you <verse eid="ROM 1:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 1:10" />every time I pray. I ask that somehow God will now at last make it possible for me to visit you. <verse eid="ROM 1:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 1:11" />I long to see you to share a spiritual blessing with you so that you will be strengthened. <verse eid="ROM 1:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 1:12" />What I mean is that we may be encouraged by each other’s faith.<verse eid="ROM 1:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 1:13" />I want you to know, brothers and sisters, that I often planned to visit you. However, until now I have been kept from doing so. What I want is to enjoy some of the results of working among you as I have also enjoyed the results of working among the rest of the nations. <verse eid="ROM 1:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 1:14" />I have an obligation to those who are civilized and those who aren’t, to those who are wise and those who aren’t. <verse eid="ROM 1:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 1:15" />That’s why I’m eager to tell you who live in Rome the Good News also.<verse eid="ROM 1:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 1:16" />I’m not ashamed of the Good News. It is God’s power to save everyone who believes, Jews first and Greeks as well. <verse eid="ROM 1:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 1:17" />God’s approval is revealed in this Good News. This approval begins and ends with faith as Scripture says, “The person who has God’s approval will live by faith.”<verse eid="ROM 1:17" /></para>
  <para style="s1">God’s Anger against Sinful Humanity</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 1:18" />God’s anger is revealed from heaven against every ungodly and immoral thing people do as they try to suppress the truth by their immoral living. <verse eid="ROM 1:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 1:19" />What can be known about God is clear to them because he has made it clear to them. <verse eid="ROM 1:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 1:20" />From the creation of the world, God’s invisible qualities, his eternal power and divine nature, have been clearly observed in what he made. As a result, people have no excuse. <verse eid="ROM 1:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 1:21" />They knew God but did not praise and thank him for being God. Instead, their thoughts were pointless, and their misguided minds were plunged into darkness. <verse eid="ROM 1:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 1:22" />While claiming to be wise, they became fools. <verse eid="ROM 1:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 1:23" />They exchanged the glory of the immortal God for statues that looked like mortal humans, birds, animals, and snakes.<verse eid="ROM 1:23" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 1:24" />For this reason God allowed their lusts to control them. As a result, they dishonor their bodies by sexual perversion with each other. <verse eid="ROM 1:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 1:25" />These people have exchanged God’s truth for a lie. So they have become ungodly and serve what is created rather than the Creator, who is blessed forever. Amen!<verse eid="ROM 1:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 1:26" />For this reason God allowed their shameful passions to control them. Their women have exchanged natural sexual relations for unnatural ones. <verse eid="ROM 1:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 1:27" />Likewise, their men have given up natural sexual relations with women and burn with lust for each other. Men commit indecent acts with men, so they experience among themselves the punishment they deserve for their perversion.<verse eid="ROM 1:27" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 1:28" />And because they thought it was worthless to acknowledge God, God allowed their own immoral minds to control them. So they do these indecent things. <verse eid="ROM 1:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 1:29" />Their lives are filled with all kinds of sexual sins, wickedness, and greed. They are mean. They are filled with envy, murder, quarreling, deceit, and viciousness. They are gossips, <verse eid="ROM 1:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 1:30" />slanderers, haters of God, haughty, arrogant, and boastful. They think up new ways to be cruel. They don’t obey their parents, <verse eid="ROM 1:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 1:31" />don’t have any sense, don’t keep promises, and don’t show love to their own families or mercy to others. <verse eid="ROM 1:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ROM 1:32" />Although they know God’s judgment that those who do such things deserve to die, they not only do these things but also approve of others who do them.<verse eid="ROM 1:32" /></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 1" />
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="ROM 2" />
  <para style="s1">God Will Judge Everyone</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 2:1" />No matter who you are, if you judge anyone, you have no excuse. When you judge another person, you condemn yourself, since you, the judge, do the same things. <verse eid="ROM 2:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 2:2" />We know that God’s judgment is right when he condemns people for doing these things. <verse eid="ROM 2:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 2:3" />When you judge people for doing these things but then do them yourself, do you think you will escape God’s judgment? <verse eid="ROM 2:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 2:4" />Do you have contempt for God, who is very kind to you, puts up with you, and deals patiently with you? Don’t you realize that it is God’s kindness that is trying to lead you to him and change the way you think and act?<verse eid="ROM 2:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 2:5" />Since you are stubborn and don’t want to change the way you think and act, you are adding to the anger that God will have against you on that day when God vents his anger. At that time God will reveal that his decisions are fair. <verse eid="ROM 2:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 2:6" />He will pay all people back for what they have done. <verse eid="ROM 2:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 2:7" />He will give everlasting life to those who search for glory, honor, and immortality by persisting in doing what is good. But he will bring <verse eid="ROM 2:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 2:8" />anger and fury on those who, in selfish pride, refuse to believe the truth and who follow what is wrong. <verse eid="ROM 2:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 2:9" />There will be suffering and distress for every person who does evil, for Jews first and Greeks as well. <verse eid="ROM 2:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 2:10" />But there will be glory, honor, and peace for every person who does what is good, for Jews first and Greeks as well. <verse eid="ROM 2:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 2:11" />God does not play favorites.<verse eid="ROM 2:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 2:12" />Here’s the reason: Whoever sins without having the laws in Moses’ Teachings will still be condemned to destruction. And whoever has these laws from God and sins will still be judged by them. <verse eid="ROM 2:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 2:13" />People who merely listen to the laws in Moses’ Teachings don’t have God’s approval. Rather, people who do what those laws demand will have God’s approval.<verse eid="ROM 2:13" /></para>
  <para style="s1">God Will Judge People Who Are Not Jewish</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 2:14" />For example, whenever non-Jews who don’t have the laws in Moses’ Teachings do by nature the things that those laws contain, they are a law to themselves even though they don’t have any of those laws. <verse eid="ROM 2:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 2:15" />They show that some requirements found in Moses’ Teachings are written in their hearts. Their consciences speak to them. Their thoughts accuse them on one occasion and defend them on another. <verse eid="ROM 2:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 2:16" />This happens as they face the day when God, through Christ Jesus, will judge people’s secret thoughts. He will use the Good News that I am spreading to make that judgment.<verse eid="ROM 2:16" /></para>
  <para style="s1">God Will Judge Jewish People</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 2:17" />You call yourself a Jew, rely on the laws in Moses’ Teachings, brag about your God, <verse eid="ROM 2:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 2:18" />know what he wants, and distinguish right from wrong because you have been taught Moses’ Teachings. <verse eid="ROM 2:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 2:19" />You are confident that you are a guide for the blind, a light to those in the dark, <verse eid="ROM 2:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 2:20" />an instructor of ignorant people, and a teacher of children because you have the full content of knowledge and truth in Moses’ Teachings. <verse eid="ROM 2:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 2:21" />As you teach others, are you failing to teach yourself? As you preach against stealing, are you stealing? <verse eid="ROM 2:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 2:22" />As you tell others not to commit adultery, are you committing adultery? As you treat idols with disgust, are you robbing temples? <verse eid="ROM 2:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 2:23" />As you brag about the laws in Moses’ Teachings, are you dishonoring God by ignoring those laws? <verse eid="ROM 2:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 2:24" />As Scripture says, “God’s name is cursed among the nations because of you.”<verse eid="ROM 2:24" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 2:25" />For example, circumcision is valuable if you follow the laws in Moses’ Teachings. If you don’t follow those laws, your circumcision amounts to uncircumcision. <verse eid="ROM 2:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 2:26" />So if a man does what those laws demand, won’t he be considered circumcised even if he is uncircumcised? <verse eid="ROM 2:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 2:27" />The uncircumcised man who carries out what those laws say will condemn you for not following them. He will condemn you in spite of the fact that you are circumcised and have those laws in writing. <verse eid="ROM 2:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 2:28" />A person is not a Jew because of his appearance, nor is circumcision a matter of how the body looks. <verse eid="ROM 2:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 2:29" />Rather, a person is a Jew inwardly, and circumcision is something that happens in a person’s heart. Circumcision is spiritual, not just a written rule. That person’s praise will come from God, not from people.<verse eid="ROM 2:29" /></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 2" />
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="ROM 3" />
  <para style="s1">Everyone Is a Sinner</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 3:1" />Is there any advantage, then, in being a Jew? Or is there any value in being circumcised? <verse eid="ROM 3:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 3:2" />There are all kinds of advantages. First of all, God entrusted them with his word.<verse eid="ROM 3:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 3:3" />What if some of them were unfaithful? Can their unfaithfulness cancel God’s faithfulness? <verse eid="ROM 3:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 3:4" />That would be unthinkable! God is honest, and everyone else is a liar, as Scripture says,</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ROM 3:4" />
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 3:4">“So you hand down justice when you speak,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 3:4">and you win your case in court.”<verse eid="ROM 3:4" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 3:5" />But if what we do wrong shows that God is fair, what should we say? Is God unfair when he vents his anger on us? (I’m arguing the way humans would.) <verse eid="ROM 3:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 3:6" />That’s unthinkable! Otherwise, how would God be able to judge the world? <verse eid="ROM 3:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 3:7" />If my lie increases the glory that God receives by showing that God is truthful, why am I still judged as a sinner? <verse eid="ROM 3:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 3:8" />Or can we say, “Let’s do evil so that good will come from it”? Some slander us and claim that this is what we say. They are condemned, and that’s what they deserve.<verse eid="ROM 3:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 3:9" />What, then, is the situation? Do we have any advantage? Not at all. We have already accused everyone (both Jews and Greeks) of being under the power of sin, <verse eid="ROM 3:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 3:10" />as Scripture says,</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ROM 3:10" />
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 3:10">“Not one person has God’s approval.<verse eid="ROM 3:10" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 3:11" />No one understands.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 3:11">No one searches for God.<verse eid="ROM 3:11" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 3:12" />Everyone has turned away.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 3:12">Together they have become rotten to the core.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 3:12">No one does anything good,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 3:12">not even one person.<verse eid="ROM 3:12" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 3:13" />Their throats are open graves.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 3:13">Their tongues practice deception.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 3:13">Their lips hide the venom of poisonous snakes.<verse eid="ROM 3:13" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 3:14" />Their mouths are full of curses and bitter resentment.<verse eid="ROM 3:14" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 3:15" />They run quickly to murder people.<verse eid="ROM 3:15" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 3:16" />There is ruin and suffering wherever they go.<verse eid="ROM 3:16" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 3:17" />They have not learned to live in peace.<verse eid="ROM 3:17" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 3:18" />They are not terrified of God.”<verse eid="ROM 3:18" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 3:19" />We know that whatever the Scriptures say applies to everyone under their influence, and no one can say a thing. The whole world is brought under the judgment of God. <verse eid="ROM 3:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 3:20" />Not one person can have God’s approval by any effort to follow the laws in the Scriptures. These laws show what sin is.<verse eid="ROM 3:20" /></para>
  <para style="s1">God Gives Us His Approval as a Gift</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 3:21" />Now, the way to receive God’s approval has been made plain in a way other than the laws in the Scriptures. Moses’ Teachings and the Prophets tell us this. <verse eid="ROM 3:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 3:22" />Everyone who believes has God’s approval through faith in Jesus Christ.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ROM 3:22">There is no difference between people. <verse eid="ROM 3:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 3:23" />Because all people have sinned, they have fallen short of God’s glory. <verse eid="ROM 3:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 3:24" />They receive God’s approval freely by an act of his kindness <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“grace.”</char></note> through the price Christ Jesus paid to set us free <char style="add">⌞from sin⌟</char>. <verse eid="ROM 3:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 3:25" />God showed that Christ is the throne of mercy where God’s approval is given through faith in Christ’s blood. In his patience God waited to deal with sins committed in the past. <verse eid="ROM 3:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 3:26" />He waited so that he could display his approval at the present time. This shows that he is a God of justice, a God who approves of people who believe in Jesus.<verse eid="ROM 3:26" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 3:27" />So, do we have anything to brag about? Bragging has been eliminated. On what basis was it eliminated? On the basis of our own efforts? No, indeed! Rather, it is eliminated on the basis of faith. <verse eid="ROM 3:27" /><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 3:28" />We conclude that a person has God’s approval by faith, not by his own efforts.<verse eid="ROM 3:28" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 3:29" />Is God only the God of the Jews? Isn’t he also the God of people who are not Jewish? Certainly, he is, <verse eid="ROM 3:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 3:30" />since it is the same God who approves circumcised people by faith and uncircumcised people through this same faith.<verse eid="ROM 3:30" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 3:31" />Are we abolishing the laws in the Scriptures by this faith? That’s unthinkable! Rather, we are supporting these laws.<verse eid="ROM 3:31" /></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 3" />
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="ROM 4" />
  <para style="s1">We Have God’s Approval by Faith</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 4:1" />What can we say that we have discovered about our ancestor Abraham? <verse eid="ROM 4:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 4:2" />If Abraham had God’s approval because of something he did, he would have had a reason to brag. But he could not brag to God about it. <verse eid="ROM 4:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 4:3" />What does Scripture say? “Abraham believed God, and that faith was regarded as the basis of Abraham’s approval by God.”<verse eid="ROM 4:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 4:4" />When people work, their pay is not regarded as a gift but something they have earned. <verse eid="ROM 4:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 4:5" />However, when people don’t work but believe God, the one who approves ungodly people, their faith is regarded as the basis of God’s approval. <verse eid="ROM 4:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 4:6" />David says the same thing about those who are blessed: God approves of people without their earning it. David said,<verse eid="ROM 4:6" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 4:7" />“Blessed are those whose disobedience is forgiven</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 4:7">and whose sins are pardoned.<verse eid="ROM 4:7" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 4:8" />Blessed is the person whom the Lord no longer considers sinful.”<verse eid="ROM 4:8" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 4:9" />Are only the circumcised people blessed, or are uncircumcised people blessed as well? We say, “Abraham’s faith was regarded as the basis of God’s approval.” <verse eid="ROM 4:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 4:10" />How was his faith regarded as the basis of God’s approval? Was he circumcised or was he uncircumcised at that time? He had not been circumcised. <verse eid="ROM 4:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 4:11" />Abraham’s faith was the basis of his approval by God while he was still uncircumcised. The mark of circumcision is the seal of that approval. Therefore, he is the father of every believer who is not circumcised, and their faith, too, is regarded as the basis of their approval by God. <verse eid="ROM 4:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 4:12" />He is also the father of those who not only are circumcised but also are following in the footsteps of his faith. Our father Abraham had that faith before he was circumcised.<verse eid="ROM 4:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 4:13" />So it was not by obeying the laws in Moses’ Teachings that Abraham or his descendants received the promise that he would inherit the world. Rather, he received this promise through God’s approval that comes by faith. <verse eid="ROM 4:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 4:14" />If those who obey Moses’ Teachings are the heirs, then faith is useless and the promise is worthless. <verse eid="ROM 4:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 4:15" />The laws in Moses’ Teachings bring about anger. But where those laws don’t exist, they can’t be broken. <verse eid="ROM 4:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 4:16" />Therefore, the promise is based on faith so that it can be a gift.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“grace.”</char></note> Consequently, the promise is guaranteed for every descendant, not only for those who are descendants by obeying Moses’ Teachings but also for those who are descendants by believing as Abraham did. He is the father of all of us, <verse eid="ROM 4:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 4:17" />as Scripture says: “I have made you a father of many nations.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ROM 4:17">Abraham believed when he stood in the presence of the God who gives life to dead people and calls into existence things that don’t even exist. <verse eid="ROM 4:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 4:18" />When there was nothing left to hope for, Abraham still hoped and believed. As a result, he became a father of many nations, as he had been told: “That is how many descendants you will have.” <verse eid="ROM 4:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 4:19" />Abraham didn’t weaken. Through faith he regarded the facts: His body was already as good as dead now that he was about a hundred years old, and Sarah was unable to have children. <verse eid="ROM 4:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 4:20" />He didn’t doubt God’s promise out of a lack of faith. Instead, giving honor to God <char style="add">⌞for the promise⌟</char>, he became strong because of faith <verse eid="ROM 4:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 4:21" />and was absolutely confident that God would do what he promised. <verse eid="ROM 4:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 4:22" />That is why Abraham’s faith was regarded as the basis of his approval by God.<verse eid="ROM 4:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 4:23" />But the words “his faith was regarded as the basis of his approval by God” were written not only for him <verse eid="ROM 4:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 4:24" />but also for us. Our faith will be regarded as the basis of our approval by God—each of us who believe in the one who brought Jesus, our Lord, back to life. <verse eid="ROM 4:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 4:25" />Jesus, our Lord, was handed over to death because of our failures and was brought back to life so that we could receive God’s approval.<verse eid="ROM 4:25" /></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 4" />
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="ROM 5" />
  <para style="s1">We Are at Peace with God because of Jesus</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 5:1" />Now that we have God’s approval by faith, we have peace with God because of what our Lord Jesus Christ has done. <verse eid="ROM 5:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 5:2" />Through Christ we can approach God <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts read </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“we can approach God through faith.”</char></note> and stand in his favor.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“grace.”</char></note> So we brag because of our confidence that we will receive glory from God. <verse eid="ROM 5:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 5:3" />But that’s not all. We also brag when we are suffering. We know that suffering creates endurance, <verse eid="ROM 5:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 5:4" />endurance creates character, and character creates confidence. <verse eid="ROM 5:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 5:5" />We’re not ashamed to have this confidence, because God’s love has been poured into our hearts by the Holy Spirit, who has been given to us.<verse eid="ROM 5:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 5:6" />Look at it this way: At the right time, while we were still helpless, Christ died for ungodly people. <verse eid="ROM 5:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 5:7" />Finding someone who would die for a godly person is rare. Maybe someone would have the courage to die for a good person. <verse eid="ROM 5:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 5:8" />Christ died for us while we were still sinners. This demonstrates God’s love for us.<verse eid="ROM 5:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 5:9" />Since Christ’s blood has now given us God’s approval, we are even more certain that Christ will save us from God’s anger. <verse eid="ROM 5:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 5:10" />If the death of his Son restored our relationship with God while we were still his enemies, we are even more certain that, because of this restored relationship, the life of his Son will save us. <verse eid="ROM 5:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 5:11" />In addition, our Lord Jesus Christ lets us continue to brag about God. After all, it is through Christ that we now have this restored relationship with God.<verse eid="ROM 5:11" /></para>
  <para style="s1">A Comparison between Adam and Christ</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 5:12" />Sin came into the world through one person, and death came through sin. So death spread to everyone, because everyone sinned. <verse eid="ROM 5:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 5:13" />Sin was in the world before there were any laws. But no record of sin can be kept when there are no laws. <verse eid="ROM 5:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 5:14" />Yet, death ruled from the time of Adam to the time of Moses, even over those who did not sin in the same way Adam did when he disobeyed. Adam is an image of the one who would come.<verse eid="ROM 5:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 5:15" />There is no comparison between <char style="add">⌞God’s⌟</char> gift and <char style="add">⌞Adam’s⌟</char> failure. If humanity died as the result of one person’s failure, it is certainly true that God’s kindness <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“grace.”</char></note> and the gift given through the kindness of one person, Jesus Christ, have been showered on humanity.<verse eid="ROM 5:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 5:16" />There is also no comparison between <char style="add">⌞God’s⌟</char> gift and the one who sinned. The verdict which followed one person’s failure condemned everyone. But, even after many failures, the gift brought God’s approval. <verse eid="ROM 5:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 5:17" />It is certain that death ruled because of one person’s failure. It’s even more certain that those who receive God’s overflowing kindness and the gift of his approval will rule in life because of one person, Jesus Christ.<verse eid="ROM 5:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 5:18" />Therefore, everyone was condemned through one failure, and everyone received God’s life-giving approval through one verdict. <verse eid="ROM 5:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 5:19" />Clearly, through one person’s disobedience humanity became sinful, and through one person’s obedience humanity will receive God’s approval. <verse eid="ROM 5:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 5:20" />The laws in Moses’ Teachings were added to increase the failure. But where sin increased, God’s kindness increased even more. <verse eid="ROM 5:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 5:21" />As sin ruled by bringing death, God’s kindness would rule by bringing us his approval. This results in our living forever because of Jesus Christ our Lord.<verse eid="ROM 5:21" /></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 5" />
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="ROM 6" />
  <para style="s1">No Longer Slaves to Sin, but God’s Servants</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 6:1" />What should we say then? Should we continue to sin so that God’s kindness <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“grace.”</char></note> will increase? <verse eid="ROM 6:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 6:2" />That’s unthinkable! As far as sin is concerned, we have died. So how can we still live under sin’s influence?<verse eid="ROM 6:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 6:3" />Don’t you know that all of us who were baptized into Christ Jesus were baptized into his death? <verse eid="ROM 6:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 6:4" />When we were baptized into his death, we were placed into the tomb with him. As Christ was brought back from death to life by the glorious power of the Father, so we, too, should live a new kind of life. <verse eid="ROM 6:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 6:5" />If we’ve become united with him in a death like his, certainly we will also be united with him when we come back to life as he did. <verse eid="ROM 6:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 6:6" />We know that the person we used to be was crucified with him to put an end to sin in our bodies. Because of this we are no longer slaves to sin. <verse eid="ROM 6:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 6:7" />The person who has died has been freed from sin.<verse eid="ROM 6:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 6:8" />If we have died with Christ, we believe that we will also live with him. <verse eid="ROM 6:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 6:9" />We know that Christ, who was brought back to life, will never die again. Death no longer has any power over him. <verse eid="ROM 6:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 6:10" />When he died, he died once and for all to sin’s power. But now he lives, and he lives for God. <verse eid="ROM 6:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 6:11" />So consider yourselves dead to sin’s power but living for God in the power Christ Jesus gives you.<verse eid="ROM 6:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 6:12" />Therefore, never let sin rule your physical body so that you obey its desires. <verse eid="ROM 6:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 6:13" />Never offer any part of your body to sin’s power. No part of your body should ever be used to do any ungodly thing. Instead, offer yourselves to God as people who have come back from death and are now alive. Offer all the parts of your body to God. Use them to do everything that God approves of. <verse eid="ROM 6:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 6:14" />Certainly, sin shouldn’t have power over you because you’re not controlled by God’s laws, but by God’s favor.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“grace.”</char></note><verse eid="ROM 6:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 6:15" />Then what is the implication? Should we sin because we are not controlled by God’s laws but by God’s favor? That’s unthinkable! <verse eid="ROM 6:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 6:16" />Don’t you know that if you offer to be someone’s slave, you must obey that master? Either your master is sin, or your master is obedience. Letting sin be your master leads to death. Letting obedience be your master leads to God’s approval. <verse eid="ROM 6:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 6:17" />You were slaves to sin. But I thank God that you have become wholeheartedly obedient to the teachings which you were given. <verse eid="ROM 6:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 6:18" />Freed from sin, you were made slaves who do what God approves of.<verse eid="ROM 6:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 6:19" />I’m speaking in a human way because of the weakness of your corrupt nature. Clearly, you once offered all the parts of your body as slaves to sexual perversion and disobedience. This led you to live disobedient lives. Now, in the same way, offer all the parts of your body as slaves that do what God approves of. This leads you to live holy lives. <verse eid="ROM 6:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 6:20" />When you were slaves to sin, you were free from doing what God approves of.<verse eid="ROM 6:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 6:21" />What did you gain by doing those things? You’re ashamed of what you used to do because it ended in death. <verse eid="ROM 6:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 6:22" />Now you have been freed from sin and have become God’s slaves. This results in a holy life and, finally, in everlasting life. <verse eid="ROM 6:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 6:23" />The payment for sin is death, but the gift that God freely gives is everlasting life found in Christ Jesus our Lord.<verse eid="ROM 6:23" /></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 6" />
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="ROM 7" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 7:1" />Don’t you realize, brothers and sisters, that laws have power over people only as long as they are alive? (I’m speaking to people who are familiar with Moses’ Teachings.) <verse eid="ROM 7:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 7:2" />For example, a married woman is bound by law to her husband as long as he is alive. But if her husband dies, that marriage law is no longer in effect for her. <verse eid="ROM 7:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 7:3" />So if she marries another man while her husband is still alive, she will be called an adulterer. But if her husband dies, she is free from this law, so she is not committing adultery if she marries another man.<verse eid="ROM 7:3" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 7:4" />In the same way, brothers and sisters, you have died to the laws in Moses’ Teachings through Christ’s body. You belong to someone else, the one who was brought back to life.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ROM 7:4">As a result, we can do what God wants. <verse eid="ROM 7:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 7:5" />While we were living under the influence of our corrupt nature, sinful passions were at work throughout our bodies. Stirred up by the laws in Moses’ Teachings, our sinful passions did things that result in death. <verse eid="ROM 7:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 7:6" />But now we have died to those laws that bound us. God has broken their effect on us so that we are serving in a new spiritual way, not in an old way dictated by written words.<verse eid="ROM 7:6" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Moses’ Laws Show What Sin Is</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 7:7" />What should we say, then? Are the laws in Moses’ Teachings sinful? That’s unthinkable! In fact, I wouldn’t have recognized sin if those laws hadn’t shown it to me. For example, I wouldn’t have known that some desires are sinful if Moses’ Teachings hadn’t said, “Never have wrong desires.” <verse eid="ROM 7:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 7:8" />But sin took the opportunity provided by this commandment and made me have all kinds of wrong desires. Clearly, without laws sin is dead. <verse eid="ROM 7:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 7:9" />At one time I was alive without any laws. But when this commandment came, sin became alive <verse eid="ROM 7:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 7:10" />and I died. I found that the commandment which was intended to bring me life actually brought me death. <verse eid="ROM 7:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 7:11" />Sin, taking the opportunity provided by this commandment, deceived me and then killed me.<verse eid="ROM 7:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 7:12" />So the laws in Moses’ Teachings are holy, and the commandment is holy, right, and good. <verse eid="ROM 7:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 7:13" />Now, did something good cause my death? That’s unthinkable! Rather, my death was caused by sin so that sin would be recognized for what it is. Through a commandment sin became more sinful than ever.<verse eid="ROM 7:13" /></para>
  <para style="s1">God’s Standards Are at War with Sin’s Standards</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 7:14" />I know that God’s standards in Moses’ Teachings are spiritual, but I have a corrupt nature, sold as a slave to sin. <verse eid="ROM 7:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 7:15" />I don’t realize what I’m doing. I don’t do what I want to do. Instead, I do what I hate. <verse eid="ROM 7:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 7:16" />I don’t do what I want to do, but I agree that God’s standards are good. <verse eid="ROM 7:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 7:17" />So I am no longer the one who is doing the things I hate, but sin that lives in me is doing them.<verse eid="ROM 7:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 7:18" />I know that nothing good lives in me; that is, nothing good lives in my corrupt nature. Although I have the desire to do what is right, I don’t do it. <verse eid="ROM 7:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 7:19" />I don’t do the good I want to do. Instead, I do the evil that I don’t want to do. <verse eid="ROM 7:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 7:20" />Now, when I do what I don’t want to do, I am no longer the one who is doing it. Sin that lives in me is doing it.<verse eid="ROM 7:20" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 7:21" />So I’ve discovered this truth: Evil is present with me even when I want to do what God’s standards say is good. <verse eid="ROM 7:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 7:22" />I take pleasure in God’s standards in my inner being. <verse eid="ROM 7:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 7:23" />However, I see a different standard <char style="add">⌞at work⌟</char> throughout my body. It is at war with the standards my mind sets and tries to take me captive to sin’s standards which still exist throughout my body. <verse eid="ROM 7:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 7:24" />What a miserable person I am! Who will rescue me from my dying body? <verse eid="ROM 7:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 7:25" />I thank God that our Lord Jesus Christ rescues me! So I am obedient to God’s standards with my mind, but I am obedient to sin’s standards with my corrupt nature.<verse eid="ROM 7:25" /></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 7" />
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="ROM 8" />
  <para style="s1">God’s Spirit Makes Us His Children</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 8:1" />So those who are believers in Christ Jesus can no longer be condemned. <verse eid="ROM 8:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 8:2" />The standards of the Spirit, who gives life through Christ Jesus, have set you free from the standards of sin and death. <verse eid="ROM 8:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 8:3" />It is impossible to do what God’s standards demand because of the weakness our human nature has. But God sent his Son to have a human nature as sinners have and to pay for sin. That way God condemned sin in our corrupt nature. <verse eid="ROM 8:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 8:4" />Therefore, we, who do not live by our corrupt nature but by our spiritual nature, are able to meet God’s standards in Moses’ Teachings.<verse eid="ROM 8:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 8:5" />Those who live by the corrupt nature have the corrupt nature’s attitude. But those who live by the spiritual nature have the spiritual nature’s attitude. <verse eid="ROM 8:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 8:6" />The corrupt nature’s attitude leads to death. But the spiritual nature’s attitude leads to life and peace. <verse eid="ROM 8:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 8:7" />This is so because the corrupt nature has a hostile attitude toward God. It refuses to place itself under the authority of God’s standards because it can’t. <verse eid="ROM 8:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 8:8" />Those who are under the control of the corrupt nature can’t please God. <verse eid="ROM 8:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 8:9" />But if God’s Spirit lives in you, you are under the control of your spiritual nature, not your corrupt nature.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ROM 8:9">Whoever doesn’t have the Spirit of Christ doesn’t belong to him. <verse eid="ROM 8:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 8:10" />However, if Christ lives in you, your bodies are dead because of sin, but your spirits are alive because you have God’s approval. <verse eid="ROM 8:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 8:11" />Does the Spirit of the one who brought Jesus back to life live in you? Then the one who brought Christ back to life will also make your mortal bodies alive by his Spirit who lives in you.<verse eid="ROM 8:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 8:12" />So, brothers and sisters, we have no obligation to live the way our corrupt nature wants us to live. <verse eid="ROM 8:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 8:13" />If you live by your corrupt nature, you are going to die. But if you use your spiritual nature to put to death the evil activities of the body, you will live. <verse eid="ROM 8:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 8:14" />Certainly, all who are guided by God’s Spirit are God’s children. <verse eid="ROM 8:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 8:15" />You haven’t received the spirit of slaves that leads you into fear again. Instead, you have received the spirit of God’s adopted children by which we call out, “Abba! <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:15 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Abba </char><char style="ft" closed="false">is Aramaic for “father.”</char></note> Father!” <verse eid="ROM 8:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 8:16" />The Spirit himself testifies with our spirit that we are God’s children. <verse eid="ROM 8:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 8:17" />If we are his children, we are also God’s heirs. If we share in Christ’s suffering in order to share his glory, we are heirs together with him.<verse eid="ROM 8:17" /></para>
  <para style="s1">God’s Spirit Helps Us</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 8:18" />I consider our present sufferings insignificant compared to the glory that will soon be revealed to us. <verse eid="ROM 8:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 8:19" />All creation is eagerly waiting for God to reveal who his children are. <verse eid="ROM 8:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 8:20" />Creation was subjected to frustration but not by its own choice. The one who subjected it to frustration did so in the hope <verse eid="ROM 8:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 8:21" />that it would also be set free from slavery to decay in order to share the glorious freedom that the children of God will have. <verse eid="ROM 8:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 8:22" />We know that all creation has been groaning with the pains of childbirth up to the present time.<verse eid="ROM 8:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 8:23" />However, not only creation groans. We, who have the Spirit as the first of God’s gifts, also groan inwardly. We groan as we eagerly wait for our adoption, the freeing of our bodies <char style="add">⌞from sin⌟</char>. <verse eid="ROM 8:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 8:24" />We were saved with this hope in mind. If we hope for something we already see, it’s not really hope. Who hopes for what can be seen? <verse eid="ROM 8:24" /><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 8:25" />But if we hope for what we don’t see, we eagerly wait for it with perseverance.<verse eid="ROM 8:25" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 8:26" />At the same time the Spirit also helps us in our weakness, because we don’t know how to pray for what we need. But the Spirit intercedes along with our groans that cannot be expressed in words. <verse eid="ROM 8:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 8:27" />The one who searches our hearts knows what the Spirit has in mind. The Spirit intercedes for God’s people the way God wants him to.<verse eid="ROM 8:27" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Nothing Can Separate Us from God’s Love</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 8:28" />We know that all things work together for the good of those who love God—those whom he has called according to his plan. <verse eid="ROM 8:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 8:29" />This is true because he already knew his people and had already appointed them to have the same form as the image of his Son. Therefore, his Son is the firstborn among many children. <verse eid="ROM 8:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 8:30" />He also called those whom he had already appointed. He approved of those whom he had called, and he gave glory to those whom he had approved of.<verse eid="ROM 8:30" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 8:31" />What can we say about all of this? If God is for us, who can be against us? <verse eid="ROM 8:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ROM 8:32" />God didn’t spare his own Son but handed him over <char style="add">⌞to death⌟</char> for all of us. So he will also give us everything along with him. <verse eid="ROM 8:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="ROM 8:33" />Who will accuse those whom God has chosen? God has approved of them. <verse eid="ROM 8:33" /><verse number="34" style="v" sid="ROM 8:34" />Who will condemn them? Christ has died, and more importantly, he was brought back to life. Christ is in the honored position—the one next to God the Father on the heavenly throne. Christ also intercedes for us. <verse eid="ROM 8:34" /><verse number="35" style="v" sid="ROM 8:35" />What will separate us from the love Christ has for us? Can trouble, distress, persecution, hunger, nakedness, danger, or violent death separate us from his love? <verse eid="ROM 8:35" /><verse number="36" style="v" sid="ROM 8:36" />As Scripture says:</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ROM 8:36" />
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 8:36">“We are being killed all day long because of you.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 8:36">We are thought of as sheep to be slaughtered.”<verse eid="ROM 8:36" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ROM 8:37" />The one who loves us gives us an overwhelming victory in all these difficulties. <verse eid="ROM 8:37" /><verse number="38" style="v" sid="ROM 8:38" />I am convinced that nothing can ever separate us from God’s love which Christ Jesus our Lord shows us.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:38 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The last part of verse 39 (in Greek) has been moved to verse 38 to express the complex Greek sentence structure more clearly in English.</char></note> We can’t be separated by death or life, by angels or rulers, by anything in the present or anything in the future, by forces <verse eid="ROM 8:38" /><verse number="39" style="v" sid="ROM 8:39" />or powers in the world above or in the world below, or by anything else in creation.<verse eid="ROM 8:39" /></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 8" />
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="ROM 9" />
  <para style="s1">Paul’s Concern for the Jewish People</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 9:1" />As a Christian, I’m telling you the truth. I’m not lying. The Holy Spirit, along with my own thoughts, supports me in this. <verse eid="ROM 9:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 9:2" />I have deep sorrow and endless heartache. <verse eid="ROM 9:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 9:3" />I wish I could be condemned and cut off from Christ for the sake of others who, like me, are Jewish by birth. <verse eid="ROM 9:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 9:4" />They are Israelites, God’s adopted children. They have the Lord’s glory, the pledges,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“covenants.”</char></note> Moses’ Teachings, the true worship, and the promises. <verse eid="ROM 9:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 9:5" />The Messiah is descended from their ancestors according to his human nature. The Messiah is God over everything, forever blessed. Amen.<verse eid="ROM 9:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 9:6" />Now it is not as though God’s word has failed. Clearly, not everyone descended from Israel is part of Israel <verse eid="ROM 9:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 9:7" />or a descendant of Abraham. However, <char style="add">⌞as Scripture says,⌟</char> “Through Isaac your descendants will carry on your name.” <verse eid="ROM 9:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 9:8" />This means that children born by natural descent <char style="add">⌞from Abraham⌟</char> are not necessarily God’s children. Instead, children born by the promise are considered Abraham’s descendants.<verse eid="ROM 9:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 9:9" />For example, this is what the promise said, “I will come back at the right time, and Sarah will have a son.” <verse eid="ROM 9:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 9:10" />The same thing happened to Rebekah. Rebekah became pregnant by our ancestor Isaac. <verse eid="ROM 9:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 9:11" />Before the children had been born or had done anything good or bad, Rebekah was told that the older child would serve the younger one. This was said to Rebekah so that God’s plan would remain a matter of his choice, <verse eid="ROM 9:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 9:12" />a choice based on God’s call and not on anything people do.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The last part of verse 12 (in Greek) has been placed in verse 11 to express the complex Greek sentence structure more clearly in English.</char></note> <verse eid="ROM 9:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 9:13" />The Scriptures say, “I loved Jacob, but I hated Esau.”<verse eid="ROM 9:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 9:14" />What can we say—that God is unfair? That’s unthinkable! <verse eid="ROM 9:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 9:15" />For example, God said to Moses, “I will be kind to anyone I want to. I will be merciful to anyone I want to.” <verse eid="ROM 9:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 9:16" />Therefore, God’s choice does not depend on a person’s desire or effort, but on God’s mercy.<verse eid="ROM 9:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 9:17" />For example, Scripture says to Pharaoh, “I put you here for this reason: to demonstrate my power through you and to spread my name throughout the earth.” <verse eid="ROM 9:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 9:18" />Therefore, if God wants to be kind to anyone, he will be. If he wants to make someone stubborn, he will.<verse eid="ROM 9:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 9:19" />You may ask me, “Why does God still find fault with anyone? Who can resist whatever God wants to do?”<verse eid="ROM 9:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 9:20" />Who do you think you are to talk back to God like that? Can an object that was made say to its maker, “Why did you make me like this?” <verse eid="ROM 9:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 9:21" />A potter has the right to do whatever he wants with his clay. He can make something for a special occasion or something for everyday use from the same lump of clay.<verse eid="ROM 9:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 9:22" />If God wants to demonstrate his anger and reveal his power, he can do it. But can’t he be extremely patient with people who are objects of his anger because they are headed for destruction? <verse eid="ROM 9:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 9:23" />Can’t God also reveal the riches of his glory to people who are objects of his mercy and who he had already prepared for glory? <verse eid="ROM 9:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 9:24" />This is what God did for us whom he called—whether we are Jews or not.<verse eid="ROM 9:24" /></para>
  <para style="s1">God Chose People Who Are Not Jewish</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 9:25" />As God says in Hosea:</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ROM 9:25" />
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:25">“Those who are not my people</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:25">I will call my people.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:25">Those who are not loved</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:25">I will call my loved ones.<verse eid="ROM 9:25" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 9:26" />Wherever they were told,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:26">‘You are not my people,’</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:26">they will be called children of the living God.”<verse eid="ROM 9:26" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 9:27" />Isaiah also says about Israel:</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ROM 9:27" />
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:27">“Although the descendants of Israel are</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:27">as numerous as the grains of sand on the seashore,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:27">only a few will be saved.<verse eid="ROM 9:27" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 9:28" />The Lord will carry out his sentence on the land,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:28">completely and decisively.”<verse eid="ROM 9:28" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 9:29" />This is what Isaiah predicted:</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ROM 9:29" />
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:29">“If the Lord of Armies hadn’t left us some descendants,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:29">we would have been like Sodom and Gomorrah.”<verse eid="ROM 9:29" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 9:30" />So what can we say? We can say that non-Jewish people who were not trying to gain God’s approval won his approval, an approval based on faith. <verse eid="ROM 9:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 9:31" />The people of Israel tried to gain God’s approval by obeying the laws in Moses’ Teachings, but they did not reach their goal. <verse eid="ROM 9:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ROM 9:32" />Why? They didn’t rely on faith to gain God’s approval, but they relied on their own efforts. They stumbled over the rock that trips people. <verse eid="ROM 9:32" /><verse number="33" style="v" sid="ROM 9:33" />As Scripture says,</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ROM 9:33" />
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:33">“I am placing a rock in Zion that people trip over,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:33">a large rock that people find offensive.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:33">Whoever believes in him will not be ashamed.”<verse eid="ROM 9:33" /></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 9" />
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="ROM 10" />
  <para style="s1">If You Believe You Will Be Saved</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 10:1" />Brothers and sisters, my heart’s desire and prayer to God on behalf of the Jewish people is that they would be saved. <verse eid="ROM 10:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 10:2" />I can assure you that they are deeply devoted to God, but they are misguided. <verse eid="ROM 10:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 10:3" />They don’t understand <char style="add">⌞how to receive⌟</char> God’s approval. So they try to set up their own way to get it, and they have not accepted God’s way for receiving his approval. <verse eid="ROM 10:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 10:4" />Christ is the fulfillment of Moses’ Teachings so that everyone who has faith may receive God’s approval.<verse eid="ROM 10:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 10:5" />Moses writes about receiving God’s approval by following his laws. He says, “The person who obeys these laws will live because he obeys them.” <verse eid="ROM 10:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 10:6" />However, Scripture says about God’s approval which is based on faith, “Don’t ask yourself who will go up to heaven,” (that is, to bring Christ down). <verse eid="ROM 10:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 10:7" />“Don’t ask who will go down into the depths,” (that is, to bring Christ back from the dead). <verse eid="ROM 10:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 10:8" />However, what else does it say? “This message is near you. It’s in your mouth and in your heart.” This is the message of faith that we spread. <verse eid="ROM 10:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 10:9" />If you declare that Jesus is Lord, and believe that God brought him back to life, you will be saved. <verse eid="ROM 10:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 10:10" />By believing you receive God’s approval, and by declaring your faith you are saved. <verse eid="ROM 10:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 10:11" />Scripture says, “Whoever believes in him will not be ashamed.”<verse eid="ROM 10:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 10:12" />There is no difference between Jews and Greeks. They all have the same Lord, who gives his riches to everyone who calls on him. <verse eid="ROM 10:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 10:13" />So then, “Whoever calls on the name of the Lord will be saved.”<verse eid="ROM 10:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 10:14" />But how can people call on him if they have not believed in him? How can they believe in him if they have not heard his message? How can they hear if no one tells <char style="add">⌞the Good News⌟</char>? <verse eid="ROM 10:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 10:15" />How can people tell the Good News if no one sends them? As Scripture says, “How beautiful are the feet of the messengers who announce the Good News.” <verse eid="ROM 10:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 10:16" />But not everyone has believed the Good News.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ROM 10:16">Isaiah asks, “Lord, who has believed our message?” <verse eid="ROM 10:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 10:17" />So faith comes from hearing the message, and the message that is heard is what Christ spoke.<verse eid="ROM 10:17" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 10:18" />But I ask, “Didn’t they hear that message?” Certainly they did! “The voice of the messengers has gone out into the whole world and their words to the ends of the earth.”<verse eid="ROM 10:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 10:19" />Again I ask, “Didn’t Israel understand <char style="add">⌞that message⌟</char>?” Moses was the first to say, “I will make you jealous of people who are not a nation. I will make you angry about a nation that doesn’t understand.” <verse eid="ROM 10:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 10:20" />Isaiah said very boldly, “I was found by those who weren’t looking for me. I was revealed to those who weren’t asking for me.” <verse eid="ROM 10:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 10:21" />Then Isaiah said about Israel, “All day long I have stretched out my hands to disobedient and rebellious people.”<verse eid="ROM 10:21" /></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 10" />
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="ROM 11" />
  <para style="s1">God’s Continuing Love for Jewish People</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 11:1" />So I ask, “Has God rejected his people Israel?” That’s unthinkable! Consider this. I’m an Israelite myself, a descendant of Abraham from the tribe of Benjamin. <verse eid="ROM 11:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 11:2" />God has not rejected his people whom he knew long ago. Don’t you know what Elijah says in the Scripture passage when he complains to God about Israel? He says, <verse eid="ROM 11:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 11:3" />“Lord, they’ve killed your prophets and torn down your altars. I’m the only one left, and they’re trying to take my life.” <verse eid="ROM 11:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 11:4" />But what was God’s reply? God said, “I’ve kept 7,000 people for myself who have not knelt to worship Baal.” <verse eid="ROM 11:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 11:5" />So, as there were then, there are now a few left that God has chosen by his kindness.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“grace.”</char></note> <verse eid="ROM 11:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 11:6" />If they were chosen by God’s kindness, they weren’t chosen because of anything they did. Otherwise, God’s kindness wouldn’t be kindness.<verse eid="ROM 11:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 11:7" />So what does all this mean? It means that Israel has never achieved what it has been striving for. However, those whom God has chosen have achieved it. The minds of the rest of Israel were closed, <verse eid="ROM 11:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 11:8" />as Scripture says,</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ROM 11:8" />
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:8">“To this day God has given them a spirit of deep sleep.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:8">Their eyes don’t see,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:8">and their ears don’t hear!”<verse eid="ROM 11:8" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 11:9" />And David says,</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ROM 11:9" />
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:9">“Let the table set for them become a trap and a net,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:9">a snare and a punishment for them.<verse eid="ROM 11:9" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 11:10" />Let their vision become clouded so that they cannot see.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:10">Let them carry back-breaking burdens forever.”<verse eid="ROM 11:10" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 11:11" />So I ask, “Has Israel stumbled so badly that it can’t get up again?” That’s unthinkable! By Israel’s failure, salvation has come to people who are not Jewish to make the Jewish people jealous. <verse eid="ROM 11:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 11:12" />The fall of the Jewish people made the world spiritually rich. Their failure made people who are not Jewish spiritually rich. So the inclusion of Jewish people will make the world even richer.<verse eid="ROM 11:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 11:13" />Now, I speak to you who are not Jewish. As long as I am an apostle sent to people who are not Jewish, I bring honor to my ministry. <verse eid="ROM 11:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 11:14" />Perhaps I can make my people jealous and save some of them. <verse eid="ROM 11:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 11:15" />If Israel’s rejection means that the world has been brought back to God, what does Israel’s acceptance mean? It means that Israel has come back to life.<verse eid="ROM 11:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 11:16" />If the first handful of dough is holy, the whole batch of dough is holy. If the root is holy, the branches are holy. <verse eid="ROM 11:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 11:17" />But some of the olive branches have been broken off, and you, a wild olive branch, have been grafted in their place. You get your nourishment from the roots of the olive tree. <verse eid="ROM 11:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 11:18" />So don’t brag about being better than the other branches. If you brag, remember that you don’t support the root, the root supports you. <verse eid="ROM 11:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 11:19" />“Well,” you say, “Branches were cut off so that I could be grafted onto the tree.” <verse eid="ROM 11:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 11:20" />That’s right! They were broken off because they didn’t believe, but you remain on the tree because you do believe. Don’t feel arrogant, but be afraid. <verse eid="ROM 11:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 11:21" />If God didn’t spare the natural branches, he won’t spare you, either. <verse eid="ROM 11:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 11:22" />Look at how kind and how severe God can be. He is severe to those who fell, but kind to you if you continue to hold on to his kindness. Otherwise, you, too, will be cut off <char style="add">⌞from the tree⌟</char>.<verse eid="ROM 11:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 11:23" />If Jewish people do not continue in their unbelief, they will be grafted onto the tree again, because God is able to do that. <verse eid="ROM 11:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 11:24" />In spite of the fact that you have been cut from a wild olive tree, you have been grafted onto a cultivated one. So wouldn’t it be easier for these natural branches to be grafted onto the olive tree they belong to?<verse eid="ROM 11:24" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 11:25" />Brothers and sisters, I want you to understand this mystery so that you won’t become arrogant. The minds of some Israelites have become closed until all of God’s non-Jewish people are included. <verse eid="ROM 11:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 11:26" />In this way Israel as a whole will be saved, as Scripture says,</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ROM 11:26" />
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:26">“The Savior will come from Zion.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:26">He will remove godlessness from Jacob.<verse eid="ROM 11:26" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 11:27" />My promise <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“covenant.”</char></note> to them will be fulfilled</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:27">when I take away their sins.”<verse eid="ROM 11:27" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 11:28" />The Good News made the Jewish people enemies because of you. But by God’s choice they are loved because of their ancestors. <verse eid="ROM 11:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 11:29" />God never changes his mind when he gives gifts or when he calls someone. <verse eid="ROM 11:29" /><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 11:30" />In the past, you disobeyed God. But now God has been merciful to you because of the disobedience of the Jewish people. <verse eid="ROM 11:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 11:31" />In the same way, the Jewish people have also disobeyed so that God may be merciful to them as he was to you. <verse eid="ROM 11:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ROM 11:32" />God has placed all people into the prison of their own disobedience so that he could be merciful to all people.<verse eid="ROM 11:32" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ROM 11:33" />God’s riches, wisdom, and knowledge are so deep</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:33">that it is impossible to explain his decisions</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:33">or to understand his ways.<verse eid="ROM 11:33" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ROM 11:34" />“Who knows how the Lord thinks?</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:34">Who can become his adviser?”<verse eid="ROM 11:34" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ROM 11:35" />Who gave the Lord something</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:35">which the Lord must pay back?<verse eid="ROM 11:35" /></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ROM 11:36" />Everything is from him and by him and for him.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:36">Glory belongs to him forever! Amen!<verse eid="ROM 11:36" /></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 11" />
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="ROM 12" />
  <para style="s1">Dedicate Your Lives to God</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 12:1" />Brothers and sisters, in view of all we have just shared about God’s compassion, I encourage you to offer your bodies as living sacrifices, dedicated to God and pleasing to him. This kind of worship is appropriate for you. <verse eid="ROM 12:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 12:2" />Don’t become like the people of this world. Instead, change the way you think. Then you will always be able to determine what God really wants—what is good, pleasing, and perfect.<verse eid="ROM 12:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 12:3" />Because of the kindness <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12:3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“grace.”</char></note> that God has shown me, I ask you not to think of yourselves more highly than you should. Instead, your thoughts should lead you to use good judgment based on what God has given each of you as believers. <verse eid="ROM 12:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 12:4" />Our bodies have many parts, but these parts don’t all do the same thing. <verse eid="ROM 12:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 12:5" />In the same way, even though we are many individuals, Christ makes us one body and individuals who are connected to each other. <verse eid="ROM 12:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 12:6" />God in his kindness gave each of us different gifts. If your gift is speaking what God has revealed, make sure what you say agrees with the Christian faith. <verse eid="ROM 12:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 12:7" />If your gift is serving, then devote yourself to serving. If it is teaching, devote yourself to teaching. <verse eid="ROM 12:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 12:8" />If it is encouraging others, devote yourself to giving encouragement. If it is sharing, be generous. If it is leadership, lead enthusiastically. If it is helping people in need, help them cheerfully.<verse eid="ROM 12:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 12:9" />Love sincerely. Hate evil. Hold on to what is good. <verse eid="ROM 12:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 12:10" />Be devoted to each other like a loving family. Excel in showing respect for each other. <verse eid="ROM 12:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 12:11" />Don’t be lazy in showing your devotion. Use your energy to serve the Lord. <verse eid="ROM 12:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 12:12" />Be happy in your confidence, be patient in trouble, and pray continually. <verse eid="ROM 12:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 12:13" />Share what you have with God’s people who are in need. Be hospitable.<verse eid="ROM 12:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 12:14" />Bless those who persecute you. Bless them, and don’t curse them. <verse eid="ROM 12:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 12:15" />Be happy with those who are happy. Be sad with those who are sad. <verse eid="ROM 12:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 12:16" />Live in harmony with each other. Don’t be arrogant, but be friendly to humble people. Don’t think that you are smarter than you really are.<verse eid="ROM 12:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 12:17" />Don’t pay people back with evil for the evil they do to you. Focus your thoughts on those things that are considered noble. <verse eid="ROM 12:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 12:18" />As much as it is possible, live in peace with everyone. <verse eid="ROM 12:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 12:19" />Don’t take revenge, dear friends. Instead, let God’s anger take care of it. After all, Scripture says, “I alone have the right to take revenge. I will pay back, says the Lord.” <verse eid="ROM 12:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 12:20" />But,</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ROM 12:20" />
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 12:20">“If your enemy is hungry, feed him.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 12:20">If he is thirsty, give him a drink.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 12:20">If you do this, you will make him feel guilty and ashamed.”<verse eid="ROM 12:20" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 12:21" />Don’t let evil conquer you, but conquer evil with good.<verse eid="ROM 12:21" /></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 12" />
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="ROM 13" />
  <para style="s1">Obey the Government</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 13:1" />Every person should obey the government in power. No government would exist if it hadn’t been established by God. The governments which exist have been put in place by God. <verse eid="ROM 13:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 13:2" />Therefore, whoever resists the government opposes what God has established. Those who resist will bring punishment on themselves.<verse eid="ROM 13:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 13:3" />People who do what is right don’t have to be afraid of the government. But people who do what is wrong should be afraid of it. Would you like to live without being afraid of the government? Do what is right, and it will praise you. <verse eid="ROM 13:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 13:4" />The government is God’s servant working for your good.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ROM 13:4">But if you do what is wrong, you should be afraid. The government has the right to carry out the death sentence. It is God’s servant, an avenger to execute God’s anger on anyone who does what is wrong. <verse eid="ROM 13:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 13:5" />Therefore, it is necessary for you to obey, not only because you’re afraid of God’s anger but also because of your own conscience.<verse eid="ROM 13:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 13:6" />That is also why you pay your taxes. People in the government are God’s servants while they do the work he has given them. <verse eid="ROM 13:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 13:7" />Pay everyone whatever you owe them. If you owe taxes, pay them. If you owe tolls, pay them. If you owe someone respect, respect that person. If you owe someone honor, honor that person.<verse eid="ROM 13:7" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Love One Another</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 13:8" />Pay your debts as they come due. However, one debt you can never finish paying is the debt of love that you owe each other. The one who loves another person has fulfilled Moses’ Teachings. <verse eid="ROM 13:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 13:9" />The commandments, “Never commit adultery; never murder; never steal; never have wrong desires,” and every other commandment are summed up in this statement: “Love your neighbor as you love yourself.” <verse eid="ROM 13:9" /><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 13:10" />Love never does anything that is harmful to a neighbor. Therefore, love fulfills Moses’ Teachings.<verse eid="ROM 13:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 13:11" />You know the times <char style="add">⌞in which we are living⌟</char>. It’s time for you to wake up. Our salvation is nearer now than when we first became believers. <verse eid="ROM 13:11" /><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 13:12" />The night is almost over, and the day is near. So we should get rid of the things that belong to the dark and take up the weapons that belong to the light. <verse eid="ROM 13:12" /><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 13:13" />We should live decently, as people who live in the light of day. Wild parties, drunkenness, sexual immorality, promiscuity, rivalry, and jealousy cannot be part of our lives. <verse eid="ROM 13:13" /><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 13:14" />Instead, live like the Lord Jesus Christ did, and forget about satisfying the desires of your corrupt nature.<verse eid="ROM 13:14" /></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 13" />
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="ROM 14" />
  <para style="s1">How to Treat Christians Who Are Weak in Faith</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 14:1" />Welcome people who are weak in faith, but don’t get into an argument over differences of opinion. <verse eid="ROM 14:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 14:2" />Some people believe that they can eat all kinds of food. Other people with weak faith believe that they can eat only vegetables. <verse eid="ROM 14:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 14:3" />People who eat all foods should not despise people who eat only vegetables. In the same way, the vegetarians should not criticize people who eat all foods, because God has accepted those people. <verse eid="ROM 14:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 14:4" />Who are you to criticize someone else’s servant? The Lord will determine whether his servant has been successful. The servant will be successful because the Lord makes him successful.<verse eid="ROM 14:4" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 14:5" />One person decides that one day is holier than another. Another person decides that all days are the same. Every person must make his own decision. <verse eid="ROM 14:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 14:6" />When people observe a special day, they observe it to honor the Lord. When people eat all kinds of foods, they honor the Lord as they eat, since they give thanks to God. Vegetarians also honor the Lord when they eat, and they, too, give thanks to God. <verse eid="ROM 14:6" /><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 14:7" />It’s clear that we don’t live to honor ourselves, and we don’t die to honor ourselves. <verse eid="ROM 14:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 14:8" />If we live, we honor the Lord, and if we die, we honor the Lord. So whether we live or die, we belong to the Lord. <verse eid="ROM 14:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 14:9" />For this reason Christ died and came back to life so that he would be the Lord of both the living and the dead.<verse eid="ROM 14:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 14:10" />Why do you criticize or despise other Christians? Everyone will stand in front of God to be judged. <verse eid="ROM 14:10" /><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 14:11" />Scripture says,</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ROM 14:11" />
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 14:11">“As certainly as I live, says the Lord,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 14:11">everyone will worship me,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 14:11">and everyone will praise God.”<verse eid="ROM 14:11" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 14:12" />All of us will have to give an account of ourselves to God.<verse eid="ROM 14:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 14:13" />So let’s stop criticizing each other. Instead, you should decide never to do anything that would make other Christians have doubts or lose their faith.<verse eid="ROM 14:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 14:14" />The Lord Jesus has given me the knowledge and conviction that no food is unacceptable in and of itself. But it is unacceptable to a person who thinks it is. <verse eid="ROM 14:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 14:15" />So if what you eat hurts another Christian, you are no longer living by love. Don’t destroy anyone by what you eat. Christ died for that person. <verse eid="ROM 14:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 14:16" />Don’t allow anyone to say that what you consider good is evil.<verse eid="ROM 14:16" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 14:17" />God’s kingdom does not consist of what a person eats or drinks. Rather, God’s kingdom consists of God’s approval and peace, as well as the joy that the Holy Spirit gives. <verse eid="ROM 14:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 14:18" />The person who serves Christ with this in mind is pleasing to God and respected by people.<verse eid="ROM 14:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 14:19" />So let’s pursue those things which bring peace and which are good for each other. <verse eid="ROM 14:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 14:20" />Don’t ruin God’s work because of what you eat. All food is acceptable, but it’s wrong for a person to eat something if it causes someone else to have doubts. <verse eid="ROM 14:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 14:21" />The right thing to do is to avoid eating meat, drinking wine, or doing anything else that causes another Christian to have doubts. <verse eid="ROM 14:21" /><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 14:22" />So whatever you believe about these things, keep it between yourself and God. The person who does what he knows is right shouldn’t feel guilty. He is blessed. <verse eid="ROM 14:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 14:23" />But if a person has doubts and still eats, he is condemned because he didn’t act in faith. Anything that is not done in faith is sin.<verse eid="ROM 14:23" /></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 14" />
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="ROM 15" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 15:1" />So those of us who have a strong <char style="add">⌞faith⌟</char> must be patient with the weaknesses of those whose <char style="add">⌞faith⌟</char> is not so strong. We must not think only of ourselves. <verse eid="ROM 15:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 15:2" />We should all be concerned about our neighbor and the good things that will build his faith. <verse eid="ROM 15:2" /><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 15:3" />Christ did not think only of himself. Rather, as Scripture says, “The insults of those who insult you have fallen on me.”<verse eid="ROM 15:3" /></para>
  <para style="s1">God Gives Us Unity</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 15:4" />Everything written long ago was written to teach us so that we would have confidence through the endurance and encouragement which the Scriptures give us. <verse eid="ROM 15:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 15:5" />May God, who gives you this endurance and encouragement, allow you to live in harmony with each other by following the example of Christ Jesus. <verse eid="ROM 15:5" /><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 15:6" />Then, having the same goal, you will praise the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.<verse eid="ROM 15:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 15:7" />Therefore, accept each other in the same way that Christ accepted you. He did this to bring glory to God. <verse eid="ROM 15:7" /><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 15:8" />Let me explain. Christ became a servant for the Jewish people to reveal God’s truth. As a result, he fulfilled God’s promise to the ancestors of the Jewish people. <verse eid="ROM 15:8" /><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 15:9" />People who are not Jewish praise God for his mercy as well. This is what the Scriptures say,</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ROM 15:9" />
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 15:9">“That is why I will give thanks to you among the nations</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 15:9">and I will sing praises to your name.”<verse eid="ROM 15:9" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 15:10" />And Scripture says again,</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ROM 15:10" />
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 15:10">“You nations, be happy together with his people!”<verse eid="ROM 15:10" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 15:11" />And again,</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ROM 15:11" />
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 15:11">“Praise the Lord, all you nations!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 15:11">Praise him, all you people of the world!”<verse eid="ROM 15:11" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 15:12" />Again, Isaiah says,</para>
  <para style="b" vid="ROM 15:12" />
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 15:12">“There will be a root from Jesse.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 15:12">He will rise to rule the nations,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 15:12">and he will give the nations hope.”<verse eid="ROM 15:12" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 15:13" />May God, the source of hope, fill you with joy and peace through your faith in him. Then you will overflow with hope by the power of the Holy Spirit.<verse eid="ROM 15:13" /></para>
  <para style="s1">Paul’s Desire to Tell the Good News to the World</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 15:14" />I’m convinced, brothers and sisters, that you, too, are filled with goodness. I’m also convinced that you have all the knowledge you need and that you are able to instruct each other. <verse eid="ROM 15:14" /><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 15:15" />However, I’ve written you a letter, parts of which are rather bold, as a reminder to you. I’m doing this because God gave me the gift <verse eid="ROM 15:15" /><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 15:16" />to be a servant of Christ Jesus to people who are not Jewish. I serve as a priest by spreading the Good News of God. I do this in order that I might bring the nations to God as an acceptable offering, made holy by the Holy Spirit. <verse eid="ROM 15:16" /><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 15:17" />So Christ Jesus gives me the right to brag about what I’m doing for God. <verse eid="ROM 15:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 15:18" />I’m bold enough to tell you only what Christ has done through me to bring people who are not Jewish to obedience. By what I have said and done, <verse eid="ROM 15:18" /><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 15:19" />by the power of miraculous and amazing signs, and by the power of God’s Spirit, I have finished spreading the Good News about Christ from Jerusalem to Illyricum.<verse eid="ROM 15:19" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 15:20" />My goal was to spread the Good News where the name of Christ was not known. I didn’t want to build on a foundation which others had laid. <verse eid="ROM 15:20" /><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 15:21" />As Scripture says,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 15:21">“Those who were never told about him will see,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 15:21">and those who never heard will understand.”<verse eid="ROM 15:21" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 15:22" />This is what has so often kept me from visiting you. <verse eid="ROM 15:22" /><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 15:23" />But now I have no new opportunities for work in this region. For many years I have wanted to visit you. <verse eid="ROM 15:23" /><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 15:24" />Now I am on my way to Spain, so I hope to see you when I come your way. After I have enjoyed your company for a while, I hope that you will support my trip to Spain.<verse eid="ROM 15:24" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 15:25" />Right now I’m going to Jerusalem to bring help to the Christians there. <verse eid="ROM 15:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 15:26" />Because the believers in Macedonia and Greece owe a debt to the Christians in Jerusalem, they have decided to take up a collection for the poor among the Christians in Jerusalem. <verse eid="ROM 15:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 15:27" />These Macedonians and Greeks have shared the spiritual wealth of the Christians in Jerusalem. So they are obligated to use their earthly wealth to help them.<verse eid="ROM 15:27" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 15:28" />When the collection is completed and I have officially turned the money over to the Christians in Jerusalem, I will visit you on my way to Spain. <verse eid="ROM 15:28" /><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 15:29" />I know that when I come to you I will bring the full blessing of Christ.<verse eid="ROM 15:29" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 15:30" />Brothers and sisters, I encourage you through our Lord Jesus Christ and by the love that the Spirit creates, to join me in my struggle. Pray to God for me <verse eid="ROM 15:30" /><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 15:31" />that I will be rescued from those people in Judea who refuse to believe. Pray that God’s people in Jerusalem will accept the help I bring. <verse eid="ROM 15:31" /><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ROM 15:32" />Also pray that by the will of God I may come to you with joy and be refreshed when I am with you.<verse eid="ROM 15:32" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ROM 15:33" />May the God of peace be with you all. Amen.<verse eid="ROM 15:33" /></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 15" />
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="ROM 16" />
  <para style="s1">Farewell</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 16:1" />With this letter I’m introducing Phoebe to you. She is our sister in the Christian faith and a deacon of the church in the city of Cenchrea. <verse eid="ROM 16:1" /><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 16:2" />Give her a Christian welcome that shows you are God’s holy people. Provide her with anything she may need, because she has provided help to many people, including me.<verse eid="ROM 16:2" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 16:3" />Greet Prisca and Aquila, my coworkers in the service of Christ Jesus. <verse eid="ROM 16:3" /><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 16:4" />They risked their lives to save me. I’m thankful to them and so are all the churches among the nations. <verse eid="ROM 16:4" /><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 16:5" />Also greet the church that meets in their house.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ROM 16:5">Greet my dear friend Epaenetus. He was the first person in the province of Asia to become a believer in Christ.<verse eid="ROM 16:5" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 16:6" />Greet Mary, who has worked very hard for you.<verse eid="ROM 16:6" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 16:7" />Greet Andronicus and Junia, who are Jewish by birth like me. They are prisoners like me and are prominent among the apostles. They also were Christians before I was.<verse eid="ROM 16:7" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 16:8" />Greet Ampliatus my dear friend in the service of the Lord.<verse eid="ROM 16:8" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 16:9" />Greet Urbanus our coworker in the service of Christ, and my dear friend Stachys.<verse eid="ROM 16:9" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 16:10" />Greet Apelles, a true Christian.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ROM 16:10">Greet those who belong to the family of Aristobulus.<verse eid="ROM 16:10" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 16:11" />Greet Herodion, who is Jewish by birth like me.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ROM 16:11">Greet those Christians who belong to the family of Narcissus.<verse eid="ROM 16:11" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 16:12" />Greet Tryphaena and Tryphosa, who have worked hard for the Lord.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ROM 16:12">Greet dear Persis, who has worked very hard for the Lord.<verse eid="ROM 16:12" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 16:13" />Greet Rufus, that outstanding Christian, and his mother, who has been a mother to me too.<verse eid="ROM 16:13" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 16:14" />Greet Asyncritus, Phlegon, Hermes, Patrobas, Hermas, and the brothers and sisters who are with them.<verse eid="ROM 16:14" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 16:15" />Greet Philologus and Julia, Nereus, and his sister, and Olympas, and all God’s people who are with them.<verse eid="ROM 16:15" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 16:16" />Greet each other with a holy kiss.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ROM 16:16">All the churches of Christ greet you.<verse eid="ROM 16:16" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 16:17" />Brothers and sisters, I urge you to watch out for those people who create divisions and who make others fall away <char style="add">⌞from the Christian faith⌟</char> by teaching doctrine that is not the same as you have learned. Stay away from them. <verse eid="ROM 16:17" /><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 16:18" />People like these are not serving Christ our Lord. They are serving their own desires. By their smooth talk and flattering words they deceive unsuspecting people.<verse eid="ROM 16:18" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 16:19" />Everyone has heard about your obedience and this makes me happy for you. I want you to do what is good and to avoid what is evil. <verse eid="ROM 16:19" /><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 16:20" />The God of peace will quickly crush Satan under your feet. May the good will <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16:20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“grace.”</char></note> of our Lord Jesus be with you!<verse eid="ROM 16:20" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 16:21" />Timothy my coworker greets you; so do Lucius, Jason, and Sosipater, who are Jewish by birth like me.<verse eid="ROM 16:21" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 16:22" />I, Tertius, who wrote this letter, send you Christian greetings.<verse eid="ROM 16:22" /></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 16:23" />Gaius greets you. He is host to me and the whole church.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ROM 16:23">Erastus, the city treasurer, greets you.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ROM 16:23">Quartus, our brother in the Christian faith, greets you.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16:23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts and translations add verse 24: </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">“May the good will of our Lord Jesus Christ be with all of you. Amen.”</char></note><verse eid="ROM 16:23" /></para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 16:25" />God can strengthen you by the Good News and the message I tell about Jesus Christ. He can strengthen you by revealing the mystery that was kept in silence for a very long time <verse eid="ROM 16:25" /><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 16:26" />but now is publicly known. The everlasting God ordered that what the prophets wrote must be shown to the people of every nation to bring them to the obedience that is associated with faith. <verse eid="ROM 16:26" /><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 16:27" />God alone is wise. Glory belongs to him through Jesus Christ forever! Amen.<verse eid="ROM 16:27" /></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 16" />
</usx>